<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:13:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>ThreadWeaver: Adaptive Threading for Efficient Parallel Reasoning in Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07843</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07843.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Long Lian, Sida Wang, Felix Juefei-Xu, Tsu-Jui Fu, Xiuyu Li, Adam Yala, Trevor Darrell, Alane Suhr, Yuandong Tian, Xi Victoria Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling inference-time computation has enabled Large Language Models (LLMs) to achieve strong reasoning performance, but inherently sequential decoding leads to substantial latency, especially on complex tasks. Recent work on adaptive parallel reasoning aims to improve inference efficiency by decomposing the problem-solving process into concurrent reasoning threads when beneficial. However, existing methods on realistic tasks are either limited to supervised behavior cloning or exhibit significant accuracy drops compared to widely-used sequential long chain-of-thought (CoT) baselines. Moreover, many require customized inference engines, complicating deployment. We introduce ThreadWeaver, a framework for adaptive parallel reasoning that achieves accuracy on par with popular sequential reasoning models of comparable size while significantly reducing inference latency. ThreadWeaver's performance stems from three key innovations: 1) a two-stage parallel trajectory generator that produces large-scale, high-quality CoT data with parallel annotations for supervised fine-tuning; 2) a trie-based training-inference co-design that enables parallel reasoning on any off-the-shelf autoregressive inference engine without modifying position embeddings or KV caches; and 3) a parallelization-aware reinforcement learning framework that teaches the model to balance accuracy with effective parallelization. Across six challenging mathematical reasoning benchmarks, ThreadWeaver trained atop Qwen3-8B achieves accuracy comparable to cutting-edge sequential reasoning models (71.9% on average and 79.9% on AIME24) while delivering up to 1.53x average speedup in token latency, establishing a new Pareto frontier between accuracy and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07843</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VQRAE: Representation Quantization Autoencoders for Multimodal Understanding, Generation and Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23386</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.23386.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sinan Du, Jiahao Guo, Bo Li, Shuhao Cui, Zhengzhuo Xu, Yifu Luo, Yongxian Wei, Kun Gai, Xinggang Wang, Kai Wu, Chun Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unifying multimodal understanding, generation and reconstruction representation in a single tokenizer remains a key challenge in building unified models. Previous research predominantly attempts to address this in a dual encoder paradigm, e.g., utilizing the separate encoders for understanding and generation respectively or balancing semantic representations and low-level features with contrastive loss. In this paper, we propose VQRAE, a Vector Quantization version of Representation AutoEncoders, which pioneers the first exploration in unified representation to produce Continuous semantic features for image understanding and Discrete tokens for visual generation within a unified tokenizer. Specifically, we build upon pretrained vision foundation models with a symmetric ViT decoder and adopt a two-stage training strategy: first, it freezes the encoder and learns a high-dimensional semantic VQ codebook with pixel reconstruction objective; then jointly optimizes the encoder with self-distillation constraints. This design enables negligible semantic information for maintaining the ability of multimodal understanding, discrete tokens that are compatible for generation and fine-grained reconstruction. Besides, we identify the intriguing property in quantizing semantic encoders that rely on high-dimensional codebook in contrast to the previous common practice of low-dimensional codebook in image reconstruction. The semantic VQ codebook can achieve a 100% utilization ratio at a dimension of 1536. VQRAE presents competitive performance on several benchmarks of visual understanding, generation and reconstruction with promising scaling property in the autoregressive paradigm for its discrete merits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23386</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 17:26:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Generation Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23469</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.23469.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiahao Guo, Sinan Du, Jingfeng Yao, Wenyu Liu, Bo Li, Haoxiang Cao, Kun Gai, Chun Yuan, Kai Wu, Xinggang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Vision Language Models (VLMs) effectively bridge the modality gap through extensive pretraining, acquiring sophisticated visual representations aligned with language. However, it remains underexplored whether these representations, optimized for multimodal understanding tasks, harbor an inherent potential for visual generation. In this paper, we propose VGT, Visual Generation Tuning, a novel paradigm designed to stimulate the underlying capabilities of visual generation within any vision language models. By performing efficient visual generation tuning on well-pretrained VLMs, we significantly mitigate the alignment costs and accelerate the convergence of autoregressive modeling in the continuous space (20x speedup). Specifically, we dismiss the entangled pixel-level VAEs designed for diffusion transformers and formulate VGT-AE through aligning the semantic encoders from pretrained VLMs with the latent representations of pixel decoders. In image reconstruction tasks, we achieve 26.67 PSNR and 0.50 rFID at a 28x compression ratio, outperforming specialized VAEs; in visual generation tasks, we achieve state-of-the-art outcomes among autoregressive models, 0.77 on GenEval and 78.73 on DPG-Bench. Furthermore, our proposed VGT showcases significant scaling promise and is versatile for endowing any VLMs trained for multimodal understanding with the capabilities of visual generation, which paves the new avenue to explore next-generation unified multimodal foundation models. Models and codes are available at https://github.com/hustvl/VGT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23469</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 18:57:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RealGen: Photorealistic Text-to-Image Generation via Detector-Guided Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00473</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.00473.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyan Ye, Leiqi Zhu, Yuncheng Guo, Dongzhi Jiang, Zilong Huang, Yifan Zhang, Zhiyuan Yan, Haohuan Fu, Conghui He, Weijia Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the continuous advancement of image generation technology, advanced models such as GPT-Image-1 and Qwen-Image have achieved remarkable text-to-image consistency and world knowledge However, these models still fall short in photorealistic image generation. Even on simple T2I tasks, they tend to produce " fake" images with distinct AI artifacts, often characterized by "overly smooth skin" and "oily facial sheens". To recapture the original goal of "indistinguishable-from-reality" generation, we propose RealGen, a photorealistic text-to-image framework. RealGen integrates an LLM component for prompt optimization and a diffusion model for realistic image generation. Inspired by adversarial generation, RealGen introduces a "Detector Reward" mechanism, which quantifies artifacts and assesses realism using both semantic-level and feature-level synthetic image detectors. We leverage this reward signal with the GRPO algorithm to optimize the entire generation pipeline, significantly enhancing image realism and detail. Furthermore, we propose RealBench, an automated evaluation benchmark employing Detector-Scoring and Arena-Scoring. It enables human-free photorealism assessment, yielding results that are more accurate and aligned with real user experience. Experiments demonstrate that RealGen significantly outperforms general models like GPT-Image-1 and Qwen-Image, as well as specialized photorealistic models like FLUX-Krea, in terms of realism, detail, and aesthetics. The code is available at https://github.com/yejy53/RealGen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00473</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 12:52:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>See, Hear, and Understand: Benchmarking Audiovisual Human Speech Understanding in Multimodal Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02231</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02231.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Le Thien Phuc Nguyen, Zhuoran Yu, Samuel Low Yu Hang, Subin An, Jeongik Lee, Yohan Ban, SeungEun Chung, Thanh-Huy Nguyen, JuWan Maeng, Soochahn Lee, Yong Jae Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) are expected to jointly interpret vision, audio, and language, yet existing video benchmarks rarely assess fine-grained reasoning about human speech. Many tasks remain visually solvable or only coarsely evaluate speech, offering limited insight into whether models can align who speaks, what is said, and when it occurs. We introduce AV-SpeakerBench, a curated benchmark of 3,212 multiple-choice questions focused on speaker-centric audiovisual reasoning in real-world videos. It features: (1) a speaker-centered formulation that treats speakers-not scenes-as the core reasoning unit; (2) fusion-grounded question design embedding audiovisual dependencies into question semantics; and (3) expert-curated annotations ensuring temporal precision and cross-modal validity. Comprehensive evaluations show that the Gemini family consistently outperforms open-source systems, with Gemini 2.5 Pro achieving the best results. Among open models, Qwen3-Omni-30B approaches Gemini 2.0 Flash but remains far behind Gemini 2.5 Pro, primarily due to weaker audiovisual fusion rather than visual perception. We believe AV-SpeakerBench establishes a rigorous foundation for advancing fine-grained audiovisual reasoning in future multimodal systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02231</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 21:57:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Imitation to Discrimination: Toward A Generalized Curriculum Advantage Mechanism Enhancing Cross-Domain Reasoning Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02580</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02580.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Changpeng Yang, Jinyang Wu, Yuchen Liu, Shuai Zhang, Yang Li, Qiliang Liang, Hongzhen Wang, Shuai Nie, Jiaming Xu, Runyu Shi, Ying Huang, Guoquan Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning has emerged as a paradigm for post-training large language models, boosting their reasoning capabilities. Such approaches compute an advantage value for each sample, reflecting better or worse performance than expected, thereby yielding both positive and negative signals for training. However, the indiscriminate mixing of the two signals in existing methods, especially from the early stages, may lead to ambiguous guidance and limited gains. To address this issue, we propose **CAPO** (**C**urriculum **A**dvantage **P**olicy **O**ptimization), an adaptive curriculum mechanism based on advantage signals. The proposed mechanism bootstraps imitation learning with positive-only advantage samples to establish robust foundations, and subsequently introduces negative signals to cultivate discriminative capabilities, thereby improving generalization across complex scenarios. Compatible with diverse optimization methods including GRPO, PPO, RLOO, and Reinforce++, our method consistently achieves stable and significant improvements in mathematical reasoning tasks, and further generalizes effectively to multimodal Graphical User Interface (GUI) reasoning scenarios, establishing itself as a versatile and robust optimization framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02580</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 09:48:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PaCo-RL: Advancing Reinforcement Learning for Consistent Image Generation with Pairwise Reward Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04784</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04784.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bowen Ping, Chengyou Jia, Minnan Luo, Changliang Xia, Xin Shen, Zhuohang Dang, Hangwei Qian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Consistent image generation requires faithfully preserving identities, styles, and logical coherence across multiple images, which is essential for applications such as storytelling and character design. Supervised training approaches struggle with this task due to the lack of large-scale datasets capturing visual consistency and the complexity of modeling human perceptual preferences. In this paper, we argue that reinforcement learning (RL) offers a promising alternative by enabling models to learn complex and subjective visual criteria in a data-free manner. To achieve this, we introduce PaCo-RL, a comprehensive framework that combines a specialized consistency reward model with an efficient RL algorithm. The first component, PaCo-Reward, is a pairwise consistency evaluator trained on a large-scale dataset constructed via automated sub-figure pairing. It evaluates consistency through a generative, autoregressive scoring mechanism enhanced by task-aware instructions and CoT reasons. The second component, PaCo-GRPO, leverages a novel resolution-decoupled optimization strategy to substantially reduce RL cost, alongside a log-tamed multi-reward aggregation mechanism that ensures balanced and stable reward optimization. Extensive experiments across the two representative subtasks show that PaCo-Reward significantly improves alignment with human perceptions of visual consistency, and PaCo-GRPO achieves state-of-the-art consistency performance with improved training efficiency and stability. Together, these results highlight the promise of PaCo-RL as a practical and scalable solution for consistent image generation. The project page is available at https://x-gengroup.github.io/HomePage_PaCo-RL/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04784</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 13:39:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReVSeg: Incentivizing the Reasoning Chain for Video Segmentation with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02835</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02835.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Li, Yingda Yin, Lingting Zhu, Weikai Chen, Shengju Qian, Xin Wang, Yanwei Fu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning-centric video object segmentation is an inherently complex task: the query often refers to dynamics, causality, and temporal interactions, rather than static appearances. Yet existing solutions generally collapse these factors into simplified reasoning with latent embeddings, rendering the reasoning chain opaque and essentially intractable. We therefore adopt an explicit decomposition perspective and introduce ReVSeg, which executes reasoning as sequential decisions in the native interface of pretrained vision language models (VLMs). Rather than folding all reasoning into a single-step prediction, ReVSeg executes three explicit operations -- semantics interpretation, temporal evidence selection, and spatial grounding -- aligning pretrained capabilities. We further employ reinforcement learning to optimize the multi-step reasoning chain, enabling the model to self-refine its decision quality from outcome-driven signals. Experimental results demonstrate that ReVSeg attains state-of-the-art performances on standard video object segmentation benchmarks and yields interpretable reasoning trajectories. Project page is available at https://clementine24.github.io/ReVSeg/ .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02835</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 14:44:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast-Decoding Diffusion Language Models via Progress-Aware Confidence Schedules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02892</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02892.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amr Mohamed, Yang Zhang, Michalis Vazirgiannis, Guokan Shang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion large language models (dLLMs) offer a promising alternative to autoregressive models, but their practical utility is severely hampered by slow, iterative sampling. We present SchED, a training-free, model-agnostic early-exit algorithm that aggregates full-span logit margins and halts decoding once a smooth, progress-dependent confidence threshold is met. We evaluated SchED on two dLLM families (Dream and LLaDA), in base and instruction-tuned variants across ten benchmarks spanning downstream tasks including multiple-choice question answering (MCQ), math, long-form QA/summarization, and translation. SchED delivers large, stable accelerations: on instruction-tuned models, it achieves 3.8-4.0times speedups while retaining 99.8-100% of the baseline score on average. On base models, SchED yields consistent speedup gains with 99.1-100% performance retention, with up to 2.34times under more aggressive settings. Using a conservative speed metric that heavily penalizes quality loss (QPS, γ{=}4), we show that SchED is robust and clearly outperforms prior confidence-based early-exit methods, which break down on long-form generation. An entropy analysis of the model's token predictions reveals that instruction tuning speeds up the decay of predictive entropy. By turning genuine confidence stabilization into computational savings, SchED makes dLLM decoding substantially more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02892</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 16:01:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Improving VLM Judges Without Human Annotations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05145</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05145.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Inna Wanyin Lin, Yushi Hu, Shuyue Stella Li, Scott Geng, Pang Wei Koh, Luke Zettlemoyer, Tim Althoff, Marjan Ghazvininejad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Effective judges of Vision-Language Models (VLMs) are crucial for model development. Current methods for training VLM judges mainly rely on large-scale human preference annotations. However, such an approach is costly, and the annotations easily become obsolete as models rapidly improve. In this work, we present a framework to self-train a VLM judge model without any human preference annotations, using only self-synthesized data. Our method is iterative and has three stages: (1) generate diverse multimodal instruction-response pairs at varying quality levels, (2) generate reasoning traces and judgments for each pair, removing the ones that do not match our expected quality levels, and (3) training on correct judge answers and their reasoning traces. We evaluate the resulting judge on Multimodal RewardBench and VL-RewardBench across domains: correctness, preference, reasoning, safety, and visual question-answering. Our method improves a Llama-3.2-11B multimodal judge from 0.38 to 0.51 in overall accuracy on VL-RewardBench, often outperforming much larger models including Llama-3.2-90B, GPT-4o, and Claude 3.5 Sonnet, with particularly strong gains in general, hallucination, and reasoning dimensions. The overall strength of these human-annotation-free results suggest the potential for a future self-judge that evolves alongside rapidly improving VLM capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05145</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 20:52:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPARK: Stepwise Process-Aware Rewards for Reference-Free Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03244</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.03244.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Salman Rahman, Sruthi Gorantla, Arpit Gupta, Swastik Roy, Nanyun Peng, Yang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Process reward models (PRMs) that provide dense, step-level feedback have shown promise for reinforcement learning, yet their adoption remains limited by the need for expensive step-level annotations or ground truth references. We propose SPARK: a three-stage framework where in the first stage a generator model produces diverse solutions and a verifier model evaluates them using parallel scaling (self-consistency) and sequential scaling (meta-critique). In the second stage, we use these verification outputs as synthetic training data to fine-tune generative process reward models, which subsequently serve as reward signals during training. We show that aggregating multiple independent verifications at the step level produces training data for process reward models that surpass ground-truth outcome supervision, achieving 67.5 F1 on ProcessBench (a benchmark for identifying erroneous steps in mathematical reasoning) compared to 66.4 for reference-guided training and 61.9 for GPT-4o. In the final stage, we apply our generative PRM with chain-of-thought verification (PRM-CoT) as the reward model in RL experiments on mathematical reasoning, and introduce format constraints to prevent reward hacking. Using Qwen2.5-Math-7B, we achieve 47.4% average accuracy across six mathematical reasoning benchmarks, outperforming ground-truth-based RLVR (43.9%). Our work enables reference-free RL training that exceeds ground-truth methods, opening new possibilities for domains lacking verifiable answers or accessible ground truth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03244</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 21:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>M3DR: Towards Universal Multilingual Multimodal Document Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03514</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.03514.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Adithya S Kolavi, Vyoman Jain&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal document retrieval systems have shown strong progress in aligning visual and textual content for semantic search. However, most existing approaches remain heavily English-centric, limiting their effectiveness in multilingual contexts. In this work, we present M3DR (Multilingual Multimodal Document Retrieval), a framework designed to bridge this gap across languages, enabling applicability across diverse linguistic and cultural contexts. M3DR leverages synthetic multilingual document data and generalizes across different vision-language architectures and model sizes, enabling robust cross-lingual and cross-modal alignment. Using contrastive training, our models learn unified representations for text and document images that transfer effectively across languages. We validate this capability on 22 typologically diverse languages, demonstrating consistent performance and adaptability across linguistic and script variations. We further introduce a comprehensive benchmark that captures real-world multilingual scenarios, evaluating models under monolingual, multilingual, and mixed-language settings. M3DR generalizes across both single dense vector and ColBERT-style token-level multi-vector retrieval paradigms. Our models, NetraEmbed and ColNetraEmbed achieve state-of-the-art performance with ~150% relative improvements on cross-lingual retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03514</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 07:17:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TwinFlow: Realizing One-step Generation on Large Models with Self-adversarial Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05150</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05150.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenglin Cheng, Peng Sun, Jianguo Li, Tao Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large multi-modal generative models have demonstrated impressive capabilities in multi-modal generation, including image and video generation. These models are typically built upon multi-step frameworks like diffusion and flow matching, which inherently limits their inference efficiency (requiring 40-100 Number of Function Evaluations (NFEs)). While various few-step methods aim to accelerate the inference, existing solutions have clear limitations. Prominent distillation-based methods, such as progressive and consistency distillation, either require an iterative distillation procedure or show significant degradation at very few steps (&lt; 4-NFE). Meanwhile, integrating adversarial training into distillation (e.g., DMD/DMD2 and SANA-Sprint) to enhance performance introduces training instability, added complexity, and high GPU memory overhead due to the auxiliary trained models. To this end, we propose TwinFlow, a simple yet effective framework for training 1-step generative models that bypasses the need of fixed pretrained teacher models and avoids standard adversarial networks during training, making it ideal for building large-scale, efficient models. On text-to-image tasks, our method achieves a GenEval score of 0.83 in 1-NFE, outperforming strong baselines like SANA-Sprint (a GAN loss-based framework) and RCGM (a consistency-based framework). Notably, we demonstrate the scalability of TwinFlow by full-parameter training on Qwen-Image-20B and transform it into an efficient few-step generator. With just 1-NFE, our approach matches the performance of the original 100-NFE model on both the GenEval and DPG-Bench benchmarks, reducing computational cost by 100times with minor quality degradation. Project page is available at https://zhenglin-cheng.com/twinflow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05150</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 07:45:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReCamDriving: LiDAR-Free Camera-Controlled Novel Trajectory Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03621</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.03621.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yaokun Li, Shuaixian Wang, Mantang Guo, Jiehui Huang, Taojun Ding, Mu Hu, Kaixuan Wang, Shaojie Shen, Guang Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose ReCamDriving, a purely vision-based, camera-controlled novel-trajectory video generation framework. While repair-based methods fail to restore complex artifacts and LiDAR-based approaches rely on sparse and incomplete cues, ReCamDriving leverages dense and scene-complete 3DGS renderings for explicit geometric guidance, achieving precise camera-controllable generation. To mitigate overfitting to restoration behaviors when conditioned on 3DGS renderings, ReCamDriving adopts a two-stage training paradigm: the first stage uses camera poses for coarse control, while the second stage incorporates 3DGS renderings for fine-grained viewpoint and geometric guidance. Furthermore, we present a 3DGS-based cross-trajectory data curation strategy to eliminate the train-test gap in camera transformation patterns, enabling scalable multi-trajectory supervision from monocular videos. Based on this strategy, we construct the ParaDrive dataset, containing over 110K parallel-trajectory video pairs. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ReCamDriving achieves state-of-the-art camera controllability and structural consistency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03621</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 09:55:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colon-X: Advancing Intelligent Colonoscopy from Multimodal Understanding to Clinical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03667</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.03667.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ge-Peng Ji, Jingyi Liu, Deng-Ping Fan, Nick Barnes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this study, we present Colon-X, an open initiative aimed at advancing multimodal intelligence in colonoscopy. We begin by constructing ColonVQA, the most comprehensive multimodal dataset ever built for colonoscopy, featuring over 1.1M+ visual question answering entries across 76 clinical findings and 18 multimodal tasks. Beyond serving as a community-wide data foundation, we further investigate a critical yet underexplored transition in colonoscopy - evolving from multimodal understanding to clinical reasoning: (a) To capture the current landscape of multimodal understanding behaviors, we systematically assess the generalizability of 22 multimodal large language models and examine their reliability under human-induced perturbations. The results reveal that clinical outputs from leading MLLMs remain far from robust and trustworthy. (b) To narrow this gap, we further explore reasoning-centric intelligence tailored for colonoscopy. Specifically, we curate ColonReason, a clinically grounded reasoning dataset annotated through a multi-expert debating pipeline, and develop ColonR1, the first R1-styled model incorporating task-adaptive rewarding and gradient-stable optimization techniques. Under data-scarce conditions, our ColonR1 achieves 56.61% overall accuracy, outperforming supervised fine-tuning by 25.22%, and sets a new reasoning-enabled baseline for multimodal colonoscopy analysis. All data and model resources are publicly available at https://github.com/ai4colonoscopy/Colon-X.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03667</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 10:55:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoSSM: Autoregressive Long Video Generation with Hybrid State-Space Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04519</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04519.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifei Yu, Xiaoshan Wu, Xinting Hu, Tao Hu, Yangtian Sun, Xiaoyang Lyu, Bo Wang, Lin Ma, Yuewen Ma, Zhongrui Wang, Xiaojuan Qi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive (AR) diffusion enables streaming, interactive long-video generation by producing frames causally, yet maintaining coherence over minute-scale horizons remains challenging due to accumulated errors, motion drift, and content repetition. We approach this problem from a memory perspective, treating video synthesis as a recurrent dynamical process that requires coordinated short- and long-term context. We propose VideoSSM, a Long Video Model that unifies AR diffusion with a hybrid state-space memory. The state-space model (SSM) serves as an evolving global memory of scene dynamics across the entire sequence, while a context window provides local memory for motion cues and fine details. This hybrid design preserves global consistency without frozen, repetitive patterns, supports prompt-adaptive interaction, and scales in linear time with sequence length. Experiments on short- and long-range benchmarks demonstrate state-of-the-art temporal consistency and motion stability among autoregressive video generator especially at minute-scale horizons, enabling content diversity and interactive prompt-based control, thereby establishing a scalable, memory-aware framework for long video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04519</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 07:06:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-Humanoid: Robotize Human Videos to Generate Humanoid Videos at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04537</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04537.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pei Yang, Hai Ci, Yiren Song, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The advancement of embodied AI has unlocked significant potential for intelligent humanoid robots. However, progress in both Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models and world models is severely hampered by the scarcity of large-scale, diverse training data. A promising solution is to "robotize" web-scale human videos, which has been proven effective for policy training. However, these solutions mainly "overlay" robot arms to egocentric videos, which cannot handle complex full-body motions and scene occlusions in third-person videos, making them unsuitable for robotizing humans. To bridge this gap, we introduce X-Humanoid, a generative video editing approach that adapts the powerful Wan 2.2 model into a video-to-video structure and finetunes it for the human-to-humanoid translation task. This finetuning requires paired human-humanoid videos, so we designed a scalable data creation pipeline, turning community assets into 17+ hours of paired synthetic videos using Unreal Engine. We then apply our trained model to 60 hours of the Ego-Exo4D videos, generating and releasing a new large-scale dataset of over 3.6 million "robotized" humanoid video frames. Quantitative analysis and user studies confirm our method's superiority over existing baselines: 69% of users rated it best for motion consistency, and 62.1% for embodiment correctness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04537</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 07:34:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>COOPER: A Unified Model for Cooperative Perception and Reasoning in Spatial Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04563</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04563.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zefeng Zhang, Xiangzhao Hao, Hengzhu Tang, Zhenyu Zhang, Jiawei Sheng, Xiaodong Li, Zhenyang Li, Li Gao, Daiting Shi, Dawei Yin, Tingwen Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual Spatial Reasoning is crucial for enabling Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) to understand object properties and spatial relationships, yet current models still struggle with 3D-aware reasoning. Existing approaches typically enhance either perception, by augmenting RGB inputs with auxiliary modalities such as depth and segmentation, or reasoning, by training on spatial VQA datasets and applying reinforcement learning, and thus treat these two aspects in isolation. In this work, we investigate whether a unified MLLM can develop an intrinsic ability to enhance spatial perception and, through adaptive interleaved reasoning, achieve stronger spatial intelligence. We propose COOPER, a unified MLLM that leverages depth and segmentation as auxiliary modalities and is trained in two stages to acquire auxiliary modality generation and adaptive, interleaved reasoning capabilities. COOPER achieves an average 6.91\% improvement in spatial reasoning while maintaining general performance. Moreover, even a variant trained only for auxiliary modality generation attains a 7.92\% gain on distance and size estimation, suggesting that learning to generate auxiliary modalities helps internalize spatial knowledge and strengthen spatial understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04563</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 08:26:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EtCon: Edit-then-Consolidate for Reliable Knowledge Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04753</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04753.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruilin Li, Yibin Wang, Wenhong Zhu, Chenglin Li, Jinghao Zhang, Chenliang Li, Junchi Yan, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Knowledge editing aims to update specific facts in large language models (LLMs) without full retraining. Prior efforts sought to tune the knowledge layers of LLMs, proving effective for making selective edits. However, a significant gap exists between their performance in controlled, teacher-forcing evaluations and their real-world effectiveness in lifelong learning scenarios, which greatly limits their practical applicability. This work's empirical analysis reveals two recurring issues associated with this gap: (1) Most traditional methods lead the edited model to overfit to the new fact, thereby degrading pre-trained capabilities; (2) There is a critical absence of a knowledge consolidation stage, leaving new facts insufficiently integrated into LLMs' inference-time behavior under autoregressive generation, thereby leading to a mismatch between parametric knowledge and actual generation behavior. To this end, we propose Edit-then-Consolidate, a novel knowledge editing paradigm that aims to bridge the gap between theoretical knowledge editing methods and their real-world applicability. Specifically, (1) our framework mitigates overfitting via Targeted Proximal Supervised Fine-Tuning (TPSFT) that localizes the edit via a trust-region objective to limit policy drift; (2) Then, a consolidation stage using Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) aligns the edited knowledge with CoT-based inference policy by optimizing trajectory-level behavior under comprehensive reward signals. Extensive experiments demonstrate our framework consistently improves editing reliability and generalization under real-world evaluations, while better preserving locality and pre-trained capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04753</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 12:43:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MemLoRA: Distilling Expert Adapters for On-Device Memory Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04763</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04763.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Massimo Bini, Ondrej Bohdal, Umberto Michieli, Zeynep Akata, Mete Ozay, Taha Ceritli&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Memory-augmented Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable consistency during prolonged dialogues by storing relevant memories and incorporating them as context. Such memory-based personalization is also key in on-device settings that allow users to keep their conversations and data private. However, memory-augmented systems typically rely on LLMs that are too costly for local on-device deployment. Even though Small Language Models (SLMs) are more suitable for on-device inference than LLMs, they cannot achieve sufficient performance. Additionally, these LLM-based systems lack native visual capabilities, limiting their applicability in multimodal contexts. In this paper, we introduce (i) MemLoRA, a novel memory system that enables local deployment by equipping SLMs with specialized memory adapters, and (ii) its vision extension MemLoRA-V, which integrates small Vision-Language Models (SVLMs) to memory systems, enabling native visual understanding. Following knowledge distillation principles, each adapter is trained separately for specific memory operationsx2013knowledge extraction, memory update, and memory-augmented generation. Equipped with memory adapters, small models enable accurate on-device memory operations without cloud dependency. On text-only operations, MemLoRA outperforms 10times larger baseline models (e.g., Gemma2-27B) and achieves performance comparable to 60times larger models (e.g., GPT-OSS-120B) on the LoCoMo benchmark. To evaluate visual understanding operations instead, we extend LoCoMo with challenging Visual Question Answering tasks that require direct visual reasoning. On this, our VLM-integrated MemLoRA-V shows massive improvements over caption-based approaches (81.3 vs. 23.7 accuracy) while keeping strong performance in text-based tasks, demonstrating the efficacy of our method in multimodal contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04763</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 12:56:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EMMA: Efficient Multimodal Understanding, Generation, and Editing with a Unified Architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04810</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04810.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin He, Longhui Wei, Jianbo Ouyang, Lingxi Xie, Qi Tian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose EMMA, an efficient and unified architecture for multimodal understanding, generation and editing. Specifically, EMMA primarily consists of 1) An efficient autoencoder with a 32x compression ratio, which significantly reduces the number of tokens required for generation. This also ensures the training balance between understanding and generation tasks by applying the same compression ratio to images. 2) Channel-wise concatenation instead of token-wise concatenation among visual understanding and generation tokens, which further reduces the visual tokens in unified architectures. 3) A shared-and-decoupled network that enables mutual improvements across tasks while meeting the task-specific modeling requirements. 4) A mixture-of-experts mechanism adopted for visual understanding encoder, which substantially improves perceptual capabilities with a few parameters increase. Extensive experiments have shown that EMMA-4B can significantly outperform state-of-the-art unified multimodal approaches (e.g., BAGEL-7B) in both efficiency and performance, while also achieving competitive results compared to recent multimodal understanding and generation experts (e.g., Qwen3-VL and Qwen-Image). We believe that EMMA lays a solid foundation for the future development of unified multimodal architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04810</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 14:01:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arbitrage: Efficient Reasoning via Advantage-Aware Speculation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05033</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05033.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Monishwaran Maheswaran, Rishabh Tiwari, Yuezhou Hu, Kerem Dilmen, Coleman Hooper, Haocheng Xi, Nicholas Lee, Mehrdad Farajtabar, Michael W. Mahoney, Kurt Keutzer, Amir Gholami&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern Large Language Models achieve impressive reasoning capabilities with long Chain of Thoughts, but they incur substantial computational cost during inference, and this motivates techniques to improve the performance-cost ratio. Among these techniques, Speculative Decoding accelerates inference by employing a fast but inaccurate draft model to autoregressively propose tokens, which are then verified in parallel by a more capable target model. However, due to unnecessary rejections caused by token mismatches in semantically equivalent steps, traditional token-level Speculative Decoding struggles in reasoning tasks. Although recent works have shifted to step-level semantic verification, which improve efficiency by accepting or rejecting entire reasoning steps, existing step-level methods still regenerate many rejected steps with little improvement, wasting valuable target compute. To address this challenge, we propose Arbitrage, a novel step-level speculative generation framework that routes generation dynamically based on the relative advantage between draft and target models. Instead of applying a fixed acceptance threshold, Arbitrage uses a lightweight router trained to predict when the target model is likely to produce a meaningfully better step. This routing approximates an ideal Arbitrage Oracle that always chooses the higher-quality step, achieving near-optimal efficiency-accuracy trade-offs. Across multiple mathematical reasoning benchmarks, Arbitrage consistently surpasses prior step-level Speculative Decoding baselines, reducing inference latency by up to sim2times at matched accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05033</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 17:50:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint 3D Geometry Reconstruction and Motion Generation for 4D Synthesis from a Single Image</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05044</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05044.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanran Zhang, Ziyi Wang, Wenzhao Zheng, Zheng Zhu, Jie Zhou, Jiwen Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating interactive and dynamic 4D scenes from a single static image remains a core challenge. Most existing generate-then-reconstruct and reconstruct-then-generate methods decouple geometry from motion, causing spatiotemporal inconsistencies and poor generalization. To address these, we extend the reconstruct-then-generate framework to jointly perform Motion generation and geometric Reconstruction for 4D Synthesis (MoRe4D). We first introduce TrajScene-60K, a large-scale dataset of 60,000 video samples with dense point trajectories, addressing the scarcity of high-quality 4D scene data. Based on this, we propose a diffusion-based 4D Scene Trajectory Generator (4D-STraG) to jointly generate geometrically consistent and motion-plausible 4D point trajectories. To leverage single-view priors, we design a depth-guided motion normalization strategy and a motion-aware module for effective geometry and dynamics integration. We then propose a 4D View Synthesis Module (4D-ViSM) to render videos with arbitrary camera trajectories from 4D point track representations. Experiments show that MoRe4D generates high-quality 4D scenes with multi-view consistency and rich dynamic details from a single image. Code: https://github.com/Zhangyr2022/MoRe4D.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05044</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 17:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Segments to Scenes: Temporal Understanding in Autonomous Driving via Vision-Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05277</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05277.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kevin Cannons, Saeed Ranjbar Alvar, Mohammad Asiful Hossain, Ahmad Rezaei, Mohsen Gholami, Alireza Heidarikhazaei, Zhou Weimin, Yong Zhang, Mohammad Akbari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Temporal understanding in autonomous driving (AD) remains a significant challenge, even for recent state-of-the-art (SoTA) Vision-Language Models (VLMs). Prior work has introduced datasets and benchmarks aimed at improving temporal reasoning, but these have emphasized other video content, including sports, cooking, and movies. No existing benchmark focuses exclusively on the unique challenges of temporal understanding in ego-centric AD footage. To fill this gap, the Temporal Understanding in Autonomous Driving (TAD) benchmark is presented, which evaluates VLMs' ability to capture the dynamic relationships between actions in AD. TAD comprises nearly 6,000 question-answer (QA) pairs, spanning 7 human-designed tasks. In addition, an evaluation is performed that consists of 9 closed- and open-source generalist models as well as SoTA AD specialist models. When applied to TAD, current SoTA models demonstrated substandard accuracies, largely due to imperfect fine-grained motion understanding. To improve motion understanding and overall accuracy on TAD, two novel training-free solutions are proposed: Scene-CoT, that leverages Chain-of-Thought (CoT) and TCogMap, which incorporates an ego-centric temporal cognitive map. The proposed approaches are integrated with existing VLMs and improve average accuracy on TAD by up to 17.72%. By introducing TAD, benchmarking multiple SoTA models, and proposing effective enhancements, this work aims to catalyze future research on temporal understanding in AD. The benchmark and evaluation code are available at https://huggingface.co/datasets/vbdai/TAD{Hugging Face} and https://github.com/vbdi/tad_bench{Github}, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05277</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 21:57:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LYNX: Learning Dynamic Exits for Confidence-Controlled Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05325</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05325.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ömer Faruk Akgül, Yusuf Hakan Kalaycı, Rajgopal Kannan, Willie Neiswanger, Viktor Prasanna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models achieve strong performance on complex tasks by generating extended chains of thought, but they often "overthink": continuing to reason long after they have enough information to answer correctly. This wastes inference-time compute and can hurt accuracy. Existing attempts to stop early either manipulate decoding with extra sampling and heuristics, rely on auxiliary verifier models, or operate only as post-hoc analysis pipelines without formal guarantees. We introduce LYNX, an online early-exit mechanism that turns a model's own hidden-state awareness into confidence-controlled stopping decisions. LYNX attaches exit decisions to naturally occurring reasoning cues (e.g., "hmm", "wait") during generation, trains a lightweight probe on hidden states at those cue tokens using supervision from forced exits, and wraps the resulting scores in split conformal prediction to obtain distribution-free control over premature exits. Crucially, we train and calibrate this probe once on a generic mathematical corpus and reuse it unchanged across benchmarks, decoding temperatures, and even non-mathematical tasks. Across three model families spanning 1.5B to 32B parameters, a single mathematically trained probe per base model yields strong accuracy--efficiency tradeoffs. On GSM8K, LYNX matches or improves baseline accuracy while reducing tokens by 40--65\%; on MATH-500 it improves accuracy by up to 12 points with roughly 35--60\% fewer tokens; on AIME 2024 it recovers baseline accuracy with more than 50\% token savings; and on CommonsenseQA, a non-math benchmark, it transfers zero-shot with modest accuracy gains and up to 70\% fewer tokens. Compared to state-of-the-art early-exit methods, LYNX offers competitive or superior Pareto frontiers while remaining fully online, requiring no proxy models at inference, and providing explicit, user-tunable confidence guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05325</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:04:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpaceControl: Introducing Test-Time Spatial Control to 3D Generative Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05343</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05343.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Elisabetta Fedele, Francis Engelmann, Ian Huang, Or Litany, Marc Pollefeys, Leonidas Guibas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative methods for 3D assets have recently achieved remarkable progress, yet providing intuitive and precise control over the object geometry remains a key challenge. Existing approaches predominantly rely on text or image prompts, which often fall short in geometric specificity: language can be ambiguous, and images are cumbersome to edit. In this work, we introduce SpaceControl, a training-free test-time method for explicit spatial control of 3D generation. Our approach accepts a wide range of geometric inputs, from coarse primitives to detailed meshes, and integrates seamlessly with modern pre-trained generative models without requiring any additional training. A controllable parameter lets users trade off between geometric fidelity and output realism. Extensive quantitative evaluation and user studies demonstrate that SpaceControl outperforms both training-based and optimization-based baselines in geometric faithfulness while preserving high visual quality. Finally, we present an interactive user interface that enables online editing of superquadrics for direct conversion into textured 3D assets, facilitating practical deployment in creative workflows. Find our project page at https://spacecontrol3d.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05343</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:54:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI &amp; Human Co-Improvement for Safer Co-Superintelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05356</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05356.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jason Weston, Jakob Foerster&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-improvement is a goal currently exciting the field of AI, but is fraught with danger, and may take time to fully achieve. We advocate that a more achievable and better goal for humanity is to maximize co-improvement: collaboration between human researchers and AIs to achieve co-superintelligence. That is, specifically targeting improving AI systems' ability to work with human researchers to conduct AI research together, from ideation to experimentation, in order to both accelerate AI research and to generally endow both AIs and humans with safer superintelligence through their symbiosis. Focusing on including human research improvement in the loop will both get us there faster, and more safely.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05356</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 01:50:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BEAVER: An Efficient Deterministic LLM Verifier</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05439</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05439.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tarun Suresh, Nalin Wadhwa, Debangshu Banerjee, Gagandeep Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language models (LLMs) transition from research prototypes to production systems, practitioners often need reliable methods to verify that model outputs satisfy required constraints. While sampling-based estimates provide an intuition of model behavior, they offer no sound guarantees. We present BEAVER, the first practical framework for computing deterministic, sound probability bounds on LLM constraint satisfaction. Given any prefix-closed semantic constraint, BEAVER systematically explores the generation space using novel token trie and frontier data structures, maintaining provably sound bounds at every iteration. We formalize the verification problem, prove soundness of our approach, and evaluate BEAVER on correctness verification, privacy verification and secure code generation tasks across multiple state of the art LLMs. BEAVER achieves 6 to 8 times tighter probability bounds and identifies 3 to 4 times more high risk instances compared to baseline methods under identical computational budgets, enabling precise characterization and risk assessment that loose bounds or empirical evaluation cannot provide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05439</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 05:34:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TED-4DGS: Temporally Activated and Embedding-based Deformation for 4DGS Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05446</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05446.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng-Yuan Ho, He-Bi Yang, Jui-Chiu Chiang, Yu-Lun Liu, Wen-Hsiao Peng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Building on the success of 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) in static 3D scene representation, its extension to dynamic scenes, commonly referred to as 4DGS or dynamic 3DGS, has attracted increasing attention. However, designing more compact and efficient deformation schemes together with rate-distortion-optimized compression strategies for dynamic 3DGS representations remains an underexplored area. Prior methods either rely on space-time 4DGS with overspecified, short-lived Gaussian primitives or on canonical 3DGS with deformation that lacks explicit temporal control. To address this, we present TED-4DGS, a temporally activated and embedding-based deformation scheme for rate-distortion-optimized 4DGS compression that unifies the strengths of both families. TED-4DGS is built on a sparse anchor-based 3DGS representation. Each canonical anchor is assigned learnable temporal-activation parameters to specify its appearance and disappearance transitions over time, while a lightweight per-anchor temporal embedding queries a shared deformation bank to produce anchor-specific deformation. For rate-distortion compression, we incorporate an implicit neural representation (INR)-based hyperprior to model anchor attribute distributions, along with a channel-wise autoregressive model to capture intra-anchor correlations. With these novel elements, our scheme achieves state-of-the-art rate-distortion performance on several real-world datasets. To the best of our knowledge, this work represents one of the first attempts to pursue a rate-distortion-optimized compression framework for dynamic 3DGS representations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05446</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 05:46:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ProPhy: Progressive Physical Alignment for Dynamic World Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05564</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05564.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijun Wang, Panwen Hu, Jing Wang, Terry Jingchen Zhang, Yuhao Cheng, Long Chen, Yiqiang Yan, Zutao Jiang, Hanhui Li, Xiaodan Liang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in video generation have shown remarkable potential for constructing world simulators. However, current models still struggle to produce physically consistent results, particularly when handling large-scale or complex dynamics. This limitation arises primarily because existing approaches respond isotropically to physical prompts and neglect the fine-grained alignment between generated content and localized physical cues. To address these challenges, we propose ProPhy, a Progressive Physical Alignment Framework that enables explicit physics-aware conditioning and anisotropic generation. ProPhy employs a two-stage Mixture-of-Physics-Experts (MoPE) mechanism for discriminative physical prior extraction, where Semantic Experts infer semantic-level physical principles from textual descriptions, and Refinement Experts capture token-level physical dynamics. This mechanism allows the model to learn fine-grained, physics-aware video representations that better reflect underlying physical laws. Furthermore, we introduce a physical alignment strategy that transfers the physical reasoning capabilities of vision-language models (VLMs) into the Refinement Experts, facilitating a more accurate representation of dynamic physical phenomena. Extensive experiments on physics-aware video generation benchmarks demonstrate that ProPhy produces more realistic, dynamic, and physically coherent results than existing state-of-the-art methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05564</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 09:39:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy Ratio Clipping as a Soft Global Constraint for Stable Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05591</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05591.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenpeng Su, Leiyu Pan, Minxuan Lv, Tiehua Mei, Zijia Lin, Yuntao Li, Wenping Hu, Ruiming Tang, Kun Gai, Guorui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model post-training relies on reinforcement learning to improve model capability and alignment quality. However, the off-policy training paradigm introduces distribution shift, which often pushes the policy beyond the trust region, leading to training instabilities manifested as fluctuations in policy entropy and unstable gradients. Although PPO-Clip mitigates this issue through importance clipping, it still overlooks the global distributional shift of actions. To address these challenges, we propose using the entropy ratio between the current and previous policies as a new global metric that effectively quantifies the relative change in policy exploration throughout updates. Building on this metric, we introduce an Entropy Ratio Clipping (ERC) mechanism that imposes bidirectional constraints on the entropy ratio. This stabilizes policy updates at the global distribution level and compensates for the inability of PPO-clip to regulate probability shifts of un-sampled actions. We integrate ERC into both DAPO and GPPO reinforcement learning algorithms. Experiments across multiple benchmarks show that ERC consistently improves performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05591</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 10:26:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Video Perception: Iterative Evidence Seeking for Agentic Long Video Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05774</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05774.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyang Wang, Honglu Zhou, Shijie Wang, Junnan Li, Caiming Xiong, Silvio Savarese, Mohit Bansal, Michael S. Ryoo, Juan Carlos Niebles&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long video understanding (LVU) is challenging because answering real-world queries often depends on sparse, temporally dispersed cues buried in hours of mostly redundant and irrelevant content. While agentic pipelines improve video reasoning capabilities, prevailing frameworks rely on a query-agnostic captioner to perceive video information, which wastes computation on irrelevant content and blurs fine-grained temporal and spatial information. Motivated by active perception theory, we argue that LVU agents should actively decide what, when, and where to observe, and continuously assess whether the current observation is sufficient to answer the query. We present Active Video Perception (AVP), an evidence-seeking framework that treats the video as an interactive environment and acquires compact, queryrelevant evidence directly from pixels. Concretely, AVP runs an iterative plan-observe-reflect process with MLLM agents. In each round, a planner proposes targeted video interactions, an observer executes them to extract time-stamped evidence, and a reflector evaluates the sufficiency of the evidence for the query, either halting with an answer or triggering further observation. Across five LVU benchmarks, AVP achieves highest performance with significant improvements. Notably, AVP outperforms the best agentic method by 5.7% in average accuracy while only requires 18.4% inference time and 12.4% input tokens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05774</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 15:03:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCAIL: Towards Studio-Grade Character Animation via In-Context Learning of 3D-Consistent Pose Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05905</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05905.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenhao Yan, Sheng Ye, Zhuoyi Yang, Jiayan Teng, ZhenHui Dong, Kairui Wen, Xiaotao Gu, Yong-Jin Liu, Jie Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Achieving character animation that meets studio-grade production standards remains challenging despite recent progress. Existing approaches can transfer motion from a driving video to a reference image, but often fail to preserve structural fidelity and temporal consistency in wild scenarios involving complex motion and cross-identity animations. In this work, we present SCAIL (Studio-grade Character Animation via In-context Learning), a framework designed to address these challenges from two key innovations. First, we propose a novel 3D pose representation, providing a more robust and flexible motion signal. Second, we introduce a full-context pose injection mechanism within a diffusion-transformer architecture, enabling effective spatio-temporal reasoning over full motion sequences. To align with studio-level requirements, we develop a curated data pipeline ensuring both diversity and quality, and establish a comprehensive benchmark for systematic evaluation. Experiments show that SCAIL achieves state-of-the-art performance and advances character animation toward studio-grade reliability and realism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05905</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 17:38:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Models That Know When They Don't Know: Controllable Video Generation with Calibrated Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05927</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05927.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiting Mei, Tenny Yin, Micah Baker, Ola Shorinwa, Anirudha Majumdar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in generative video models have led to significant breakthroughs in high-fidelity video synthesis, specifically in controllable video generation where the generated video is conditioned on text and action inputs, e.g., in instruction-guided video editing and world modeling in robotics. Despite these exceptional capabilities, controllable video models often hallucinate - generating future video frames that are misaligned with physical reality - which raises serious concerns in many tasks such as robot policy evaluation and planning. However, state-of-the-art video models lack the ability to assess and express their confidence, impeding hallucination mitigation. To rigorously address this challenge, we propose C3, an uncertainty quantification (UQ) method for training continuous-scale calibrated controllable video models for dense confidence estimation at the subpatch level, precisely localizing the uncertainty in each generated video frame. Our UQ method introduces three core innovations to empower video models to estimate their uncertainty. First, our method develops a novel framework that trains video models for correctness and calibration via strictly proper scoring rules. Second, we estimate the video model's uncertainty in latent space, avoiding training instability and prohibitive training costs associated with pixel-space approaches. Third, we map the dense latent-space uncertainty to interpretable pixel-level uncertainty in the RGB space for intuitive visualization, providing high-resolution uncertainty heatmaps that identify untrustworthy regions. Through extensive experiments on large-scale robot learning datasets (Bridge and DROID) and real-world evaluations, we demonstrate that our method not only provides calibrated uncertainty estimates within the training distribution, but also enables effective out-of-distribution detection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05927</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 18:06:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EgoEdit: Dataset, Real-Time Streaming Model, and Benchmark for Egocentric Video Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06065</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06065.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runjia Li, Moayed Haji-Ali, Ashkan Mirzaei, Chaoyang Wang, Arpit Sahni, Ivan Skorokhodov, Aliaksandr Siarohin, Tomas Jakab, Junlin Han, Sergey Tulyakov, Philip Torr, Willi Menapace&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We study instruction-guided editing of egocentric videos for interactive AR applications. While recent AI video editors perform well on third-person footage, egocentric views present unique challenges - including rapid egomotion and frequent hand-object interactions - that create a significant domain gap. Moreover, existing offline editing pipelines suffer from high latency, limiting real-time interaction. To address these issues, we present a complete ecosystem for egocentric video editing. First, we construct EgoEditData, a carefully designed and manually curated dataset specifically designed for egocentric editing scenarios, featuring rich hand-object interactions, while explicitly preserving hands. Second, we develop EgoEdit, an instruction-following egocentric video editor that supports real-time streaming inference on a single GPU. Finally, we introduce EgoEditBench, an evaluation suite targeting instruction faithfulness, hand and interaction preservation, and temporal stability under egomotion. Across both egocentric and general editing tasks, EgoEdit produces temporally stable, instruction-faithful results with interactive latency. It achieves clear gains on egocentric editing benchmarks-where existing methods struggle-while maintaining performance comparable to the strongest baselines on general editing tasks. EgoEditData and EgoEditBench will be made public for the research community. See our website at https://snap-research.github.io/EgoEdit&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06065</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 18:57:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EditThinker: Unlocking Iterative Reasoning for Any Image Editor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05965</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05965.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongyu Li, Manyuan Zhang, Dian Zheng, Ziyu Guo, Yimeng Jia, Kaituo Feng, Hao Yu, Yexin Liu, Yan Feng, Peng Pei, Xunliang Cai, Linjiang Huang, Hongsheng Li, Si Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-based image editing has emerged as a prominent research area, which, benefiting from image generation foundation models, have achieved high aesthetic quality, making instruction-following capability the primary challenge. Existing approaches improve instruction adherence via supervised or reinforcement learning, yet single-turn success rates remain limited due to inherent stochasticity and a lack of deliberation. In this work, we propose a deliberative editing framework to 'think' while they edit, which simulates the human cognitive loop by iteratively executing a Think-while-Edit cycle: Critiquing results and Refining instructions , followed by Repeating the generation until satisfactory. Specifically, we train a single MLLM, EditThinker, to act as the reasoning engine of this framework, which jointly produce the critique score, reasoning process, and refined instructions. We employ reinforcement learning to align the EditThinker's thinking with its editing, thereby generating more targeted instruction improvements. Extensive experiments on four benchmarks demonstrate that our approach significantly improves the instruction-following capability of any image editing model by a large margin. We will release our data construction framework, datasets, and models to benefit the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05965</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 18:58:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Training Dynamics in Scale-wise Autoregressive Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06421</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06421.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gengze Zhou, Chongjian Ge, Hao Tan, Feng Liu, Yicong Hong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in autoregressive (AR) generative models have produced increasingly powerful systems for media synthesis. Among them, next-scale prediction has emerged as a popular paradigm, where models generate images in a coarse-to-fine manner. However, scale-wise AR models suffer from exposure bias, which undermines generation quality. We identify two primary causes of this issue: (1) train-test mismatch, where the model must rely on its own imperfect predictions during inference, and (2) imbalance in scale-wise learning difficulty, where certain scales exhibit disproportionately higher optimization complexity. Through a comprehensive analysis of training dynamics, we propose Self-Autoregressive Refinement (SAR) to address these limitations. SAR introduces a Stagger-Scale Rollout (SSR) mechanism that performs lightweight autoregressive rollouts to expose the model to its own intermediate predictions, thereby aligning train-test patterns, and a complementary Contrastive Student-Forcing Loss (CSFL) that provides adequate supervision for self-generated contexts to ensure stable training. Experimental results show that applying SAR to pretrained AR models consistently improves generation quality with minimal computational overhead. For instance, SAR yields a 5.2% FID reduction on FlexVAR-d16 trained on ImageNet 256 within 10 epochs (5 hours on 32xA100 GPUs). Given its efficiency, scalability, and effectiveness, we expect SAR to serve as a reliable post-training method for visual autoregressive generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06421</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:41:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied Referring Expression Comprehension in Human-Robot Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06558</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06558.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Md Mofijul Islam, Alexi Gladstone, Sujan Sarker, Ganesh Nanduru, Md Fahim, Keyan Du, Aman Chadha, Tariq Iqbal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As robots enter human workspaces, there is a crucial need for them to comprehend embodied human instructions, enabling intuitive and fluent human-robot interaction (HRI). However, accurate comprehension is challenging due to a lack of large-scale datasets that capture natural embodied interactions in diverse HRI settings. Existing datasets suffer from perspective bias, single-view collection, inadequate coverage of nonverbal gestures, and a predominant focus on indoor environments. To address these issues, we present the Refer360 dataset, a large-scale dataset of embodied verbal and nonverbal interactions collected across diverse viewpoints in both indoor and outdoor settings. Additionally, we introduce MuRes, a multimodal guided residual module designed to improve embodied referring expression comprehension. MuRes acts as an information bottleneck, extracting salient modality-specific signals and reinforcing them into pre-trained representations to form complementary features for downstream tasks. We conduct extensive experiments on four HRI datasets, including the Refer360 dataset, and demonstrate that current multimodal models fail to capture embodied interactions comprehensively; however, augmenting them with MuRes consistently improves performance. These findings establish Refer360 as a valuable benchmark and exhibit the potential of guided residual learning to advance embodied referring expression comprehension in robots operating within human environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06558</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 20:10:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniSafeBench-MM: A Unified Benchmark and Toolbox for Multimodal Jailbreak Attack-Defense Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06589</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06589.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaojun Jia, Jie Liao, Qi Guo, Teng Ma, Simeng Qin, Ranjie Duan, Tianlin Li, Yihao Huang, Zhitao Zeng, Dongxian Wu, Yiming Li, Wenqi Ren, Xiaochun Cao, Yang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multi-modal large language models (MLLMs) have enabled unified perception-reasoning capabilities, yet these systems remain highly vulnerable to jailbreak attacks that bypass safety alignment and induce harmful behaviors. Existing benchmarks such as JailBreakV-28K, MM-SafetyBench, and HADES provide valuable insights into multi-modal vulnerabilities, but they typically focus on limited attack scenarios, lack standardized defense evaluation, and offer no unified, reproducible toolbox. To address these gaps, we introduce OmniSafeBench-MM, which is a comprehensive toolbox for multi-modal jailbreak attack-defense evaluation. OmniSafeBench-MM integrates 13 representative attack methods, 15 defense strategies, and a diverse dataset spanning 9 major risk domains and 50 fine-grained categories, structured across consultative, imperative, and declarative inquiry types to reflect realistic user intentions. Beyond data coverage, it establishes a three-dimensional evaluation protocol measuring (1) harmfulness, distinguished by a granular, multi-level scale ranging from low-impact individual harm to catastrophic societal threats, (2) intent alignment between responses and queries, and (3) response detail level, enabling nuanced safety-utility analysis. We conduct extensive experiments on 10 open-source and 8 closed-source MLLMs to reveal their vulnerability to multi-modal jailbreak. By unifying data, methodology, and evaluation into an open-source, reproducible platform, OmniSafeBench-MM provides a standardized foundation for future research. The code is released at https://github.com/jiaxiaojunQAQ/OmniSafeBench-MM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06589</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 22:56:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MIND-V: Hierarchical Video Generation for Long-Horizon Robotic Manipulation with RL-based Physical Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06628</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06628.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruicheng Zhang, Mingyang Zhang, Jun Zhou, Zhangrui Guo, Xiaofan Liu, Zunnan Xu, Zhizhou Zhong, Puxin Yan, Haocheng Luo, Xiu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Embodied imitation learning is constrained by the scarcity of diverse, long-horizon robotic manipulation data. Existing video generation models for this domain are limited to synthesizing short clips of simple actions and often rely on manually defined trajectories. To this end, we introduce MIND-V, a hierarchical framework designed to synthesize physically plausible and logically coherent videos of long-horizon robotic manipulation. Inspired by cognitive science, MIND-V bridges high-level reasoning with pixel-level synthesis through three core components: a Semantic Reasoning Hub (SRH) that leverages a pre-trained vision-language model for task planning; a Behavioral Semantic Bridge (BSB) that translates abstract instructions into domain-invariant representations; and a Motor Video Generator (MVG) for conditional video rendering. MIND-V employs Staged Visual Future Rollouts, a test-time optimization strategy to enhance long-horizon robustness. To align the generated videos with physical laws, we introduce a GRPO reinforcement learning post-training phase guided by a novel Physical Foresight Coherence (PFC) reward. PFC leverages the V-JEPA world model to enforce physical plausibility by aligning the predicted and actual dynamic evolutions in the feature space. MIND-V demonstrates state-of-the-art performance in long-horizon robotic manipulation video generation, establishing a scalable and controllable paradigm for embodied data synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06628</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 02:28:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DoVer: Intervention-Driven Auto Debugging for LLM Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06749</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06749.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Ma, Jue Zhang, Fangkai Yang, Yu Kang, Qingwei Lin, Saravan Rajmohan, Dongmei Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM)-based multi-agent systems are challenging to debug because failures often arise from long, branching interaction traces. The prevailing practice is to leverage LLMs for log-based failure localization, attributing errors to a specific agent and step. However, this paradigm has two key limitations: (i) log-only debugging lacks validation, producing untested hypotheses, and (ii) single-step or single-agent attribution is often ill-posed, as we find that multiple distinct interventions can independently repair the failed task. To address the first limitation, we introduce DoVer, an intervention-driven debugging framework, which augments hypothesis generation with active verification through targeted interventions (e.g., editing messages, altering plans). For the second limitation, rather than evaluating on attribution accuracy, we focus on measuring whether the system resolves the failure or makes quantifiable progress toward task success, reflecting a more outcome-oriented view of debugging. Within the Magnetic-One agent framework, on the datasets derived from GAIA and AssistantBench, DoVer flips 18-28% of failed trials into successes, achieves up to 16% milestone progress, and validates or refutes 30-60% of failure hypotheses. DoVer also performs effectively on a different dataset (GSMPlus) and agent framework (AG2), where it recovers 49% of failed trials. These results highlight intervention as a practical mechanism for improving reliability in agentic systems and open opportunities for more robust, scalable debugging methods for LLM-based multi-agent systems. Project website and code will be available at https://aka.ms/DoVer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06749</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 09:23:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Next-Token to Next-Block: A Principled Adaptation Path for Diffusion LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06776</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06776.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuchuan Tian, Yuchen Liang, Jiacheng Sun, Shuo Zhang, Guangwen Yang, Yingte Shu, Sibo Fang, Tianyu Guo, Kai Han, Chao Xu, Hanting Chen, Xinghao Chen, Yunhe Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) excel at generation but dominant autoregressive (AR) decoding is inherently sequential, creating a throughput bottleneck. Diffusion Language Models (DLMs)--especially block-wise variants--enable parallel generation and intra-block bidirectional reasoning, yet training large DLMs from scratch is costly and wastes the knowledge in mature AR checkpoints. Prior "adaptation" attempts either modify logits or randomly grow attention masks to full-sequence diffusion, or simply transplant AR weights into a block-diffusion recipe, leaving a fundamental mismatch between AR causality and block-wise bidirectionality unaddressed. We reframe adaptation as a intra-paradigm path from AR to Block-Diffusion by viewing AR as Block-Diffusion with blocksize=1. Concretely, we design the pathway of adaptation as follows: we use a context-causal attention mask (causal in context, bidirectional only within the active block), an efficient parallel adaptation procedure, an auxiliary AR loss to maximize data utilization and retain pretrained knowledge, and gradual increment of the generation block size. The recipe integrates cleanly with masked block-diffusion and maintains train-inference consistency. Built on these components, NBDiff-7B (Base and Instruct) could inherit the long-context modeling and reasoning capabilities, and achieve state-of-the-art performance among the 7B-class DLMs, delivering strong gains on general-knowledge, math, and code benchmarks over strong baselines. These results demonstrate that principled AR-to-block-diffusion adaptation is an effective and compute-efficient alternative to training DLMs from scratch. Codes: https://github.com/YuchuanTian/NBDiff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06776</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 10:28:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boosting Unsupervised Video Instance Segmentation with Automatic Quality-Guided Self-Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06864</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06864.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaixuan Lu, Mehmet Onurcan Kaya, Dim P. Papadopoulos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video Instance Segmentation (VIS) faces significant annotation challenges due to its dual requirements of pixel-level masks and temporal consistency labels. While recent unsupervised methods like VideoCutLER eliminate optical flow dependencies through synthetic data, they remain constrained by the synthetic-to-real domain gap. We present AutoQ-VIS, a novel unsupervised framework that bridges this gap through quality-guided self-training. Our approach establishes a closed-loop system between pseudo-label generation and automatic quality assessment, enabling progressive adaptation from synthetic to real videos. Experiments demonstrate state-of-the-art performance with 52.6 AP_{50} on YouTubeVIS-2019 val set, surpassing the previous state-of-the-art VideoCutLER by 4.4%, while requiring no human annotations. This demonstrates the viability of quality-aware self-training for unsupervised VIS. We will release the code at https://github.com/wcbup/AutoQ-VIS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06864</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 14:37:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Zero-Shot Reference-to-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06905</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06905.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijian Zhou, Shikun Liu, Haozhe Liu, Haonan Qiu, Zhaochong An, Weiming Ren, Zhiheng Liu, Xiaoke Huang, Kam Woh Ng, Tian Xie, Xiao Han, Yuren Cong, Hang Li, Chuyan Zhu, Aditya Patel, Tao Xiang, Sen He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reference-to-video (R2V) generation aims to synthesize videos that align with a text prompt while preserving the subject identity from reference images. However, current R2V methods are hindered by the reliance on explicit reference image-video-text triplets, whose construction is highly expensive and difficult to scale. We bypass this bottleneck by introducing Saber, a scalable zero-shot framework that requires no explicit R2V data. Trained exclusively on video-text pairs, Saber employs a masked training strategy and a tailored attention-based model design to learn identity-consistent and reference-aware representations. Mask augmentation techniques are further integrated to mitigate copy-paste artifacts common in reference-to-video generation. Moreover, Saber demonstrates remarkable generalization capabilities across a varying number of references and achieves superior performance on the OpenS2V-Eval benchmark compared to methods trained with R2V data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06905</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 16:10:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoVLA: Video Generators Can Be Generalizable Robot Manipulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06963</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06963.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yichao Shen, Fangyun Wei, Zhiying Du, Yaobo Liang, Yan Lu, Jiaolong Yang, Nanning Zheng, Baining Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generalization in robot manipulation is essential for deploying robots in open-world environments and advancing toward artificial general intelligence. While recent Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models leverage large pre-trained understanding models for perception and instruction following, their ability to generalize to novel tasks, objects, and settings remains limited. In this work, we present VideoVLA, a simple approach that explores the potential of transforming large video generation models into robotic VLA manipulators. Given a language instruction and an image, VideoVLA predicts an action sequence as well as the future visual outcomes. Built on a multi-modal Diffusion Transformer, VideoVLA jointly models video, language, and action modalities, using pre-trained video generative models for joint visual and action forecasting. Our experiments show that high-quality imagined futures correlate with reliable action predictions and task success, highlighting the importance of visual imagination in manipulation. VideoVLA demonstrates strong generalization, including imitating other embodiments' skills and handling novel objects. This dual-prediction strategy - forecasting both actions and their visual consequences - explores a paradigm shift in robot learning and unlocks generalization capabilities in manipulation systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06963</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 18:57:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>COREA: Coarse-to-Fine 3D Representation Alignment Between Relightable 3D Gaussians and SDF via Bidirectional 3D-to-3D Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07107</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07107.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaeyoon Lee, Hojoon Jung, Sungtae Hwang, Jihyong Oh, Jongwon Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present COREA, the first unified framework that jointly learns relightable 3D Gaussians and a Signed Distance Field (SDF) for accurate geometry reconstruction and faithful relighting. While recent 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) methods have extended toward mesh reconstruction and physically-based rendering (PBR), their geometry is still learned from 2D renderings, leading to coarse surfaces and unreliable BRDF-lighting decomposition. To address these limitations, COREA introduces a coarse-to-fine bidirectional 3D-to-3D alignment strategy that allows geometric signals to be learned directly in 3D space. Within this strategy, depth provides coarse alignment between the two representations, while depth gradients and normals refine fine-scale structure, and the resulting geometry supports stable BRDF-lighting decomposition. A density-control mechanism further stabilizes Gaussian growth, balancing geometric fidelity with memory efficiency. Experiments on standard benchmarks demonstrate that COREA achieves superior performance in novel-view synthesis, mesh reconstruction, and PBR within a unified framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07107</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 02:41:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SUCCESS-GS: Survey of Compactness and Compression for Efficient Static and Dynamic Gaussian Splatting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07197</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07197.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seokhyun Youn, Soohyun Lee, Geonho Kim, Weeyoung Kwon, Sung-Ho Bae, Jihyong Oh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) has emerged as a powerful explicit representation enabling real-time, high-fidelity 3D reconstruction and novel view synthesis. However, its practical use is hindered by the massive memory and computational demands required to store and render millions of Gaussians. These challenges become even more severe in 4D dynamic scenes. To address these issues, the field of Efficient Gaussian Splatting has rapidly evolved, proposing methods that reduce redundancy while preserving reconstruction quality. This survey provides the first unified overview of efficient 3D and 4D Gaussian Splatting techniques. For both 3D and 4D settings, we systematically categorize existing methods into two major directions, Parameter Compression and Restructuring Compression, and comprehensively summarize the core ideas and methodological trends within each category. We further cover widely used datasets, evaluation metrics, and representative benchmark comparisons. Finally, we discuss current limitations and outline promising research directions toward scalable, compact, and real-time Gaussian Splatting for both static and dynamic 3D scene representation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07197</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 06:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Native Parallel Reasoner: Reasoning in Parallelism via Self-Distilled Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07461</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07461.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tong Wu, Yang Liu, Jun Bai, Zixia Jia, Shuyi Zhang, Ziyong Lin, Yanting Wang, Song-Chun Zhu, Zilong Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 71&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Native Parallel Reasoner (NPR), a teacher-free framework that enables Large Language Models (LLMs) to self-evolve genuine parallel reasoning capabilities. NPR transforms the model from sequential emulation to native parallel cognition through three key innovations: 1) a self-distilled progressive training paradigm that transitions from ``cold-start'' format discovery to strict topological constraints without external supervision; 2) a novel Parallel-Aware Policy Optimization (PAPO) algorithm that optimizes branching policies directly within the execution graph, allowing the model to learn adaptive decomposition via trial and error; and 3) a robust NPR Engine that refactors memory management and flow control of SGLang to enable stable, large-scale parallel RL training. Across eight reasoning benchmarks, NPR trained on Qwen3-4B achieves performance gains of up to 24.5% and inference speedups up to 4.6x. Unlike prior baselines that often fall back to autoregressive decoding, NPR demonstrates 100% genuine parallel execution, establishing a new standard for self-evolving, efficient, and scalable agentic reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07461</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:39:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Video Editing with Temporal Reasoner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07469</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07469.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangpeng Yang, Ji Xie, Yiyuan Yang, Yan Huang, Min Xu, Qiang Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing video editing methods face a critical trade-off: expert models offer precision but rely on task-specific priors like masks, hindering unification; conversely, unified temporal in-context learning models are mask-free but lack explicit spatial cues, leading to weak instruction-to-region mapping and imprecise localization. To resolve this conflict, we propose VideoCoF, a novel Chain-of-Frames approach inspired by Chain-of-Thought reasoning. VideoCoF enforces a ``see, reason, then edit" procedure by compelling the video diffusion model to first predict reasoning tokens (edit-region latents) before generating the target video tokens. This explicit reasoning step removes the need for user-provided masks while achieving precise instruction-to-region alignment and fine-grained video editing. Furthermore, we introduce a RoPE alignment strategy that leverages these reasoning tokens to ensure motion alignment and enable length extrapolation beyond the training duration. We demonstrate that with a minimal data cost of only 50k video pairs, VideoCoF achieves state-of-the-art performance on VideoCoF-Bench, validating the efficiency and effectiveness of our approach. Our code, weight, data are available at https://github.com/knightyxp/VideoCoF.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07469</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:50:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Real: Imaginary Extension of Rotary Position Embeddings for Long-Context LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07525</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07525.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoran Liu, Yuerong Song, Zhigeng Liu, Zengfeng Huang, Qipeng Guo, Zhaoxiang Liu, Shiguo Lian, Ziwei He, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Rotary Position Embeddings (RoPE) have become a standard for encoding sequence order in Large Language Models (LLMs) by applying rotations to query and key vectors in the complex plane. Standard implementations, however, utilize only the real component of the complex-valued dot product for attention score calculation. This simplification discards the imaginary component, which contains valuable phase information, leading to a potential loss of relational details crucial for modeling long-context dependencies. In this paper, we propose an extension that re-incorporates this discarded imaginary component. Our method leverages the full complex-valued representation to create a dual-component attention score. We theoretically and empirically demonstrate that this approach enhances the modeling of long-context dependencies by preserving more positional information. Furthermore, evaluations on a suite of long-context language modeling benchmarks show that our method consistently improves performance over the standard RoPE, with the benefits becoming more significant as context length increases. The code is available at https://github.com/OpenMOSS/rope_pp.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07525</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongCat-Image Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07584</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07584.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Meituan LongCat Team, Hanghang Ma, Haoxian Tan, Jiale Huang, Junqiang Wu, Jun-Yan He, Lishuai Gao, Songlin Xiao, Xiaoming Wei, Xiaoqi Ma, Xunliang Cai, Yayong Guan, Jie Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce LongCat-Image, a pioneering open-source and bilingual (Chinese-English) foundation model for image generation, designed to address core challenges in multilingual text rendering, photorealism, deployment efficiency, and developer accessibility prevalent in current leading models. 1) We achieve this through rigorous data curation strategies across the pre-training, mid-training, and SFT stages, complemented by the coordinated use of curated reward models during the RL phase. This strategy establishes the model as a new state-of-the-art (SOTA), delivering superior text-rendering capabilities and remarkable photorealism, and significantly enhancing aesthetic quality. 2) Notably, it sets a new industry standard for Chinese character rendering. By supporting even complex and rare characters, it outperforms both major open-source and commercial solutions in coverage, while also achieving superior accuracy. 3) The model achieves remarkable efficiency through its compact design. With a core diffusion model of only 6B parameters, it is significantly smaller than the nearly 20B or larger Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architectures common in the field. This ensures minimal VRAM usage and rapid inference, significantly reducing deployment costs. Beyond generation, LongCat-Image also excels in image editing, achieving SOTA results on standard benchmarks with superior editing consistency compared to other open-source works. 4) To fully empower the community, we have established the most comprehensive open-source ecosystem to date. We are releasing not only multiple model versions for text-to-image and image editing, including checkpoints after mid-training and post-training stages, but also the entire toolchain of training procedure. We believe that the openness of LongCat-Image will provide robust support for developers and researchers, pushing the frontiers of visual content creation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07584</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 14:26:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepCode: Open Agentic Coding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07921</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07921.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zongwei Li, Zhonghang Li, Zirui Guo, Xubin Ren, Chao Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have given rise to powerful coding agents, making it possible for code assistants to evolve into code engineers. However, existing methods still face significant challenges in achieving high-fidelity document-to-codebase synthesis--such as scientific papers to code--primarily due to a fundamental conflict between information overload and the context bottlenecks of LLMs. In this work, we introduce DeepCode, a fully autonomous framework that fundamentally addresses this challenge through principled information-flow management. By treating repository synthesis as a channel optimization problem, DeepCode seamlessly orchestrates four information operations to maximize task-relevant signals under finite context budgets: source compression via blueprint distillation, structured indexing using stateful code memory, conditional knowledge injection via retrieval-augmented generation, and closed-loop error correction. Extensive evaluations on the PaperBench benchmark demonstrate that DeepCode achieves state-of-the-art performance, decisively outperforming leading commercial agents such as Cursor and Claude Code, and crucially, surpassing PhD-level human experts from top institutes on key reproduction metrics. By systematically transforming paper specifications into production-grade implementations comparable to human expert quality, this work establishes new foundations for autonomous scientific reproduction that can accelerate research evaluation and discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07921</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 16:07:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distribution Matching Variational AutoEncoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07778</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07778.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sen Ye, Jianning Pei, Mengde Xu, Shuyang Gu, Chunyu Wang, Liwei Wang, Han Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Most visual generative models compress images into a latent space before applying diffusion or autoregressive modelling. Yet, existing approaches such as VAEs and foundation model aligned encoders implicitly constrain the latent space without explicitly shaping its distribution, making it unclear which types of distributions are optimal for modeling. We introduce Distribution-Matching VAE (DMVAE), which explicitly aligns the encoder's latent distribution with an arbitrary reference distribution via a distribution matching constraint. This generalizes beyond the Gaussian prior of conventional VAEs, enabling alignment with distributions derived from self-supervised features, diffusion noise, or other prior distributions. With DMVAE, we can systematically investigate which latent distributions are more conducive to modeling, and we find that SSL-derived distributions provide an excellent balance between reconstruction fidelity and modeling efficiency, reaching gFID equals 3.2 on ImageNet with only 64 training epochs. Our results suggest that choosing a suitable latent distribution structure (achieved via distribution-level alignment), rather than relying on fixed priors, is key to bridging the gap between easy-to-model latents and high-fidelity image synthesis. Code is avaliable at https://github.com/sen-ye/dmvae.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07778</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 17:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Interplay of Pre-Training, Mid-Training, and RL on Reasoning Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07783</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07783.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Charlie Zhang, Graham Neubig, Xiang Yue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reinforcement learning (RL) techniques have yielded impressive reasoning improvements in language models, yet it remains unclear whether post-training truly extends a model's reasoning ability beyond what it acquires during pre-training. A central challenge is the lack of control in modern training pipelines: large-scale pre-training corpora are opaque, mid-training is often underexamined, and RL objectives interact with unknown prior knowledge in complex ways. To resolve this ambiguity, we develop a fully controlled experimental framework that isolates the causal contributions of pre-training, mid-training, and RL-based post-training. Our approach employs synthetic reasoning tasks with explicit atomic operations, parseable step-by-step reasoning traces, and systematic manipulation of training distributions. We evaluate models along two axes: extrapolative generalization to more complex compositions and contextual generalization across surface contexts. Using this framework, we reconcile competing views on RL's effectiveness. We show that: 1) RL produces true capability gains (pass@128) only when pre-training leaves sufficient headroom and when RL data target the model's edge of competence, tasks at the boundary that are difficult but not yet out of reach. 2) Contextual generalization requires minimal yet sufficient pre-training exposure, after which RL can reliably transfer. 3) Mid-training significantly enhances performance under fixed compute compared with RL only, demonstrating its central but underexplored role in training pipelines. 4) Process-level rewards reduce reward hacking and improve reasoning fidelity. Together, these results clarify the interplay between pre-training, mid-training, and RL, offering a foundation for understanding and improving reasoning LM training strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07783</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OneStory: Coherent Multi-Shot Video Generation with Adaptive Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07802</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07802.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaochong An, Menglin Jia, Haonan Qiu, Zijian Zhou, Xiaoke Huang, Zhiheng Liu, Weiming Ren, Kumara Kahatapitiya, Ding Liu, Sen He, Chenyang Zhang, Tao Xiang, Fanny Yang, Serge Belongie, Tian Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Storytelling in real-world videos often unfolds through multiple shots -- discontinuous yet semantically connected clips that together convey a coherent narrative. However, existing multi-shot video generation (MSV) methods struggle to effectively model long-range cross-shot context, as they rely on limited temporal windows or single keyframe conditioning, leading to degraded performance under complex narratives. In this work, we propose OneStory, enabling global yet compact cross-shot context modeling for consistent and scalable narrative generation. OneStory reformulates MSV as a next-shot generation task, enabling autoregressive shot synthesis while leveraging pretrained image-to-video (I2V) models for strong visual conditioning. We introduce two key modules: a Frame Selection module that constructs a semantically-relevant global memory based on informative frames from prior shots, and an Adaptive Conditioner that performs importance-guided patchification to generate compact context for direct conditioning. We further curate a high-quality multi-shot dataset with referential captions to mirror real-world storytelling patterns, and design effective training strategies under the next-shot paradigm. Finetuned from a pretrained I2V model on our curated 60K dataset, OneStory achieves state-of-the-art narrative coherence across diverse and complex scenes in both text- and image-conditioned settings, enabling controllable and immersive long-form video storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07802</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:32:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group Representational Position Encoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07805</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07805.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Zhang, Zixiang Chen, Yifeng Liu, Zhen Qin, Huizhuo Yuan, Kangping Xu, Yang Yuan, Quanquan Gu, Andrew Chi-Chih Yao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present GRAPE (Group RepresentAtional Position Encoding), a unified framework for positional encoding based on group actions. GRAPE brings together two families of mechanisms: (i) multiplicative rotations (Multiplicative GRAPE) in SO(d) and (ii) additive logit biases (Additive GRAPE) arising from unipotent actions in the general linear group GL. In Multiplicative GRAPE, a position n in Z (or t in R) acts as G(n)=exp(n,ω,L) with a rank-2 skew generator L in R^{d times d}, yielding a relative, compositional, norm-preserving map with a closed-form matrix exponential. RoPE is recovered exactly when the d/2 planes are the canonical coordinate pairs with log-uniform spectrum. Learned commuting subspaces and compact non-commuting mixtures strictly extend this geometry to capture cross-subspace feature coupling at O(d) and O(r d) cost per head, respectively. In Additive GRAPE, additive logits arise as rank-1 (or low-rank) unipotent actions, recovering ALiBi and the Forgetting Transformer (FoX) as exact special cases while preserving an exact relative law and streaming cacheability. Altogether, GRAPE supplies a principled design space for positional geometry in long-context models, subsuming RoPE and ALiBi as special cases. Project Page: https://github.com/model-architectures/GRAPE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07805</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:39:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-view Pyramid Transformer: Look Coarser to See Broader</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07806</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07806.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gyeongjin Kang, Seungkwon Yang, Seungtae Nam, Younggeun Lee, Jungwoo Kim, Eunbyung Park&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose Multi-view Pyramid Transformer (MVP), a scalable multi-view transformer architecture that directly reconstructs large 3D scenes from tens to hundreds of images in a single forward pass. Drawing on the idea of ``looking broader to see the whole, looking finer to see the details," MVP is built on two core design principles: 1) a local-to-global inter-view hierarchy that gradually broadens the model's perspective from local views to groups and ultimately the full scene, and 2) a fine-to-coarse intra-view hierarchy that starts from detailed spatial representations and progressively aggregates them into compact, information-dense tokens. This dual hierarchy achieves both computational efficiency and representational richness, enabling fast reconstruction of large and complex scenes. We validate MVP on diverse datasets and show that, when coupled with 3D Gaussian Splatting as the underlying 3D representation, it achieves state-of-the-art generalizable reconstruction quality while maintaining high efficiency and scalability across a wide range of view configurations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07806</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:39:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One Layer Is Enough: Adapting Pretrained Visual Encoders for Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07829</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07829.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuan Gao, Chen Chen, Tianrong Chen, Jiatao Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual generative models (e.g., diffusion models) typically operate in compressed latent spaces to balance training efficiency and sample quality. In parallel, there has been growing interest in leveraging high-quality pre-trained visual representations, either by aligning them inside VAEs or directly within the generative model. However, adapting such representations remains challenging due to fundamental mismatches between understanding-oriented features and generation-friendly latent spaces. Representation encoders benefit from high-dimensional latents that capture diverse hypotheses for masked regions, whereas generative models favor low-dimensional latents that must faithfully preserve injected noise. This discrepancy has led prior work to rely on complex objectives and architectures. In this work, we propose FAE (Feature Auto-Encoder), a simple yet effective framework that adapts pre-trained visual representations into low-dimensional latents suitable for generation using as little as a single attention layer, while retaining sufficient information for both reconstruction and understanding. The key is to couple two separate deep decoders: one trained to reconstruct the original feature space, and a second that takes the reconstructed features as input for image generation. FAE is generic; it can be instantiated with a variety of self-supervised encoders (e.g., DINO, SigLIP) and plugged into two distinct generative families: diffusion models and normalizing flows. Across class-conditional and text-to-image benchmarks, FAE achieves strong performance. For example, on ImageNet 256x256, our diffusion model with CFG attains a near state-of-the-art FID of 1.29 (800 epochs) and 1.70 (80 epochs). Without CFG, FAE reaches the state-of-the-art FID of 1.48 (800 epochs) and 2.08 (80 epochs), demonstrating both high quality and fast learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07829</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:57:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UnityVideo: Unified Multi-Modal Multi-Task Learning for Enhancing World-Aware Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07831</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07831.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiehui Huang, Yuechen Zhang, Xu He, Yuan Gao, Zhi Cen, Bin Xia, Yan Zhou, Xin Tao, Pengfei Wan, Jiaya Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent video generation models demonstrate impressive synthesis capabilities but remain limited by single-modality conditioning, constraining their holistic world understanding. This stems from insufficient cross-modal interaction and limited modal diversity for comprehensive world knowledge representation. To address these limitations, we introduce UnityVideo, a unified framework for world-aware video generation that jointly learns across multiple modalities (segmentation masks, human skeletons, DensePose, optical flow, and depth maps) and training paradigms. Our approach features two core components: (1) dynamic noising to unify heterogeneous training paradigms, and (2) a modality switcher with an in-context learner that enables unified processing via modular parameters and contextual learning. We contribute a large-scale unified dataset with 1.3M samples. Through joint optimization, UnityVideo accelerates convergence and significantly enhances zero-shot generalization to unseen data. We demonstrate that UnityVideo achieves superior video quality, consistency, and improved alignment with physical world constraints. Code and data can be found at: https://github.com/dvlab-research/UnityVideo&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07831</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:59:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relational Visual Similarity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07833</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07833.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Thao Nguyen, Sicheng Mo, Krishna Kumar Singh, Yilin Wang, Jing Shi, Nicholas Kolkin, Eli Shechtman, Yong Jae Lee, Yuheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humans do not just see attribute similarity -- we also see relational similarity. An apple is like a peach because both are reddish fruit, but the Earth is also like a peach: its crust, mantle, and core correspond to the peach's skin, flesh, and pit. This ability to perceive and recognize relational similarity, is arguable by cognitive scientist to be what distinguishes humans from other species. Yet, all widely used visual similarity metrics today (e.g., LPIPS, CLIP, DINO) focus solely on perceptual attribute similarity and fail to capture the rich, often surprising relational similarities that humans perceive. How can we go beyond the visible content of an image to capture its relational properties? How can we bring images with the same relational logic closer together in representation space? To answer these questions, we first formulate relational image similarity as a measurable problem: two images are relationally similar when their internal relations or functions among visual elements correspond, even if their visual attributes differ. We then curate 114k image-caption dataset in which the captions are anonymized -- describing the underlying relational logic of the scene rather than its surface content. Using this dataset, we finetune a Vision-Language model to measure the relational similarity between images. This model serves as the first step toward connecting images by their underlying relational structure rather than their visible appearance. Our study shows that while relational similarity has a lot of real-world applications, existing image similarity models fail to capture it -- revealing a critical gap in visual computing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07833</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voxify3D: Pixel Art Meets Volumetric Rendering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07834</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07834.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi-Chuan Huang, Jiewen Chan, Hao-Jen Chien, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Voxel art is a distinctive stylization widely used in games and digital media, yet automated generation from 3D meshes remains challenging due to conflicting requirements of geometric abstraction, semantic preservation, and discrete color coherence. Existing methods either over-simplify geometry or fail to achieve the pixel-precise, palette-constrained aesthetics of voxel art. We introduce Voxify3D, a differentiable two-stage framework bridging 3D mesh optimization with 2D pixel art supervision. Our core innovation lies in the synergistic integration of three components: (1) orthographic pixel art supervision that eliminates perspective distortion for precise voxel-pixel alignment; (2) patch-based CLIP alignment that preserves semantics across discretization levels; (3) palette-constrained Gumbel-Softmax quantization enabling differentiable optimization over discrete color spaces with controllable palette strategies. This integration addresses fundamental challenges: semantic preservation under extreme discretization, pixel-art aesthetics through volumetric rendering, and end-to-end discrete optimization. Experiments show superior performance (37.12 CLIP-IQA, 77.90\% user preference) across diverse characters and controllable abstraction (2-8 colors, 20x-50x resolutions). Project page: https://yichuanh.github.io/Voxify-3D/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07834</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving Source Video Realism: High-Fidelity Face Swapping for Cinematic Quality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07951</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07951.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zekai Luo, Zongze Du, Zhouhang Zhu, Hao Zhong, Muzhi Zhu, Wen Wang, Yuling Xi, Chenchen Jing, Hao Chen, Chunhua Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video face swapping is crucial in film and entertainment production, where achieving high fidelity and temporal consistency over long and complex video sequences remains a significant challenge. Inspired by recent advances in reference-guided image editing, we explore whether rich visual attributes from source videos can be similarly leveraged to enhance both fidelity and temporal coherence in video face swapping. Building on this insight, this work presents LivingSwap, the first video reference guided face swapping model. Our approach employs keyframes as conditioning signals to inject the target identity, enabling flexible and controllable editing. By combining keyframe conditioning with video reference guidance, the model performs temporal stitching to ensure stable identity preservation and high-fidelity reconstruction across long video sequences. To address the scarcity of data for reference-guided training, we construct a paired face-swapping dataset, Face2Face, and further reverse the data pairs to ensure reliable ground-truth supervision. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method achieves state-of-the-art results, seamlessly integrating the target identity with the source video's expressions, lighting, and motion, while significantly reducing manual effort in production workflows. Project webpage: https://aim-uofa.github.io/LivingSwap&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07951</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 19:00:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Unified Models: A Service-Oriented Approach to Low Latency, Context Aware Phonemization for Real Time TTS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08006</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08006.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mahta Fetrat, Donya Navabi, Zahra Dehghanian, Morteza Abolghasemi, Hamid R. Rabiee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Lightweight, real-time text-to-speech systems are crucial for accessibility. However, the most efficient TTS models often rely on lightweight phonemizers that struggle with context-dependent challenges. In contrast, more advanced phonemizers with a deeper linguistic understanding typically incur high computational costs, which prevents real-time performance.   This paper examines the trade-off between phonemization quality and inference speed in G2P-aided TTS systems, introducing a practical framework to bridge this gap. We propose lightweight strategies for context-aware phonemization and a service-oriented TTS architecture that executes these modules as independent services. This design decouples heavy context-aware components from the core TTS engine, effectively breaking the latency barrier and enabling real-time use of high-quality phonemization models. Experimental results confirm that the proposed system improves pronunciation soundness and linguistic accuracy while maintaining real-time responsiveness, making it well-suited for offline and end-device TTS applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 19:49:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TreeGRPO: Tree-Advantage GRPO for Online RL Post-Training of Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08153</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08153.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zheng Ding, Weirui Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) post-training is crucial for aligning generative models with human preferences, but its prohibitive computational cost remains a major barrier to widespread adoption. We introduce TreeGRPO, a novel RL framework that dramatically improves training efficiency by recasting the denoising process as a search tree. From shared initial noise samples, TreeGRPO strategically branches to generate multiple candidate trajectories while efficiently reusing their common prefixes. This tree-structured approach delivers three key advantages: (1) High sample efficiency, achieving better performance under same training samples (2) Fine-grained credit assignment via reward backpropagation that computes step-specific advantages, overcoming the uniform credit assignment limitation of trajectory-based methods, and (3) Amortized computation where multi-child branching enables multiple policy updates per forward pass. Extensive experiments on both diffusion and flow-based models demonstrate that TreeGRPO achieves 2.4times faster training while establishing a superior Pareto frontier in the efficiency-reward trade-off space. Our method consistently outperforms GRPO baselines across multiple benchmarks and reward models, providing a scalable and effective pathway for RL-based visual generative model alignment. The project website is available at treegrpo.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08153</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 01:17:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ground Slow, Move Fast: A Dual-System Foundation Model for Generalizable Vision-and-Language Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08186</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08186.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Meng Wei, Chenyang Wan, Jiaqi Peng, Xiqian Yu, Yuqiang Yang, Delin Feng, Wenzhe Cai, Chenming Zhu, Tai Wang, Jiangmiao Pang, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While recent large vision-language models (VLMs) have improved generalization in vision-language navigation (VLN), existing methods typically rely on end-to-end pipelines that map vision-language inputs directly to short-horizon discrete actions. Such designs often produce fragmented motions, incur high latency, and struggle with real-world challenges like dynamic obstacle avoidance. We propose DualVLN, the first dual-system VLN foundation model that synergistically integrates high-level reasoning with low-level action execution. System 2, a VLM-based global planner, "grounds slowly" by predicting mid-term waypoint goals via image-grounded reasoning. System 1, a lightweight, multi-modal conditioning Diffusion Transformer policy, "moves fast" by leveraging both explicit pixel goals and latent features from System 2 to generate smooth and accurate trajectories. The dual-system design enables robust real-time control and adaptive local decision-making in complex, dynamic environments. By decoupling training, the VLM retains its generalization, while System 1 achieves interpretable and effective local navigation. DualVLN outperforms prior methods across all VLN benchmarks and real-world experiments demonstrate robust long-horizon planning and real-time adaptability in dynamic environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08186</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 02:29:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenSubject: Leveraging Video-Derived Identity and Diversity Priors for Subject-driven Image Generation and Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08294</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08294.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yexin Liu, Manyuan Zhang, Yueze Wang, Hongyu Li, Dian Zheng, Weiming Zhang, Changsheng Lu, Xunliang Cai, Yan Feng, Peng Pei, Harry Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the promising progress in subject-driven image generation, current models often deviate from the reference identities and struggle in complex scenes with multiple subjects. To address this challenge, we introduce OpenSubject, a video-derived large-scale corpus with 2.5M samples and 4.35M images for subject-driven generation and manipulation. The dataset is built with a four-stage pipeline that exploits cross-frame identity priors. (i) Video Curation. We apply resolution and aesthetic filtering to obtain high-quality clips. (ii) Cross-Frame Subject Mining and Pairing. We utilize vision-language model (VLM)-based category consensus, local grounding, and diversity-aware pairing to select image pairs. (iii) Identity-Preserving Reference Image Synthesis. We introduce segmentation map-guided outpainting to synthesize the input images for subject-driven generation and box-guided inpainting to generate input images for subject-driven manipulation, together with geometry-aware augmentations and irregular boundary erosion. (iv) Verification and Captioning. We utilize a VLM to validate synthesized samples, re-synthesize failed samples based on stage (iii), and then construct short and long captions. In addition, we introduce a benchmark covering subject-driven generation and manipulation, and then evaluate identity fidelity, prompt adherence, manipulation consistency, and background consistency with a VLM judge. Extensive experiments show that training with OpenSubject improves generation and manipulation performance, particularly in complex scenes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08294</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 06:49:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Science of Scaling Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08296</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08296.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yubin Kim, Ken Gu, Chanwoo Park, Chunjong Park, Samuel Schmidgall, A. Ali Heydari, Yao Yan, Zhihan Zhang, Yuchen Zhuang, Mark Malhotra, Paul Pu Liang, Hae Won Park, Yuzhe Yang, Xuhai Xu, Yilun Du, Shwetak Patel, Tim Althoff, Daniel McDuff, Xin Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agents, language model (LM)-based systems that are capable of reasoning, planning, and acting are becoming the dominant paradigm for real-world AI applications. Despite this widespread adoption, the principles that determine their performance remain underexplored, leaving practitioners to rely on heuristics rather than principled design choices. We address this gap by deriving quantitative scaling principles for agent systems. We evaluate this across four diverse benchmarks: Finance-Agent, BrowseComp-Plus, PlanCraft, and Workbench. Using five canonical architectures (Single, Independent, Centralized, Decentralized, Hybrid) instantiated across three LLM families, we perform a controlled evaluation spanning 180 configurations with standardized tools and token budgets. We derive a predictive model using empirical coordination metrics, including efficiency, overhead, error amplification, and redundancy, that achieves cross-validated R^2=0.513. We identify three dominant effects: (1) a tool-coordination trade-off: under fixed computational budgets, tool-heavy tasks suffer disproportionately from multi-agent overhead. (2) a capability saturation: coordination yields diminishing or negative returns (beta=-0.408, p&lt;0.001) once single-agent baselines exceed ~45%. (3) topology-dependent error amplification: independent agents amplify errors 17.2x through unchecked propagation, while centralized coordination contains this to 4.4x. Centralized coordination improves performance by 80.9% on parallelizable tasks like financial reasoning, while decentralized coordination excels on dynamic web navigation (+9.2% vs. +0.2%). Yet for sequential reasoning tasks, all multi-agent variants degraded performance by 39-70%. The framework predicts the optimal coordination strategy for 87% of held-out configurations, providing a predictive principle of agentic scaling based on measurable task properties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08296</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 06:52:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terrain Diffusion: A Diffusion-Based Successor to Perlin Noise in Infinite, Real-Time Terrain Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08309</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08309.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Goslin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; For decades, procedural worlds have been built on procedural noise functions such as Perlin noise, which are fast and infinite, yet fundamentally limited in realism and large-scale coherence. We introduce Terrain Diffusion, an AI-era successor to Perlin noise that bridges the fidelity of diffusion models with the properties that made procedural noise indispensable: seamless infinite extent, seed-consistency, and constant-time random access. At its core is InfiniteDiffusion, a novel algorithm for infinite generation, enabling seamless, real-time synthesis of boundless landscapes. A hierarchical stack of diffusion models couples planetary context with local detail, while a compact Laplacian encoding stabilizes outputs across Earth-scale dynamic ranges. An open-source infinite-tensor framework supports constant-memory manipulation of unbounded tensors, and few-step consistency distillation enables efficient generation. Together, these components establish diffusion models as a practical foundation for procedural world generation, capable of synthesizing entire planets coherently, controllably, and without limits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08309</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 07:10:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TrackingWorld: World-centric Monocular 3D Tracking of Almost All Pixels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08358</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08358.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiahao Lu, Weitao Xiong, Jiacheng Deng, Peng Li, Tianyu Huang, Zhiyang Dou, Cheng Lin, Sai-Kit Yeung, Yuan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Monocular 3D tracking aims to capture the long-term motion of pixels in 3D space from a single monocular video and has witnessed rapid progress in recent years. However, we argue that the existing monocular 3D tracking methods still fall short in separating the camera motion from foreground dynamic motion and cannot densely track newly emerging dynamic subjects in the videos. To address these two limitations, we propose TrackingWorld, a novel pipeline for dense 3D tracking of almost all pixels within a world-centric 3D coordinate system. First, we introduce a tracking upsampler that efficiently lifts the arbitrary sparse 2D tracks into dense 2D tracks. Then, to generalize the current tracking methods to newly emerging objects, we apply the upsampler to all frames and reduce the redundancy of 2D tracks by eliminating the tracks in overlapped regions. Finally, we present an efficient optimization-based framework to back-project dense 2D tracks into world-centric 3D trajectories by estimating the camera poses and the 3D coordinates of these 2D tracks. Extensive evaluations on both synthetic and real-world datasets demonstrate that our system achieves accurate and dense 3D tracking in a world-centric coordinate frame.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08358</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 08:35:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAM-Body4D: Training-Free 4D Human Body Mesh Recovery from Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08406</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08406.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingqi Gao, Yunqi Miao, Jungong Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human Mesh Recovery (HMR) aims to reconstruct 3D human pose and shape from 2D observations and is fundamental to human-centric understanding in real-world scenarios. While recent image-based HMR methods such as SAM 3D Body achieve strong robustness on in-the-wild images, they rely on per-frame inference when applied to videos, leading to temporal inconsistency and degraded performance under occlusions. We address these issues without extra training by leveraging the inherent human continuity in videos. We propose SAM-Body4D, a training-free framework for temporally consistent and occlusion-robust HMR from videos. We first generate identity-consistent masklets using a promptable video segmentation model, then refine them with an Occlusion-Aware module to recover missing regions. The refined masklets guide SAM 3D Body to produce consistent full-body mesh trajectories, while a padding-based parallel strategy enables efficient multi-human inference. Experimental results demonstrate that SAM-Body4D achieves improved temporal stability and robustness in challenging in-the-wild videos, without any retraining. Our code and demo are available at: https://github.com/gaomingqi/sam-body4d.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08406</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 09:37:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visionary: The World Model Carrier Built on WebGPU-Powered Gaussian Splatting Platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08478</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08478.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuning Gong, Yifei Liu, Yifan Zhan, Muyao Niu, Xueying Li, Yuanjun Liao, Jiaming Chen, Yuanyuan Gao, Jiaqi Chen, Minming Chen, Li Zhou, Yuning Zhang, Wei Wang, Xiaoqing Hou, Huaxi Huang, Shixiang Tang, Le Ma, Dingwen Zhang, Xue Yang, Junchi Yan, Yanchi Zhang, Yinqiang Zheng, Xiao Sun, Zhihang Zhong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Neural rendering, particularly 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS), has evolved rapidly and become a key component for building world models. However, existing viewer solutions remain fragmented, heavy, or constrained by legacy pipelines, resulting in high deployment friction and limited support for dynamic content and generative models. In this work, we present Visionary, an open, web-native platform for real-time various Gaussian Splatting and meshes rendering. Built on an efficient WebGPU renderer with per-frame ONNX inference, Visionary enables dynamic neural processing while maintaining a lightweight, "click-to-run" browser experience. It introduces a standardized Gaussian Generator contract, which not only supports standard 3DGS rendering but also allows plug-and-play algorithms to generate or update Gaussians each frame. Such inference also enables us to apply feedforward generative post-processing. The platform further offers a plug in three.js library with a concise TypeScript API for seamless integration into existing web applications. Experiments show that, under identical 3DGS assets, Visionary achieves superior rendering efficiency compared to current Web viewers due to GPU-based primitive sorting. It already supports multiple variants, including MLP-based 3DGS, 4DGS, neural avatars, and style transformation or enhancement networks. By unifying inference and rendering directly in the browser, Visionary significantly lowers the barrier to reproduction, comparison, and deployment of 3DGS-family methods, serving as a unified World Model Carrier for both reconstructive and generative paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08478</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 10:54:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking with Images via Self-Calling Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08511</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08511.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenxi Yang, Yuzhong Zhao, Fang Wan, Qixiang Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Thinking-with-images paradigms have showcased remarkable visual reasoning capability by integrating visual information as dynamic elements into the Chain-of-Thought (CoT). However, optimizing interleaved multimodal CoT (iMCoT) through reinforcement learning remains challenging, as it relies on scarce high-quality reasoning data. In this study, we propose Self-Calling Chain-of-Thought (sCoT), a novel visual reasoning paradigm that reformulates iMCoT as a language-only CoT with self-calling. Specifically, a main agent decomposes the complex visual reasoning task to atomic subtasks and invokes its virtual replicas, i.e. parameter-sharing subagents, to solve them in isolated context. sCoT enjoys substantial training effectiveness and efficiency, as it requires no explicit interleaving between modalities. sCoT employs group-relative policy optimization to reinforce effective reasoning behavior to enhance optimization. Experiments on HR-Bench 4K show that sCoT improves the overall reasoning performance by up to 1.9% with sim 75% fewer GPU hours compared to strong baseline approaches. Code is available at https://github.com/YWenxi/think-with-images-through-self-calling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08511</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:53:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BrainExplore: Large-Scale Discovery of Interpretable Visual Representations in the Human Brain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08560</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08560.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Navve Wasserman, Matias Cosarinsky, Yuval Golbari, Aude Oliva, Antonio Torralba, Tamar Rott Shaham, Michal Irani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding how the human brain represents visual concepts, and in which brain regions these representations are encoded, remains a long-standing challenge. Decades of work have advanced our understanding of visual representations, yet brain signals remain large and complex, and the space of possible visual concepts is vast. As a result, most studies remain small-scale, rely on manual inspection, focus on specific regions and properties, and rarely include systematic validation. We present a large-scale, automated framework for discovering and explaining visual representations across the human cortex. Our method comprises two main stages. First, we discover candidate interpretable patterns in fMRI activity through unsupervised, data-driven decomposition methods. Next, we explain each pattern by identifying the set of natural images that most strongly elicit it and generating a natural-language description of their shared visual meaning. To scale this process, we introduce an automated pipeline that tests multiple candidate explanations, assigns quantitative reliability scores, and selects the most consistent description for each voxel pattern. Our framework reveals thousands of interpretable patterns spanning many distinct visual concepts, including fine-grained representations previously unreported.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08560</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 13:01:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Neural Image Signal Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08564</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08564.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mahmoud Afifi, Zhongling Wang, Ran Zhang, Michael S. Brown&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents a modular neural image signal processing (ISP) framework that processes raw inputs and renders high-quality display-referred images. Unlike prior neural ISP designs, our method introduces a high degree of modularity, providing full control over multiple intermediate stages of the rendering process.~This modular design not only achieves high rendering accuracy but also improves scalability, debuggability, generalization to unseen cameras, and flexibility to match different user-preference styles. To demonstrate the advantages of this design, we built a user-interactive photo-editing tool that leverages our neural ISP to support diverse editing operations and picture styles. The tool is carefully engineered to take advantage of the high-quality rendering of our neural ISP and to enable unlimited post-editable re-rendering. Our method is a fully learning-based framework with variants of different capacities, all of moderate size (ranging from ~0.5 M to ~3.9 M parameters for the entire pipeline), and consistently delivers competitive qualitative and quantitative results across multiple test sets. Watch the supplemental video at: https://youtu.be/ByhQjQSjxVM&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08564</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 13:04:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wan-Move: Motion-controllable Video Generation via Latent Trajectory Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08765</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08765.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruihang Chu, Yefei He, Zhekai Chen, Shiwei Zhang, Xiaogang Xu, Bin Xia, Dingdong Wang, Hongwei Yi, Xihui Liu, Hengshuang Zhao, Yu Liu, Yingya Zhang, Yujiu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 121&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Wan-Move, a simple and scalable framework that brings motion control to video generative models. Existing motion-controllable methods typically suffer from coarse control granularity and limited scalability, leaving their outputs insufficient for practical use. We narrow this gap by achieving precise and high-quality motion control. Our core idea is to directly make the original condition features motion-aware for guiding video synthesis. To this end, we first represent object motions with dense point trajectories, allowing fine-grained control over the scene. We then project these trajectories into latent space and propagate the first frame's features along each trajectory, producing an aligned spatiotemporal feature map that tells how each scene element should move. This feature map serves as the updated latent condition, which is naturally integrated into the off-the-shelf image-to-video model, e.g., Wan-I2V-14B, as motion guidance without any architecture change. It removes the need for auxiliary motion encoders and makes fine-tuning base models easily scalable. Through scaled training, Wan-Move generates 5-second, 480p videos whose motion controllability rivals Kling 1.5 Pro's commercial Motion Brush, as indicated by user studies. To support comprehensive evaluation, we further design MoveBench, a rigorously curated benchmark featuring diverse content categories and hybrid-verified annotations. It is distinguished by larger data volume, longer video durations, and high-quality motion annotations. Extensive experiments on MoveBench and the public dataset consistently show Wan-Move's superior motion quality. Code, models, and benchmark data are made publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08765</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 16:13:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfiniteVL: Synergizing Linear and Sparse Attention for Highly-Efficient, Unlimited-Input Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08829</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08829.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongyuan Tao, Bencheng Liao, Shaoyu Chen, Haoran Yin, Qian Zhang, Wenyu Liu, Xinggang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Window attention and linear attention represent two principal strategies for mitigating the quadratic complexity and ever-growing KV cache in Vision-Language Models (VLMs). However, we observe that window-based VLMs suffer performance degradation when sequence length exceeds the window size, while linear attention underperforms on information-intensive tasks such as OCR and document understanding. To overcome these limitations, we propose InfiniteVL, a linear-complexity VLM architecture that synergizes sliding window attention (SWA) with Gated DeltaNet. For achieving competitive multimodal performance under constrained resources, we design a three-stage training strategy comprising distillation pretraining, instruction tuning, and long-sequence SFT. Remarkably, using less than 2\% of the training data required by leading VLMs, InfiniteVL not only substantially outperforms previous linear-complexity VLMs but also matches the performance of leading Transformer-based VLMs, while demonstrating effective long-term memory retention. Compared to similar-sized Transformer-based VLMs accelerated by FlashAttention-2, InfiniteVL achieves over 3.6\times inference speedup while maintaining constant latency and memory footprint. In streaming video understanding scenarios, it sustains a stable 24 FPS real-time prefill speed while preserving long-term memory cache. Code and models are available at https://github.com/hustvl/InfiniteVL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08829</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 17:18:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fed-SE: Federated Self-Evolution for Privacy-Constrained Multi-Environment LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08870</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08870.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiang Chen, Yuling Shi, Qizhen Lan, Yuchao Qiu, Xiaodong Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM agents are widely deployed in complex interactive tasks, yet privacy constraints often preclude centralized optimization and co-evolution across dynamic environments. While Federated Learning (FL) has proven effective on static datasets, its extension to the open-ended self-evolution of agents remains underexplored. Directly applying standard FL is challenging: heterogeneous tasks and sparse, trajectory-level rewards introduce severe gradient conflicts, destabilizing the global optimization process. To bridge this gap, we propose Fed-SE, a Federated Self-Evolution framework for LLM agents. Fed-SE establishes a local evolution-global aggregation paradigm. Locally, agents employ parameter-efficient fine-tuning on filtered, high-return trajectories to achieve stable gradient updates. Globally, Fed-SE aggregates updates within a low-rank subspace that disentangles environment-specific dynamics, effectively reducing negative transfer across clients. Experiments across five heterogeneous environments demonstrate that Fed-SE improves average task success rates by approximately 18% over federated baselines, validating its effectiveness in robust cross-environment knowledge transfer in privacy-constrained deployments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08870</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 18:04:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficiently Reconstructing Dynamic Scenes One D4RT at a Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08924</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08924.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chuhan Zhang, Guillaume Le Moing, Skanda Koppula, Ignacio Rocco, Liliane Momeni, Junyu Xie, Shuyang Sun, Rahul Sukthankar, Joëlle K Barral, Raia Hadsell, Zoubin Ghahramani, Andrew Zisserman, Junlin Zhang, Mehdi SM Sajjadi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding and reconstructing the complex geometry and motion of dynamic scenes from video remains a formidable challenge in computer vision. This paper introduces D4RT, a simple yet powerful feedforward model designed to efficiently solve this task. D4RT utilizes a unified transformer architecture to jointly infer depth, spatio-temporal correspondence, and full camera parameters from a single video. Its core innovation is a novel querying mechanism that sidesteps the heavy computation of dense, per-frame decoding and the complexity of managing multiple, task-specific decoders. Our decoding interface allows the model to independently and flexibly probe the 3D position of any point in space and time. The result is a lightweight and highly scalable method that enables remarkably efficient training and inference. We demonstrate that our approach sets a new state of the art, outperforming previous methods across a wide spectrum of 4D reconstruction tasks. We refer to the project webpage for animated results: https://d4rt-paper.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08924</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 18:57:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Unmasking Policies for Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Metod Jazbec, Theo X. Olausson, Louis Béthune, Pierre Ablin, Michael Kirchhof, Joao Monterio, Victor Turrisi, Jason Ramapuram, Marco Cuturi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion (Large) Language Models (dLLMs) now match the downstream performance of their autoregressive counterparts on many tasks, while holding the promise of being more efficient during inference. One particularly successful variant is masked discrete diffusion, in which a buffer filled with special mask tokens is progressively replaced with tokens sampled from the model's vocabulary. Efficiency can be gained by unmasking several tokens in parallel, but doing too many at once risks degrading the generation quality. Thus, one critical design aspect of dLLMs is the sampling procedure that selects, at each step of the diffusion process, which tokens to replace. Indeed, recent work has found that heuristic strategies such as confidence thresholding lead to both higher quality and token throughput compared to random unmasking. However, such heuristics have downsides: they require manual tuning, and we observe that their performance degrades with larger buffer sizes. In this work, we instead propose to train sampling procedures using reinforcement learning. Specifically, we formalize masked diffusion sampling as a Markov decision process in which the dLLM serves as the environment, and propose a lightweight policy architecture based on a single-layer transformer that maps dLLM token confidences to unmasking decisions. Our experiments show that these trained policies match the performance of state-of-the-art heuristics when combined with semi-autoregressive generation, while outperforming them in the full diffusion setting. We also examine the transferability of these policies, finding that they can generalize to new underlying dLLMs and longer sequence lengths. However, we also observe that their performance degrades when applied to out-of-domain data, and that fine-grained tuning of the accuracy-efficiency trade-off can be challenging with our approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09106</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:44:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WonderZoom: Multi-Scale 3D World Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09164</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09164.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jin Cao, Hong-Xing Yu, Jiajun Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present WonderZoom, a novel approach to generating 3D scenes with contents across multiple spatial scales from a single image. Existing 3D world generation models remain limited to single-scale synthesis and cannot produce coherent scene contents at varying granularities. The fundamental challenge is the lack of a scale-aware 3D representation capable of generating and rendering content with largely different spatial sizes. WonderZoom addresses this through two key innovations: (1) scale-adaptive Gaussian surfels for generating and real-time rendering of multi-scale 3D scenes, and (2) a progressive detail synthesizer that iteratively generates finer-scale 3D contents. Our approach enables users to "zoom into" a 3D region and auto-regressively synthesize previously non-existent fine details from landscapes to microscopic features. Experiments demonstrate that WonderZoom significantly outperforms state-of-the-art video and 3D models in both quality and alignment, enabling multi-scale 3D world creation from a single image. We show video results and an interactive viewer of generated multi-scale 3D worlds in https://wonderzoom.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09164</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 22:21:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniPSD: Layered PSD Generation with Diffusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09247</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09247.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng Liu, Yiren Song, Haofan Wang, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in diffusion models have greatly improved image generation and editing, yet generating or reconstructing layered PSD files with transparent alpha channels remains highly challenging. We propose OmniPSD, a unified diffusion framework built upon the Flux ecosystem that enables both text-to-PSD generation and image-to-PSD decomposition through in-context learning. For text-to-PSD generation, OmniPSD arranges multiple target layers spatially into a single canvas and learns their compositional relationships through spatial attention, producing semantically coherent and hierarchically structured layers. For image-to-PSD decomposition, it performs iterative in-context editing, progressively extracting and erasing textual and foreground components to reconstruct editable PSD layers from a single flattened image. An RGBA-VAE is employed as an auxiliary representation module to preserve transparency without affecting structure learning. Extensive experiments on our new RGBA-layered dataset demonstrate that OmniPSD achieves high-fidelity generation, structural consistency, and transparency awareness, offering a new paradigm for layered design generation and decomposition with diffusion transformers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09247</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 02:09:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MoRel: Long-Range Flicker-Free 4D Motion Modeling via Anchor Relay-based Bidirectional Blending with Hierarchical Densification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09270</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09270.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sangwoon Kwak, Weeyoung Kwon, Jun Young Jeong, Geonho Kim, Won-Sik Cheong, Jihyong Oh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in 4D Gaussian Splatting (4DGS) have extended the high-speed rendering capability of 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) into the temporal domain, enabling real-time rendering of dynamic scenes. However, one of the major remaining challenges lies in modeling long-range motion-contained dynamic videos, where a naive extension of existing methods leads to severe memory explosion, temporal flickering, and failure to handle appearing or disappearing occlusions over time. To address these challenges, we propose a novel 4DGS framework characterized by an Anchor Relay-based Bidirectional Blending (ARBB) mechanism, named MoRel, which enables temporally consistent and memory-efficient modeling of long-range dynamic scenes. Our method progressively constructs locally canonical anchor spaces at key-frame time index and models inter-frame deformations at the anchor level, enhancing temporal coherence. By learning bidirectional deformations between KfA and adaptively blending them through learnable opacity control, our approach mitigates temporal discontinuities and flickering artifacts. We further introduce a Feature-variance-guided Hierarchical Densification (FHD) scheme that effectively densifies KfA's while keeping rendering quality, based on an assigned level of feature-variance. To effectively evaluate our model's capability to handle real-world long-range 4D motion, we newly compose long-range 4D motion-contained dataset, called SelfCap_{LR}. It has larger average dynamic motion magnitude, captured at spatially wider spaces, compared to previous dynamic video datasets. Overall, our MoRel achieves temporally coherent and flicker-free long-range 4D reconstruction while maintaining bounded memory usage, demonstrating both scalability and efficiency in dynamic Gaussian-based representations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09270</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 02:49:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StereoWorld: Geometry-Aware Monocular-to-Stereo Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09363</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09363.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ke Xing, Longfei Li, Yuyang Yin, Hanwen Liang, Guixun Luo, Chen Fang, Jue Wang, Konstantinos N. Plataniotis, Xiaojie Jin, Yao Zhao, Yunchao Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 66&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The growing adoption of XR devices has fueled strong demand for high-quality stereo video, yet its production remains costly and artifact-prone. To address this challenge, we present StereoWorld, an end-to-end framework that repurposes a pretrained video generator for high-fidelity monocular-to-stereo video generation. Our framework jointly conditions the model on the monocular video input while explicitly supervising the generation with a geometry-aware regularization to ensure 3D structural fidelity. A spatio-temporal tiling scheme is further integrated to enable efficient, high-resolution synthesis. To enable large-scale training and evaluation, we curate a high-definition stereo video dataset containing over 11M frames aligned to natural human interpupillary distance (IPD). Extensive experiments demonstrate that StereoWorld substantially outperforms prior methods, generating stereo videos with superior visual fidelity and geometric consistency. The project webpage is available at https://ke-xing.github.io/StereoWorld/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09363</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 06:50:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H2R-Grounder: A Paired-Data-Free Paradigm for Translating Human Interaction Videos into Physically Grounded Robot Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09406</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09406.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hai Ci, Xiaokang Liu, Pei Yang, Yiren Song, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Robots that learn manipulation skills from everyday human videos could acquire broad capabilities without tedious robot data collection. We propose a video-to-video translation framework that converts ordinary human-object interaction videos into motion-consistent robot manipulation videos with realistic, physically grounded interactions. Our approach does not require any paired human-robot videos for training only a set of unpaired robot videos, making the system easy to scale. We introduce a transferable representation that bridges the embodiment gap: by inpainting the robot arm in training videos to obtain a clean background and overlaying a simple visual cue (a marker and arrow indicating the gripper's position and orientation), we can condition a generative model to insert the robot arm back into the scene. At test time, we apply the same process to human videos (inpainting the person and overlaying human pose cues) and generate high-quality robot videos that mimic the human's actions. We fine-tune a SOTA video diffusion model (Wan 2.2) in an in-context learning manner to ensure temporal coherence and leveraging of its rich prior knowledge. Empirical results demonstrate that our approach achieves significantly more realistic and grounded robot motions compared to baselines, pointing to a promising direction for scaling up robot learning from unlabeled human videos. Project page: https://showlab.github.io/H2R-Grounder/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09406</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 07:59:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Chain-of-Thought Reasoning for Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09616</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09616.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiwu Zhong, Zi-Yuan Hu, Yin Li, Liwei Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning has been highly successful in solving complex tasks in natural language processing, and recent multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have extended this paradigm to video reasoning. However, these models typically build on lengthy reasoning chains and large numbers of input visual tokens. Motivated by empirical observations from our benchmark study, we hypothesize that concise reasoning combined with a reduced set of visual tokens can be sufficient for effective video reasoning. To evaluate this hypothesis, we design and validate an efficient post-training and inference framework that enhances a video MLLM's reasoning capability. Our framework enables models to operate on compressed visual tokens and generate brief reasoning traces prior to answering. The resulting models achieve substantially improved inference efficiency, deliver competitive performance across diverse benchmarks, and avoid reliance on manual CoT annotations or supervised fine-tuning. Collectively, our results suggest that long, human-like CoT reasoning may not be necessary for general video reasoning, and that concise reasoning can be both effective and efficient. Our code will be released at https://github.com/LaVi-Lab/Rethink_CoT_Video.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09616</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 13:05:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composing Concepts from Images and Videos via Concept-prompt Binding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09824</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09824.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xianghao Kong, Zeyu Zhang, Yuwei Guo, Zhuoran Zhao, Songchun Zhang, Anyi Rao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual concept composition, which aims to integrate different elements from images and videos into a single, coherent visual output, still falls short in accurately extracting complex concepts from visual inputs and flexibly combining concepts from both images and videos. We introduce Bind &amp; Compose, a one-shot method that enables flexible visual concept composition by binding visual concepts with corresponding prompt tokens and composing the target prompt with bound tokens from various sources. It adopts a hierarchical binder structure for cross-attention conditioning in Diffusion Transformers to encode visual concepts into corresponding prompt tokens for accurate decomposition of complex visual concepts. To improve concept-token binding accuracy, we design a Diversify-and-Absorb Mechanism that uses an extra absorbent token to eliminate the impact of concept-irrelevant details when training with diversified prompts. To enhance the compatibility between image and video concepts, we present a Temporal Disentanglement Strategy that decouples the training process of video concepts into two stages with a dual-branch binder structure for temporal modeling. Evaluations demonstrate that our method achieves superior concept consistency, prompt fidelity, and motion quality over existing approaches, opening up new possibilities for visual creativity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09824</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 16:57:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniUGP: Unifying Understanding, Generation, and Planing For End-to-end Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09864</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09864.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Lu, Ziyang Liu, Guangfeng Jiang, Yuanfei Luo, Sheng Chen, Yangang Zhang, Ying-Cong Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autonomous driving (AD) systems struggle in long-tail scenarios due to limited world knowledge and weak visual dynamic modeling. Existing vision-language-action (VLA)-based methods cannot leverage unlabeled videos for visual causal learning, while world model-based methods lack reasoning capabilities from large language models. In this paper, we construct multiple specialized datasets providing reasoning and planning annotations for complex scenarios. Then, a unified Understanding-Generation-Planning framework, named UniUGP, is proposed to synergize scene reasoning, future video generation, and trajectory planning through a hybrid expert architecture. By integrating pre-trained VLMs and video generation models, UniUGP leverages visual dynamics and semantic reasoning to enhance planning performance. Taking multi-frame observations and language instructions as input, it produces interpretable chain-of-thought reasoning, physically consistent trajectories, and coherent future videos. We introduce a four-stage training strategy that progressively builds these capabilities across multiple existing AD datasets, along with the proposed specialized datasets. Experiments demonstrate state-of-the-art performance in perception, reasoning, and decision-making, with superior generalization to challenging long-tail situations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09864</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 17:50:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReViSE: Towards Reason-Informed Video Editing in Unified Models with Self-Reflective Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09924</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09924.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinyu Liu, Hangjie Yuan, Yujie Wei, Jiazheng Xing, Yujin Han, Jiahao Pan, Yanbiao Ma, Chi-Min Chan, Kang Zhao, Shiwei Zhang, Wenhan Luo, Yike Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video unified models exhibit strong capabilities in understanding and generation, yet they struggle with reason-informed visual editing even when equipped with powerful internal vision-language models (VLMs). We attribute this gap to two factors: 1) existing datasets are inadequate for training and evaluating reasoning-aware video editing, and 2) an inherent disconnect between the models' reasoning and editing capabilities, which prevents the rich understanding from effectively instructing the editing process. Bridging this gap requires an integrated framework that connects reasoning with visual transformation. To address this gap, we introduce the Reason-Informed Video Editing (RVE) task, which requires reasoning about physical plausibility and causal dynamics during editing. To support systematic evaluation, we construct RVE-Bench, a comprehensive benchmark with two complementary subsets: Reasoning-Informed Video Editing and In-Context Video Generation. These subsets cover diverse reasoning dimensions and real-world editing scenarios. Building upon this foundation, we propose the ReViSE, a Self-Reflective Reasoning (SRF) framework that unifies generation and evaluation within a single architecture. The model's internal VLM provides intrinsic feedback by assessing whether the edited video logically satisfies the given instruction. The differential feedback that refines the generator's reasoning behavior during training. Extensive experiments on RVE-Bench demonstrate that ReViSE significantly enhances editing accuracy and visual fidelity, achieving a 32% improvement of the Overall score in the reasoning-informed video editing subset over state-of-the-art methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09924</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:57:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HiF-VLA: Hindsight, Insight and Foresight through Motion Representation for Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09928</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09928.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minghui Lin, Pengxiang Ding, Shu Wang, Zifeng Zhuang, Yang Liu, Xinyang Tong, Wenxuan Song, Shangke Lyu, Siteng Huang, Donglin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models have recently enabled robotic manipulation by grounding visual and linguistic cues into actions. However, most VLAs assume the Markov property, relying only on the current observation and thus suffering from temporal myopia that degrades long-horizon coherence. In this work, we view motion as a more compact and informative representation of temporal context and world dynamics, capturing inter-state changes while filtering static pixel-level noise. Building on this idea, we propose HiF-VLA (Hindsight, Insight, and Foresight for VLAs), a unified framework that leverages motion for bidirectional temporal reasoning. HiF-VLA encodes past dynamics through hindsight priors, anticipates future motion via foresight reasoning, and integrates both through a hindsight-modulated joint expert to enable a ''think-while-acting'' paradigm for long-horizon manipulation. As a result, HiF-VLA surpasses strong baselines on LIBERO-Long and CALVIN ABC-D benchmarks, while incurring negligible additional inference latency. Furthermore, HiF-VLA achieves substantial improvements in real-world long-horizon manipulation tasks, demonstrating its broad effectiveness in practical robotic settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09928</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MotionEdit: Benchmarking and Learning Motion-Centric Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10284</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10284.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yixin Wan, Lei Ke, Wenhao Yu, Kai-Wei Chang, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce MotionEdit, a novel dataset for motion-centric image editing-the task of modifying subject actions and interactions while preserving identity, structure, and physical plausibility. Unlike existing image editing datasets that focus on static appearance changes or contain only sparse, low-quality motion edits, MotionEdit provides high-fidelity image pairs depicting realistic motion transformations extracted and verified from continuous videos. This new task is not only scientifically challenging but also practically significant, powering downstream applications such as frame-controlled video synthesis and animation.   To evaluate model performance on the novel task, we introduce MotionEdit-Bench, a benchmark that challenges models on motion-centric edits and measures model performance with generative, discriminative, and preference-based metrics. Benchmark results reveal that motion editing remains highly challenging for existing state-of-the-art diffusion-based editing models. To address this gap, we propose MotionNFT (Motion-guided Negative-aware Fine Tuning), a post-training framework that computes motion alignment rewards based on how well the motion flow between input and model-edited images matches the ground-truth motion, guiding models toward accurate motion transformations. Extensive experiments on FLUX.1 Kontext and Qwen-Image-Edit show that MotionNFT consistently improves editing quality and motion fidelity of both base models on the motion editing task without sacrificing general editing ability, demonstrating its effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10284</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 04:53:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tool-Augmented Spatiotemporal Reasoning for Streamlining Video Question Answering Task</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10359</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10359.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sunqi Fan, Jiashuo Cui, Meng-Hao Guo, Shuojin Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video Question Answering (VideoQA) task serves as a critical playground for evaluating whether foundation models can effectively perceive, understand, and reason about dynamic real-world scenarios. However, existing Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) struggle with simultaneously modeling spatial relationships within video frames and understanding the causal dynamics of temporal evolution on complex and reasoning-intensive VideoQA task. In this work, we equip MLLM with a comprehensive and extensible Video Toolkit, to enhance MLLM's spatiotemporal reasoning capabilities and ensure the harmony between the quantity and diversity of tools. To better control the tool invocation sequence and avoid toolchain shortcut issues, we propose a Spatiotemporal Reasoning Framework (STAR) that strategically schedules temporal and spatial tools, thereby progressively localizing the key area in the video. Our STAR framework enhances GPT-4o using lightweight tools, achieving an 8.2% gain on VideoMME and 4.6% on LongVideoBench. We believe that our proposed Video Toolkit and STAR framework make an important step towards building autonomous and intelligent video analysis assistants. The code is publicly available at https://github.com/fansunqi/VideoTool.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10359</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 07:17:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confucius Code Agent: An Open-sourced AI Software Engineer at Industrial Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10398</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10398.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaodong Wang, Zhenting Qi, Sherman Wong, Nathan Hu, Samuel Lin, Jun Ge, Erwin Gao, Yining Yang, Ben Maurer, Wenlin Chen, David Recordon, Yilun Du, Minlan Yu, Ying Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Real-world AI software engineering demands coding agents that can reason over massive repositories, maintain durable memory across and within long sessions, and robustly coordinate complex toolchains at test time. Existing open-source coding agents provide transparency but frequently fall short when pushed to these industrial-scale workloads, while proprietary coding agents offer strong practical performance but limited extensibility, interpretability, and controllability. We present the Confucius Code Agent (CCA), an open-sourced AI software engineer that can operate at an industrial scale. CCA is built atop the Confucius SDK, an open-sourced agent development platform designed around three complementary perspectives: Agent Experience (AX), User Experience (UX), and Developer Experience (DX). The SDK introduces a unified orchestrator with hierarchical working memory for long-context reasoning, a persistent note-taking system for cross-session continual learning, and a modular extension module for robust tool use. Moreover, a meta-agent automates the synthesis, evaluation, and refinement of agent configurations through a build-test-improve loop, enabling rapid agent development on new tasks, environments, and tool stacks. Instantiated on Confucius SDK with these mechanisms, CCA delivers strong performance on real-world software engineering tasks. On SWE-Bench-Pro, CCA achieves a state-of-the-art Resolve@1 performance of 54.3%, substantially improving over prior coding agents. Together, the Confucius SDK and CCA provide a transparent, extensible, and reproducible foundation for AI agents, bridge gaps between research prototypes and production-grade systems, and support agent development and deployment at industrial scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10398</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 08:05:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-pro 2.0: An Efficient Russian Hybrid-Reasoning Model and Playground</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10430</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10430.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dmitrii Stoianov, Danil Taranets, Olga Tsymboi, Ramil Latypov, Almaz Dautov, Vladislav Kruglikov, Nikita Surkov, German Abramov, Pavel Gein, Dmitry Abulkhanov, Mikhail Gashkov, Viktor Zelenkovskiy, Artem Batalov, Aleksandr Medvedev, Anatolii Potapov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce T-pro 2.0, an open-weight Russian LLM for hybrid reasoning and efficient inference. The model supports direct answering and reasoning-trace generation, using a Cyrillic-dense tokenizer and an adapted EAGLE speculative-decoding pipeline to reduce latency. To enable reproducible and extensible research, we release the model weights, the T-Wix 500k instruction corpus, the T-Math reasoning benchmark, and the EAGLE weights on Hugging Face. These resources allow users to study Russian-language reasoning and to extend or adapt both the model and the inference pipeline. A public web demo exposes reasoning and non-reasoning modes and illustrates the speedups achieved by our inference stack across domains. T-pro 2.0 thus serves as an accessible open system for building and evaluating efficient, practical Russian LLM applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10430</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 08:40:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving Olympia-Level Geometry Large Language Model Agent via Complexity Boosting Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10534</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10534.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haiteng Zhao, Junhao Shen, Yiming Zhang, Songyang Gao, Kuikun Liu, Tianyou Ma, Fan Zheng, Dahua Lin, Wenwei Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM) agents exhibit strong mathematical problem-solving abilities and can even solve International Mathematical Olympiad (IMO) level problems with the assistance of formal proof systems. However, due to weak heuristics for auxiliary constructions, AI for geometry problem solving remains dominated by expert models such as AlphaGeometry 2, which rely heavily on large-scale data synthesis and search for both training and evaluation. In this work, we make the first attempt to build a medalist-level LLM agent for geometry and present InternGeometry. InternGeometry overcomes the heuristic limitations in geometry by iteratively proposing propositions and auxiliary constructions, verifying them with a symbolic engine, and reflecting on the engine's feedback to guide subsequent proposals. A dynamic memory mechanism enables InternGeometry to conduct more than two hundred interactions with the symbolic engine per problem. To further accelerate learning, we introduce Complexity-Boosting Reinforcement Learning (CBRL), which gradually increases the complexity of synthesized problems across training stages. Built on InternThinker-32B, InternGeometry solves 44 of 50 IMO geometry problems (2000-2024), exceeding the average gold medalist score (40.9), using only 13K training examples, just 0.004% of the data used by AlphaGeometry 2, demonstrating the potential of LLM agents on expert-level geometry tasks. InternGeometry can also propose novel auxiliary constructions for IMO problems that do not appear in human solutions. We will release the model, data, and symbolic engine to support future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10534</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 11:05:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Gemini Robotics Policies in a Veo World Simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10675</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10675.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gemini Robotics Team, Coline Devin, Yilun Du, Debidatta Dwibedi, Ruiqi Gao, Abhishek Jindal, Thomas Kipf, Sean Kirmani, Fangchen Liu, Anirudha Majumdar, Andrew Marmon, Carolina Parada, Yulia Rubanova, Dhruv Shah, Vikas Sindhwani, Jie Tan, Fei Xia, Ted Xiao, Sherry Yang, Wenhao Yu, Allan Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative world models hold significant potential for simulating interactions with visuomotor policies in varied environments. Frontier video models can enable generation of realistic observations and environment interactions in a scalable and general manner. However, the use of video models in robotics has been limited primarily to in-distribution evaluations, i.e., scenarios that are similar to ones used to train the policy or fine-tune the base video model. In this report, we demonstrate that video models can be used for the entire spectrum of policy evaluation use cases in robotics: from assessing nominal performance to out-of-distribution (OOD) generalization, and probing physical and semantic safety. We introduce a generative evaluation system built upon a frontier video foundation model (Veo). The system is optimized to support robot action conditioning and multi-view consistency, while integrating generative image-editing and multi-view completion to synthesize realistic variations of real-world scenes along multiple axes of generalization. We demonstrate that the system preserves the base capabilities of the video model to enable accurate simulation of scenes that have been edited to include novel interaction objects, novel visual backgrounds, and novel distractor objects. This fidelity enables accurately predicting the relative performance of different policies in both nominal and OOD conditions, determining the relative impact of different axes of generalization on policy performance, and performing red teaming of policies to expose behaviors that violate physical or semantic safety constraints. We validate these capabilities through 1600+ real-world evaluations of eight Gemini Robotics policy checkpoints and five tasks for a bimanual manipulator.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10675</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 14:22:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-horizon Reasoning Agent for Olympiad-Level Mathematical Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10739</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10739.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Songyang Gao, Yuzhe Gu, Zijian Wu, Lingkai Kong, Wenwei Zhang, Zhongrui Cai, Fan Zheng, Tianyou Ma, Junhao Shen, Haiteng Zhao, Duanyang Zhang, Huilun Zhang, Kuikun Liu, Chengqi Lyu, Yanhui Duan, Chiyu Chen, Ningsheng Ma, Jianfei Gao, Han Lyu, Dahua Lin, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have achieved significant progress in solving complex reasoning tasks by Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR). This advancement is also inseparable from the oversight automated by reliable verifiers. However, current outcome-based verifiers (OVs) are unable to inspect the unreliable intermediate steps in the long reasoning chains of thought (CoTs). Meanwhile, current process-based verifiers (PVs) have difficulties in reliably detecting errors in the complex long CoTs, limited by the scarcity of high-quality annotations due to the prohibitive costs of human annotations. Therefore, we propose the Outcome-based Process Verifier (OPV), which verifies the rationale process of summarized outcomes from long CoTs to achieve both accurate and efficient verification and enable large-scale annotation. To empower the proposed verifier, we adopt an iterative active learning framework with expert annotations to progressively improve the verification capability of OPV with fewer annotation costs. Specifically, in each iteration, the most uncertain cases of the current best OPV are annotated and then subsequently used to train a new OPV through Rejection Fine-Tuning (RFT) and RLVR for the next round. Extensive experiments demonstrate OPV's superior performance and broad applicability. It achieves new state-of-the-art results on our held-out \thisbench, outperforming much larger open-source models such as Qwen3-Max-Preview with an F1 score of 83.1 compared to 76.3. Furthermore, OPV effectively detects false positives within synthetic dataset, closely align with expert assessment. When collaborating with policy models, OPV consistently yields performance gains, e.g., raising the accuracy of DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-32B from 55.2\% to 73.3\% on AIME2025 as the compute budget scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10739</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 15:26:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OPV: Outcome-based Process Verifier for Efficient Long Chain-of-Thought Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10756</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10756.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijian Wu, Lingkai Kong, Wenwei Zhang, Songyang Gao, Yuzhe Gu, Zhongrui Cai, Tianyou Ma, Yuhong Liu, Zhi Wang, Runyuan Ma, Guangyu Wang, Wei Li, Conghui He, Dahua Lin, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have achieved significant progress in solving complex reasoning tasks by Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR). This advancement is also inseparable from the oversight automated by reliable verifiers. However, current outcome-based verifiers (OVs) are unable to inspect the unreliable intermediate steps in the long reasoning chains of thought (CoTs). Meanwhile, current process-based verifiers (PVs) have difficulties in reliably detecting errors in the complex long CoTs, limited by the scarcity of high-quality annotations due to the prohibitive costs of human annotations. Therefore, we propose the Outcome-based Process Verifier (OPV), which verifies the rationale process of summarized outcomes from long CoTs to achieve both accurate and efficient verification and enable large-scale annotation. To empower the proposed verifier, we adopt an iterative active learning framework with expert annotations to progressively improve the verification capability of OPV with fewer annotation costs. Specifically, in each iteration, the most uncertain cases of the current best OPV are annotated and then subsequently used to train a new OPV through Rejection Fine-Tuning (RFT) and RLVR for the next round. Extensive experiments demonstrate OPV's superior performance and broad applicability. It achieves new state-of-the-art results on our held-out OPV-Bench, outperforming much larger open-source models such as Qwen3-Max-Preview with an F1 score of 83.1 compared to 76.3. Furthermore, OPV effectively detects false positives within synthetic dataset, closely align with expert assessment. When collaborating with policy models, OPV consistently yields performance gains, e.g., raising the accuracy of DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-32B from 55.2% to 73.3% on AIME2025 as the compute budget scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10756</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 15:47:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The FACTS Leaderboard: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Large Language Model Factuality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10791</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10791.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aileen Cheng, Alon Jacovi, Amir Globerson, Ben Golan, Charles Kwong, Chris Alberti, Connie Tao, Eyal Ben-David, Gaurav Singh Tomar, Lukas Haas, Yonatan Bitton, Adam Bloniarz, Aijun Bai, Andrew Wang, Anfal Siddiqui, Arturo Bajuelos Castillo, Aviel Atias, Chang Liu, Corey Fry, Daniel Balle, Deepanway Ghosal, Doron Kukliansky, Dror Marcus, Elena Gribovskaya, Eran Ofek, Honglei Zhuang, Itay Laish, Jan Ackermann, Lily Wang, Meg Risdal, Megan Barnes, Michael Fink, Mohamed Amin, Moran Ambar, Natan Potikha, Nikita Gupta, Nitzan Katz, Noam Velan, Ofir Roval, Ori Ram, Polina Zablotskaia, Prathamesh Bang, Priyanka Agrawal, Rakesh Ghiya, Sanjay Ganapathy, Simon Baumgartner, Sofia Erell, Sushant Prakash, Thibault Sellam, Vikram Rao, Xuanhui Wang, Yaroslav Akulov, Yulong Yang, Zhen Yang, Zhixin Lai, Zhongru Wu, Anca Dragan, Avinatan Hassidim, Fernando Pereira, Slav Petrov, Srinivasan Venkatachary, Tulsee Doshi, Yossi Matias, Sasha Goldshtein, Dipanjan Das&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce The FACTS Leaderboard, an online leaderboard suite and associated set of benchmarks that comprehensively evaluates the ability of language models to generate factually accurate text across diverse scenarios. The suite provides a holistic measure of factuality by aggregating the performance of models on four distinct sub-leaderboards: (1) FACTS Multimodal, which measures the factuality of responses to image-based questions; (2) FACTS Parametric, which assesses models' world knowledge by answering closed-book factoid questions from internal parameters; (3) FACTS Search, which evaluates factuality in information-seeking scenarios, where the model must use a search API; and (4) FACTS Grounding (v2), which evaluates whether long-form responses are grounded in provided documents, featuring significantly improved judge models. Each sub-leaderboard employs automated judge models to score model responses, and the final suite score is an average of the four components, designed to provide a robust and balanced assessment of a model's overall factuality. The FACTS Leaderboard Suite will be actively maintained, containing both public and private splits to allow for external participation while guarding its integrity. It can be found at https://www.kaggle.com/benchmarks/google/facts .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10791</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 16:35:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Macro to Micro: Benchmarking Microscopic Spatial Intelligence on Molecules via Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10867</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10867.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zongzhao Li, Xiangzhe Kong, Jiahui Su, Zongyang Ma, Mingze Li, Songyou Li, Yuelin Zhang, Yu Rong, Tingyang Xu, Deli Zhao, Wenbing Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces the concept of Microscopic Spatial Intelligence (MiSI), the capability to perceive and reason about the spatial relationships of invisible microscopic entities, which is fundamental to scientific discovery. To assess the potential of Vision-Language Models (VLMs) in this domain, we propose a systematic benchmark framework MiSI-Bench. This framework features over 163,000 question-answer pairs and 587,000 images derived from approximately 4,000 molecular structures, covering nine complementary tasks that evaluate abilities ranging from elementary spatial transformations to complex relational identifications. Experimental results reveal that current state-of-the-art VLMs perform significantly below human level on this benchmark. However, a fine-tuned 7B model demonstrates substantial potential, even surpassing humans in spatial transformation tasks, while its poor performance in scientifically-grounded tasks like hydrogen bond recognition underscores the necessity of integrating explicit domain knowledge for progress toward scientific AGI. The datasets are available at https://huggingface.co/datasets/zongzhao/MiSI-bench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10867</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MoCapAnything: Unified 3D Motion Capture for Arbitrary Skeletons from Monocular Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10881</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10881.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kehong Gong, Zhengyu Wen, Weixia He, Mingxi Xu, Qi Wang, Ning Zhang, Zhengyu Li, Dongze Lian, Wei Zhao, Xiaoyu He, Mingyuan Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Motion capture now underpins content creation far beyond digital humans, yet most existing pipelines remain species- or template-specific. We formalize this gap as Category-Agnostic Motion Capture (CAMoCap): given a monocular video and an arbitrary rigged 3D asset as a prompt, the goal is to reconstruct a rotation-based animation such as BVH that directly drives the specific asset. We present MoCapAnything, a reference-guided, factorized framework that first predicts 3D joint trajectories and then recovers asset-specific rotations via constraint-aware inverse kinematics. The system contains three learnable modules and a lightweight IK stage: (1) a Reference Prompt Encoder that extracts per-joint queries from the asset's skeleton, mesh, and rendered images; (2) a Video Feature Extractor that computes dense visual descriptors and reconstructs a coarse 4D deforming mesh to bridge the gap between video and joint space; and (3) a Unified Motion Decoder that fuses these cues to produce temporally coherent trajectories. We also curate Truebones Zoo with 1038 motion clips, each providing a standardized skeleton-mesh-render triad. Experiments on both in-domain benchmarks and in-the-wild videos show that MoCapAnything delivers high-quality skeletal animations and exhibits meaningful cross-species retargeting across heterogeneous rigs, enabling scalable, prompt-driven 3D motion capture for arbitrary assets. Project page: https://animotionlab.github.io/MoCapAnything/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10881</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DuetSVG: Unified Multimodal SVG Generation with Internal Visual Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10894</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10894.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peiying Zhang, Nanxuan Zhao, Matthew Fisher, Yiran Xu, Jing Liao, Difan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent vision-language model (VLM)-based approaches have achieved impressive results on SVG generation. However, because they generate only text and lack visual signals during decoding, they often struggle with complex semantics and fail to produce visually appealing or geometrically coherent SVGs. We introduce DuetSVG, a unified multimodal model that jointly generates image tokens and corresponding SVG tokens in an end-to-end manner. DuetSVG is trained on both image and SVG datasets. At inference, we apply a novel test-time scaling strategy that leverages the model's native visual predictions as guidance to improve SVG decoding quality. Extensive experiments show that our method outperforms existing methods, producing visually faithful, semantically aligned, and syntactically clean SVGs across a wide range of applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10894</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:23:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stronger Normalization-Free Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10938</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10938.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingzhi Chen, Taiming Lu, Jiachen Zhu, Mingjie Sun, Zhuang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although normalization layers have long been viewed as indispensable components of deep learning architectures, the recent introduction of Dynamic Tanh (DyT) has demonstrated that alternatives are possible. The point-wise function DyT constrains extreme values for stable convergence and reaches normalization-level performance; this work seeks further for function designs that can surpass it. We first study how the intrinsic properties of point-wise functions influence training and performance. Building on these findings, we conduct a large-scale search for a more effective function design. Through this exploration, we introduce Derf(x) = erf(αx + s), where erf(x) is the rescaled Gaussian cumulative distribution function, and identify it as the most performant design. Derf outperforms LayerNorm, RMSNorm, and DyT across a wide range of domains, including vision (image recognition and generation), speech representation, and DNA sequence modeling. Our findings suggest that the performance gains of Derf largely stem from its improved generalization rather than stronger fitting capacity. Its simplicity and stronger performance make Derf a practical choice for normalization-free Transformer architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10938</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:58:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are We Ready for RL in Text-to-3D Generation? A Progressive Investigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10949</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10949.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiwen Tang, Zoey Guo, Kaixin Zhu, Ray Zhang, Qizhi Chen, Dongzhi Jiang, Junli Liu, Bohan Zeng, Haoming Song, Delin Qu, Tianyi Bai, Dan Xu, Wentao Zhang, Bin Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL), earlier proven to be effective in large language and multi-modal models, has been successfully extended to enhance 2D image generation recently. However, applying RL to 3D generation remains largely unexplored due to the higher spatial complexity of 3D objects, which require globally consistent geometry and fine-grained local textures. This makes 3D generation significantly sensitive to reward designs and RL algorithms. To address these challenges, we conduct the first systematic study of RL for text-to-3D autoregressive generation across several dimensions. (1) Reward designs: We evaluate reward dimensions and model choices, showing that alignment with human preference is crucial, and that general multi-modal models provide robust signal for 3D attributes. (2) RL algorithms: We study GRPO variants, highlighting the effectiveness of token-level optimization, and further investigate the scaling of training data and iterations. (3) Text-to-3D Benchmarks: Since existing benchmarks fail to measure implicit reasoning abilities in 3D generation models, we introduce MME-3DR. (4) Advanced RL paradigms: Motivated by the natural hierarchy of 3D generation, we propose Hi-GRPO, which optimizes the global-to-local hierarchical 3D generation through dedicated reward ensembles. Based on these insights, we develop AR3D-R1, the first RL-enhanced text-to-3D model, expert from coarse shape to texture refinement. We hope this study provides insights into RL-driven reasoning for 3D generation. Code is released at https://github.com/Ivan-Tang-3D/3DGen-R1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10949</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Omni-Attribute: Open-vocabulary Attribute Encoder for Visual Concept Personalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10955</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10955.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tsai-Shien Chen, Aliaksandr Siarohin, Guocheng Gordon Qian, Kuan-Chieh Jackson Wang, Egor Nemchinov, Moayed Haji-Ali, Riza Alp Guler, Willi Menapace, Ivan Skorokhodov, Anil Kag, Jun-Yan Zhu, Sergey Tulyakov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual concept personalization aims to transfer only specific image attributes, such as identity, expression, lighting, and style, into unseen contexts. However, existing methods rely on holistic embeddings from general-purpose image encoders, which entangle multiple visual factors and make it difficult to isolate a single attribute. This often leads to information leakage and incoherent synthesis. To address this limitation, we introduce Omni-Attribute, the first open-vocabulary image attribute encoder designed to learn high-fidelity, attribute-specific representations. Our approach jointly designs the data and model: (i) we curate semantically linked image pairs annotated with positive and negative attributes to explicitly teach the encoder what to preserve or suppress; and (ii) we adopt a dual-objective training paradigm that balances generative fidelity with contrastive disentanglement. The resulting embeddings prove effective for open-vocabulary attribute retrieval, personalization, and compositional generation, achieving state-of-the-art performance across multiple benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10955</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StereoSpace: Depth-Free Synthesis of Stereo Geometry via End-to-End Diffusion in a Canonical Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10959</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10959.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tjark Behrens, Anton Obukhov, Bingxin Ke, Fabio Tosi, Matteo Poggi, Konrad Schindler&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce StereoSpace, a diffusion-based framework for monocular-to-stereo synthesis that models geometry purely through viewpoint conditioning, without explicit depth or warping. A canonical rectified space and the conditioning guide the generator to infer correspondences and fill disocclusions end-to-end. To ensure fair and leakage-free evaluation, we introduce an end-to-end protocol that excludes any ground truth or proxy geometry estimates at test time. The protocol emphasizes metrics reflecting downstream relevance: iSQoE for perceptual comfort and MEt3R for geometric consistency. StereoSpace surpasses other methods from the warp &amp; inpaint, latent-warping, and warped-conditioning categories, achieving sharp parallax and strong robustness on layered and non-Lambertian scenes. This establishes viewpoint-conditioned diffusion as a scalable, depth-free solution for stereo generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10959</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
