<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 00:02:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>TurboDiffusion: Accelerating Video Diffusion Models by 100-200 Times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16093</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16093.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Kaiwen Zheng, Kai Jiang, Haoxu Wang, Ion Stoica, Joseph E. Gonzalez, Jianfei Chen, Jun Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce TurboDiffusion, a video generation acceleration framework that can speed up end-to-end diffusion generation by 100-200x while maintaining video quality. TurboDiffusion mainly relies on several components for acceleration: (1) Attention acceleration: TurboDiffusion uses low-bit SageAttention and trainable Sparse-Linear Attention (SLA) to speed up attention computation. (2) Step distillation: TurboDiffusion adopts rCM for efficient step distillation. (3) W8A8 quantization: TurboDiffusion quantizes model parameters and activations to 8 bits to accelerate linear layers and compress the model. In addition, TurboDiffusion incorporates several other engineering optimizations.   We conduct experiments on the Wan2.2-I2V-14B-720P, Wan2.1-T2V-1.3B-480P, Wan2.1-T2V-14B-720P, and Wan2.1-T2V-14B-480P models. Experimental results show that TurboDiffusion achieves 100-200x speedup for video generation even on a single RTX 5090 GPU, while maintaining comparable video quality. The GitHub repository, which includes model checkpoints and easy-to-use code, is available at https://github.com/thu-ml/TurboDiffusion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16093</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 02:21:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-EVO: Benchmarking Coding Agents in Long-Horizon Software Evolution Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18470</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.18470.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minh V. T. Thai, Tue Le, Dung Nguyen Manh, Huy Phan Nhat, Nghi D. Q. Bui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing benchmarks for AI coding agents focus on isolated, single-issue tasks such as fixing a bug or implementing a small feature. However, real-world software engineering is fundamentally a long-horizon endeavor: developers must interpret high-level requirements, plan coordinated changes across many files, and evolve codebases over multiple iterations while preserving existing functionality. We introduce SWE-EVO, a benchmark that evaluates agents on this long-horizon software evolution challenge. Constructed from release notes and version histories of seven mature open-source Python projects, Tool comprises 48 evolution tasks that require agents to implement multi-step modifications spanning an average of 21 files, validated against comprehensive test suites averaging 874 tests per instance. Experiments with state-of-the-art models reveal a striking capability gap: even GPT-5 with OpenHands achieves only a 21 percent resolution rate on Tool, compared to 65 percent on the single-issue SWE-Bench Verified. This demonstrates that current agents struggle with sustained, multi-file reasoning. We also propose Fix Rate, a fine-grained metric that captures partial progress toward solving these complex, long-horizon tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18470</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 19:08:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Word to World: Can Large Language Models be Implicit Text-based World Models?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18832</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.18832.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yixia Li, Hongru Wang, Jiahao Qiu, Zhenfei Yin, Dongdong Zhang, Cheng Qian, Zeping Li, Pony Ma, Guanhua Chen, Heng Ji, Mengdi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic reinforcement learning increasingly relies on experience-driven scaling, yet real-world environments remain non-adaptive, limited in coverage, and difficult to scale. World models offer a potential way to improve learning efficiency through simulated experience, but it remains unclear whether large language models can reliably serve this role and under what conditions they meaningfully benefit agents. We study these questions in text-based environments, which provide a controlled setting to reinterpret language modeling as next-state prediction under interaction. We introduce a three-level framework for evaluating LLM-based world models: (i) fidelity and consistency, (ii) scalability and robustness, and (iii) agent utility. Across five representative environments, we find that sufficiently trained world models maintain coherent latent state, scale predictably with data and model size, and improve agent performance via action verification, synthetic trajectory generation, and warm-starting reinforcement learning. Meanwhile, these gains depend critically on behavioral coverage and environment complexity, delineating clear boundry on when world modeling effectively supports agent learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18832</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 17:28:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-hop Reasoning via Early Knowledge Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20144</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20144.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxin Wang, Shicheng Fang, Bo Wang, Qi Luo, Xuanjing Huang, Yining Zheng, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has emerged as a powerful paradigm for Large Language Models (LLMs) to address knowledge-intensive queries requiring domain-specific or up-to-date information. To handle complex multi-hop questions that are challenging for single-step retrieval, iterative RAG approaches incorporating reinforcement learning have been proposed. However, existing iterative RAG systems typically plan to decompose questions without leveraging information about the available retrieval corpus, leading to inefficient retrieval and reasoning chains that cascade into suboptimal performance. In this paper, we introduce Early Knowledge Alignment (EKA), a simple but effective module that aligns LLMs with retrieval set before planning in iterative RAG systems with contextually relevant retrieved knowledge. Extensive experiments on six standard RAG datasets demonstrate that by establishing a stronger reasoning foundation, EKA significantly improves retrieval precision, reduces cascading errors, and enhances both performance and efficiency. Our analysis from an entropy perspective demonstrate that incorporating early knowledge reduces unnecessary exploration during the reasoning process, enabling the model to focus more effectively on relevant information subsets. Moreover, EKA proves effective as a versatile, training-free inference strategy that scales seamlessly to large models. Generalization tests across diverse datasets and retrieval corpora confirm the robustness of our approach. Overall, EKA advances the state-of-the-art in iterative RAG systems while illuminating the critical interplay between structured reasoning and efficient exploration in reinforcement learning-augmented frameworks. The code is released at https://github.com/yxzwang/EarlyKnowledgeAlignment{Github}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20144</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 08:14:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Reason in 4D: Dynamic Spatial Understanding for Vision Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20557</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20557.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengchao Zhou, Yuxin Chen, Yuying Ge, Wei Huang, Jiehong Lin, Ying Shan, Xiaojuan Qi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language models (VLM) excel at general understanding yet remain weak at dynamic spatial reasoning (DSR), i.e., reasoning about the evolvement of object geometry and relationship in 3D space over time, largely due to the scarcity of scalable 4D-aware training resources. To bridge this gap across aspects of dataset, benchmark and model, we introduce DSR Suite. First, we propose an automated pipeline that generates multiple-choice question-answer pairs from in-the-wild videos for DSR. By leveraging modern vision foundation models, the pipeline extracts rich geometric and motion information, including camera poses, local point clouds, object masks, orientations, and 3D trajectories. These geometric cues enable the construction of DSR-Train for learning and further human-refined DSR-Bench for evaluation. Compared with previous works, our data emphasize (i) in-the-wild video sources, (ii) object- and scene-level 3D requirements, (iii) viewpoint transformations, (iv) multi-object interactions, and (v) fine-grained, procedural answers. Beyond data, we propose a lightweight Geometry Selection Module (GSM) to seamlessly integrate geometric priors into VLMs, which condenses question semantics and extracts question-relevant knowledge from pretrained 4D reconstruction priors into a compact set of geometry tokens. This targeted extraction avoids overwhelming the model with irrelevant knowledge. Experiments show that integrating DSR-Train and GSM into Qwen2.5-VL-7B significantly enhances its dynamic spatial reasoning capability, while maintaining accuracy on general video understanding benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20557</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 17:56:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TokSuite: Measuring the Impact of Tokenizer Choice on Language Model Behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20757</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20757.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gül Sena Altıntaş, Malikeh Ehghaghi, Brian Lester, Fengyuan Liu, Wanru Zhao, Marco Ciccone, Colin Raffel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Tokenizers provide the fundamental basis through which text is represented and processed by language models (LMs). Despite the importance of tokenization, its role in LM performance and behavior is poorly understood due to the challenge of measuring the impact of tokenization in isolation. To address this need, we present TokSuite, a collection of models and a benchmark that supports research into tokenization's influence on LMs. Specifically, we train fourteen models that use different tokenizers but are otherwise identical using the same architecture, dataset, training budget, and initialization. Additionally, we curate and release a new benchmark that specifically measures model performance subject to real-world perturbations that are likely to influence tokenization. Together, TokSuite allows robust decoupling of the influence of a model's tokenizer, supporting a series of novel findings that elucidate the respective benefits and shortcomings of a wide range of popular tokenizers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20757</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 20:43:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nemotron 3 Nano: Open, Efficient Mixture-of-Experts Hybrid Mamba-Transformer Model for Agentic Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20848</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20848.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NVIDIA, Aaron Blakeman, Aaron Grattafiori, Aarti Basant, Abhibha Gupta, Abhinav Khattar, Adi Renduchintala, Aditya Vavre, Akanksha Shukla, Akhiad Bercovich, Aleksander Ficek, Aleksandr Shaposhnikov, Alex Kondratenko, Alexander Bukharin, Alexandre Milesi, Ali Taghibakhshi, Alisa Liu, Amelia Barton, Ameya Sunil Mahabaleshwarkar, Amir Klein, Amit Zuker, Amnon Geifman, Amy Shen, Anahita Bhiwandiwalla, Andrew Tao, Ann Guan, Anubhav Mandarwal, Arham Mehta, Ashwath Aithal, Ashwin Poojary, Asif Ahamed, Asma Kuriparambil Thekkumpate, Ayush Dattagupta, Banghua Zhu, Bardiya Sadeghi, Barnaby Simkin, Ben Lanir, Benedikt Schifferer, Besmira Nushi, Bilal Kartal, Bita Darvish Rouhani, Boris Ginsburg, Brandon Norick, Brandon Soubasis, Branislav Kisacanin, Brian Yu, Bryan Catanzaro, Carlo del Mundo, Chantal Hwang, Charles Wang, Cheng-Ping Hsieh, Chenghao Zhang, Chenhan Yu, Chetan Mungekar, Chintan Patel, Chris Alexiuk, Christopher Parisien, Collin Neale, Damon Mosk-Aoyama, Dan Su, Dane Corneil, Daniel Afrimi, Daniel Rohrer, Daniel Serebrenik, Daria Gitman, Daria Levy, Darko Stosic, David Mosallanezhad, Deepak Narayanan, Dhruv Nathawani, Dima Rekesh, Dina Yared, Divyanshu Kakwani, Dong Ahn, Duncan Riach, Dusan Stosic, Edgar Minasyan, Edward Lin, Eileen Long, Eileen Peters Long, Elena Lantz, Ellie Evans, Elliott Ning, Eric Chung, Eric Harper, Eric Tramel, Erick Galinkin, Erik Pounds, Evan Briones, Evelina Bakhturina, Faisal Ladhak, Fay Wang, Fei Jia, Felipe Soares, Feng Chen, Ferenc Galko, Frankie Siino, Gal Hubara Agam, Ganesh Ajjanagadde, Gantavya Bhatt, Gargi Prasad, George Armstrong, Gerald Shen, Gorkem Batmaz, Grigor Nalbandyan, Haifeng Qian, Harsh Sharma, Hayley Ross, Helen Ngo, Herman Sahota, Hexin Wang, Himanshu Soni, Hiren Upadhyay, Huizi Mao, Huy C Nguyen, Huy Q Nguyen, Iain Cunningham, Ido Shahaf, Igor Gitman, Ilya Loshchilov, Ivan Moshkov, Izzy Putterman, Jan Kautz, Jane Polak Scowcroft, Jared Casper, Jatin Mitra, Jeffrey Glick, Jenny Chen, Jesse Oliver, Jian Zhang, Jiaqi Zeng, Jie Lou, Jimmy Zhang, Jining Huang, Joey Conway, Joey Guman, John Kamalu, Johnny Greco, Jonathan Cohen, Joseph Jennings, Joyjit Daw, Julien Veron Vialard, Junkeun Yi, Jupinder Parmar, Kai Xu, Kan Zhu, Kari Briski, Katherine Cheung, Katherine Luna, Keshav Santhanam, Kevin Shih, Kezhi Kong, Khushi Bhardwaj, Krishna C. Puvvada, Krzysztof Pawelec, Kumar Anik, Lawrence McAfee, Laya Sleiman, Leon Derczynski, Li Ding, Lucas Liebenwein, Luis Vega, Maanu Grover, Maarten Van Segbroeck, Maer Rodrigues de Melo, Makesh Narsimhan Sreedhar, Manoj Kilaru, Maor Ashkenazi, Marc Romeijn, Mark Cai, Markus Kliegl, Maryam Moosaei, Matvei Novikov, Mehrzad Samadi, Melissa Corpuz, Mengru Wang, Meredith Price, Michael Boone, Michael Evans, Miguel Martinez, Mike Chrzanowski, Mohammad Shoeybi, Mostofa Patwary, Nabin Mulepati, Natalie Hereth, Nave Assaf, Negar Habibi, Neta Zmora, Netanel Haber, Nicola Sessions, Nidhi Bhatia, Nikhil Jukar, Nikki Pope, Nikolai Ludwig, Nima Tajbakhsh, Nirmal Juluru, Oleksii Hrinchuk, Oleksii Kuchaiev, Olivier Delalleau, Oluwatobi Olabiyi, Omer Ullman Argov, Ouye Xie, Parth Chadha, Pasha Shamis, Pavlo Molchanov, Pawel Morkisz, Peter Dykas, Peter Jin, Pinky Xu, Piotr Januszewski, Pranav Prashant Thombre, Prasoon Varshney, Pritam Gundecha, Qing Miao, Rabeeh Karimi Mahabadi, Ran El-Yaniv, Ran Zilberstein, Rasoul Shafipour, Rich Harang, Rick Izzo, Rima Shahbazyan, Rishabh Garg, Ritika Borkar, Ritu Gala, Riyad Islam, Roger Waleffe, Rohit Watve, Roi Koren, Ruoxi Zhang, Russell J. Hewett, Ryan Prenger, Ryan Timbrook, Sadegh Mahdavi, Sahil Modi, Samuel Kriman, Sanjay Kariyappa, Sanjeev Satheesh, Saori Kaji, Satish Pasumarthi, Sean Narentharen, Sean Narenthiran, Seonmyeong Bak, Sergey Kashirsky, Seth Poulos, Shahar Mor, Shanmugam Ramasamy, Shantanu Acharya, Shaona Ghosh, Sharath Turuvekere Sreenivas, Shelby Thomas, Shiqing Fan, Shreya Gopal, Shrimai Prabhumoye, Shubham Pachori, Shubham Toshniwal, Shuoyang Ding, Siddharth Singh, Simeng Sun, Smita Ithape, Somshubra Majumdar, Soumye Singhal, Stefania Alborghetti, Stephen Ge, Sugam Dipak Devare, Sumeet Kumar Barua, Suseella Panguluri, Suyog Gupta, Sweta Priyadarshi, Syeda Nahida Akter, Tan Bui, Teodor-Dumitru Ene, Terry Kong, Thanh Do, Tijmen Blankevoort, Tom Balough, Tomer Asida, Tomer Bar Natan, Tugrul Konuk, Twinkle Vashishth, Udi Karpas, Ushnish De, Vahid Noorozi, Vahid Noroozi, Venkat Srinivasan, Venmugil Elango, Vijay Korthikanti, Vitaly Kurin, Vitaly Lavrukhin, Wanli Jiang, Wasi Uddin Ahmad, Wei Du, Wei Ping, Wenfei Zhou, Will Jennings, William Zhang, Wojciech Prazuch, Xiaowei Ren, Yashaswi Karnati, Yejin Choi, Yev Meyer, Yi-Fu Wu, Yian Zhang, Ying Lin, Yonatan Geifman, Yonggan Fu, Yoshi Subara, Yoshi Suhara, Yubo Gao, Zach Moshe, Zhen Dong, Zihan Liu, Zijia Chen, Zijie Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Nemotron 3 Nano 30B-A3B, a Mixture-of-Experts hybrid Mamba-Transformer language model. Nemotron 3 Nano was pretrained on 25 trillion text tokens, including more than 3 trillion new unique tokens over Nemotron 2, followed by supervised fine tuning and large-scale RL on diverse environments. Nemotron 3 Nano achieves better accuracy than our previous generation Nemotron 2 Nano while activating less than half of the parameters per forward pass. It achieves up to 3.3x higher inference throughput than similarly-sized open models like GPT-OSS-20B and Qwen3-30B-A3B-Thinking-2507, while also being more accurate on popular benchmarks. Nemotron 3 Nano demonstrates enhanced agentic, reasoning, and chat abilities and supports context lengths up to 1M tokens. We release both our pretrained Nemotron 3 Nano 30B-A3B Base and post-trained Nemotron 3 Nano 30B-A3B checkpoints on Hugging Face.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20848</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 23:54:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NVIDIA Nemotron 3: Efficient and Open Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20856</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20856.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NVIDIA, Aaron Blakeman, Aaron Grattafiori, Aarti Basant, Abhibha Gupta, Abhinav Khattar, Adi Renduchintala, Aditya Vavre, Akanksha Shukla, Akhiad Bercovich, Aleksander Ficek, Aleksandr Shaposhnikov, Alex Kondratenko, Alexander Bukharin, Alexandre Milesi, Ali Taghibakhshi, Alisa Liu, Amelia Barton, Ameya Sunil Mahabaleshwarkar, Amir Klein, Amit Zuker, Amnon Geifman, Amy Shen, Anahita Bhiwandiwalla, Andrew Tao, Anjulie Agrusa, Ankur Verma, Ann Guan, Anubhav Mandarwal, Arham Mehta, Ashwath Aithal, Ashwin Poojary, Asif Ahamed, Asit Mishra, Asma Kuriparambil Thekkumpate, Ayush Dattagupta, Banghua Zhu, Bardiya Sadeghi, Barnaby Simkin, Ben Lanir, Benedikt Schifferer, Besmira Nushi, Bilal Kartal, Bita Darvish Rouhani, Boris Ginsburg, Brandon Norick, Brandon Soubasis, Branislav Kisacanin, Brian Yu, Bryan Catanzaro, Carlo del Mundo, Chantal Hwang, Charles Wang, Cheng-Ping Hsieh, Chenghao Zhang, Chenhan Yu, Chetan Mungekar, Chintan Patel, Chris Alexiuk, Christopher Parisien, Collin Neale, Cyril Meurillon, Damon Mosk-Aoyama, Dan Su, Dane Corneil, Daniel Afrimi, Daniel Lo, Daniel Rohrer, Daniel Serebrenik, Daria Gitman, Daria Levy, Darko Stosic, David Mosallanezhad, Deepak Narayanan, Dhruv Nathawani, Dima Rekesh, Dina Yared, Divyanshu Kakwani, Dong Ahn, Duncan Riach, Dusan Stosic, Edgar Minasyan, Edward Lin, Eileen Long, Eileen Peters Long, Elad Segal, Elena Lantz, Ellie Evans, Elliott Ning, Eric Chung, Eric Harper, Eric Tramel, Erick Galinkin, Erik Pounds, Evan Briones, Evelina Bakhturina, Evgeny Tsykunov, Faisal Ladhak, Fay Wang, Fei Jia, Felipe Soares, Feng Chen, Ferenc Galko, Frank Sun, Frankie Siino, Gal Hubara Agam, Ganesh Ajjanagadde, Gantavya Bhatt, Gargi Prasad, George Armstrong, Gerald Shen, Gorkem Batmaz, Grigor Nalbandyan, Haifeng Qian, Harsh Sharma, Hayley Ross, Helen Ngo, Herbert Hum, Herman Sahota, Hexin Wang, Himanshu Soni, Hiren Upadhyay, Huizi Mao, Huy C Nguyen, Huy Q Nguyen, Iain Cunningham, Ido Galil, Ido Shahaf, Igor Gitman, Ilya Loshchilov, Itamar Schen, Itay Levy, Ivan Moshkov, Izik Golan, Izzy Putterman, Jan Kautz, Jane Polak Scowcroft, Jared Casper, Jatin Mitra, Jeffrey Glick, Jenny Chen, Jesse Oliver, Jian Zhang, Jiaqi Zeng, Jie Lou, Jimmy Zhang, Jinhang Choi, Jining Huang, Joey Conway, Joey Guman, John Kamalu, Johnny Greco, Jonathan Cohen, Joseph Jennings, Joyjit Daw, Julien Veron Vialard, Junkeun Yi, Jupinder Parmar, Kai Xu, Kan Zhu, Kari Briski, Katherine Cheung, Katherine Luna, Keith Wyss, Keshav Santhanam, Kevin Shih, Kezhi Kong, Khushi Bhardwaj, Kirthi Shankar, Krishna C. Puvvada, Krzysztof Pawelec, Kumar Anik, Lawrence McAfee, Laya Sleiman, Leon Derczynski, Li Ding, Lizzie Wei, Lucas Liebenwein, Luis Vega, Maanu Grover, Maarten Van Segbroeck, Maer Rodrigues de Melo, Mahdi Nazemi, Makesh Narsimhan Sreedhar, Manoj Kilaru, Maor Ashkenazi, Marc Romeijn, Marcin Chochowski, Mark Cai, Markus Kliegl, Maryam Moosaei, Matt Kulka, Matvei Novikov, Mehrzad Samadi, Melissa Corpuz, Mengru Wang, Meredith Price, Michael Andersch, Michael Boone, Michael Evans, Miguel Martinez, Mikail Khona, Mike Chrzanowski, Minseok Lee, Mohammad Dabbah, Mohammad Shoeybi, Mostofa Patwary, Nabin Mulepati, Najeeb Nabwani, Natalie Hereth, Nave Assaf, Negar Habibi, Neta Zmora, Netanel Haber, Nicola Sessions, Nidhi Bhatia, Nikhil Jukar, Nikki Pope, Nikolai Ludwig, Nima Tajbakhsh, Nir Ailon, Nirmal Juluru, Nishant Sharma, Oleksii Hrinchuk, Oleksii Kuchaiev, Olivier Delalleau, Oluwatobi Olabiyi, Omer Ullman Argov, Omri Puny, Oren Tropp, Ouye Xie, Parth Chadha, Pasha Shamis, Paul Gibbons, Pavlo Molchanov, Pawel Morkisz, Peter Dykas, Peter Jin, Pinky Xu, Piotr Januszewski, Pranav Prashant Thombre, Prasoon Varshney, Pritam Gundecha, Przemek Tredak, Qing Miao, Qiyu Wan, Rabeeh Karimi Mahabadi, Rachit Garg, Ran El-Yaniv, Ran Zilberstein, Rasoul Shafipour, Rich Harang, Rick Izzo, Rima Shahbazyan, Rishabh Garg, Ritika Borkar, Ritu Gala, Riyad Islam, Robert Hesse, Roger Waleffe, Rohit Watve, Roi Koren, Ruoxi Zhang, Russell Hewett, Russell J. Hewett, Ryan Prenger, Ryan Timbrook, Sadegh Mahdavi, Sahil Modi, Samuel Kriman, Sangkug Lim, Sanjay Kariyappa, Sanjeev Satheesh, Saori Kaji, Satish Pasumarthi, Saurav Muralidharan, Sean Narentharen, Sean Narenthiran, Seonmyeong Bak, Sergey Kashirsky, Seth Poulos, Shahar Mor, Shanmugam Ramasamy, Shantanu Acharya, Shaona Ghosh, Sharath Turuvekere Sreenivas, Shelby Thomas, Shiqing Fan, Shreya Gopal, Shrimai Prabhumoye, Shubham Pachori, Shubham Toshniwal, Shuoyang Ding, Siddharth Singh, Simeng Sun, Smita Ithape, Somshubra Majumdar, Soumye Singhal, Stas Sergienko, Stefania Alborghetti, Stephen Ge, Sugam Dipak Devare, Sumeet Kumar Barua, Suseella Panguluri, Suyog Gupta, Sweta Priyadarshi, Syeda Nahida Akter, Tan Bui, Teodor-Dumitru Ene, Terry Kong, Thanh Do, Tijmen Blankevoort, Tim Moon, Tom Balough, Tomer Asida, Tomer Bar Natan, Tomer Ronen, Tugrul Konuk, Twinkle Vashishth, Udi Karpas, Ushnish De, Vahid Noorozi, Vahid Noroozi, Venkat Srinivasan, Venmugil Elango, Victor Cui, Vijay Korthikanti, Vinay Rao, Vitaly Kurin, Vitaly Lavrukhin, Vladimir Anisimov, Wanli Jiang, Wasi Uddin Ahmad, Wei Du, Wei Ping, Wenfei Zhou, Will Jennings, William Zhang, Wojciech Prazuch, Xiaowei Ren, Yashaswi Karnati, Yejin Choi, Yev Meyer, Yi-Fu Wu, Yian Zhang, Yigong Qin, Ying Lin, Yonatan Geifman, Yonggan Fu, Yoshi Subara, Yoshi Suhara, Yubo Gao, Zach Moshe, Zhen Dong, Zhongbo Zhu, Zihan Liu, Zijia Chen, Zijie Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce the Nemotron 3 family of models - Nano, Super, and Ultra. These models deliver strong agentic, reasoning, and conversational capabilities. The Nemotron 3 family uses a Mixture-of-Experts hybrid Mamba-Transformer architecture to provide best-in-class throughput and context lengths of up to 1M tokens. Super and Ultra models are trained with NVFP4 and incorporate LatentMoE, a novel approach that improves model quality. The two larger models also include MTP layers for faster text generation. All Nemotron 3 models are post-trained using multi-environment reinforcement learning enabling reasoning, multi-step tool use, and support granular reasoning budget control. Nano, the smallest model, outperforms comparable models in accuracy while remaining extremely cost-efficient for inference. Super is optimized for collaborative agents and high-volume workloads such as IT ticket automation. Ultra, the largest model, provides state-of-the-art accuracy and reasoning performance. Nano is released together with its technical report and this white paper, while Super and Ultra will follow in the coming months. We will openly release the model weights, pre- and post-training software, recipes, and all data for which we hold redistribution rights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20856</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:24:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning from Next-Frame Prediction: Autoregressive Video Modeling Encodes Effective Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21004</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21004.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinghan Li, Yang Jin, Hao Jiang, Yadong Mu, Yang Song, Kun Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in pretraining general foundation models have significantly improved performance across diverse downstream tasks. While autoregressive (AR) generative models like GPT have revolutionized NLP, most visual generative pretraining methods still rely on BERT-style masked modeling, which often disregards the temporal information essential for video analysis. The few existing autoregressive visual pretraining methods suffer from issues such as inaccurate semantic localization and poor generation quality, leading to poor semantics. In this work, we propose NExT-Vid, a novel autoregressive visual generative pretraining framework that utilizes masked next-frame prediction to jointly model images and videos. NExT-Vid introduces a context-isolated autoregressive predictor to decouple semantic representation from target decoding, and a conditioned flow-matching decoder to enhance generation quality and diversity. Through context-isolated flow-matching pretraining, our approach achieves strong representations. Extensive experiments on large-scale pretrained models demonstrate that our proposed method consistently outperforms previous generative pretraining methods for visual representation learning via attentive probing in downstream classification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21004</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 07:07:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM Swiss Round: Aggregating Multi-Benchmark Performance via Competitive Swiss-System Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21010</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21010.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiashuo Liu, Jiayun Wu, Chunjie Wu, Jingkai Liu, Zaiyuan Wang, Huan Zhou, Wenhao Huang, Hongseok Namkoong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid proliferation of Large Language Models (LLMs) and diverse specialized benchmarks necessitates a shift from fragmented, task-specific metrics to a holistic, competitive ranking system that effectively aggregates performance across multiple ability dimensions. Primarily using static scoring, current evaluation methods are fundamentally limited. They struggle to determine the proper mix ratio across diverse benchmarks, and critically, they fail to capture a model's dynamic competitive fitness or its vulnerability when confronted with sequential, high-stakes tasks. To address this, we introduce the novel Competitive Swiss-System Dynamics (CSD) framework. CSD simulates a multi-round, sequential contest where models are dynamically paired across a curated sequence of benchmarks based on their accumulated win-loss record. And Monte Carlo Simulation (N=100,000 iterations) is used to approximate the statistically robust Expected Win Score (E[S_m]), which eliminates the noise of random pairing and early-round luck. Furthermore, we implement a Failure Sensitivity Analysis by parameterizing the per-round elimination quantity (T_k), which allows us to profile models based on their risk appetite--distinguishing between robust generalists and aggressive specialists. We demonstrate that CSD provides a more nuanced and context-aware ranking than traditional aggregate scoring and static pairwise models, representing a vital step towards risk-informed, next-generation LLM evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21010</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 07:14:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T2AV-Compass: Towards Unified Evaluation for Text-to-Audio-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21094</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21094.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhe Cao, Tao Wang, Jiaming Wang, Yanghai Wang, Yuanxing Zhang, Jialu Chen, Miao Deng, Jiahao Wang, Yubin Guo, Chenxi Liao, Yize Zhang, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Jiaheng Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-Audio-Video (T2AV) generation aims to synthesize temporally coherent video and semantically synchronized audio from natural language, yet its evaluation remains fragmented, often relying on unimodal metrics or narrowly scoped benchmarks that fail to capture cross-modal alignment, instruction following, and perceptual realism under complex prompts. To address this limitation, we present T2AV-Compass, a unified benchmark for comprehensive evaluation of T2AV systems, consisting of 500 diverse and complex prompts constructed via a taxonomy-driven pipeline to ensure semantic richness and physical plausibility. Besides, T2AV-Compass introduces a dual-level evaluation framework that integrates objective signal-level metrics for video quality, audio quality, and cross-modal alignment with a subjective MLLM-as-a-Judge protocol for instruction following and realism assessment. Extensive evaluation of 11 representative T2AVsystems reveals that even the strongest models fall substantially short of human-level realism and cross-modal consistency, with persistent failures in audio realism, fine-grained synchronization, instruction following, etc. These results indicate significant improvement room for future models and highlight the value of T2AV-Compass as a challenging and diagnostic testbed for advancing text-to-audio-video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21094</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 10:30:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhononBench:A Large-Scale Phonon-Based Benchmark for Dynamical Stability in Crystal Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21227</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21227.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiao-Qi Han, Ze-Feng Gao, Peng-Jie Guo, Zhong-Yi Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we introduce PhononBench, the first large-scale benchmark for dynamical stability in AI-generated crystals. Leveraging the recently developed MatterSim interatomic potential, which achieves DFT-level accuracy in phonon predictions across more than 10,000 materials, PhononBench enables efficient large-scale phonon calculations and dynamical-stability analysis for 108,843 crystal structures generated by six leading crystal generation models. PhononBench reveals a widespread limitation of current generative models in ensuring dynamical stability: the average dynamical-stability rate across all generated structures is only 25.83%, with the top-performing model, MatterGen, reaching just 41.0%. Further case studies show that in property-targeted generation-illustrated here by band-gap conditioning with MatterGen--the dynamical-stability rate remains as low as 23.5% even at the optimal band-gap condition of 0.5 eV. In space-group-controlled generation, higher-symmetry crystals exhibit better stability (e.g., cubic systems achieve rates up to 49.2%), yet the average stability across all controlled generations is still only 34.4%. An important additional outcome of this study is the identification of 28,119 crystal structures that are phonon-stable across the entire Brillouin zone, providing a substantial pool of reliable candidates for future materials exploration. By establishing the first large-scale dynamical-stability benchmark, this work systematically highlights the current limitations of crystal generation models and offers essential evaluation criteria and guidance for their future development toward the design and discovery of physically viable materials. All model-generated crystal structures, phonon calculation results, and the high-throughput evaluation workflows developed in PhononBench will be openly released at https://github.com/xqh19970407/PhononBench&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21227</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 15:07:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreaMontage: Arbitrary Frame-Guided One-Shot Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21252</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21252.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiawei Liu, Junqiao Li, Jiangfan Deng, Gen Li, Siyu Zhou, Zetao Fang, Shanshan Lao, Zengde Deng, Jianing Zhu, Tingting Ma, Jiayi Li, Yunqiu Wang, Qian He, Xinglong Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The "one-shot" technique represents a distinct and sophisticated aesthetic in filmmaking. However, its practical realization is often hindered by prohibitive costs and complex real-world constraints. Although emerging video generation models offer a virtual alternative, existing approaches typically rely on naive clip concatenation, which frequently fails to maintain visual smoothness and temporal coherence. In this paper, we introduce DreaMontage, a comprehensive framework designed for arbitrary frame-guided generation, capable of synthesizing seamless, expressive, and long-duration one-shot videos from diverse user-provided inputs. To achieve this, we address the challenge through three primary dimensions. (i) We integrate a lightweight intermediate-conditioning mechanism into the DiT architecture. By employing an Adaptive Tuning strategy that effectively leverages base training data, we unlock robust arbitrary-frame control capabilities. (ii) To enhance visual fidelity and cinematic expressiveness, we curate a high-quality dataset and implement a Visual Expression SFT stage. In addressing critical issues such as subject motion rationality and transition smoothness, we apply a Tailored DPO scheme, which significantly improves the success rate and usability of the generated content. (iii) To facilitate the production of extended sequences, we design a Segment-wise Auto-Regressive (SAR) inference strategy that operates in a memory-efficient manner. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach achieves visually striking and seamlessly coherent one-shot effects while maintaining computational efficiency, empowering users to transform fragmented visual materials into vivid, cohesive one-shot cinematic experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21252</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 16:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Streaming Video Instruction Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21334</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21334.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaer Xia, Peixian Chen, Mengdan Zhang, Xing Sun, Kaiyang Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Streamo, a real-time streaming video LLM that serves as a general-purpose interactive assistant. Unlike existing online video models that focus narrowly on question answering or captioning, Streamo performs a broad spectrum of streaming video tasks, including real-time narration, action understanding, event captioning, temporal event grounding, and time-sensitive question answering. To develop such versatility, we construct Streamo-Instruct-465K, a large-scale instruction-following dataset tailored for streaming video understanding. The dataset covers diverse temporal contexts and multi-task supervision, enabling unified training across heterogeneous streaming tasks. After training end-to-end on the instruction-following dataset through a streamlined pipeline, Streamo exhibits strong temporal reasoning, responsive interaction, and broad generalization across a variety of streaming benchmarks. Extensive experiments show that Streamo bridges the gap between offline video perception models and real-time multimodal assistants, making a step toward unified, intelligent video understanding in continuous video streams.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21334</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 18:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Memorization: A Multi-Modal Ordinal Regression Benchmark to Expose Popularity Bias in Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21337</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21337.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Li-Zhong Szu-Tu, Ting-Lin Wu, Chia-Jui Chang, He Syu, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We expose a significant popularity bias in state-of-the-art vision-language models (VLMs), which achieve up to 34% higher accuracy on famous buildings compared to ordinary ones, indicating a reliance on memorization over generalizable understanding. To systematically investigate this, we introduce the largest open benchmark for this task: the YearGuessr dataset, a collection of 55,546 building images with multi-modal attributes from 157 countries, annotated with continuous ordinal labels of their construction year (1001-2024), GPS data, and page-view counts as a proxy for popularity. Using this dataset, we frame the construction year prediction task as ordinal regression and introduce popularity-aware interval accuracy metrics to quantify this bias. Our resulting benchmark of 30+ models, including our YearCLIP model, confirms that VLMs excel on popular, memorized items but struggle significantly with unrecognized subjects, exposing a critical flaw in their reasoning capabilities. Project page: https://sytwu.github.io/BeyondMemo/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21337</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 18:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HiStream: Efficient High-Resolution Video Generation via Redundancy-Eliminated Streaming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21338</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21338.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haonan Qiu, Shikun Liu, Zijian Zhou, Zhaochong An, Weiming Ren, Zhiheng Liu, Jonas Schult, Sen He, Shoufa Chen, Yuren Cong, Tao Xiang, Ziwei Liu, Juan-Manuel Perez-Rua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; High-resolution video generation, while crucial for digital media and film, is computationally bottlenecked by the quadratic complexity of diffusion models, making practical inference infeasible. To address this, we introduce HiStream, an efficient autoregressive framework that systematically reduces redundancy across three axes: i) Spatial Compression: denoising at low resolution before refining at high resolution with cached features; ii) Temporal Compression: a chunk-by-chunk strategy with a fixed-size anchor cache, ensuring stable inference speed; and iii) Timestep Compression: applying fewer denoising steps to subsequent, cache-conditioned chunks. On 1080p benchmarks, our primary HiStream model (i+ii) achieves state-of-the-art visual quality while demonstrating up to 76.2x faster denoising compared to the Wan2.1 baseline and negligible quality loss. Our faster variant, HiStream+, applies all three optimizations (i+ii+iii), achieving a 107.5x acceleration over the baseline, offering a compelling trade-off between speed and quality, thereby making high-resolution video generation both practical and scalable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21338</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 18:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
