<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:03:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>STR-Match: Matching SpatioTemporal Relevance Score for Training-Free   Video Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22868</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.22868.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junsung Lee, Junoh Kang, Bohyung Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Previous text-guided video editing methods often suffer from temporal inconsistency, motion distortion, and-most notably-limited domain transformation. We attribute these limitations to insufficient modeling of spatiotemporal pixel relevance during the editing process. To address this, we propose STR-Match, a training-free video editing algorithm that produces visually appealing and spatiotemporally coherent videos through latent optimization guided by our novel STR score. The score captures spatiotemporal pixel relevance across adjacent frames by leveraging 2D spatial attention and 1D temporal modules in text-to-video (T2V) diffusion models, without the overhead of computationally expensive 3D attention mechanisms. Integrated into a latent optimization framework with a latent mask, STR-Match generates temporally consistent and visually faithful videos, maintaining strong performance even under significant domain transformations while preserving key visual attributes of the source. Extensive experiments demonstrate that STR-Match consistently outperforms existing methods in both visual quality and spatiotemporal consistency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22868</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 12:36:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JAM-Flow: Joint Audio-Motion Synthesis with Flow Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23552</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.23552.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingi Kwon, Joonghyuk Shin, Jaeseok Jung, Jaesik Park, Youngjung Uh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The intrinsic link between facial motion and speech is often overlooked in generative modeling, where talking head synthesis and text-to-speech (TTS) are typically addressed as separate tasks. This paper introduces JAM-Flow, a unified framework to simultaneously synthesize and condition on both facial motion and speech. Our approach leverages flow matching and a novel Multi-Modal Diffusion Transformer (MM-DiT) architecture, integrating specialized Motion-DiT and Audio-DiT modules. These are coupled via selective joint attention layers and incorporate key architectural choices, such as temporally aligned positional embeddings and localized joint attention masking, to enable effective cross-modal interaction while preserving modality-specific strengths. Trained with an inpainting-style objective, JAM-Flow supports a wide array of conditioning inputs-including text, reference audio, and reference motion-facilitating tasks such as synchronized talking head generation from text, audio-driven animation, and much more, within a single, coherent model. JAM-Flow significantly advances multi-modal generative modeling by providing a practical solution for holistic audio-visual synthesis. project page: https://joonghyuk.com/jamflow-web&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23552</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 06:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>μ^2Tokenizer: Differentiable Multi-Scale Multi-Modal Tokenizer for   Radiology Report Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00316</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.00316.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyou Li, Pengyao Qin, Huanan Wu, Dong Nie, Arun J. Thirunavukarasu, Juntao Yu, Le Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Automated radiology report generation (RRG) aims to produce detailed textual reports from clinical imaging, such as computed tomography (CT) scans, to improve the accuracy and efficiency of diagnosis and provision of management advice. RRG is complicated by two key challenges: (1) inherent complexity in extracting relevant information from imaging data under resource constraints, and (2) difficulty in objectively evaluating discrepancies between model-generated and expert-written reports. To address these challenges, we propose mu^2LLM, a textbf{mu}ltiscale textbf{mu}ltimodal large language models for RRG tasks. The novel {mu}^2Tokenizer, as an intermediate layer, integrates multi-modal features from the multiscale visual tokenizer and the text tokenizer, then enhances report generation quality through direct preference optimization (DPO), guided by GREEN-RedLlama. Experimental results on four large CT image-report medical datasetdemonstrate that our method outperforms existing approaches, highlighting the potential of our fine-tuned mu^2LLMs on limited data for RRG tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00316</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 23:14:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARIG: Autoregressive Interactive Head Generation for Real-time   Conversations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00472</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.00472.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ying Guo, Xi Liu, Cheng Zhen, Pengfei Yan, Xiaoming Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Face-to-face communication, as a common human activity, motivates the research on interactive head generation. A virtual agent can generate motion responses with both listening and speaking capabilities based on the audio or motion signals of the other user and itself. However, previous clip-wise generation paradigm or explicit listener/speaker generator-switching methods have limitations in future signal acquisition, contextual behavioral understanding, and switching smoothness, making it challenging to be real-time and realistic. In this paper, we propose an autoregressive (AR) based frame-wise framework called ARIG to realize the real-time generation with better interaction realism. To achieve real-time generation, we model motion prediction as a non-vector-quantized AR process. Unlike discrete codebook-index prediction, we represent motion distribution using diffusion procedure, achieving more accurate predictions in continuous space. To improve interaction realism, we emphasize interactive behavior understanding (IBU) and detailed conversational state understanding (CSU). In IBU, based on dual-track dual-modal signals, we summarize short-range behaviors through bidirectional-integrated learning and perform contextual understanding over long ranges. In CSU, we use voice activity signals and context features of IBU to understand the various states (interruption, feedback, pause, etc.) that exist in actual conversations. These serve as conditions for the final progressive motion prediction. Extensive experiments have verified the effectiveness of our model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00472</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 06:38:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MARVIS: Modality Adaptive Reasoning over VISualizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01544</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01544.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Benjamin Feuer, Lennart Purucker, Oussama Elachqar, Chinmay Hegde&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scientific applications of machine learning often rely on small, specialized models tuned to particular domains. Such models often achieve excellent performance, but lack flexibility. Foundation models offer versatility, but typically underperform specialized approaches, especially on non-traditional modalities and long-tail domains. We propose MARVIS (Modality Adaptive Reasoning over VISualizations), a training-free method that enables even small vision-language models to predict any data modality with high accuracy. MARVIS transforms latent embedding spaces into visual representations and then leverages the spatial and fine-grained reasoning skills of VLMs to successfully interpret and utilize them. MARVIS achieves competitive performance on vision, audio, biological, and tabular domains using a single 3B parameter model, achieving results that beat Gemini by 16\% on average and approach specialized methods, without exposing personally identifiable information (P.I.I.) or requiring any domain-specific training. We open source our code and datasets at https://github.com/penfever/marvis&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01544</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 09:56:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depth Anything at Any Condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01634</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01634.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Boyuan Sun, Modi Jin, Bowen Yin, Qibin Hou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Depth Anything at Any Condition (DepthAnything-AC), a foundation monocular depth estimation (MDE) model capable of handling diverse environmental conditions. Previous foundation MDE models achieve impressive performance across general scenes but not perform well in complex open-world environments that involve challenging conditions, such as illumination variations, adverse weather, and sensor-induced distortions. To overcome the challenges of data scarcity and the inability of generating high-quality pseudo-labels from corrupted images, we propose an unsupervised consistency regularization finetuning paradigm that requires only a relatively small amount of unlabeled data. Furthermore, we propose the Spatial Distance Constraint to explicitly enforce the model to learn patch-level relative relationships, resulting in clearer semantic boundaries and more accurate details. Experimental results demonstrate the zero-shot capabilities of DepthAnything-AC across diverse benchmarks, including real-world adverse weather benchmarks, synthetic corruption benchmarks, and general benchmarks.   Project Page: https://ghost233lism.github.io/depthanything-AC-page   Code: https://github.com/HVision-NKU/DepthAnythingAC&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01634</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 12:05:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Vision-Language-Action Models: An Action Tokenization   Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01925</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01925.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Zhong, Fengshuo Bai, Shaofei Cai, Xuchuan Huang, Zhang Chen, Xiaowei Zhang, Yuanfei Wang, Shaoyang Guo, Tianrui Guan, Ka Nam Lui, Zhiquan Qi, Yitao Liang, Yuanpei Chen, Yaodong Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The remarkable advancements of vision and language foundation models in multimodal understanding, reasoning, and generation has sparked growing efforts to extend such intelligence to the physical world, fueling the flourishing of vision-language-action (VLA) models. Despite seemingly diverse approaches, we observe that current VLA models can be unified under a single framework: vision and language inputs are processed by a series of VLA modules, producing a chain of action tokens that progressively encode more grounded and actionable information, ultimately generating executable actions. We further determine that the primary design choice distinguishing VLA models lies in how action tokens are formulated, which can be categorized into language description, code, affordance, trajectory, goal state, latent representation, raw action, and reasoning. However, there remains a lack of comprehensive understanding regarding action tokens, significantly impeding effective VLA development and obscuring future directions. Therefore, this survey aims to categorize and interpret existing VLA research through the lens of action tokenization, distill the strengths and limitations of each token type, and identify areas for improvement. Through this systematic review and analysis, we offer a synthesized outlook on the broader evolution of VLA models, highlight underexplored yet promising directions, and contribute guidance for future research, hoping to bring the field closer to general-purpose intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01925</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:34:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongAnimation: Long Animation Generation with Dynamic Global-Local   Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01945</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01945.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nan Chen, Mengqi Huang, Yihao Meng, Zhendong Mao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Animation colorization is a crucial part of real animation industry production. Long animation colorization has high labor costs. Therefore, automated long animation colorization based on the video generation model has significant research value. Existing studies are limited to short-term colorization. These studies adopt a local paradigm, fusing overlapping features to achieve smooth transitions between local segments. However, the local paradigm neglects global information, failing to maintain long-term color consistency. In this study, we argue that ideal long-term color consistency can be achieved through a dynamic global-local paradigm, i.e., dynamically extracting global color-consistent features relevant to the current generation. Specifically, we propose LongAnimation, a novel framework, which mainly includes a SketchDiT, a Dynamic Global-Local Memory (DGLM), and a Color Consistency Reward. The SketchDiT captures hybrid reference features to support the DGLM module. The DGLM module employs a long video understanding model to dynamically compress global historical features and adaptively fuse them with the current generation features. To refine the color consistency, we introduce a Color Consistency Reward. During inference, we propose a color consistency fusion to smooth the video segment transition. Extensive experiments on both short-term (14 frames) and long-term (average 500 frames) animations show the effectiveness of LongAnimation in maintaining short-term and long-term color consistency for open-domain animation colorization task. The code can be found at https://cn-makers.github.io/long_animation_web/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01945</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:55:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kwai Keye-VL Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01949</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01949.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kwai Keye Team, Biao Yang, Bin Wen, Changyi Liu, Chenglong Chu, Chengru Song, Chongling Rao, Chuan Yi, Da Li, Dunju Zang, Fan Yang, Guorui Zhou, Hao Peng, Haojie Ding, Jiaming Huang, Jiangxia Cao, Jiankang Chen, Jingyun Hua, Jin Ouyang, Kaibing Chen, Kaiyu Jiang, Kaiyu Tang, Kun Gai, Shengnan Zhang, Siyang Mao, Sui Huang, Tianke Zhang, Tingting Gao, Wei Chen, Wei Yuan, Xiangyu Wu, Xiao Hu, Xingyu Lu, Yang Zhou, Yi-Fan Zhang, Yiping Yang, Yulong Chen, Zhenhua Wu, Zhenyu Li, Zhixin Ling, Ziming Li, Dehua Ma, Di Xu, Haixuan Gao, Hang Li, Jiawei Guo, Jing Wang, Lejian Ren, Muhao Wei, Qianqian Wang, Qigen Hu, Shiyao Wang, Tao Yu, Xinchen Luo, Yan Li, Yiming Liang, Yuhang Hu, Zeyi Lu, Zhuoran Yang, Zixing Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 94&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) demonstrate remarkable capabilities on static images, they often fall short in comprehending dynamic, information-dense short-form videos, a dominant medium in today's digital landscape. To bridge this gap, we introduce Kwai Keye-VL, an 8-billion-parameter multimodal foundation model engineered for leading-edge performance in short-video understanding while maintaining robust general-purpose vision-language abilities. The development of Keye-VL rests on two core pillars: a massive, high-quality dataset exceeding 600 billion tokens with a strong emphasis on video, and an innovative training recipe. This recipe features a four-stage pre-training process for solid vision-language alignment, followed by a meticulous two-phase post-training process. The first post-training stage enhances foundational capabilities like instruction following, while the second phase focuses on stimulating advanced reasoning. In this second phase, a key innovation is our five-mode ``cold-start'' data mixture, which includes ``thinking'', ``non-thinking'', ``auto-think'', ``think with image'', and high-quality video data. This mixture teaches the model to decide when and how to reason. Subsequent reinforcement learning (RL) and alignment steps further enhance these reasoning capabilities and correct abnormal model behaviors, such as repetitive outputs. To validate our approach, we conduct extensive evaluations, showing that Keye-VL achieves state-of-the-art results on public video benchmarks and remains highly competitive on general image-based tasks (Figure 1). Furthermore, we develop and release the KC-MMBench, a new benchmark tailored for real-world short-video scenarios, where Keye-VL shows a significant advantage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01949</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:57:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FreeMorph: Tuning-Free Generalized Image Morphing with Diffusion Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01953</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01953.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yukang Cao, Chenyang Si, Jinghao Wang, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present FreeMorph, the first tuning-free method for image morphing that accommodates inputs with different semantics or layouts. Unlike existing methods that rely on finetuning pre-trained diffusion models and are limited by time constraints and semantic/layout discrepancies, FreeMorph delivers high-fidelity image morphing without requiring per-instance training. Despite their efficiency and potential, tuning-free methods face challenges in maintaining high-quality results due to the non-linear nature of the multi-step denoising process and biases inherited from the pre-trained diffusion model. In this paper, we introduce FreeMorph to address these challenges by integrating two key innovations. 1) We first propose a guidance-aware spherical interpolation design that incorporates explicit guidance from the input images by modifying the self-attention modules, thereby addressing identity loss and ensuring directional transitions throughout the generated sequence. 2) We further introduce a step-oriented variation trend that blends self-attention modules derived from each input image to achieve controlled and consistent transitions that respect both inputs. Our extensive evaluations demonstrate that FreeMorph outperforms existing methods, being 10x ~ 50x faster and establishing a new state-of-the-art for image morphing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01953</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locality-aware Parallel Decoding for Efficient Autoregressive Image   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01957</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01957.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuoyang Zhang, Luke J. Huang, Chengyue Wu, Shang Yang, Kelly Peng, Yao Lu, Song Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Locality-aware Parallel Decoding (LPD) to accelerate autoregressive image generation. Traditional autoregressive image generation relies on next-patch prediction, a memory-bound process that leads to high latency. Existing works have tried to parallelize next-patch prediction by shifting to multi-patch prediction to accelerate the process, but only achieved limited parallelization. To achieve high parallelization while maintaining generation quality, we introduce two key techniques: (1) Flexible Parallelized Autoregressive Modeling, a novel architecture that enables arbitrary generation ordering and degrees of parallelization. It uses learnable position query tokens to guide generation at target positions while ensuring mutual visibility among concurrently generated tokens for consistent parallel decoding. (2) Locality-aware Generation Ordering, a novel schedule that forms groups to minimize intra-group dependencies and maximize contextual support, enhancing generation quality. With these designs, we reduce the generation steps from 256 to 20 (256times256 res.) and 1024 to 48 (512times512 res.) without compromising quality on the ImageNet class-conditional generation, and achieving at least 3.4times lower latency than previous parallelized autoregressive models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01957</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:59:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
