<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 00:02:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>RoboVerse: Towards a Unified Platform, Dataset and Benchmark for   Scalable and Generalizable Robot Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18904</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.18904.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran Geng, Feishi Wang, Songlin Wei, Yuyang Li, Bangjun Wang, Boshi An, Charlie Tianyue Cheng, Haozhe Lou, Peihao Li, Yen-Jen Wang, Yutong Liang, Dylan Goetting, Chaoyi Xu, Haozhe Chen, Yuxi Qian, Yiran Geng, Jiageng Mao, Weikang Wan, Mingtong Zhang, Jiangran Lyu, Siheng Zhao, Jiazhao Zhang, Jialiang Zhang, Chengyang Zhao, Haoran Lu, Yufei Ding, Ran Gong, Yuran Wang, Yuxuan Kuang, Ruihai Wu, Baoxiong Jia, Carlo Sferrazza, Hao Dong, Siyuan Huang, Yue Wang, Jitendra Malik, Pieter Abbeel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data scaling and standardized evaluation benchmarks have driven significant advances in natural language processing and computer vision. However, robotics faces unique challenges in scaling data and establishing evaluation protocols. Collecting real-world data is resource-intensive and inefficient, while benchmarking in real-world scenarios remains highly complex. Synthetic data and simulation offer promising alternatives, yet existing efforts often fall short in data quality, diversity, and benchmark standardization. To address these challenges, we introduce RoboVerse, a comprehensive framework comprising a simulation platform, a synthetic dataset, and unified benchmarks. Our simulation platform supports multiple simulators and robotic embodiments, enabling seamless transitions between different environments. The synthetic dataset, featuring high-fidelity physics and photorealistic rendering, is constructed through multiple approaches. Additionally, we propose unified benchmarks for imitation learning and reinforcement learning, enabling evaluation across different levels of generalization. At the core of the simulation platform is MetaSim, an infrastructure that abstracts diverse simulation environments into a universal interface. It restructures existing simulation environments into a simulator-agnostic configuration system, as well as an API aligning different simulator functionalities, such as launching simulation environments, loading assets with initial states, stepping the physics engine, etc. This abstraction ensures interoperability and extensibility. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that RoboVerse enhances the performance of imitation learning, reinforcement learning, world model learning, and sim-to-real transfer. These results validate the reliability of our dataset and benchmarks, establishing RoboVerse as a robust solution for advancing robot learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18904</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 12:31:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selecting Optimal Candidate Profiles in Adversarial Environments Using   Conjoint Analysis and Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19043</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.19043.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Connor T. Jerzak, Priyanshi Chandra, Rishi Hazra&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Conjoint analysis, an application of factorial experimental design, is a popular tool in social science research for studying multidimensional preferences. In such experiments in the political analysis context, respondents are asked to choose between two hypothetical political candidates with randomly selected features, which can include partisanship, policy positions, gender and race. We consider the problem of identifying optimal candidate profiles. Because the number of unique feature combinations far exceeds the total number of observations in a typical conjoint experiment, it is impossible to determine the optimal profile exactly. To address this identification challenge, we derive an optimal stochastic intervention that represents a probability distribution of various attributes aimed at achieving the most favorable average outcome. We first consider an environment where one political party optimizes their candidate selection. We then move to the more realistic case where two political parties optimize their own candidate selection simultaneously and in opposition to each other. We apply the proposed methodology to an existing candidate choice conjoint experiment concerning vote choice for US president. We find that, in contrast to the non-adversarial approach, expected outcomes in the adversarial regime fall within range of historical electoral outcomes, with optimal strategies suggested by the method more likely to match the actual observed candidates compared to strategies derived from a non-adversarial approach. These findings indicate that incorporating adversarial dynamics into conjoint analysis may yield unique insight into social science data from experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19043</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 22:35:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI for Character Animation: A Comprehensive Survey of   Techniques, Applications, and Future Directions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19056</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.19056.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohammad Mahdi Abootorabi, Omid Ghahroodi, Pardis Sadat Zahraei, Hossein Behzadasl, Alireza Mirrokni, Mobina Salimipanah, Arash Rasouli, Bahar Behzadipour, Sara Azarnoush, Benyamin Maleki, Erfan Sadraiye, Kiarash Kiani Feriz, Mahdi Teymouri Nahad, Ali Moghadasi, Abolfazl Eshagh Abianeh, Nizi Nazar, Hamid R. Rabiee, Mahdieh Soleymani Baghshah, Meisam Ahmadi, Ehsaneddin Asgari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative AI is reshaping art, gaming, and most notably animation. Recent breakthroughs in foundation and diffusion models have reduced the time and cost of producing animated content. Characters are central animation components, involving motion, emotions, gestures, and facial expressions. The pace and breadth of advances in recent months make it difficult to maintain a coherent view of the field, motivating the need for an integrative review. Unlike earlier overviews that treat avatars, gestures, or facial animation in isolation, this survey offers a single, comprehensive perspective on all the main generative AI applications for character animation. We begin by examining the state-of-the-art in facial animation, expression rendering, image synthesis, avatar creation, gesture modeling, motion synthesis, object generation, and texture synthesis. We highlight leading research, practical deployments, commonly used datasets, and emerging trends for each area. To support newcomers, we also provide a comprehensive background section that introduces foundational models and evaluation metrics, equipping readers with the knowledge needed to enter the field. We discuss open challenges and map future research directions, providing a roadmap to advance AI-driven character-animation technologies. This survey is intended as a resource for researchers and developers entering the field of generative AI animation or adjacent fields. Resources are available at: https://github.com/llm-lab-org/Generative-AI-for-Character-Animation-Survey.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19056</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2025 00:09:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Llama-3.1-FoundationAI-SecurityLLM-Base-8B Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21039</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21039.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Paul Kassianik, Baturay Saglam, Alexander Chen, Blaine Nelson, Anu Vellore, Massimo Aufiero, Fraser Burch, Dhruv Kedia, Avi Zohary, Sajana Weerawardhena, Aman Priyanshu, Adam Swanda, Amy Chang, Hyrum Anderson, Kojin Oshiba, Omar Santos, Yaron Singer, Amin Karbasi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As transformer-based large language models (LLMs) increasingly permeate society, they have revolutionized domains such as software engineering, creative writing, and digital arts. However, their adoption in cybersecurity remains limited due to challenges like scarcity of specialized training data and complexity of representing cybersecurity-specific knowledge. To address these gaps, we present Foundation-Sec-8B, a cybersecurity-focused LLM built on the Llama 3.1 architecture and enhanced through continued pretraining on a carefully curated cybersecurity corpus. We evaluate Foundation-Sec-8B across both established and new cybersecurity benchmarks, showing that it matches Llama 3.1-70B and GPT-4o-mini in certain cybersecurity-specific tasks. By releasing our model to the public, we aim to accelerate progress and adoption of AI-driven tools in both public and private cybersecurity contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21039</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 08:41:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taming the Titans: A Survey of Efficient LLM Inference Serving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19720</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.19720.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ranran Zhen, Juntao Li, Yixin Ji, Zhenlin Yang, Tong Liu, Qingrong Xia, Xinyu Duan, Zhefeng Wang, Baoxing Huai, Min Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) for Generative AI have achieved remarkable progress, evolving into sophisticated and versatile tools widely adopted across various domains and applications. However, the substantial memory overhead caused by their vast number of parameters, combined with the high computational demands of the attention mechanism, poses significant challenges in achieving low latency and high throughput for LLM inference services. Recent advancements, driven by groundbreaking research, have significantly accelerated progress in this field. This paper provides a comprehensive survey of these methods, covering fundamental instance-level approaches, in-depth cluster-level strategies, emerging scenario directions, and other miscellaneous but important areas. At the instance level, we review model placement, request scheduling, decoding length prediction, storage management, and the disaggregation paradigm. At the cluster level, we explore GPU cluster deployment, multi-instance load balancing, and cloud service solutions. For emerging scenarios, we organize the discussion around specific tasks, modules, and auxiliary methods. To ensure a holistic overview, we also highlight several niche yet critical areas. Finally, we outline potential research directions to further advance the field of LLM inference serving.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19720</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 12:14:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Last Answer: Your Reasoning Trace Uncovers More than You   Think</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20708</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20708.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hasan Abed Al Kader Hammoud, Hani Itani, Bernard Ghanem&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) leverage step-by-step reasoning to solve complex problems. Standard evaluation practice involves generating a complete reasoning trace and assessing the correctness of the final answer presented at its conclusion. In this paper, we challenge the reliance on the final answer by posing the following two questions: Does the final answer reliably represent the model's optimal conclusion? Can alternative reasoning paths yield different results? To answer these questions, we analyze intermediate reasoning steps, termed subthoughts, and propose a method based on our findings. Our approach involves segmenting a reasoning trace into sequential subthoughts based on linguistic cues. We start by prompting the model to generate continuations from the end-point of each intermediate subthought. We extract a potential answer from every completed continuation originating from different subthoughts. We find that aggregating these answers by selecting the most frequent one (the mode) often yields significantly higher accuracy compared to relying solely on the answer derived from the original complete trace. Analyzing the consistency among the answers derived from different subthoughts reveals characteristics that correlate with the model's confidence and correctness, suggesting potential for identifying less reliable answers. Our experiments across various LLMs and challenging mathematical reasoning datasets (AIME2024 and AIME2025) show consistent accuracy improvements, with gains reaching up to 13\% and 10\% respectively. Implementation is available at: https://github.com/hammoudhasan/SubthoughtReasoner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20708</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 12:39:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Softpick: No Attention Sink, No Massive Activations with Rectified   Softmax</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20966</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20966.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zayd M. K. Zuhri, Erland Hilman Fuadi, Alham Fikri Aji&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce softpick, a rectified, not sum-to-one, drop-in replacement for softmax in transformer attention mechanisms that eliminates attention sink and massive activations. Our experiments with 340M parameter models demonstrate that softpick maintains performance parity with softmax on standard benchmarks while achieving 0% sink rate. The softpick transformer produces hidden states with significantly lower kurtosis (340 vs 33,510) and creates sparse attention maps (46.97% sparsity). Models using softpick consistently outperform softmax when quantized, with particularly pronounced advantages at lower bit precisions. Our analysis and discussion shows how softpick has the potential to open new possibilities for quantization, low-precision training, sparsity optimization, pruning, and interpretability. Our code is available at https://github.com/zaydzuhri/softpick-attention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20966</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 17:36:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phi-4-Mini-Reasoning: Exploring the Limits of Small Reasoning Language   Models in Math</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21233</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21233.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran Xu, Baolin Peng, Hany Awadalla, Dongdong Chen, Yen-Chun Chen, Mei Gao, Young Jin Kim, Yunsheng Li, Liliang Ren, Yelong Shen, Shuohang Wang, Weijian Xu, Jianfeng Gao, Weizhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-Thought (CoT) significantly enhances formal reasoning capabilities in Large Language Models (LLMs) by training them to explicitly generate intermediate reasoning steps. While LLMs readily benefit from such techniques, improving reasoning in Small Language Models (SLMs) remains challenging due to their limited model capacity. Recent work by Deepseek-R1 demonstrates that distillation from LLM-generated synthetic data can substantially improve the reasoning ability of SLM. However, the detailed modeling recipe is not disclosed. In this work, we present a systematic training recipe for SLMs that consists of four steps: (1) large-scale mid-training on diverse distilled long-CoT data, (2) supervised fine-tuning on high-quality long-CoT data, (3) Rollout DPO leveraging a carefully curated preference dataset, and (4) Reinforcement Learning (RL) with Verifiable Reward. We apply our method on Phi-4-Mini, a compact 3.8B-parameter model. The resulting Phi-4-Mini-Reasoning model exceeds, on math reasoning tasks, much larger reasoning models, e.g., outperforming DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-7B by 3.2 points and DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Llama-8B by 7.7 points on Math-500. Our results validate that a carefully designed training recipe, with large-scale high-quality CoT data, is effective to unlock strong reasoning capabilities even in resource-constrained small models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21233</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:04:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phi-4-reasoning Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21318</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21318.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marah Abdin, Sahaj Agarwal, Ahmed Awadallah, Vidhisha Balachandran, Harkirat Behl, Lingjiao Chen, Gustavo de Rosa, Suriya Gunasekar, Mojan Javaheripi, Neel Joshi, Piero Kauffmann, Yash Lara, Caio César Teodoro Mendes, Arindam Mitra, Besmira Nushi, Dimitris Papailiopoulos, Olli Saarikivi, Shital Shah, Vaishnavi Shrivastava, Vibhav Vineet, Yue Wu, Safoora Yousefi, Guoqing Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Phi-4-reasoning, a 14-billion parameter reasoning model that achieves strong performance on complex reasoning tasks. Trained via supervised fine-tuning of Phi-4 on carefully curated set of "teachable" prompts-selected for the right level of complexity and diversity-and reasoning demonstrations generated using o3-mini, Phi-4-reasoning generates detailed reasoning chains that effectively leverage inference-time compute. We further develop Phi-4-reasoning-plus, a variant enhanced through a short phase of outcome-based reinforcement learning that offers higher performance by generating longer reasoning traces. Across a wide range of reasoning tasks, both models outperform significantly larger open-weight models such as DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Llama-70B model and approach the performance levels of full DeepSeek-R1 model. Our comprehensive evaluations span benchmarks in math and scientific reasoning, coding, algorithmic problem solving, planning, and spatial understanding. Interestingly, we observe a non-trivial transfer of improvements to general-purpose benchmarks as well. In this report, we provide insights into our training data, our training methodologies, and our evaluations. We show that the benefit of careful data curation for supervised fine-tuning (SFT) extends to reasoning language models, and can be further amplified by reinforcement learning (RL). Finally, our evaluation points to opportunities for improving how we assess the performance and robustness of reasoning models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21318</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 05:05:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniBiomed: A Universal Foundation Model for Grounded Biomedical Image   Interpretation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21336</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21336.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Linshan Wu, Yuxiang Nie, Sunan He, Jiaxin Zhuang, Hao Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-modal interpretation of biomedical images opens up novel opportunities in biomedical image analysis. Conventional AI approaches typically rely on disjointed training, i.e., Large Language Models (LLMs) for clinical text generation and segmentation models for target extraction, which results in inflexible real-world deployment and a failure to leverage holistic biomedical information. To this end, we introduce UniBiomed, the first universal foundation model for grounded biomedical image interpretation. UniBiomed is based on a novel integration of Multi-modal Large Language Model (MLLM) and Segment Anything Model (SAM), which effectively unifies the generation of clinical texts and the segmentation of corresponding biomedical objects for grounded interpretation. In this way, UniBiomed is capable of tackling a wide range of biomedical tasks across ten diverse biomedical imaging modalities. To develop UniBiomed, we curate a large-scale dataset comprising over 27 million triplets of images, annotations, and text descriptions across ten imaging modalities. Extensive validation on 84 internal and external datasets demonstrated that UniBiomed achieves state-of-the-art performance in segmentation, disease recognition, region-aware diagnosis, visual question answering, and report generation. Moreover, unlike previous models that rely on clinical experts to pre-diagnose images and manually craft precise textual or visual prompts, UniBiomed can provide automated and end-to-end grounded interpretation for biomedical image analysis. This represents a novel paradigm shift in clinical workflows, which will significantly improve diagnostic efficiency. In summary, UniBiomed represents a novel breakthrough in biomedical AI, unlocking powerful grounded interpretation capabilities for more accurate and efficient biomedical image analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21336</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 05:51:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sadeed: Advancing Arabic Diacritization Through Small Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21635</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21635.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeina Aldallal, Sara Chrouf, Khalil Hennara, Mohamed Motaism Hamed, Muhammad Hreden, Safwan AlModhayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Arabic text diacritization remains a persistent challenge in natural language processing due to the language's morphological richness. In this paper, we introduce Sadeed, a novel approach based on a fine-tuned decoder-only language model adapted from Kuwain 1.5B Hennara et al. [2025], a compact model originally trained on diverse Arabic corpora. Sadeed is fine-tuned on carefully curated, high-quality diacritized datasets, constructed through a rigorous data-cleaning and normalization pipeline. Despite utilizing modest computational resources, Sadeed achieves competitive results compared to proprietary large language models and outperforms traditional models trained on similar domains. Additionally, we highlight key limitations in current benchmarking practices for Arabic diacritization. To address these issues, we introduce SadeedDiac-25, a new benchmark designed to enable fairer and more comprehensive evaluation across diverse text genres and complexity levels. Together, Sadeed and SadeedDiac-25 provide a robust foundation for advancing Arabic NLP applications, including machine translation, text-to-speech, and language learning tools.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21635</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 13:37:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebThinker: Empowering Large Reasoning Models with Deep Research   Capability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21776</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21776.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoxi Li, Jiajie Jin, Guanting Dong, Hongjin Qian, Yutao Zhu, Yongkang Wu, Ji-Rong Wen, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs), such as OpenAI-o1 and DeepSeek-R1, demonstrate impressive long-horizon reasoning capabilities. However, their reliance on static internal knowledge limits their performance on complex, knowledge-intensive tasks and hinders their ability to produce comprehensive research reports requiring synthesis of diverse web information. To address this, we propose WebThinker, a deep research agent that empowers LRMs to autonomously search the web, navigate web pages, and draft research reports during the reasoning process. WebThinker integrates a Deep Web Explorer module, enabling LRMs to dynamically search, navigate, and extract information from the web when encountering knowledge gaps. It also employs an Autonomous Think-Search-and-Draft strategy, allowing the model to seamlessly interleave reasoning, information gathering, and report writing in real time. To further enhance research tool utilization, we introduce an RL-based training strategy via iterative online Direct Preference Optimization (DPO). Extensive experiments on complex reasoning benchmarks (GPQA, GAIA, WebWalkerQA, HLE) and scientific report generation tasks (Glaive) demonstrate that WebThinker significantly outperforms existing methods and strong proprietary systems. Our approach enhances LRM reliability and applicability in complex scenarios, paving the way for more capable and versatile deep research systems. The code is available at https://github.com/RUC-NLPIR/WebThinker.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21776</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 16:25:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>COMPACT: COMPositional Atomic-to-Complex Visual Capability Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21850</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21850.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xindi Wu, Hee Seung Hwang, Polina Kirichenko, Olga Russakovsky&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) excel at simple vision-language tasks but struggle when faced with complex tasks that require multiple capabilities, such as simultaneously recognizing objects, counting them, and understanding their spatial relationships. This might be partially the result of the fact that Visual Instruction Tuning (VIT), a critical training step for MLLMs, has traditionally focused on scaling data volume, but not the compositional complexity of training examples. We propose COMPACT (COMPositional Atomic-to-complex visual Capability Tuning), which generates a training dataset explicitly controlling for the compositional complexity of the training examples. The data from COMPACT allows MLLMs to train on combinations of atomic capabilities to learn complex capabilities more efficiently. Across all benchmarks, COMPACT achieves comparable performance to the LLaVA-665k VIT while using less than 10% of its data budget, and even outperforms it on several, especially those involving complex multi-capability tasks. For example, COMPACT achieves substantial 83.3% improvement on MMStar and 94.0% improvement on MM-Vet compared to the full-scale VIT on particularly complex questions that require four or more atomic capabilities. COMPACT offers a scalable, data-efficient, visual compositional tuning recipe to improve on complex visual-language tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21850</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 17:57:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReVision: High-Quality, Low-Cost Video Generation with Explicit 3D   Physics Modeling for Complex Motion and Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21855</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21855.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qihao Liu, Ju He, Qihang Yu, Liang-Chieh Chen, Alan Yuille&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In recent years, video generation has seen significant advancements. However, challenges still persist in generating complex motions and interactions. To address these challenges, we introduce ReVision, a plug-and-play framework that explicitly integrates parameterized 3D physical knowledge into a pretrained conditional video generation model, significantly enhancing its ability to generate high-quality videos with complex motion and interactions. Specifically, ReVision consists of three stages. First, a video diffusion model is used to generate a coarse video. Next, we extract a set of 2D and 3D features from the coarse video to construct a 3D object-centric representation, which is then refined by our proposed parameterized physical prior model to produce an accurate 3D motion sequence. Finally, this refined motion sequence is fed back into the same video diffusion model as additional conditioning, enabling the generation of motion-consistent videos, even in scenarios involving complex actions and interactions. We validate the effectiveness of our approach on Stable Video Diffusion, where ReVision significantly improves motion fidelity and coherence. Remarkably, with only 1.5B parameters, it even outperforms a state-of-the-art video generation model with over 13B parameters on complex video generation by a substantial margin. Our results suggest that, by incorporating 3D physical knowledge, even a relatively small video diffusion model can generate complex motions and interactions with greater realism and controllability, offering a promising solution for physically plausible video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21855</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
