<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 10:20:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>ViSMaP: Unsupervised Hour-long Video Summarisation by Meta-Prompting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15921</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15921.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jian Hu, Dimitrios Korkinof, Shaogang Gong, Mariano Beguerisse-Diaz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce ViSMap: Unsupervised Video Summarisation by Meta Prompting, a system to summarise hour long videos with no-supervision. Most existing video understanding models work well on short videos of pre-segmented events, yet they struggle to summarise longer videos where relevant events are sparsely distributed and not pre-segmented. Moreover, long-form video understanding often relies on supervised hierarchical training that needs extensive annotations which are costly, slow and prone to inconsistency. With ViSMaP we bridge the gap between short videos (where annotated data is plentiful) and long ones (where it's not). We rely on LLMs to create optimised pseudo-summaries of long videos using segment descriptions from short ones. These pseudo-summaries are used as training data for a model that generates long-form video summaries, bypassing the need for expensive annotations of long videos. Specifically, we adopt a meta-prompting strategy to iteratively generate and refine creating pseudo-summaries of long videos. The strategy leverages short clip descriptions obtained from a supervised short video model to guide the summary. Each iteration uses three LLMs working in sequence: one to generate the pseudo-summary from clip descriptions, another to evaluate it, and a third to optimise the prompt of the generator. This iteration is necessary because the quality of the pseudo-summaries is highly dependent on the generator prompt, and varies widely among videos. We evaluate our summaries extensively on multiple datasets; our results show that ViSMaP achieves performance comparable to fully supervised state-of-the-art models while generalising across domains without sacrificing performance. Code will be released upon publication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15921</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 14:06:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boosting Generative Image Modeling via Joint Image-Feature Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16064</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.16064.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Theodoros Kouzelis, Efstathios Karypidis, Ioannis Kakogeorgiou, Spyros Gidaris, Nikos Komodakis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Latent diffusion models (LDMs) dominate high-quality image generation, yet integrating representation learning with generative modeling remains a challenge. We introduce a novel generative image modeling framework that seamlessly bridges this gap by leveraging a diffusion model to jointly model low-level image latents (from a variational autoencoder) and high-level semantic features (from a pretrained self-supervised encoder like DINO). Our latent-semantic diffusion approach learns to generate coherent image-feature pairs from pure noise, significantly enhancing both generative quality and training efficiency, all while requiring only minimal modifications to standard Diffusion Transformer architectures. By eliminating the need for complex distillation objectives, our unified design simplifies training and unlocks a powerful new inference strategy: Representation Guidance, which leverages learned semantics to steer and refine image generation. Evaluated in both conditional and unconditional settings, our method delivers substantial improvements in image quality and training convergence speed, establishing a new direction for representation-aware generative modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16064</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 17:41:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuaDMix: Quality-Diversity Balanced Data Selection for Efficient LLM   Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16511</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.16511.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fengze Liu, Weidong Zhou, Binbin Liu, Zhimiao Yu, Yifan Zhang, Haobin Lin, Yifeng Yu, Xiaohuan Zhou, Taifeng Wang, Yong Cao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Quality and diversity are two critical metrics for the training data of large language models (LLMs), positively impacting performance. Existing studies often optimize these metrics separately, typically by first applying quality filtering and then adjusting data proportions. However, these approaches overlook the inherent trade-off between quality and diversity, necessitating their joint consideration. Given a fixed training quota, it is essential to evaluate both the quality of each data point and its complementary effect on the overall dataset. In this paper, we introduce a unified data selection framework called QuaDMix, which automatically optimizes the data distribution for LLM pretraining while balancing both quality and diversity. Specifically, we first propose multiple criteria to measure data quality and employ domain classification to distinguish data points, thereby measuring overall diversity. QuaDMix then employs a unified parameterized data sampling function that determines the sampling probability of each data point based on these quality and diversity related labels. To accelerate the search for the optimal parameters involved in the QuaDMix framework, we conduct simulated experiments on smaller models and use LightGBM for parameters searching, inspired by the RegMix method. Our experiments across diverse models and datasets demonstrate that QuaDMix achieves an average performance improvement of 7.2% across multiple benchmarks. These results outperform the independent strategies for quality and diversity, highlighting the necessity and ability to balance data quality and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16511</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 08:36:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IberBench: LLM Evaluation on Iberian Languages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16921</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.16921.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; José Ángel González, Ian Borrego Obrador, Álvaro Romo Herrero, Areg Mikael Sarvazyan, Mara Chinea-Ríos, Angelo Basile, Marc Franco-Salvador&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) remain difficult to evaluate comprehensively, particularly for languages other than English, where high-quality data is often limited. Existing benchmarks and leaderboards are predominantly English-centric, with only a few addressing other languages. These benchmarks fall short in several key areas: they overlook the diversity of language varieties, prioritize fundamental Natural Language Processing (NLP) capabilities over tasks of industrial relevance, and are static. With these aspects in mind, we present IberBench, a comprehensive and extensible benchmark designed to assess LLM performance on both fundamental and industry-relevant NLP tasks, in languages spoken across the Iberian Peninsula and Ibero-America. IberBench integrates 101 datasets from evaluation campaigns and recent benchmarks, covering 22 task categories such as sentiment and emotion analysis, toxicity detection, and summarization. The benchmark addresses key limitations in current evaluation practices, such as the lack of linguistic diversity and static evaluation setups by enabling continual updates and community-driven model and dataset submissions moderated by a committee of experts. We evaluate 23 LLMs ranging from 100 million to 14 billion parameters and provide empirical insights into their strengths and limitations. Our findings indicate that (i) LLMs perform worse on industry-relevant tasks than in fundamental ones, (ii) performance is on average lower for Galician and Basque, (iii) some tasks show results close to random, and (iv) in other tasks LLMs perform above random but below shared task systems. IberBench offers open-source implementations for the entire evaluation pipeline, including dataset normalization and hosting, incremental evaluation of LLMs, and a publicly accessible leaderboard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16921</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 17:48:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DyMU: Dynamic Merging and Virtual Unmerging for Efficient VLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17040</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17040.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenhailong Wang, Senthil Purushwalkam, Caiming Xiong, Silvio Savarese, Heng Ji, Ran Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present DyMU, an efficient, training-free framework that dynamically reduces the computational burden of vision-language models (VLMs) while maintaining high task performance. Our approach comprises two key components. First, Dynamic Token Merging (DToMe) reduces the number of visual token embeddings by merging similar tokens based on image complexity, addressing the inherent inefficiency of fixed-length outputs in vision transformers. Second, Virtual Token Unmerging (VTU) simulates the expected token sequence for large language models (LLMs) by efficiently reconstructing the attention dynamics of a full sequence, thus preserving the downstream performance without additional fine-tuning. Unlike previous approaches, our method dynamically adapts token compression to the content of the image and operates completely training-free, making it readily applicable to most state-of-the-art VLM architectures. Extensive experiments on image and video understanding tasks demonstrate that DyMU can reduce the average visual token count by 32%-85% while achieving comparable performance to full-length models across diverse VLM architectures, including the recently popularized AnyRes-based visual encoders. Furthermore, through qualitative analyses, we demonstrate that DToMe effectively adapts token reduction based on image complexity and, unlike existing systems, provides users more control over computational costs. Project page: https://mikewangwzhl.github.io/dymu/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17040</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 18:38:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distilling semantically aware orders for autoregressive image generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17069</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17069.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rishav Pramanik, Antoine Poupon, Juan A. Rodriguez, Masih Aminbeidokhti, David Vazquez, Christopher Pal, Zhaozheng Yin, Marco Pedersoli&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive patch-based image generation has recently shown competitive results in terms of image quality and scalability. It can also be easily integrated and scaled within Vision-Language models. Nevertheless, autoregressive models require a defined order for patch generation. While a natural order based on the dictation of the words makes sense for text generation, there is no inherent generation order that exists for image generation. Traditionally, a raster-scan order (from top-left to bottom-right) guides autoregressive image generation models. In this paper, we argue that this order is suboptimal, as it fails to respect the causality of the image content: for instance, when conditioned on a visual description of a sunset, an autoregressive model may generate clouds before the sun, even though the color of clouds should depend on the color of the sun and not the inverse. In this work, we show that first by training a model to generate patches in any-given-order, we can infer both the content and the location (order) of each patch during generation. Secondly, we use these extracted orders to finetune the any-given-order model to produce better-quality images. Through our experiments, we show on two datasets that this new generation method produces better images than the traditional raster-scan approach, with similar training costs and no extra annotations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17069</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 19:33:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paper2Code: Automating Code Generation from Scientific Papers in Machine   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17192</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17192.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minju Seo, Jinheon Baek, Seongyun Lee, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the rapid growth of machine learning research, corresponding code implementations are often unavailable, making it slow and labor-intensive for researchers to reproduce results and build upon prior work. In the meantime, recent Large Language Models (LLMs) excel at understanding scientific documents and generating high-quality code. Inspired by this, we introduce PaperCoder, a multi-agent LLM framework that transforms machine learning papers into functional code repositories. PaperCoder operates in three stages: planning, where it constructs a high-level roadmap, designs the system architecture with diagrams, identifies file dependencies, and generates configuration files; analysis, which focuses on interpreting implementation-specific details; and generation, where modular, dependency-aware code is produced. Moreover, each phase is instantiated through a set of specialized agents designed to collaborate effectively across the pipeline. We then evaluate PaperCoder on generating code implementations from machine learning papers based on both model-based and human evaluations, specifically from the original paper authors, with author-released repositories as ground truth if available. Our results demonstrate the effectiveness of PaperCoder in creating high-quality, faithful implementations. Furthermore, it consistently shows strengths in the recently released PaperBench benchmark, surpassing strong baselines by substantial margins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17192</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 01:57:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perspective-Aware Reasoning in Vision-Language Models via Mental Imagery   Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17207</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17207.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Phillip Y. Lee, Jihyeon Je, Chanho Park, Mikaela Angelina Uy, Leonidas Guibas, Minhyuk Sung&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present a framework for perspective-aware reasoning in vision-language models (VLMs) through mental imagery simulation. Perspective-taking, the ability to perceive an environment or situation from an alternative viewpoint, is a key benchmark for human-level visual understanding, essential for environmental interaction and collaboration with autonomous agents. Despite advancements in spatial reasoning within VLMs, recent research has shown that modern VLMs significantly lack perspective-aware reasoning capabilities and exhibit a strong bias toward egocentric interpretations. To bridge the gap between VLMs and human perception, we focus on the role of mental imagery, where humans perceive the world through abstracted representations that facilitate perspective shifts. Motivated by this, we propose a framework for perspective-aware reasoning, named Abstract Perspective Change (APC), that effectively leverages vision foundation models, such as object detection, segmentation, and orientation estimation, to construct scene abstractions and enable perspective transformations. Our experiments on synthetic and real-image benchmarks, compared with various VLMs, demonstrate significant improvements in perspective-aware reasoning with our framework, further outperforming fine-tuned spatial reasoning models and novel-view-synthesis-based approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17207</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 02:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TimeChat-Online: 80% Visual Tokens are Naturally Redundant in Streaming   Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17343</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17343.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Linli Yao, Yicheng Li, Yuancheng Wei, Lei Li, Shuhuai Ren, Yuanxin Liu, Kun Ouyang, Lean Wang, Shicheng Li, Sida Li, Lingpeng Kong, Qi Liu, Yuanxing Zhang, Xu Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid growth of online video platforms, particularly live streaming services, has created an urgent need for real-time video understanding systems. These systems must process continuous video streams and respond to user queries instantaneously, presenting unique challenges for current Video Large Language Models (VideoLLMs). While existing VideoLLMs excel at processing complete videos, they face significant limitations in streaming scenarios due to their inability to handle dense, redundant frames efficiently. We introduce TimeChat-Online, a novel online VideoLLM that revolutionizes real-time video interaction. At its core lies our innovative Differential Token Drop (DTD) module, which addresses the fundamental challenge of visual redundancy in streaming videos. Drawing inspiration from human visual perception's Change Blindness phenomenon, DTD preserves meaningful temporal changes while filtering out static, redundant content between frames. Remarkably, our experiments demonstrate that DTD achieves an 82.8% reduction in video tokens while maintaining 98% performance on StreamingBench, revealing that over 80% of visual content in streaming videos is naturally redundant without requiring language guidance. To enable seamless real-time interaction, we present TimeChat-Online-139K, a comprehensive streaming video dataset featuring diverse interaction patterns including backward-tracing, current-perception, and future-responding scenarios. TimeChat-Online's unique Proactive Response capability, naturally achieved through continuous monitoring of video scene transitions via DTD, sets it apart from conventional approaches. Our extensive evaluation demonstrates TimeChat-Online's superior performance on streaming benchmarks (StreamingBench and OvOBench) and maintaining competitive results on long-form video tasks such as Video-MME and MLVU.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17343</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 07:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3DV-TON: Textured 3D-Guided Consistent Video Try-on via Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17414</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17414.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Min Wei, Chaohui Yu, Jingkai Zhou, Fan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video try-on replaces clothing in videos with target garments. Existing methods struggle to generate high-quality and temporally consistent results when handling complex clothing patterns and diverse body poses. We present 3DV-TON, a novel diffusion-based framework for generating high-fidelity and temporally consistent video try-on results. Our approach employs generated animatable textured 3D meshes as explicit frame-level guidance, alleviating the issue of models over-focusing on appearance fidelity at the expanse of motion coherence. This is achieved by enabling direct reference to consistent garment texture movements throughout video sequences. The proposed method features an adaptive pipeline for generating dynamic 3D guidance: (1) selecting a keyframe for initial 2D image try-on, followed by (2) reconstructing and animating a textured 3D mesh synchronized with original video poses. We further introduce a robust rectangular masking strategy that successfully mitigates artifact propagation caused by leaking clothing information during dynamic human and garment movements. To advance video try-on research, we introduce HR-VVT, a high-resolution benchmark dataset containing 130 videos with diverse clothing types and scenarios. Quantitative and qualitative results demonstrate our superior performance over existing methods. The project page is at this link https://2y7c3.github.io/3DV-TON/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17414</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 10:12:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking the Modality Barrier: Universal Embedding Learning with   Multimodal LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17432</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17432.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tiancheng Gu, Kaicheng Yang, Ziyong Feng, Xingjun Wang, Yanzhao Zhang, Dingkun Long, Yingda Chen, Weidong Cai, Jiankang Deng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Contrastive Language-Image Pre-training (CLIP) framework has become a widely used approach for multimodal representation learning, particularly in image-text retrieval and clustering. However, its efficacy is constrained by three key limitations: (1) text token truncation, (2) isolated image-text encoding, and (3) deficient compositionality due to bag-of-words behavior. While recent Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have demonstrated significant advances in generalized vision-language understanding, their potential for learning transferable multimodal representations remains underexplored.In this work, we present UniME (Universal Multimodal Embedding), a novel two-stage framework that leverages MLLMs to learn discriminative representations for diverse downstream tasks. In the first stage, we perform textual discriminative knowledge distillation from a powerful LLM-based teacher model to enhance the embedding capability of the MLLM\'s language component. In the second stage, we introduce hard negative enhanced instruction tuning to further advance discriminative representation learning. Specifically, we initially mitigate false negative contamination and then sample multiple hard negatives per instance within each batch, forcing the model to focus on challenging samples. This approach not only improves discriminative power but also enhances instruction-following ability in downstream tasks. We conduct extensive experiments on the MMEB benchmark and multiple retrieval tasks, including short and long caption retrieval and compositional retrieval. Results demonstrate that UniME achieves consistent performance improvement across all tasks, exhibiting superior discriminative and compositional capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17432</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 10:51:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RefVNLI: Towards Scalable Evaluation of Subject-driven Text-to-image   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17502</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17502.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aviv Slobodkin, Hagai Taitelbaum, Yonatan Bitton, Brian Gordon, Michal Sokolik, Nitzan Bitton Guetta, Almog Gueta, Royi Rassin, Itay Laish, Dani Lischinski, Idan Szpektor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Subject-driven text-to-image (T2I) generation aims to produce images that align with a given textual description, while preserving the visual identity from a referenced subject image. Despite its broad downstream applicability -- ranging from enhanced personalization in image generation to consistent character representation in video rendering -- progress in this field is limited by the lack of reliable automatic evaluation. Existing methods either assess only one aspect of the task (i.e., textual alignment or subject preservation), misalign with human judgments, or rely on costly API-based evaluation. To address this, we introduce RefVNLI, a cost-effective metric that evaluates both textual alignment and subject preservation in a single prediction. Trained on a large-scale dataset derived from video-reasoning benchmarks and image perturbations, RefVNLI outperforms or matches existing baselines across multiple benchmarks and subject categories (e.g., Animal, Object), achieving up to 6.4-point gains in textual alignment and 8.5-point gains in subject consistency. It also excels with lesser-known concepts, aligning with human preferences at over 87\% accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17502</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 12:44:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretable non-linear dimensionality reduction using gaussian   weighted linear transformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17601</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17601.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Erik Bergh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Dimensionality reduction techniques are fundamental for analyzing and visualizing high-dimensional data. With established methods like t-SNE and PCA presenting a trade-off between representational power and interpretability. This paper introduces a novel approach that bridges this gap by combining the interpretability of linear methods with the expressiveness of non-linear transformations. The proposed algorithm constructs a non-linear mapping between high-dimensional and low-dimensional spaces through a combination of linear transformations, each weighted by Gaussian functions. This architecture enables complex non-linear transformations while preserving the interpretability advantages of linear methods, as each transformation can be analyzed independently. The resulting model provides both powerful dimensionality reduction and transparent insights into the transformed space. Techniques for interpreting the learned transformations are presented, including methods for identifying suppressed dimensions and how space is expanded and contracted. These tools enable practitioners to understand how the algorithm preserves and modifies geometric relationships during dimensionality reduction. To ensure the practical utility of this algorithm, the creation of user-friendly software packages is emphasized, facilitating its adoption in both academia and industry.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17601</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 14:26:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step1X-Edit: A Practical Framework for General Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17761</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17761.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiyu Liu, Yucheng Han, Peng Xing, Fukun Yin, Rui Wang, Wei Cheng, Jiaqi Liao, Yingming Wang, Honghao Fu, Chunrui Han, Guopeng Li, Yuang Peng, Quan Sun, Jingwei Wu, Yan Cai, Zheng Ge, Ranchen Ming, Lei Xia, Xianfang Zeng, Yibo Zhu, Binxing Jiao, Xiangyu Zhang, Gang Yu, Daxin Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In recent years, image editing models have witnessed remarkable and rapid development. The recent unveiling of cutting-edge multimodal models such as GPT-4o and Gemini2 Flash has introduced highly promising image editing capabilities. These models demonstrate an impressive aptitude for fulfilling a vast majority of user-driven editing requirements, marking a significant advancement in the field of image manipulation. However, there is still a large gap between the open-source algorithm with these closed-source models. Thus, in this paper, we aim to release a state-of-the-art image editing model, called Step1X-Edit, which can provide comparable performance against the closed-source models like GPT-4o and Gemini2 Flash. More specifically, we adopt the Multimodal LLM to process the reference image and the user's editing instruction. A latent embedding has been extracted and integrated with a diffusion image decoder to obtain the target image. To train the model, we build a data generation pipeline to produce a high-quality dataset. For evaluation, we develop the GEdit-Bench, a novel benchmark rooted in real-world user instructions. Experimental results on GEdit-Bench demonstrate that Step1X-Edit outperforms existing open-source baselines by a substantial margin and approaches the performance of leading proprietary models, thereby making significant contributions to the field of image editing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17761</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 17:25:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Token-Shuffle: Towards High-Resolution Image Generation with   Autoregressive Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17789</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17789.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xu Ma, Peize Sun, Haoyu Ma, Hao Tang, Chih-Yao Ma, Jialiang Wang, Kunpeng Li, Xiaoliang Dai, Yujun Shi, Xuan Ju, Yushi Hu, Artsiom Sanakoyeu, Felix Juefei-Xu, Ji Hou, Junjiao Tian, Tao Xu, Tingbo Hou, Yen-Cheng Liu, Zecheng He, Zijian He, Matt Feiszli, Peizhao Zhang, Peter Vajda, Sam Tsai, Yun Fu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive (AR) models, long dominant in language generation, are increasingly applied to image synthesis but are often considered less competitive than Diffusion-based models. A primary limitation is the substantial number of image tokens required for AR models, which constrains both training and inference efficiency, as well as image resolution. To address this, we present Token-Shuffle, a novel yet simple method that reduces the number of image tokens in Transformer. Our key insight is the dimensional redundancy of visual vocabularies in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs), where low-dimensional visual codes from visual encoder are directly mapped to high-dimensional language vocabularies. Leveraging this, we consider two key operations: token-shuffle, which merges spatially local tokens along channel dimension to decrease the input token number, and token-unshuffle, which untangles the inferred tokens after Transformer blocks to restore the spatial arrangement for output. Jointly training with textual prompts, our strategy requires no additional pretrained text-encoder and enables MLLMs to support extremely high-resolution image synthesis in a unified next-token prediction way while maintaining efficient training and inference. For the first time, we push the boundary of AR text-to-image generation to a resolution of 2048x2048 with gratifying generation performance. In GenAI-benchmark, our 2.7B model achieves 0.77 overall score on hard prompts, outperforming AR models LlamaGen by 0.18 and diffusion models LDM by 0.15. Exhaustive large-scale human evaluations also demonstrate our prominent image generation ability in terms of text-alignment, visual flaw, and visual appearance. We hope that Token-Shuffle can serve as a foundational design for efficient high-resolution image generation within MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17789</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
