<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:02:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Reference-free Evaluation of Video Captions with Factual   Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16538</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16538.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shubhashis Roy Dipta, Tz-Ying Wu, Subarna Tripathi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video captions offer concise snapshots of actors, objects, and actions within a video, serving as valuable assets for applications such as question answering and event localization. However, acquiring human annotations for video captions is costly or even impractical, especially when dealing with diverse video domains. Existing models trained on supervised datasets face challenges in evaluating performance across different domains due to the reliance on reference-based evaluation protocols, which necessitate ground truth captions. This assumption is unrealistic for evaluating videos in the wild. To address these limitations, we propose a reference-free evaluation framework that does not require ground truth captions, focusing on factual grounding to ensure accurate assessment of caption quality. We introduce VC-Inspector, a novel caption quality evaluator that is both reference-free and factually grounded. Utilizing large language models, we generate pseudo captions of varying quality based on supervised data, which are subsequently used to train a multimodal model (i.e., Qwen2.5-VL) as the evaluator. Our approach demonstrates superior alignment with human judgments on the VATEX-Eval dataset, outperforming existing methods. The performance also generalizes to image caption datasets, Flickr8K-Expert and Flickr8K-CF, when viewing images as 1-frame videos. Overall, VC-Inspector offers a scalable and generalizable solution for evaluating the factual accuracy of video captions, paving the way for more effective and objective assessment methodologies in diverse video domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16538</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 05:04:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Photographer Eye: Teaching Multimodal Large Language Models to See   and Critique like Photographers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18582</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18582.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daiqing Qi, Handong Zhao, Jing Shi, Simon Jenni, Yifei Fan, Franck Dernoncourt, Scott Cohen, Sheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While editing directly from life, photographers have found it too difficult to see simultaneously both the blue and the sky. Photographer and curator, Szarkowski insightfully revealed one of the notable gaps between general and aesthetic visual understanding: while the former focuses on identifying the factual element in an image (sky), the latter transcends such object identification, viewing it instead as an aesthetic component--a pure color block (blue). Such fundamental distinctions between general (detection, localization, etc.) and aesthetic (color, lighting, composition, etc.) visual understanding present a significant challenge for Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs). Although some recent works have made initial explorations, they are often limited to general and basic aesthetic commonsense. As a result, they frequently fall short in real-world scenarios (Fig. 1), which require extensive expertise--including photographic techniques, photo pre/post-processing knowledge, and more, to provide a detailed analysis and description. To fundamentally enhance the aesthetics understanding of MLLMs, we first introduce a novel dataset, PhotoCritique, derived from extensive discussions among professional photographers and enthusiasts, and characterized by the large scale, expertise, and diversity. Then, to better learn visual aesthetics from PhotoCritique, we furthur propose a novel model, PhotoEye, featuring a languageguided multi-view vision fusion mechanism to understand image aesthetics from multiple perspectives. Finally, we present a novel benchmark, PhotoBench, a comprehensive and professional benchmark for aesthetic visual understanding. On existing benchmarks and PhotoBench, our model demonstrates clear advantages over existing models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18582</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 02:59:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charting a Decade of Computational Linguistics in Italy: The CLiC-it   Corpus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19033</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19033.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chiara Alzetta, Serena Auriemma, Alessandro Bondielli, Luca Dini, Chiara Fazzone, Alessio Miaschi, Martina Miliani, Marta Sartor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Over the past decade, Computational Linguistics (CL) and Natural Language Processing (NLP) have evolved rapidly, especially with the advent of Transformer-based Large Language Models (LLMs). This shift has transformed research goals and priorities, from Lexical and Semantic Resources to Language Modelling and Multimodality. In this study, we track the research trends of the Italian CL and NLP community through an analysis of the contributions to CLiC-it, arguably the leading Italian conference in the field. We compile the proceedings from the first 10 editions of the CLiC-it conference (from 2014 to 2024) into the CLiC-it Corpus, providing a comprehensive analysis of both its metadata, including author provenance, gender, affiliations, and more, as well as the content of the papers themselves, which address various topics. Our goal is to provide the Italian and international research communities with valuable insights into emerging trends and key developments over time, supporting informed decisions and future directions in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19033</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 14:06:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combinatorial Creativity: A New Frontier in Generalization Abilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21043</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21043.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Samuel Schapiro, Sumuk Shashidhar, Alexi Gladstone, Jonah Black, Royce Moon, Dilek Hakkani-Tur, Lav R. Varshney&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Artificial intelligence (AI) systems, and Large Language Models (LLMs) in particular, are increasingly employed for creative tasks like scientific idea generation, constituting a form of generalization from training data unaddressed by existing conceptual frameworks. Despite its similarities to compositional generalization (CG), combinatorial creativity (CC) is an open-ended ability. Instead of evaluating for accuracy or correctness against fixed targets, which would contradict the open-ended nature of CC, we propose a theoretical framework and algorithmic task for evaluating outputs by their degrees of novelty and utility. From here, we make several important empirical contributions: (1) We obtain the first insights into the scaling behavior of creativity for LLMs. (2) We discover that, for fixed compute budgets, there exist optimal model depths and widths for creative ability. (3) We find that the ideation-execution gap, whereby LLMs excel at generating novel scientific ideas but struggle to ensure their practical feasibility, may be explained by a more fundamental novelty-utility tradeoff characteristic of creativity algorithms in general. Importantly, this tradeoff remains persistent even at scale, casting doubt on the long-term creative potential of LLMs in their current form. Together, our conceptual framework and empirical findings provide a foundation for understanding and improving creativity in modern AI models, bridging the gap between human and machine intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21043</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 11:48:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LUMINA: Detecting Hallucinations in RAG System with Context-Knowledge   Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21875</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21875.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Min-Hsuan Yeh, Yixuan Li, Tanwi Mallick&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) aims to mitigate hallucinations in large language models (LLMs) by grounding responses in retrieved documents. Yet, RAG-based LLMs still hallucinate even when provided with correct and sufficient context. A growing line of work suggests that this stems from an imbalance between how models use external context and their internal knowledge, and several approaches have attempted to quantify these signals for hallucination detection. However, existing methods require extensive hyperparameter tuning, limiting their generalizability. We propose LUMINA, a novel framework that detects hallucinations in RAG systems through context-knowledge signals: external context utilization is quantified via distributional distance, while internal knowledge utilization is measured by tracking how predicted tokens evolve across transformer layers. We further introduce a framework for statistically validating these measurements. Experiments on common RAG hallucination benchmarks and four open-source LLMs show that LUMINA achieves consistently high AUROC and AUPRC scores, outperforming prior utilization-based methods by up to +13% AUROC on HalluRAG. Moreover, LUMINA remains robust under relaxed assumptions about retrieval quality and model matching, offering both effectiveness and practicality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21875</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 04:57:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MultiCrafter: High-Fidelity Multi-Subject Generation via Spatially   Disentangled Attention and Identity-Aware Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21953</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21953.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tao Wu, Yibo Jiang, Yehao Lu, Zhizhong Wang, Zeyi Huang, Zequn Qin, Xi Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-subject image generation aims to synthesize user-provided subjects in a single image while preserving subject fidelity, ensuring prompt consistency, and aligning with human aesthetic preferences. However, existing methods, particularly those built on the In-Context-Learning paradigm, are limited by their reliance on simple reconstruction-based objectives, leading to both severe attribute leakage that compromises subject fidelity and failing to align with nuanced human preferences. To address this, we propose MultiCrafter, a framework that ensures high-fidelity, preference-aligned generation. First, we find that the root cause of attribute leakage is a significant entanglement of attention between different subjects during the generation process. Therefore, we introduce explicit positional supervision to explicitly separate attention regions for each subject, effectively mitigating attribute leakage. To enable the model to accurately plan the attention region of different subjects in diverse scenarios, we employ a Mixture-of-Experts architecture to enhance the model's capacity, allowing different experts to focus on different scenarios. Finally, we design a novel online reinforcement learning framework to align the model with human preferences, featuring a scoring mechanism to accurately assess multi-subject fidelity and a more stable training strategy tailored for the MoE architecture. Experiments validate that our framework significantly improves subject fidelity while aligning with human preferences better.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21953</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 06:41:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Does Reasoning Matter? A Controlled Study of Reasoning's   Contribution to Model Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22193</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22193.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nicolas Boizard, Hippolyte Gisserot-Boukhlef, Kevin El-Haddad, Céline Hudelot, Pierre Colombo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) with reasoning capabilities have achieved state-of-the-art performance on a wide range of tasks. Despite its empirical success, the tasks and model scales at which reasoning becomes effective, as well as its training and inference costs, remain underexplored. In this work, we rely on a synthetic data distillation framework to conduct a large-scale supervised study. We compare Instruction Fine-Tuning (IFT) and reasoning models of varying sizes, on a wide range of math-centric and general-purpose tasks, evaluating both multiple-choice and open-ended formats. Our analysis reveals that reasoning consistently improves model performance, often matching or surpassing significantly larger IFT systems. Notably, while IFT remains Pareto-optimal in training and inference costs, reasoning models become increasingly valuable as model size scales, overcoming IFT performance limits on reasoning-intensive and open-ended tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22193</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 10:53:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StableToken: A Noise-Robust Semantic Speech Tokenizer for Resilient   SpeechLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22220</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22220.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhan Song, Linhao Zhang, Chuhan Wu, Aiwei Liu, Wei Jia, Houfeng Wang, Xiao Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Prevalent semantic speech tokenizers, designed to capture linguistic content, are surprisingly fragile. We find they are not robust to meaning-irrelevant acoustic perturbations; even at high Signal-to-Noise Ratios (SNRs) where speech is perfectly intelligible, their output token sequences can change drastically, increasing the learning burden for downstream LLMs. This instability stems from two flaws: a brittle single-path quantization architecture and a distant training signal indifferent to intermediate token stability. To address this, we introduce StableToken, a tokenizer that achieves stability through a consensus-driven mechanism. Its multi-branch architecture processes audio in parallel, and these representations are merged via a powerful bit-wise voting mechanism to form a single, stable token sequence. StableToken sets a new state-of-the-art in token stability, drastically reducing Unit Edit Distance (UED) under diverse noise conditions. This foundational stability translates directly to downstream benefits, significantly improving the robustness of SpeechLLMs on a variety of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22220</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 11:32:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REMA: A Unified Reasoning Manifold Framework for Interpreting Large   Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22518</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22518.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bo Li, Guanzhi Deng, Ronghao Chen, Junrong Yue, Shuo Zhang, Qinghua Zhao, Linqi Song, Lijie Wen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding how Large Language Models (LLMs) perform complex reasoning and their failure mechanisms is a challenge in interpretability research. To provide a measurable geometric analysis perspective, we define the concept of the Reasoning Manifold, a latent low-dimensional geometric structure formed by the internal representations corresponding to all correctly reasoned generations. This structure can be conceptualized as the embodiment of the effective thinking paths that the model has learned to successfully solve a given task. Based on this concept, we build REMA, a framework that explains the origins of failures by quantitatively comparing the spatial relationships of internal model representations corresponding to both erroneous and correct reasoning samples. Specifically, REMA first quantifies the geometric deviation of each erroneous representation by calculating its k-nearest neighbors distance to the approximated manifold formed by correct representations, thereby providing a unified failure signal. It then localizes the divergence points where these deviations first become significant by tracking this deviation metric across the model's layers and comparing it against a baseline of internal fluctuations from correct representations, thus identifying where the reasoning chain begins to go off-track. Our extensive experiments on diverse language and multimodal models and tasks demonstrate the low-dimensional nature of the reasoning manifold and the high separability between erroneous and correct reasoning representations. The results also validate the effectiveness of the REMA framework in analyzing the origins of reasoning failures. This research connects abstract reasoning failures to measurable geometric deviations in representations, providing new avenues for in-depth understanding and diagnosis of the internal computational processes of black-box models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22518</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 16:02:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniMIC: Token-Based Multimodal Interactive Coding for Human-AI   Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22570</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22570.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qi Mao, Tinghan Yang, Jiahao Li, Bin Li, Libiao Jin, Yan Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid progress of Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) and cloud-based AI agents is transforming human-AI collaboration into bidirectional, multimodal interaction. However, existing codecs remain optimized for unimodal, one-way communication, resulting in repeated degradation under conventional compress-transmit-reconstruct pipelines. To address this limitation, we propose UniMIC, a Unified token-based Multimodal Interactive Coding framework that bridges edge devices and cloud AI agents. Instead of transmitting raw pixels or plain text, UniMIC employs compact tokenized representations as the communication medium, enabling efficient low-bitrate transmission while maintaining compatibility with LMMs. To further enhance compression, lightweight Transformer-based entropy models with scenario-specific designs-generic, masked, and text-conditioned-effectively minimize inter-token redundancy. Extensive experiments on text-to-image generation, text-guided inpainting, outpainting, and visual question answering show that UniMIC achieves substantial bitrate savings and remains robust even at ultra-low bitrates (&lt;0.05bpp), without compromising downstream task performance. These results establish UniMIC as a practical and forward-looking paradigm for next-generation multimodal interactive communication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22570</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 16:46:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Experts Search: Enhancing Reasoning in Mixture-of-Experts LLMs   at Test Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22572</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22572.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yixuan Han, Fan Ma, Ruijie Quan, Yi Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Test-Time Scaling (TTS) enhances the reasoning ability of large language models (LLMs) by allocating additional computation during inference. However, existing approaches primarily rely on output-level sampling while overlooking the role of model architecture. In mainstream Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) LLMs, we observe that varying the number of activated experts yields complementary solution sets with stable accuracy, revealing a new and underexplored source of diversity. Motivated by this observation, we propose Dynamic Experts Search (DES), a TTS strategy that elevates expert activation into a controllable dimension of the search space. DES integrates two key components: (1) Dynamic MoE, which enables direct control of expert counts during inference to generate diverse reasoning trajectories without additional cost; and (2) Expert Configuration Inheritance, which preserves consistent expert counts within a reasoning path while varying them across runs, thereby balancing stability and diversity throughout the search. Extensive experiments across MoE architectures, verifiers and reasoning benchmarks (i.e., math, code and knowledge) demonstrate that DES reliably outperforms TTS baselines, enhancing accuracy and stability without additional cost. These results highlight DES as a practical and scalable form of architecture-aware TTS, illustrating how structural flexibility in modern LLMs can advance reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22572</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 16:49:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoScore2: Think before You Score in Generative Video Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22799</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22799.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuan He, Dongfu Jiang, Ping Nie, Minghao Liu, Zhengxuan Jiang, Mingyi Su, Wentao Ma, Junru Lin, Chun Ye, Yi Lu, Keming Wu, Benjamin Schneider, Quy Duc Do, Zhuofeng Li, Yiming Jia, Yuxuan Zhang, Guo Cheng, Haozhe Wang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Qunshu Lin, Yuanxing Zhang, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in text-to-video generation have produced increasingly realistic and diverse content, yet evaluating such videos remains a fundamental challenge due to their multi-faceted nature encompassing visual quality, semantic alignment, and physical consistency. Existing evaluators and reward models are limited to single opaque scores, lack interpretability, or provide only coarse analysis, making them insufficient for capturing the comprehensive nature of video quality assessment. We present VideoScore2, a multi-dimensional, interpretable, and human-aligned framework that explicitly evaluates visual quality, text-to-video alignment, and physical/common-sense consistency while producing detailed chain-of-thought rationales. Our model is trained on a large-scale dataset VideoFeedback2 containing 27,168 human-annotated videos with both scores and reasoning traces across three dimensions, using a two-stage pipeline of supervised fine-tuning followed by reinforcement learning with Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) to enhance analytical robustness. Extensive experiments demonstrate that VideoScore2 achieves superior performance with 44.35 (+5.94) accuracy on our in-domain benchmark VideoScore-Bench-v2 and 50.37 (+4.32) average performance across four out-of-domain benchmarks (VideoGenReward-Bench, VideoPhy2, etc), while providing interpretable assessments that bridge the gap between evaluation and controllable generation through effective reward modeling for Best-of-N sampling. Project Page: https://tiger-ai-lab.github.io/VideoScore2/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22799</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 18:09:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMPB: It's Time for Multi-Modal Personalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22820</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22820.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaeik Kim, Woojin Kim, Woohyeon Park, Jaeyoung Do&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual personalization is essential in user-facing AI systems such as smart homes and healthcare, where aligning model behavior with user-centric concepts is critical. However, recent large Vision-Language Models (VLMs), despite their broad applicability, remain underexplored in their ability to adapt to individual users. In this paper, we introduce MMPB, the first extensive benchmark for evaluating VLMs on personalization. MMPB comprises 10k image-query pairs and includes 111 personalizable concepts across four categories: humans, animals, objects, and characters, with the human category enriched with preference-grounded queries. We structure personalization into three main task types, each highlighting a different key property of VLMs. Using 23 widely used VLMs including both open- and closed-source models, we evaluate personalization performance via a three-stage protocol: concept injection, multi-turn dialogue, and personalized querying. Our findings indicate that most VLMs (including some closed-source models) struggle with personalization, particularly in maintaining consistency over dialogue, handling user preferences, and adapting to visual cues. Our analysis reveals that the challenges in VLM personalization (such as refusal behaviors and long-context forgetting) highlight substantial room for improvement. By identifying these limitations and offering a scalable benchmark, MMPB offers valuable insights and a solid foundation for future research toward truly personalized multi-modal AI. Project Page: aidaslab.github.io/MMPB&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22820</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 18:24:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critique-Coder: Enhancing Coder Models by Critique Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22824</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22824.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chi Ruan, Dongfu Jiang, Yubo Wang, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning (RL) has emerged as a popular training paradigm, particularly when paired with reasoning models. While effective, it primarily focuses on generating responses and lacks mechanisms to explicitly foster critique or reflection. Several recent studies, like Critique-Fine-Tuning (CFT) and Critique-Guided-Distillation (CGD) have shown the benefits of explicitly teaching LLMs how to critique. Motivated by them, we propose Critique Reinforcement Learning (CRL), where the model is tasked with generating a critique for a given (question, solution) pair. The reward is determined solely by whether the final judgment label c in {True, False} of the generated critique aligns with the ground-truth judgment c^*. Building on this point, we introduce Critique-Coder, which is trained on a hybrid of RL and CRL by substituting 20\% of the standard RL data with CRL data. We fine-tune multiple models (Critique-Coder) and evaluate them on different benchmarks to show their advantages over RL-only models. We show that Critique-Coder consistently outperforms RL-only baselines on all the evaluated benchmarks. Notably, our Critique-Coder-8B can reach over 60\% on LiveCodeBench (v5), outperforming other reasoning models like DeepCoder-14B and GPT-o1. Beyond code generation, Critique-Coder also demonstrates enhanced general reasoning abilities, as evidenced by its better performance on logic reasoning tasks from the BBEH dataset. This indicates that the application of CRL on coding datasets enhances general reasoning and critique abilities, which are transferable across a broad range of tasks. Hence, we believe that CRL works as a great complement to standard RL for LLM reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22824</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 18:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChatInject: Abusing Chat Templates for Prompt Injection in LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22830</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22830.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hwan Chang, Yonghyun Jun, Hwanhee Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The growing deployment of large language model (LLM) based agents that interact with external environments has created new attack surfaces for adversarial manipulation. One major threat is indirect prompt injection, where attackers embed malicious instructions in external environment output, causing agents to interpret and execute them as if they were legitimate prompts. While previous research has focused primarily on plain-text injection attacks, we find a significant yet underexplored vulnerability: LLMs' dependence on structured chat templates and their susceptibility to contextual manipulation through persuasive multi-turn dialogues. To this end, we introduce ChatInject, an attack that formats malicious payloads to mimic native chat templates, thereby exploiting the model's inherent instruction-following tendencies. Building on this foundation, we develop a persuasion-driven Multi-turn variant that primes the agent across conversational turns to accept and execute otherwise suspicious actions. Through comprehensive experiments across frontier LLMs, we demonstrate three critical findings: (1) ChatInject achieves significantly higher average attack success rates than traditional prompt injection methods, improving from 5.18% to 32.05% on AgentDojo and from 15.13% to 45.90% on InjecAgent, with multi-turn dialogues showing particularly strong performance at average 52.33% success rate on InjecAgent, (2) chat-template-based payloads demonstrate strong transferability across models and remain effective even against closed-source LLMs, despite their unknown template structures, and (3) existing prompt-based defenses are largely ineffective against this attack approach, especially against Multi-turn variants. These findings highlight vulnerabilities in current agent systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22830</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 18:38:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Large Language Model Distillation: A Constrained Markov   Decision Process Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22921</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22921.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Matthieu Zimmer, Xiaotong Ji, Tu Nguyen, Haitham Bou Ammar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce a novel approach to large language model (LLM) distillation by formulating it as a constrained reinforcement learning problem. While recent work has begun exploring the integration of task-specific rewards into distillation processes, existing methods typically rely on ad-hoc reward weighting. We propose a principled optimization framework that maximizes task-specific rewards while constraining the divergence from the teacher model to remain below a specified threshold. Our approach adapts constrained state augmented reinforcement learning to the distillation setting, introducing a modified reward function that maintains theoretical guarantees of constraint satisfaction without requiring state augmentation or teacher model access during deployment and without the computational overhead of the dual Lagrangian methods. Through extensive experiments on mathematical reasoning tasks, we demonstrate that our method achieves better constraint satisfaction rates and better reasoning compared to the soft Lagrangian relaxation baselines while maintaining competitive task performance. Our framework provides a theoretically grounded and practically efficient solution for reward-aware distillation in resource-constrained settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22921</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 20:47:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ADAM: A Diverse Archive of Mankind for Evaluating and Enhancing LLMs in   Biographical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22991</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22991.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jasin Cekinmez, Omid Ghahroodi, Saad Fowad Chandle, Dhiman Gupta, Ehsaneddin Asgari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce ADAM (A Diverse Archive of Mankind), a framework for evaluating and improving multimodal large language models (MLLMs) in biographical reasoning. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to systematically examine LLM capabilities in biography, a critical yet underexplored dimension of factual knowledge. At its core, AdamDB is a multilingual and multimodal dataset covering over 4 million individuals across geography, time, and profession, while AdamBench provides cognitively structured evaluations based on Bloom's taxonomy, spanning six reasoning levels in both English and native languages. To address hallucinations, particularly for lesser-known individuals, we propose AdamRAG, a retrieval-augmented generation system tailored to biographical contexts. Experiments show that AdamRAG substantially improves open-source models and modestly benefits closed-source ones, with the largest gains on lower-order reasoning. Popularity strongly mediates accuracy, and multimodal input via face images offers smaller, less consistent improvements than retrieval. ADAM establishes the first benchmark and framework for cognitively, culturally, and multimodally grounded biographical evaluation, advancing the development of multilingual, accurate, and hallucination-resistant MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22991</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 23:04:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Language Prior of LVLMs by Contrasting Chain-of-Embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23050</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23050.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lin Long, Changdae Oh, Seongheon Park, Yixuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large vision-language models (LVLMs) achieve strong performance on multimodal tasks, yet they often default to their language prior (LP) -- memorized textual patterns from pre-training while under-utilizing visual evidence. Prior analyses of LP mostly rely on input-output probing, which fails to reveal the internal mechanisms governing when and how vision influences model behavior. To address this gap, we present the first systematic analysis of language prior through the lens of chain-of-embedding, which examines the layer-wise representation dynamics within LVLMs. Our analysis reveals a universal phenomenon: each model exhibits a Visual Integration Point (VIP), a critical layer at which visual information begins to meaningfully reshape hidden representations and influence decoding. Building on this observation, we introduce the Total Visual Integration (TVI) estimator, which aggregates representation distance beyond the VIP to quantify how strongly visual query influences response generation. Across 54 model-dataset combinations spanning 9 contemporary LVLMs and 6 benchmarks, we demonstrate that VIP consistently emerges, and that TVI reliably predicts the strength of language prior. This offers a principled toolkit for diagnosing and understanding language prior in LVLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23050</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 02:12:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local Success Does Not Compose: Benchmarking Large Language Models for   Compositional Formal Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23061</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23061.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xu Xu, Xin Li, Xingwei Qu, Jie Fu, Binhang Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce DafnyCOMP, a benchmark for evaluating large language models (LLMs) on compositional specification generation in Dafny. Unlike prior benchmarks that focus on single-function tasks, DafnyCOMP targets programs composed of multiple interacting functions with data dependencies, requiring reasoning across component boundaries. The benchmark consists of 300 automatically synthesized multi-function programs. We evaluate several state-of-the-art LLM families and find that, while they perform well on single-function verification, their performance drops sharply on compositional tasks. Analysis reveals systematic failures in cross-functional reasoning, including fragile specifications, misalignment between implementations and proofs, and unstable reasoning. DafnyCOMP thus provides a diagnostic tool for measuring progress toward reliable, verifiable, and compositional code generation with LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23061</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 02:33:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplayer Nash Preference Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23102</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23102.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fang Wu, Xu Huang, Weihao Xuan, Zhiwei Zhang, Yijia Xiao, Guancheng Wan, Xiaomin Li, Bing Hu, Peng Xia, Jure Leskovec, Yejin Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF) has emerged as the standard paradigm for aligning large language models (LLMs) with human preferences. However, reward-based methods built on the Bradley-Terry assumption struggle to capture the non-transitive and heterogeneous nature of real-world preferences. To address this, recent studies have reframed alignment as a two-player Nash game, giving rise to Nash learning from human feedback (NLHF). While this perspective has inspired algorithms such as INPO, ONPO, and EGPO with strong theoretical and empirical guarantees, they remain fundamentally restricted to two-player interactions, creating a single-opponent bias that fails to capture the full complexity of realistic preference structures. In this work, we introduce Multiplayer Nash Preference Optimization (MNPO), a novel framework that generalizes NLHF to the multiplayer regime. It formulates alignment as an n-player game, where each policy competes against a population of opponents while being regularized toward a reference model. Our framework establishes well-defined Nash equilibria in multiplayer settings and extends the concept of duality gap to quantify approximation quality. We demonstrate that MNPO inherits the equilibrium guarantees of two-player methods while enabling richer competitive dynamics and improved coverage of diverse preference structures. Through comprehensive empirical evaluation, we show that MNPO consistently outperforms existing NLHF baselines on instruction-following benchmarks, achieving superior alignment quality under heterogeneous annotator conditions and mixed-policy evaluation scenarios. Together, these results establish MNPO as a principled and scalable framework for aligning LLMs with complex, non-transitive human preferences. Code is available at https://github.com/smiles724/MNPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23102</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 04:18:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RHYTHM: Reasoning with Hierarchical Temporal Tokenization for Human   Mobility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23115</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23115.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoyu He, Haozheng Luo, Yan Chen, Qi R. Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Predicting human mobility is inherently challenging due to complex long-range dependencies and multi-scale periodic behaviors. To address this, we introduce RHYTHM (Reasoning with Hierarchical Temporal Tokenization for Human Mobility), a unified framework that leverages large language models (LLMs) as general-purpose spatio-temporal predictors and trajectory reasoners. Methodologically, RHYTHM employs temporal tokenization to partition each trajectory into daily segments and encode them as discrete tokens with hierarchical attention that captures both daily and weekly dependencies, thereby significantly reducing the sequence length while preserving cyclical information. Additionally, we enrich token representations by adding pre-computed prompt embeddings for trajectory segments and prediction targets via a frozen LLM, and feeding these combined embeddings back into the LLM backbone to capture complex interdependencies. Computationally, RHYTHM freezes the pretrained LLM's backbone to reduce attention complexity and memory cost. We evaluate our model against state-of-the-art methods using three real-world datasets. Notably, RHYTHM achieves a 2.4% improvement in overall accuracy, a 5.0% increase on weekends, and a 24.6% reduction in training time. Code is publicly available at https://github.com/he-h/rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23115</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 04:55:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MathBode: Frequency-Domain Fingerprints of LLM Mathematical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23143</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23143.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Charles L. Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents MathBode, a dynamic diagnostic for mathematical reasoning in large language models (LLMs). Instead of one-shot accuracy, MathBode treats each parametric problem as a system: we drive a single parameter sinusoidally and fit first-harmonic responses of model outputs and exact solutions. This yields interpretable, frequency-resolved metrics -- gain (amplitude tracking) and phase (lag) -- that form Bode-style fingerprints. Across five closed-form families (linear solve, ratio/saturation, compound interest, 2x2 linear systems, similar triangles), the diagnostic surfaces systematic low-pass behavior and growing phase lag that accuracy alone obscures. We compare several models against a symbolic baseline that calibrates the instrument (G approx 1, phi approx 0). Results separate frontier from mid-tier models on dynamics, providing a compact, reproducible protocol that complements standard benchmarks with actionable measurements of reasoning fidelity and consistency. We open-source the dataset and code to enable further research and adoption.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23143</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 06:06:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Harm to Help: Turning Reasoning In-Context Demos into Assets for   Reasoning LMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23196</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23196.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haonan Wang, Weida Liang, Zihang Fu, Nie Zheng, Yifan Zhang, Yao Tong, Tongyao Zhu, Hao Jiang, Chuang Li, Jiaying Wu, Kenji Kawaguchi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reasoning LLMs (RLMs), especially those trained with verifier-based reinforcement learning, often perform worse with few-shot CoT than with direct answering. We revisit this paradox using high-quality reasoning traces from DeepSeek-R1 as demonstrations and find that adding more exemplars consistently degrades accuracy, even when demonstrations are optimal. A detailed analysis reveals two mechanisms behind this decline: (i) semantic misguidance, where high textual similarity leads the model to treat the target as the same as the exemplar and to copy intermediate steps verbatim; and (ii) strategy transfer failure, where the model struggles to extract useful reasoning strategies and apply them to target questions. Guided by these, we introduce Insight-to-Solve (I2S), a sequential test-time procedure that turns demonstrations into explicit, reusable insights and derives a target-specific reasoning trace; optionally, the reasoning is self-refined for coherence and correctness (I2S+). Extensive experiments on diverse benchmarks show that I2S and I2S+ consistently outperform both direct answering and test-time scaling baselines across open- and closed-source models. Even for GPT models, our method helps: on AIME'25, GPT-4.1 rises by +14.0%, and o1-mini improves by +2.7% on AIME and +1.7% on GPQA, indicating that in-context demonstrations can be harnessed effectively via insight-refine-solve framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23196</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 08:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WirelessMathLM: Teaching Mathematical Reasoning for LLMs in Wireless   Communications with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23219</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23219.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Li, Mengbing Liu, Yiyang Zhu, Wenhe Zhang, Li Wei, Jiancheng An, Chau Yuen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) excel at general mathematical reasoning but fail catastrophically on specialized technical mathematics. In wireless communications, where problems require precise manipulation of information-theoretic bounds, optimization constraints, and signal processing formulations, even state-of-the-art models struggle to achieve competent performance. We present WirelessMathLM, demonstrating that compact models (0.5B-7B parameters) can match or exceed much larger models through domain-specific reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards. Our key insight is that wireless mathematics problems possess a unique property--verifiable correctness--that enables effective reinforcement learning without human feedback. We construct WirelessMathBench-XL, a comprehensive benchmark of 4,027 problems from 970 papers. Using Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) with binary verification rewards, we train models directly from base checkpoints without supervised warm-start. Our 7B model achieves 39.5% accuracy on WirelessMathBench-XL, approaching GPT-4o (40.4%) while using about 100 times fewer parameters than DeepSeek-R1 (671B, 57.4%). Remarkably, GRPO training nearly doubles performance across all model scales (0.5B +11%, 3B +103%, 7B +81%), with positive transfer to general mathematics benchmarks--our models gain +8.4 points on average across MATH, Minerva-Math, OlympiadBench, AMC, and AIME without any training on these tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23219</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 09:58:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Corpus-Level Knowledge Inconsistencies in Wikipedia with Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23233</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23233.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sina J. Semnani, Jirayu Burapacheep, Arpandeep Khatua, Thanawan Atchariyachanvanit, Zheng Wang, Monica S. Lam&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Wikipedia is the largest open knowledge corpus, widely used worldwide and serving as a key resource for training large language models (LLMs) and retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) systems. Ensuring its accuracy is therefore critical. But how accurate is Wikipedia, and how can we improve it?   We focus on inconsistencies, a specific type of factual inaccuracy, and introduce the task of corpus-level inconsistency detection. We present CLAIRE, an agentic system that combines LLM reasoning with retrieval to surface potentially inconsistent claims along with contextual evidence for human review. In a user study with experienced Wikipedia editors, 87.5% reported higher confidence when using CLAIRE, and participants identified 64.7% more inconsistencies in the same amount of time.   Combining CLAIRE with human annotation, we contribute WIKICOLLIDE, the first benchmark of real Wikipedia inconsistencies. Using random sampling with CLAIRE-assisted analysis, we find that at least 3.3% of English Wikipedia facts contradict another fact, with inconsistencies propagating into 7.3% of FEVEROUS and 4.0% of AmbigQA examples. Benchmarking strong baselines on this dataset reveals substantial headroom: the best fully automated system achieves an AUROC of only 75.1%.   Our results show that contradictions are a measurable component of Wikipedia and that LLM-based systems like CLAIRE can provide a practical tool to help editors improve knowledge consistency at scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23233</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 10:32:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Effective Tool-Integrated Reasoning via Self-Evolved Preference   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23285</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23285.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifei Chen, Guanting Dong, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Tool-Integrated Reasoning (TIR) enables large language models (LLMs) to improve their internal reasoning ability by integrating external tools. However, models employing TIR often display suboptimal behaviors, such as insufficient or excessive tool usage and overthinking after tool calls. The challenge of incentivizing LLMs to perform TIR efficiently and accurately, while stabilizing the reasoning process, remains an open question. In this paper, we start by exploring the impact of tool calls on model reasoning from the perspective of information entropy. Our findings indicate that tool call results lead to a distinct change in the information entropy of subsequent reasoning, with the overall entropy of the reasoning chain varying based on the number of tool calls. Building on these insights, we propose Tool-Light, a framework designed to encourage LLMs to perform TIR efficiently and accurately. Our framework includes dataset construction and multi-stage fine-tuning. For dataset construction, we employ continuous self-evolved sampling using the fine-tuned model, integrating both vanilla sampling and entropy-guided sampling. Besides, we establish strict criteria for selecting positive-negative pairs during sampling. The training process involves a two-stage approach, comprising Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) and Self-Evolved Direct Preference Optimization (DPO). Experimental results on 10 datasets demonstrate the effectiveness of Tool-Light, significantly improving the model's efficiency in executing TIR tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23285</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 12:53:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PARROT: A Benchmark for Evaluating LLMs in Cross-System SQL Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23338</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23338.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei Zhou, Guoliang Li, Haoyu Wang, Yuxing Han, Xufei Wu, Fan Wu, Xuanhe Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMS) have shown increasing effectiveness in Text-to-SQL tasks. However, another closely related problem, Cross-System SQL Translation (a.k.a., SQL-to-SQL), which adapts a query written for one database system (e.g., MySQL) into its equivalent one for another system (e.g., ClickHouse), is of great practical importance but remains underexplored. Existing SQL benchmarks are not well-suited for SQL-to-SQL evaluation, which (1) focus on a limited set of database systems (often just SQLite) and (2) cannot capture many system-specific SQL dialects (e.g., customized functions, data types, and syntax rules). Thus, in this paper, we introduce PARROT, a Practical And Realistic BenchmaRk for CrOss-System SQL Translation. PARROT comprises 598 translation pairs from 38 open-source benchmarks and real-world business services, specifically prepared to challenge system-specific SQL understanding (e.g., LLMS achieve lower than 38.53% accuracy on average). We also provide multiple benchmark variants, including PARROT-Diverse with 28,003 translations (for extensive syntax testing) and PARROT-Simple with 5,306 representative samples (for focused stress testing), covering 22 production-grade database systems. To promote future research, we release a public leaderboard and source code at: https://code4db.github.io/parrot-bench/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23338</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 14:41:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alignment through Meta-Weighted Online Sampling: Bridging the Gap   between Data Generation and Preference Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23371</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23371.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junming Yang, Ning Xu, Biao Liu, Shiqi Qiao, Xin Geng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Preference optimization is crucial for aligning large language models (LLMs) with human values and intentions. A significant challenge in this process is the distribution mismatch between pre-collected offline preference data and the evolving model policy. Existing methods attempt to reduce this gap using static heuristics or decoupled online sampling strategies, but they often fail to adapt to the model's dynamic learning state. To bridge this gap, we propose Meta-Weighted Adaptive Preference Optimization (MetaAPO), a novel framework that dynamically couples data generation with model training. MetaAPO employs a lightweight meta-learner, as an "alignment gap estimator", to evaluate the potential benefits of on-policy sampling in relation to offline data. This guides targeted online generation and assigns sample-wise meta-weights to the optimization objective, dynamically balancing the quality and distribution of online and offline data. Experiments on AlpacaEval 2, Arena-Hard and MT-Bench demonstrate that MetaAPO consistently outperforms existing preference optimization approaches across various settings, while reducing 42% in online annotation costs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23371</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 15:38:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democratizing AI scientists using ToolUniverse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23426</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23426.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shanghua Gao, Richard Zhu, Pengwei Sui, Zhenglun Kong, Sufian Aldogom, Yepeng Huang, Ayush Noori, Reza Shamji, Krishna Parvataneni, Theodoros Tsiligkaridis, Marinka Zitnik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI scientists are emerging computational systems that serve as collaborative partners in discovery. These systems remain difficult to build because they are bespoke, tied to rigid workflows, and lack shared environments that unify tools, data, and analyses into a common ecosystem. In omics, unified ecosystems have transformed research by enabling interoperability, reuse, and community-driven development; AI scientists require comparable infrastructure. We present ToolUniverse, an ecosystem for building AI scientists from any language or reasoning model, whether open or closed. TOOLUNIVERSE standardizes how AI scientists identify and call tools, integrating more than 600 machine learning models, datasets, APIs, and scientific packages for data analysis, knowledge retrieval, and experimental design. It automatically refines tool interfaces for correct use by AI scientists, creates new tools from natural language descriptions, iteratively optimizes tool specifications, and composes tools into agentic workflows. In a case study of hypercholesterolemia, ToolUniverse was used to create an AI scientist to identify a potent analog of a drug with favorable predicted properties. The open-source ToolUniverse is available at https://aiscientist.tools.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23426</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 17:38:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clean First, Align Later: Benchmarking Preference Data Cleaning for   Reliable LLM Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23564</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23564.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Min-Hsuan Yeh, Yixuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human feedback plays a pivotal role in aligning large language models (LLMs) with human preferences. However, such feedback is often noisy or inconsistent, which can degrade the quality of reward models and hinder alignment. While various automated data cleaning methods have been proposed to mitigate this issue, a systematic evaluation of their effectiveness and generalizability remains lacking. To bridge this gap, we introduce the first comprehensive benchmark for evaluating 13 preference data cleaning methods in the context of LLM alignment. PrefCleanBench offers a standardized protocol to assess cleaning strategies in terms of alignment performance and generalizability across diverse datasets, model architectures, and optimization algorithms. By unifying disparate methods and rigorously comparing them, we uncover key factors that determine the success of data cleaning in alignment tasks. This benchmark lays the groundwork for principled and reproducible approaches to improving LLM alignment through better data quality-highlighting the crucial but underexplored role of data preprocessing in responsible AI development. We release modular implementations of all methods to catalyze further research: https://github.com/deeplearning-wisc/PrefCleanBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23564</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 01:44:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Exploration-Exploitation Trade-off: A Hidden State Approach   for LLM Reasoning in RLVR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23808</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23808.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fanding Huang, Guanbo Huang, Xiao Fan, Yi He, Xiao Liang, Xiao Chen, Qinting Jiang, Faisal Nadeem Khan, Jingyan Jiang, Zhi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A prevailing view in Reinforcement Learning for Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) interprets recent progress through the lens of an exploration-exploitation trade-off, a perspective largely shaped by token-level metrics. We re-examine this perspective, proposing that this perceived trade-off may not be a fundamental constraint but rather an artifact of the measurement level. To investigate this, we shift the analysis to the semantically rich hidden-state space, adopting Effective Rank (ER) to quantify exploration and proposing its novel first- and second-order derivatives, named Effective Rank Velocity (ERV) and Effective Rank Acceleration (ERA), to capture exploitation dynamics. Our analysis reveals that at the hidden-state level, exploration and exploitation could be decoupled (Sec. 4). This finding reveals an opportunity to enhance both capacities simultaneously. This insight motivates our method, Velocity-Exploiting Rank-Learning (VERL), the first to operationalize the principle of synergistic exploration-exploitation enhancement by directly shaping the RL advantage function. The key innovation is leveraging the theoretically stable ERA as a predictive meta-controller to create a synergistic, dual-channel incentive structure. Instead of forcing a trade-off, VERL prospectively amplifies rewards for exploration to preempt overconfidence and reinforces exploitative gains to consolidate reasoning. Experiments across diverse LLMs and reasoning benchmarks show consistent gains, including up to 21.4% absolute accuracy improvement on the challenging Gaokao 2024 dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23808</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 11:14:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Multi-turn RL for GUI Agents via Decoupled Training and   Adaptive Data Curation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23866</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23866.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengxiang Li, Zechen Hu, Zirui Shang, Jingrong Wu, Yang Liu, Hui Liu, Zhi Gao, Chenrui Shi, Bofei Zhang, Zihao Zhang, Xiaochuan Shi, Zedong YU, Yuwei Wu, Xinxiao Wu, Yunde Jia, Liuyu Xiang, Zhaofeng He, Qing Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language model (VLM) based GUI agents show promise for automating complex desktop and mobile tasks, but face significant challenges in applying reinforcement learning (RL): (1) slow multi-turn interactions with GUI environments for policy rollout, and (2) insufficient high-quality agent-environment interactions for policy learning. To address these challenges, we propose DART, a Decoupled Agentic RL Training framework for GUI agents, which coordinates heterogeneous modules in a highly decoupled manner. DART separates the training system into four asynchronous modules: environment cluster, rollout service, data manager, and trainer. This design enables non-blocking communication, asynchronous training, rollout-wise trajectory sampling, and per-worker model synchronization, significantly improving the system efficiency: 1.6*GPU utilization for rollout, 1.9* training throughput, and 5.5* environment utilization. To facilitate effective learning from abundant samples, we introduce an adaptive data curation scheme: (1) pre-collecting successful trajectories for challenging tasks to supplement sparse success in online sampling; (2) dynamically adjusting rollout numbers and trajectory lengths based on task difficulty; (3) training selectively on high-entropy steps to prioritize critical decisions; (4) stabilizing learning via truncated importance sampling for policy mismatch between policy rollout and updating. On the OSWorld benchmark, DART-GUI-7B achieves a 42.13% task success rate, a 14.61% absolute gain over the base model, and 7.34% higher than open-source SOTA. We will fully open-source our training framework, data, and model checkpoints via computer-use-agents.github.io/dart-gui, which we believe is a timely contribution to the open-source community of agentic RL training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23866</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 13:19:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EditScore: Unlocking Online RL for Image Editing via High-Fidelity   Reward Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23909</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23909.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Luo, Jiahao Wang, Chenyuan Wu, Shitao Xiao, Xiyan Jiang, Defu Lian, Jiajun Zhang, Dong Liu, Zheng liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-guided image editing has achieved remarkable progress, yet current models still face challenges with complex instructions and often require multiple samples to produce a desired result. Reinforcement Learning (RL) offers a promising solution, but its adoption in image editing has been severely hindered by the lack of a high-fidelity, efficient reward signal. In this work, we present a comprehensive methodology to overcome this barrier, centered on the development of a state-of-the-art, specialized reward model. We first introduce EditReward-Bench, a comprehensive benchmark to systematically evaluate reward models on editing quality. Building on this benchmark, we develop EditScore, a series of reward models (7B-72B) for evaluating the quality of instruction-guided image editing. Through meticulous data curation and filtering, EditScore effectively matches the performance of learning proprietary VLMs. Furthermore, coupled with an effective self-ensemble strategy tailored for the generative nature of EditScore, our largest variant even surpasses GPT-5 in the benchmark. We then demonstrate that a high-fidelity reward model is the key to unlocking online RL for image editing. Our experiments show that, while even the largest open-source VLMs fail to provide an effective learning signal, EditScore enables efficient and robust policy optimization. Applying our framework to a strong base model, OmniGen2, results in a final model that shows a substantial and consistent performance uplift. Overall, this work provides the first systematic path from benchmarking to reward modeling to RL training in image editing, showing that a high-fidelity, domain-specialized reward model is the key to unlocking the full potential of RL in this domain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23909</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 14:28:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taming Masked Diffusion Language Models via Consistency Trajectory   Reinforcement Learning with Fewer Decoding Step</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23924</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23924.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingyi Yang, Guanxu Chen, Xuhao Hu, Jing Shao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Masked diffusion language models (MDLMs) have recently emerged as a promising alternative to autoregressive (AR) language models, offering properties such as parallel decoding, flexible generation orders, and the potential for fewer inference steps. Despite these advantages, decoding strategies and reinforcement learning (RL) algorithms tailored for MDLMs remain underexplored. A naive approach is to directly transfer techniques well-established for AR models to MDLMs. However, this raises an immediate question: Is such a naive transfer truly optimal? For example, 1) Block-wise and semi-AR decoding strategies are not employed during the training of MDLMs, so why do they outperform full diffusion-style decoding during inference? 2) Applying RL algorithms designed for AR models directly to MDLMs exhibits a training-inference inconsistency, since MDLM decoding are non-causal (parallel). This results in inconsistencies between the rollout trajectory and the optimization trajectory. To address these challenges, we propose EOS Early Rejection (EOSER) and Ascending Step-Size (ASS) decoding scheduler, which unlock the potential of MDLMs to perform full diffusion-style decoding, achieving competitive performance with fewer decoding steps. Additionally, we introduce Consistency Trajectory Group Relative Policy Optimization (CJ-GRPO) for taming MDLMs, which emphasizes the consistency between rollout trajectory and optimization trajectory, and reduces the optimization errors caused by skip-step optimization. We conduct extensive experiments on reasoning tasks, such as mathematical and planning benchmarks, using LLaDA-8B-Instruct. The results demonstrate that the proposed EOSER and ASS mechanisms, together with CJ-GRPO, hold significant promise for effectively and efficiently taming MDLMs. Code: https://github.com/yjyddq/EOSER-ASS-RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23924</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 15:01:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HunyuanImage 3.0 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23951</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23951.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyu Cao, Hangting Chen, Peng Chen, Yiji Cheng, Yutao Cui, Xinchi Deng, Ying Dong, Kipper Gong, Tianpeng Gu, Xiusen Gu, Tiankai Hang, Duojun Huang, Jie Jiang, Zhengkai Jiang, Weijie Kong, Changlin Li, Donghao Li, Junzhe Li, Xin Li, Yang Li, Zhenxi Li, Zhimin Li, Jiaxin Lin, Linus, Lucaz Liu, Shu Liu, Songtao Liu, Yu Liu, Yuhong Liu, Yanxin Long, Fanbin Lu, Qinglin Lu, Yuyang Peng, Yuanbo Peng, Xiangwei Shen, Yixuan Shi, Jiale Tao, Yangyu Tao, Qi Tian, Pengfei Wan, Chunyu Wang, Kai Wang, Lei Wang, Linqing Wang, Lucas Wang, Qixun Wang, Weiyan Wang, Hao Wen, Bing Wu, Jianbing Wu, Yue Wu, Senhao Xie, Fang Yang, Miles Yang, Xiaofeng Yang, Xuan Yang, Zhantao Yang, Jingmiao Yu, Zheng Yuan, Chao Zhang, Jian-Wei Zhang, Peizhen Zhang, Shi-Xue Zhang, Tao Zhang, Weigang Zhang, Yepeng Zhang, Yingfang Zhang, Zihao Zhang, Zijian Zhang, Penghao Zhao, Zhiyuan Zhao, Xuefei Zhe, Jianchen Zhu, Zhao Zhong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present HunyuanImage 3.0, a native multimodal model that unifies multimodal understanding and generation within an autoregressive framework, with its image generation module publicly available. The achievement of HunyuanImage 3.0 relies on several key components, including meticulous data curation, advanced architecture design, a native Chain-of-Thoughts schema, progressive model pre-training, aggressive model post-training, and an efficient infrastructure that enables large-scale training and inference. With these advancements, we successfully trained a Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) model comprising over 80 billion parameters in total, with 13 billion parameters activated per token during inference, making it the largest and most powerful open-source image generative model to date. We conducted extensive experiments and the results of automatic and human evaluation of text-image alignment and visual quality demonstrate that HunyuanImage 3.0 rivals previous state-of-the-art models. By releasing the code and weights of HunyuanImage 3.0, we aim to enable the community to explore new ideas with a state-of-the-art foundation model, fostering a dynamic and vibrant multimodal ecosystem. All open source assets are publicly available at https://github.com/Tencent-Hunyuan/HunyuanImage-3.0&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23951</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 16:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SLA: Beyond Sparsity in Diffusion Transformers via Fine-Tunable   Sparse-Linear Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24006</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24006.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Haoxu Wang, Kai Jiang, Shuo Yang, Kaiwen Zheng, Haocheng Xi, Ziteng Wang, Hongzhou Zhu, Min Zhao, Ion Stoica, Joseph E. Gonzalez, Jun Zhu, Jianfei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 98&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In Diffusion Transformer (DiT) models, particularly for video generation, attention latency is a major bottleneck due to the long sequence length and the quadratic complexity. We find that attention weights can be separated into two parts: a small fraction of large weights with high rank and the remaining weights with very low rank. This naturally suggests applying sparse acceleration to the first part and low-rank acceleration to the second. Based on this finding, we propose SLA (Sparse-Linear Attention), a trainable attention method that fuses sparse and linear attention to accelerate diffusion models. SLA classifies attention weights into critical, marginal, and negligible categories, applying O(N^2) attention to critical weights, O(N) attention to marginal weights, and skipping negligible ones. SLA combines these computations into a single GPU kernel and supports both forward and backward passes. With only a few fine-tuning steps using SLA, DiT models achieve a 20x reduction in attention computation, resulting in significant acceleration without loss of generation quality. Experiments show that SLA reduces attention computation by 95% without degrading end-to-end generation quality, outperforming baseline methods. In addition, we implement an efficient GPU kernel for SLA, which yields a 13.7x speedup in attention computation and a 2.2x end-to-end speedup in video generation on Wan2.1-1.3B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24006</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 17:58:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24007</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24007.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yangzhou Liu, Yue Cao, Hao Li, Gen Luo, Zhe Chen, Weiyun Wang, Xiaobo Liang, Biqing Qi, Lijun Wu, Changyao Tian, Yanting Zhang, Yuqiang Li, Tong Lu, Yu Qiao, Jifeng Dai, Wenhai Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion language models (DLMs) have strong theoretical efficiency but are limited by fixed-length decoding and incompatibility with key-value (KV) caches. Block diffusion mitigates these issues, yet still enforces a fixed block size and requires expensive training. We introduce Next Sequence Prediction (NSP), which unifies next-token and next-block prediction, enabling the model to adaptively determine the generation length at each step. When the length is fixed to 1, NSP reduces to standard next-token prediction. Building on NSP, we propose Sequential Diffusion Language Model (SDLM), which can retrofit pre-trained autoregressive language models (ALMs) at minimal cost. Specifically, SDLM performs diffusion inference within fixed-size mask blocks, but dynamically decodes consecutive subsequences based on model confidence, thereby preserving KV-cache compatibility and improving robustness to varying uncertainty and semantics across the sequence. Experiments show that SDLM matches or surpasses strong autoregressive baselines using only 3.5M training samples, while achieving 2.1 higher throughput than Qwen-2.5. Notably, the SDLM-32B model delivers even more pronounced efficiency gains, demonstrating the strong scalability potential of our modeling paradigm. Project page and codes: https://github.com/OpenGVLab/SDLM&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24007</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 17:59:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SparseD: Sparse Attention for Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24014</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24014.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeqing Wang, Gongfan Fang, Xinyin Ma, Xingyi Yang, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While diffusion language models (DLMs) offer a promising alternative to autoregressive models (ARs), existing open-source DLMs suffer from high inference latency. This bottleneck is mainly due to the attention's quadratic complexity with respect to context length in computing all query-key pairs. Intuitively, to reduce this complexity, a natural strategy is to restrict attention to sparse patterns that retain only the most relevant connections. Such approaches are well-established in ARs, where attention follows fixed and clearly defined sparse patterns. However, in DLMs, we observe distinct sparsity behaviors: (1) attention patterns vary across heads, (2) attention patterns in each head remain highly similar across denoising steps, and (3) early denoising steps are critical for generation. These findings render sparse attention methods designed for ARs largely incompatible with DLMs, as they fail to capture head-specific structures and risk degrading generation when applied in early denoising steps. To address these challenges, we propose SparseD, a novel sparse attention method for DLMs. Leveraging the observations, SparseD only requires pre-computing head-specific sparse patterns one time, and reuses them across all steps. This prevents recomputing sparse patterns at each denoising step. Meanwhile, SparseD uses full attention in the early steps, then switches to sparse attention later to maintain generation quality. Together, these establish SparseD as a practical and efficient solution for deploying DLMs in long-context applications. Experimental results demonstrate that SparseD achieves lossless acceleration, delivering up to 1.50times speedup over FlashAttention at a 64k context length with 1,024 denoising steps.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24014</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 18:10:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TENET: Leveraging Tests Beyond Validation for Code Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24148</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24148.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiran Hu, Nan Jiang, Shanchao Liang, Yi Wu, Lin Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Test-Driven Development (TDD) is a widely adopted software engineering practice that requires developers to create and execute tests alongside code implementation, ensuring that software behavior is continuously validated and refined. In the era of vibe coding, where developers increasingly delegate code writing to large language models (LLMs) by specifying high-level intentions, TDD becomes even more crucial, as test cases serve as executable specifications that explicitly define and verify intended functionality beyond what natural-language descriptions and code context can convey. While vibe coding under TDD is promising, there are three main challenges: (1) selecting a small yet effective test suite to improve the generation accuracy and control the execution workload, (2) retrieving context such as relevant code effectively, and (3) systematically using test feedback for effective code refinement. To address these challenges, we introduce TENET, an LLM agent for generating functions in complex real-world repositories under the TDD setting. TENET features three components: (1) a novel test harness mechanism that selects a concise test suite to maximize diversity of target usage scenarios; (2) a tailored agent toolset that performs efficient retrieval of relevant code with interactive debugging; and (3) a reflection-based refinement workflow that iteratively analyzes failures, replenishes context, and applies code refinement. TENET achieves 69.08% and 81.77% Pass@1 on RepoCod and RepoEval benchmarks, outperforming the best agentic baselines by 9.49 and 2.17 percentage points, respectively. In addition, this is the first study of test-driven code generation with repository-level context, examining how different aspects of test suites affect the performance of LLM agents under the TDD setting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24148</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:53:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AceSearcher: Bootstrapping Reasoning and Search for LLMs via Reinforced   Self-Play</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24193</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24193.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ran Xu, Yuchen Zhuang, Zihan Dong, Jonathan Wang, Yue Yu, Joyce C. Ho, Linjun Zhang, Haoyu Wang, Wenqi Shi, Carl Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Search-augmented LLMs often struggle with complex reasoning tasks due to ineffective multi-hop retrieval and limited reasoning ability. We propose AceSearcher, a cooperative self-play framework that trains a single large language model (LLM) to alternate between two roles: a decomposer that breaks down complex queries and a solver that integrates retrieved contexts for answer generation. AceSearcher couples supervised fine-tuning on a diverse mixture of search, reasoning, and decomposition tasks with reinforcement fine-tuning optimized for final answer accuracy, eliminating the need for intermediate annotations. Extensive experiments on three reasoning-intensive tasks across 10 datasets show that AceSearcher outperforms state-of-the-art baselines, achieving an average exact match improvement of 7.6%. Remarkably, on document-level finance reasoning tasks, AceSearcher-32B matches the performance of the DeepSeek-V3 model using less than 5% of its parameters. Even at smaller scales (1.5B and 8B), AceSearcher often surpasses existing search-augmented LLMs with up to 9x more parameters, highlighting its exceptional efficiency and effectiveness in tackling complex reasoning tasks. Our code will be published at https://github.com/ritaranx/AceSearcher and https://huggingface.co/AceSearcher.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24193</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 02:14:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniVid: The Open-Source Unified Video Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24200</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24200.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiabin Luo, Junhui Lin, Zeyu Zhang, Biao Wu, Meng Fang, Ling Chen, Hao Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified video modeling that combines generation and understanding capabilities is increasingly important but faces two key challenges: maintaining semantic faithfulness during flow-based generation due to text-visual token imbalance and the limitations of uniform cross-modal attention across the flow trajectory, and efficiently extending image-centric MLLMs to video without costly retraining. We present UniVid, a unified architecture that couples an MLLM with a diffusion decoder through a lightweight adapter, enabling both video understanding and generation. We introduce Temperature Modality Alignment to improve prompt adherence and Pyramid Reflection for efficient temporal reasoning via dynamic keyframe selection. Extensive experiments on standard benchmarks demonstrate state-of-the-art performance, achieving a 2.2% improvement on VBench-Long total score compared to EasyAnimateV5.1, and 1.0% and 3.3% accuracy gains on MSVD-QA and ActivityNet-QA, respectively, compared with the best prior 7B baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24200</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 02:31:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdvChain: Adversarial Chain-of-Thought Tuning for Robust Safety   Alignment of Large Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24269</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24269.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihao Zhu, Xinyu Wu, Gehan Hu, Siwei Lyu, Ke Xu, Baoyuan Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in complex problem-solving through Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning. However, the multi-step nature of CoT introduces new safety challenges that extend beyond conventional language model alignment. We identify a failure mode in current safety CoT tuning methods: the snowball effect, where minor reasoning deviations progressively amplify throughout the thought process, leading to either harmful compliance or excessive refusal. This effect stems from models being trained to imitate perfect reasoning scripts without learning to self-correct. To address this limitation, we propose AdvChain, an alignment paradigm that teaches models dynamic self-correction through adversarial CoT tuning. Our method involves constructing a dataset containing Temptation-Correction and Hesitation-Correction samples, where models learn to recover from harmful reasoning drifts and unnecessary cautions. Extensive experiments show that AdvChain significantly enhances robustness against jailbreak attacks and CoT hijacking while substantially reducing over-refusal on benign prompts, achieving a superior safety-utility balance without compromising reasoning capabilities. Our work establishes a new direction for building more robust and reliable reasoning models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24269</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 04:27:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCI-Verifier: Scientific Verifier with Thinking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24285</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24285.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shenghe Zheng, Chenyu Huang, Fangchen Yu, Junchi Yao, Jingqi Ye, Tao Chen, Yun Luo, Ning Ding, LEI BAI, Ganqu Cui, Peng Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language models (LLMs) are increasingly applied to scientific reasoning, the complexity of answer formats and the diversity of equivalent expressions make answer verification a critical yet challenging task. Existing verification studies in scientific domains suffer from two major limitations: (a) the absence of systematic evaluation standards and insufficient disciplinary coverage, which hinders their comprehensive assessment; and (b) heavy reliance on cumbersome rule design or prompt engineering, which reduces their effectiveness in complex reasoning scenarios or limits their cross-disciplinary generalization. To address these challenges, we propose solutions at both the data and model levels. On the data side, we construct SCI-VerifyBench, a cross-disciplinary benchmark covering mathematics, physics, biology, chemistry, and general scientific QA. The benchmark is built from real LLM responses and enhanced with domain-specific equivalence transformations that generate challenging and realistic data. Model-based and expert annotations ensure both quality and diversity, enabling rigorous evaluation of verification ability. On the model side, we emphasize the importance of reasoning for verification and introduce SCI-Verifier, a unified reasoning-augmented verifier for scientific domains. Through post-training, SCI-Verifier demonstrates strong logical reasoning and equivalence judgment capabilities while maintaining concise and stable outputs. Together, SCI-VerifyBench and SCI-Verifier provide a principled framework for scientific verification, offering both systematic evaluation and practical pathways to enhance the reliability and applicability of LLMs in scientific domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24285</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 04:58:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking JEPA: Compute-Efficient Video SSL with Frozen Teachers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xianhang Li, Chen Huang, Chun-Liang Li, Eran Malach, Josh Susskind, Vimal Thilak, Etai Littwin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video Joint Embedding Predictive Architectures (V-JEPA) learn generalizable off-the-shelf video representation by predicting masked regions in latent space with an exponential moving average (EMA)-updated teacher. While EMA prevents representation collapse, it complicates scalable model selection and couples teacher and student architectures. We revisit masked-latent prediction and show that a frozen teacher suffices. Concretely, we (i) train a target encoder with a simple pixel-reconstruction objective under V-JEPA masking, then (ii) freeze it and train a student to predict the teacher's latents on masked regions. This leads to a two-stage, unregularized scheme that we refer to as SALT (Static-teacher Asymmetric Latent Training). SALT decouples optimization into pixel reconstruction (teacher) and masked latent prediction (student), increasing transparency, efficiency, and scalability while preserving the ability of representation to generalize under frozen evaluation. Empirically, our student models outperform recently proposed V-JEPA 2 encoders under frozen backbone evaluation across diverse benchmarks. They are also more compute-optimal: at matched pretraining FLOPs, our method achieves higher probing accuracy, and its scaling curves dominate V-JEPA's accuracy-FLOPs Pareto frontier. Finally, we find that student quality is remarkably robust to teacher quality: high-performing students emerge even with small, sub-optimal teachers. This points to a compute budget allocation that should overwhelmingly favor the student. These results position SALT as a simple, scalable, and compute-efficient alternative to EMA-based self-distillation for video representation learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24317</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 05:55:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperspherical Latents Improve Continuous-Token Autoregressive   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24335</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24335.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guolin Ke, Hui Xue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive (AR) models are promising for image generation, yet continuous-token AR variants often trail latent diffusion and masked-generation models. The core issue is heterogeneous variance in VAE latents, which is amplified during AR decoding, especially under classifier-free guidance (CFG), and can cause variance collapse. We propose SphereAR to address this issue. Its core design is to constrain all AR inputs and outputs -- including after CFG -- to lie on a fixed-radius hypersphere (constant ell_2 norm), leveraging hyperspherical VAEs. Our theoretical analysis shows that hyperspherical constraint removes the scale component (the primary cause of variance collapse), thereby stabilizing AR decoding. Empirically, on ImageNet generation, SphereAR-H (943M) sets a new state of the art for AR models, achieving FID 1.34. Even at smaller scales, SphereAR-L (479M) reaches FID 1.54 and SphereAR-B (208M) reaches 1.92, matching or surpassing much larger baselines such as MAR-H (943M, 1.55) and VAR-d30 (2B, 1.92). To our knowledge, this is the first time a pure next-token AR image generator with raster order surpasses diffusion and masked-generation models at comparable parameter scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24335</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 06:34:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Strategies at Scale: LLM Fine-Tuning Beyond Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24372</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24372.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Qiu, Yulu Gan, Conor F. Hayes, Qiyao Liang, Elliot Meyerson, Babak Hodjat, Risto Miikkulainen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-tuning pre-trained large language models (LLMs) for down-stream tasks is a critical step in the AI deployment pipeline. Reinforcement learning (RL) is arguably the most prominent fine-tuning method, contributing to the birth of many state-of-the-art LLMs. In contrast, evolution strategies (ES), which once showed comparable performance to RL on models with a few million parameters, was neglected due to the pessimistic perception of its scalability to larger models. In this work, we report the first successful attempt to scale up ES for fine-tuning the full parameters of LLMs, showing the surprising fact that ES can search efficiently over billions of parameters and outperform existing RL fine-tuning methods in multiple respects, including sample efficiency, tolerance to long-horizon rewards, robustness to different base LLMs, less tendency to reward hacking, and more stable performance across runs. It therefore serves as a basis to unlock a new direction in LLM fine-tuning beyond what current RL techniques provide. The source codes are provided at: https://github.com/VsonicV/es-fine-tuning-paper.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24372</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 07:19:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclid's Gift: Enhancing Spatial Perception and Reasoning in   Vision-Language Models via Geometric Surrogate Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24473</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24473.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shijie Lian, Changti Wu, Laurence Tianruo Yang, Hang Yuan, Bin Yu, Lei Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatial intelligence spans a rich suite of abilities, including visualising and transforming shapes, mentally rotating objects, judging relational positions and containment, and estimating numerosity. However, it still remains a critical unresolved challenge for Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs).To fill this gap, we propose to treat Euclidean geometry problem-solving as a surrogate task. Specifically, we meticulously constructed a curated multimodal dataset, called Euclid30K, comprising approximately 30K plane and solid geometry problems. To enable the model to acquire and apply Euclidean principles from these geometry problems, we employed Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) to finetune the Qwen2.5VL family and RoboBrain2.0 family, inspiring the models to identify shapes, count, and relate entities, and perform multi-step deductive reasoning using Euclidean principles. Our experiments demonstrate that the resulting models achieve substantial zero-shot gains across four spatial reasoning benchmarks (Super-CLEVR, Omni3DBench, VSI-Bench, and MindCube) without any task-specific adaptations. Notably, after training on the Euclid30K, the mean VSI-Bench accuracy of all evaluated models rose from 34.5% to 40.5%, improving by 5.5 percentage points. Among them, RoboBrain2.0-Euclid-7B achieves 49.6\% accuracy, surpassing the previous state-of-the-art model, Spatial-MLLM.To our knowledge, this is the first systematic study showing that geometry-centric fine-tuning can confer vision-language models with broadly transferable spatial skills. Code and Euclid30K dataset can be found in https://zgca-ai4edu.github.io/Euclids_Gift.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24473</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 08:49:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRPO-MA: Multi-Answer Generation in GRPO for Stable and Efficient   Chain-of-Thought Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24494</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24494.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongcheng Wang, Yinuo Huang, Sukai Wang, Guanghui Ren, Hao Dong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress, such as DeepSeek-R1, has shown that the GRPO algorithm, a Reinforcement Learning (RL) approach, can effectively train Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning in Large Language Models (LLMs) and Vision-Language Models (VLMs). In this paper, we analyze three challenges of GRPO: gradient coupling between thoughts and answers, sparse reward signals caused by limited parallel sampling, and unstable advantage estimation. To mitigate these challenges, we propose GRPO-MA, a simple yet theoretically grounded method that leverages multi-answer generation from each thought process, enabling more robust and efficient optimization. Theoretically, we show that the variance of thought advantage decreases as the number of answers per thought increases. Empirically, our gradient analysis confirms this effect, showing that GRPO-MA reduces gradient spikes compared to GRPO. Experiments on math, code, and diverse multimodal tasks demonstrate that GRPO-MA substantially improves performance and training efficiency. Our ablation studies further reveal that increasing the number of answers per thought consistently enhances model performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24494</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 09:07:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BPMN Assistant: An LLM-Based Approach to Business Process Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24592</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24592.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Josip Tomo Licardo, Nikola Tankovic, Darko Etinger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents BPMN Assistant, a tool that leverages Large Language Models (LLMs) for natural language-based creation and editing of BPMN diagrams. A specialized JSON-based representation is introduced as a structured alternative to the direct handling of XML to enhance the accuracy of process modifications. Process generation quality is evaluated using Graph Edit Distance (GED) and Relative Graph Edit Distance (RGED), while editing performance is evaluated with a binary success metric. Results show that JSON and XML achieve similar similarity scores in generation, but JSON offers greater reliability, faster processing, and significantly higher editing success rates. We discuss key trade-offs, limitations, and future improvements. The implementation is available at https://github.com/jtlicardo/bpmn-assistant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24592</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 10:56:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfLLM-V2: Dense-Sparse Switchable Attention for Seamless Short-to-Long   Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24663</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24663.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weilin Zhao, Zihan Zhou, Zhou Su, Chaojun Xiao, Yuxuan Li, Yanghao Li, Yudi Zhang, Weilun Zhao, Zhen Li, Yuxiang Huang, Ao Sun, Xu Han, Zhiyuan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-sequence processing is a critical capability for modern large language models. However, the self-attention mechanism in the standard Transformer architecture faces severe computational and memory bottlenecks when processing long sequences. While trainable sparse attention methods offer a promising solution, existing approaches such as NSA introduce excessive extra parameters and disrupt the conventional pretrain-on-short, finetune-on-long workflow, resulting in slow convergence and difficulty in acceleration. To overcome these limitations, we introduce dense-sparse switchable attention framework, termed as InfLLM-V2. InfLLM-V2 is a trainable sparse attention that seamlessly adapts models from short to long sequences. Specifically, InfLLM-V2 reuses dense attention parameters through parameter-free architecture modification, maintaining consistency between short and long sequence processing. Additionally, InfLLM-V2 ensures computational efficiency across all sequence lengths, by using dense attention for short inputs and smoothly transitioning to sparse attention for long sequences. To achieve practical acceleration, we further introduce an efficient implementation of InfLLM-V2 that significantly reduces the computational overhead. Our experiments on long-context understanding and chain-of-thought reasoning demonstrate that InfLLM-V2 is 4times faster than dense attention while retaining 98.1% and 99.7% of the performance, respectively. Based on the InfLLM-V2 framework, we have trained and open-sourced MiniCPM4.1 (https://huggingface.co/openbmb/MiniCPM4.1-8B), a hybrid reasoning model, providing a reproducible implementation for the research community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24663</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 12:08:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SANA-Video: Efficient Video Generation with Block Linear Diffusion   Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24695</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24695.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junsong Chen, Yuyang Zhao, Jincheng Yu, Ruihang Chu, Junyu Chen, Shuai Yang, Xianbang Wang, Yicheng Pan, Daquan Zhou, Huan Ling, Haozhe Liu, Hongwei Yi, Hao Zhang, Muyang Li, Yukang Chen, Han Cai, Sanja Fidler, Ping Luo, Song Han, Enze Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SANA-Video, a small diffusion model that can efficiently generate videos up to 720x1280 resolution and minute-length duration. SANA-Video synthesizes high-resolution, high-quality and long videos with strong text-video alignment at a remarkably fast speed, deployable on RTX 5090 GPU. Two core designs ensure our efficient, effective and long video generation: (1) Linear DiT: We leverage linear attention as the core operation, which is more efficient than vanilla attention given the large number of tokens processed in video generation. (2) Constant-Memory KV cache for Block Linear Attention: we design block-wise autoregressive approach for long video generation by employing a constant-memory state, derived from the cumulative properties of linear attention. This KV cache provides the Linear DiT with global context at a fixed memory cost, eliminating the need for a traditional KV cache and enabling efficient, minute-long video generation. In addition, we explore effective data filters and model training strategies, narrowing the training cost to 12 days on 64 H100 GPUs, which is only 1% of the cost of MovieGen. Given its low cost, SANA-Video achieves competitive performance compared to modern state-of-the-art small diffusion models (e.g., Wan 2.1-1.3B and SkyReel-V2-1.3B) while being 16x faster in measured latency. Moreover, SANA-Video can be deployed on RTX 5090 GPUs with NVFP4 precision, accelerating the inference speed of generating a 5-second 720p video from 71s to 29s (2.4x speedup). In summary, SANA-Video enables low-cost, high-quality video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24695</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 12:28:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IWR-Bench: Can LVLMs reconstruct interactive webpage from a user   interaction video?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24709</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24709.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Chen, Minghao Liu, Yufan Shen, Yunwen Li, Tianyuan Huang, Xinyu Fang, Tianyu Zheng, Wenxuan Huang, Cheng Yang, Daocheng Fu, Jianbiao Mei, Rong Wu, Licheng Wen, Xuemeng Yang, Song Mao, Qunshu Lin, Zhi Yu, Yongliang Shen, Yu Qiao, Botian Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The webpage-to-code task requires models to understand visual representations of webpages and generate corresponding code. However, existing benchmarks primarily focus on static screenshot-to-code tasks, thereby overlooking the dynamic interactions fundamental to real-world web applications. To address this limitation, this paper introduces IWR-Bench, a novel benchmark for evaluating the capabilities of Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs) in interactive webpage reconstruction from video. IWR-Bench comprises 113 meticulously curated tasks from 100 real-world websites, with 1,001 actions and featuring diverse interaction complexities (e.g., web games), visual styles, and domains. Aligning with standard web development practices, each task includes not only user interaction videos but also all crawled static assets (e.g., images, videos). This benchmark evaluates models on two fundamental challenges: comprehensive multi-modal reasoning to infer interaction logic from video and assets, and advanced code generation to translate this logic into functional code. An agent-as-a-judge framework with a comprehensive metric system automatically assesses the functional correctness and visual fidelity of generated webpages. Extensive experiments on 28 LVLMs reveal a significant challenge: the best model achieves an overall score of only 36.35%, as functional correctness (24.39% IFS) lags significantly behind visual fidelity (64.25% VFS). These results highlight critical limitations in current models' ability to reason about temporal dynamics and synthesize event-driven logic, establishing IWR-Bench as a challenging frontier for vision-language research. The benchmark and evaluation code will be made publicly available. Code is available at https://github.com/L-O-I/IWR-Bench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24709</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 12:38:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Socratic-Zero : Bootstrapping Reasoning via Data-Free Agent Co-evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24726</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24726.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaobo Wang, Zhengbo Jiao, Zifan Zhang, Yilang Peng, Xu Ze, Boyu Yang, Wei Wang, Hu Wei, Linfeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent breakthroughs in large language models (LLMs) on reasoning tasks rely heavily on massive, high-quality datasets-typically human-annotated and thus difficult to scale. While data synthesis or distillation offers a promising alternative, existing methods struggle with inconsistent data quality and an inability to dynamically adapt to the evolving capabilities of the model, leading to suboptimal training signals. To address these limitations, we introduce Socratic-Zero, a fully autonomous framework that generates high-quality training data from minimal seed examples through the co-evolution of three agents: the Teacher, the Solver, and the Generator. The Solver continuously refines its reasoning by learning from preference feedback on both successful and failed trajectories; the Teacher adaptively crafts increasingly challenging questions based on the Solver's weaknesses; and the Generator distills the Teacher's question-design strategy to enable scalable, high-fidelity curriculum generation. This closed-loop system produces a self-improving curriculum-requiring no pre-existing tasks or labels. Remarkably, starting from only 100 seed questions, our Socratic-Solver-8B achieves an average gain of +20.2 percentage points over prior data synthesis methods across seven mathematical reasoning benchmarks (AMC23, AIME24-25, Olympiad, MATH-500, Minerva, and GSM8K), with consistent gains on both Qwen3 and GLM4 series models. Even more surprisingly, synthetic data from Socratic-Generator-32B enables student LLMs to achieve superior performance compared to other state-of-the-art (SOTA) commercial LLMs on these benchmarks, including Qwen3-235B-A22B, DeepSeek-V3.1-671B, GPT-5, Gemini-2.5-Pro, Grok-4, and Claude-4.1-Opus.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24726</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 12:54:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LOVE-R1: Advancing Long Video Understanding with an Adaptive Zoom-in   Mechanism via Multi-Step Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24786</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24786.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shenghao Fu, Qize Yang, Yuan-Ming Li, Xihan Wei, Xiaohua Xie, Wei-Shi Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long video understanding is still challenging for recent Large Video-Language Models (LVLMs) due to the conflict between long-form temporal understanding and detailed spatial perception. LVLMs with a uniform frame sampling mechanism, which samples frames with an equal frame size and fixed sampling rate, inevitably sacrifice either temporal clues or spatial details, resulting in suboptimal solutions. To mitigate this dilemma, we propose LOVE-R1, a model that can adaptively zoom in on a video clip. The model is first provided with densely sampled frames but in a small resolution. If some spatial details are needed, the model can zoom in on a clip of interest with a large frame resolution based on its reasoning until key visual information is obtained. The whole process is implemented as a multi-step reasoning process. To train the reasoning ability, we first finetune the model on our collected 38k high-quality CoT data and enhance it with decoupled reinforcement finetuning. As outcome rewards can not provide fine-grained process supervision, we decouple multi-step reasoning into multiple single-step reasoning and optimize the internal zoom-in ability explicitly. Experiments on long video understanding benchmarks show that our model with the slow-fast adaptive frame sampling mechanism achieves a great trade-off between sampling density and frame resolutions, and LOVE-R1 outperforms our baseline Qwen2.5-VL by an average of 3.1% points across 4 common long video understanding benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24786</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 13:43:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ThermalGen: Style-Disentangled Flow-Based Generative Models for   RGB-to-Thermal Image Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24878</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24878.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiuhong Xiao, Roshan Nayak, Ning Zhang, Daniel Tortei, Giuseppe Loianno&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Paired RGB-thermal data is crucial for visual-thermal sensor fusion and cross-modality tasks, including important applications such as multi-modal image alignment and retrieval. However, the scarcity of synchronized and calibrated RGB-thermal image pairs presents a major obstacle to progress in these areas. To overcome this challenge, RGB-to-Thermal (RGB-T) image translation has emerged as a promising solution, enabling the synthesis of thermal images from abundant RGB datasets for training purposes. In this study, we propose ThermalGen, an adaptive flow-based generative model for RGB-T image translation, incorporating an RGB image conditioning architecture and a style-disentangled mechanism. To support large-scale training, we curated eight public satellite-aerial, aerial, and ground RGB-T paired datasets, and introduced three new large-scale satellite-aerial RGB-T datasets--DJI-day, Bosonplus-day, and Bosonplus-night--captured across diverse times, sensor types, and geographic regions. Extensive evaluations across multiple RGB-T benchmarks demonstrate that ThermalGen achieves comparable or superior translation performance compared to existing GAN-based and diffusion-based methods. To our knowledge, ThermalGen is the first RGB-T image translation model capable of synthesizing thermal images that reflect significant variations in viewpoints, sensor characteristics, and environmental conditions. Project page: http://xjh19971.github.io/ThermalGen&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24878</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 14:55:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RealUnify: Do Unified Models Truly Benefit from Unification? A   Comprehensive Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24897</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24897.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Shi, Yuhao Dong, Yue Ding, Yuran Wang, Xuanyu Zhu, Sheng Zhou, Wenting Liu, Haochen Tian, Rundong Wang, Huanqian Wang, Zuyan Liu, Bohan Zeng, Ruizhe Chen, Qixun Wang, Zhuoran Zhang, Xinlong Chen, Chengzhuo Tong, Bozhou Li, Chaoyou Fu, Qiang Liu, Haotian Wang, Wenjing Yang, Yuanxing Zhang, Pengfei Wan, Yi-Fan Zhang, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The integration of visual understanding and generation into unified multimodal models represents a significant stride toward general-purpose AI. However, a fundamental question remains unanswered by existing benchmarks: does this architectural unification actually enable synergetic interaction between the constituent capabilities? Existing evaluation paradigms, which primarily assess understanding and generation in isolation, are insufficient for determining whether a unified model can leverage its understanding to enhance its generation, or use generative simulation to facilitate deeper comprehension. To address this critical gap, we introduce RealUnify, a benchmark specifically designed to evaluate bidirectional capability synergy. RealUnify comprises 1,000 meticulously human-annotated instances spanning 10 categories and 32 subtasks. It is structured around two core axes: 1) Understanding Enhances Generation, which requires reasoning (e.g., commonsense, logic) to guide image generation, and 2) Generation Enhances Understanding, which necessitates mental simulation or reconstruction (e.g., of transformed or disordered visual inputs) to solve reasoning tasks. A key contribution is our dual-evaluation protocol, which combines direct end-to-end assessment with a diagnostic stepwise evaluation that decomposes tasks into distinct understanding and generation phases. This protocol allows us to precisely discern whether performance bottlenecks stem from deficiencies in core abilities or from a failure to integrate them. Through large-scale evaluations of 12 leading unified models and 6 specialized baselines, we find that current unified models still struggle to achieve effective synergy, indicating that architectural unification alone is insufficient. These results highlight the need for new training strategies and inductive biases to fully unlock the potential of unified modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24897</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 15:07:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenGPT-4o-Image: A Comprehensive Dataset for Advanced Image Generation   and Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24900</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24900.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhihong Chen, Xuehai Bai, Yang Shi, Chaoyou Fu, Huanyu Zhang, Haotian Wang, Xiaoyan Sun, Zhang Zhang, Liang Wang, Yuanxing Zhang, Pengfei Wan, Yi-Fan Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The performance of unified multimodal models for image generation and editing is fundamentally constrained by the quality and comprehensiveness of their training data. While existing datasets have covered basic tasks like style transfer and simple object manipulation, they often lack the systematic structure and challenging scenarios required for real-world applications. To address this bottleneck, we introduce OpenGPT-4o-Image, a large-scale dataset constructed using a novel methodology that combines hierarchical task taxonomy with automated data generation. Our taxonomy not only includes fundamental capabilities such as text rendering and style control but also introduces highly practical yet challenging categories like scientific imagery for chemistry illustrations and complex instruction editing requiring simultaneous execution of multiple operations. Through an automated pipeline leveraging structured resource pools and GPT-4o, we generate 80k high-quality instruction-image pairs with controlled diversity, covering 11 major domains and 51 subtasks. Extensive experiments show that fine-tuning leading models on our dataset achieves significant performance gains across multiple benchmarks, with improvements of up to 18\% on editing tasks (UniWorld-V1 on ImgEdit-Bench) and 13% on generation tasks (Harmon on GenEval). Our work demonstrates that systematic data construction is key to advancing multimodal AI capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24900</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 15:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BOE-XSUM: Extreme Summarization in Clear Language of Spanish Legal   Decrees and Notifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24908</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24908.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Andrés Fernández García, Javier de la Rosa, Julio Gonzalo, Roser Morante, Enrique Amigó, Alejandro Benito-Santos, Jorge Carrillo-de-Albornoz, Víctor Fresno, Adrian Ghajari, Guillermo Marco, Laura Plaza, Eva Sánchez Salido&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The ability to summarize long documents succinctly is increasingly important in daily life due to information overload, yet there is a notable lack of such summaries for Spanish documents in general, and in the legal domain in particular. In this work, we present BOE-XSUM, a curated dataset comprising 3,648 concise, plain-language summaries of documents sourced from Spain's ``Bolet\'{\i}n Oficial del Estado'' (BOE), the State Official Gazette. Each entry in the dataset includes a short summary, the original text, and its document type label. We evaluate the performance of medium-sized large language models (LLMs) fine-tuned on BOE-XSUM, comparing them to general-purpose generative models in a zero-shot setting. Results show that fine-tuned models significantly outperform their non-specialized counterparts. Notably, the best-performing model -- BERTIN GPT-J 6B (32-bit precision) -- achieves a 24\% performance gain over the top zero-shot model, DeepSeek-R1 (accuracies of 41.6\% vs.\ 33.5\%).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24908</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 15:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Goal-Oriented Language-Guided Navigation with Self-Improving   Demonstrations at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24910</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24910.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Songze Li, Zun Wang, Gengze Zhou, Jialu Li, Xiangyu Zeng, Limin Wang, Yu Qiao, Qi Wu, Mohit Bansal, Yi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Goal-oriented language-guided navigation requires robust exploration capabilities for agents to navigate to specified goals in unknown environments without step-by-step instructions. Existing methods tend to exclusively utilize shortest-path trajectories, lacking effective exploration priors for training navigation agents. To address the above challenges, we present SID, a goal-oriented language-guided navigation learning approach with Self-Improving Demonstrations. Specifically, SID learns an initial agent on the shortest-path data sampled from environments and then leverages this agent to generate novel exploration trajectories. The novel rollouts provide demonstrations with stronger exploration strategies to train a better agent, which in turn produces higher-quality agent demonstrations for the next round of training. We show that this iterative self-improving pipeline readily scales to new environments, and the resulting demonstrations can be transferred across a variety of language-guided navigation tasks, elevating the performance ceiling in diverse goal-oriented navigation tasks. Extensive experiments demonstrate that SID significantly boosts the exploration capabilities and generalization of navigation agents. The resulting agent achieves new state-of-the-art performance on goal-oriented language-guided navigation tasks, including REVERIE, SOON, notably achieving a 50.9% success rate on the unseen validation splits of SOON, surpassing the prior leading approaches by a margin of 13.9%.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24910</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 15:15:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Policy Valuation is Enough for LLM Reasoning with Verifiable   Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24981</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24981.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran He, Yuxiao Ye, Qingpeng Cai, Chen Hu, Binxing Jiao, Daxin Jiang, Ling Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; RL with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as a promising paradigm for improving the reasoning abilities of large language models (LLMs). Current methods rely primarily on policy optimization frameworks like PPO and GRPO, which follow generalized policy iteration that alternates between evaluating the current policy's value and improving the policy based on evaluation. While effective, they often suffer from training instability and diversity collapse, requiring complex heuristic tricks and careful tuning. We observe that standard RLVR in math reasoning can be formalized as a specialized finite-horizon Markov Decision Process with deterministic state transitions, tree-structured dynamics, and binary terminal rewards. Though large in scale, the underlying structure is simpler than general-purpose control settings for which popular RL algorithms (e.g., PPO) were developed, suggesting that several sophisticated techniques in existing methods may be reduced or even omitted. Based on this insight, we prove a surprising result: the optimal action can be recovered from the Q-function of a fixed uniformly random policy, thereby bypassing the generalized policy iteration loop and its associated heuristics. We introduce Random Policy Valuation for Diverse Reasoning (ROVER) to translate this principle into a practical and scalable algorithm for LLM math reasoning, a minimalist yet highly effective RL method that samples actions from a softmax over these uniform-policy Q-values. ROVER preserves diversity throughout training, allowing sustained exploration of multiple valid pathways. Across multiple base models and standard math reasoning benchmarks, ROVER demonstrates superior performance in both quality (+8.2 on pass@1, +16.8 on pass@256) and diversity (+17.6\%), despite its radical simplification compared to strong, complicated existing methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24981</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 16:09:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Correctness Models: Learning Calibrated and Model-Agnostic   Correctness Predictors from Historical Patterns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24988</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24988.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hanqi Xiao, Vaidehi Patil, Hyunji Lee, Elias Stengel-Eskin, Mohit Bansal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating accurate and calibrated confidence estimates is critical for deploying LLMs in high-stakes or user-facing applications, and remains an open challenge. Prior research has often framed confidence as a problem of eliciting a model's "self-knowledge", i.e., the ability of an LLM to judge whether its own answers are correct; this approach implicitly assumes that there is some privileged information about the answer's correctness that is accessible to the model itself. However, our experiments reveal that an LLM attempting to predict the correctness of its own outputs generally performs no better than an unrelated LLM. Moreover, we hypothesize that a key factor in building a "Correctness Model" (CM) is exposure to a target model's historical predictions. We propose multiple methods to inject this historical correctness information, creating a Generalized Correctness Model (GCM). We first show that GCMs can be trained on the correctness data from many LLMs and learn patterns for correctness prediction applicable across datasets and models. We then use CMs as a lens for studying the source of correctness prediction ability and its generalization, systematically controlling their training data and finding that answer phrasing is a strong predictor for correctness. We further explore alternative methods of injecting history without training an LLM, finding that including history as in-context examples can help improve correctness prediction, and post-hoc calibration can provide complementary reductions in calibration error. We evaluate GCMs based on Qwen3-8B across 5 model families and the MMLU and TriviaQA datasets, as well as on a downstream selective prediction task, finding that reliable LLM confidence estimation is a generalizable and model-agnostic skill learned by systematically encoding correctness history rather than a model-specific skill reliant on self-introspection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24988</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 16:19:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advantage Weighted Matching: Aligning RL with Pretraining in Diffusion   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25050</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25050.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuchen Xue, Chongjian Ge, Shilong Zhang, Yichen Li, Zhi-Ming Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning (RL) has emerged as a central paradigm for advancing Large Language Models (LLMs), where pre-training and RL post-training share the same log-likelihood formulation. In contrast, recent RL approaches for diffusion models, most notably Denoising Diffusion Policy Optimization (DDPO), optimize an objective different from the pretraining objectives--score/flow matching loss. In this work, we establish a novel theoretical analysis: DDPO is an implicit form of score/flow matching with noisy targets, which increases variance and slows convergence. Building on this analysis, we introduce Advantage Weighted Matching (AWM), a policy-gradient method for diffusion. It uses the same score/flow-matching loss as pretraining to obtain a lower-variance objective and reweights each sample by its advantage. In effect, AWM raises the influence of high-reward samples and suppresses low-reward ones while keeping the modeling objective identical to pretraining. This unifies pretraining and RL conceptually and practically, is consistent with policy-gradient theory, reduces variance, and yields faster convergence. This simple yet effective design yields substantial benefits: on GenEval, OCR, and PickScore benchmarks, AWM delivers up to a 24times speedup over Flow-GRPO (which builds on DDPO), when applied to Stable Diffusion 3.5 Medium and FLUX, without compromising generation quality. Code is available at https://github.com/scxue/advantage_weighted_matching.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25050</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:02:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cogito, Ergo Ludo: An Agent that Learns to Play by Reasoning and   Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25052</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25052.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sai Wang, Yu Wu, Zhongwen Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The pursuit of artificial agents that can learn to master complex environments has led to remarkable successes, yet prevailing deep reinforcement learning methods often rely on immense experience, encoding their knowledge opaquely within neural network weights. We propose a different paradigm, one in which an agent learns to play by reasoning and planning. We introduce Cogito, ergo ludo (CEL), a novel agent architecture that leverages a Large Language Model (LLM) to build an explicit, language-based understanding of its environment's mechanics and its own strategy. Starting from a tabula rasa state with no prior knowledge (except action set), CEL operates on a cycle of interaction and reflection. After each episode, the agent analyzes its complete trajectory to perform two concurrent learning processes: Rule Induction, where it refines its explicit model of the environment's dynamics, and Strategy and Playbook Summarization, where it distills experiences into an actionable strategic playbook. We evaluate CEL on diverse grid-world tasks (i.e., Minesweeper, Frozen Lake, and Sokoban), and show that the CEL agent successfully learns to master these games by autonomously discovering their rules and developing effective policies from sparse rewards. Ablation studies confirm that the iterative process is critical for sustained learning. Our work demonstrates a path toward more general and interpretable agents that not only act effectively but also build a transparent and improving model of their world through explicit reasoning on raw experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25052</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BRIDGE - Building Reinforcement-Learning Depth-to-Image Data Generation   Engine for Monocular Depth Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25077</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25077.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dingning Liu, Haoyu Guo, Jingyi Zhou, Tong He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Monocular Depth Estimation (MDE) is a foundational task for computer vision. Traditional methods are limited by data scarcity and quality, hindering their robustness. To overcome this, we propose BRIDGE, an RL-optimized depth-to-image (D2I) generation framework that synthesizes over 20M realistic and geometrically accurate RGB images, each intrinsically paired with its ground truth depth, from diverse source depth maps. Then we train our depth estimation model on this dataset, employing a hybrid supervision strategy that integrates teacher pseudo-labels with ground truth depth for comprehensive and robust training. This innovative data generation and training paradigm enables BRIDGE to achieve breakthroughs in scale and domain diversity, consistently outperforming existing state-of-the-art approaches quantitatively and in complex scene detail capture, thereby fostering general and robust depth features. Code and models are available at https://dingning-liu.github.io/bridge.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25077</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:19:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Generalist Data-Analytic Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25084</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25084.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuofei Qiao, Yanqiu Zhao, Zhisong Qiu, Xiaobin Wang, Jintian Zhang, Zhao Bin, Ningyu Zhang, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Huajun Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data-analytic agents are emerging as a key catalyst for automated scientific discovery and for the vision of Innovating AI. Current approaches, however, rely heavily on prompt engineering over proprietary models, while open-source models struggle to face diverse-format, large-scale data files and long-horizon, multi-step reasoning that real-world analytics demands. This paper introduces DataMind, a scalable data synthesis and agent training recipe designed to build generalist data-analytic agents. DataMind tackles three key challenges in building open-source data-analytic agents, including insufficient data resources, improper training strategy, and unstable code-based multi-turn rollout. Concretely, DataMind applies 1) a fine-grained task taxonomy and a recursive easy-to-hard task composition mechanism to increase the diversity and difficulty of synthesized queries; 2) a knowledge-augmented trajectory sampling strategy followed by model-based and rule-based filtering; 3) a dynamically adjustable training objective combining both SFT and RL losses; 4) a memory-frugal and stable code-based multi-turn rollout framework. Built on DataMind, we curate DataMind-12K, a high-quality trajectory set spanning diverse domains, task categories, and data file formats for data-analytic tasks. Trained on DataMind-12K, our DataMind-14B achieves state-of-the-art with an average score of 71.16% on multiple data analysis benchmarks, outperforming the strongest proprietary baselines DeepSeek-V3.1 and GPT-5. Our DataMind-7B also performs best among all open-source models with a score of 68.10%. We also incorporate some empirical insights gained from our exploratory trials into the analysis experiments, aiming to provide actionable insights about agentic training for the community. We will release DataMind-12K and DataMind-7B,14B for the community's future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25084</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:23:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Personalized Deep Research: Benchmarks and Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuan Liang, Jiaxian Li, Yuqing Wang, Piaohong Wang, Motong Tian, Pai Liu, Shuofei Qiao, Runnan Fang, He Zhu, Ge Zhang, Minghao Liu, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Ningyu Zhang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep Research Agents (DRAs) can autonomously conduct complex investigations and generate comprehensive reports, demonstrating strong real-world potential. However, existing evaluations mostly rely on close-ended benchmarks, while open-ended deep research benchmarks remain scarce and typically neglect personalized scenarios. To bridge this gap, we introduce Personalized Deep Research Bench, the first benchmark for evaluating personalization in DRAs. It pairs 50 diverse research tasks across 10 domains with 25 authentic user profiles that combine structured persona attributes with dynamic real-world contexts, yielding 250 realistic user-task queries. To assess system performance, we propose the PQR Evaluation Framework, which jointly measures (P) Personalization Alignment, (Q) Content Quality, and (R) Factual Reliability. Our experiments on a range of systems highlight current capabilities and limitations in handling personalized deep research. This work establishes a rigorous foundation for developing and evaluating the next generation of truly personalized AI research assistants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25106</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:39:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From f(x) and g(x) to f(g(x)): LLMs Learn New Skills in RL by   Composing Old Ones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25123</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25123.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lifan Yuan, Weize Chen, Yuchen Zhang, Ganqu Cui, Hanbin Wang, Ziming You, Ning Ding, Zhiyuan Liu, Maosong Sun, Hao Peng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Does RL teach LLMs genuinely new skills, or does it merely activate existing ones? This question lies at the core of ongoing debates about the role of RL in LLM post-training. On one side, strong empirical results can be achieved with RL even without preceding supervised finetuning; on the other, critics argue that RL contributes little beyond reweighting existing reasoning strategies. This work provides concrete evidence that LLMs can acquire genuinely new skills during RL by composing existing ones, mirroring one of the central mechanisms by which humans acquire new cognitive skills. To mitigate data contamination and other confounding factors, and to allow precise control over task complexity, we develop a synthetic framework for our investigation. Specifically, we define a skill as the ability to infer the output of a string transformation function f(x) given x. When an LLM has already learned f and g prior to RL, our experiments reveal that RL enables it to learn unseen compositions of them h(x)=g(f(x)). Further, this compositional ability generalizes to more difficult problems such as compositions of &gt;2 functions unseen during RL training. Surprisingly, our experiments show that compositional skill acquired on a source task transfers to a different target task. This transfer happens even without compositional training on the target, requiring only prior knowledge of the target's atomic skills. Our qualitative analysis shows that RL fundamentally changes the reasoning behaviors of the models. In contrast, next-token training with the same data yields none of these findings. Our systematic experiments provide fresh insights into LLM learning, suggesting the value of first building base models with basic skills, then using RL to incentivize advanced, generalizable skills for complex problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25123</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:44:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MGM-Omni: Scaling Omni LLMs to Personalized Long-Horizon Speech</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25131</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25131.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chengyao Wang, Zhisheng Zhong, Bohao Peng, Senqiao Yang, Yuqi Liu, Haokun Gui, Bin Xia, Jingyao Li, Bei Yu, Jiaya Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present MGM-Omni, a unified Omni LLM for omni-modal understanding and expressive, long-horizon speech generation. Unlike cascaded pipelines that isolate speech synthesis, MGM-Omni adopts a "brain-mouth" design with a dual-track, token-based architecture that cleanly decouples multimodal reasoning from real-time speech generation. This design enables efficient cross-modal interaction and low-latency, streaming speech generation. For understanding, a unified training strategy coupled with a dual audio encoder design enables long-form audio perception across diverse acoustic conditions. For generation, a chunk-based parallel decoding scheme narrows the text speech token-rate gap, accelerating inference and supporting streaming zero-shot voice cloning with stable timbre over extended durations. Compared to concurrent work, MGM-Omni achieves these capabilities with markedly data-efficient training. Extensive experiments demonstrate that MGM-Omni outperforms existing open source models in preserving timbre identity across extended sequences, producing natural and context-aware speech, and achieving superior long-form audio and omnimodal understanding. MGM-Omni establishes an efficient, end-to-end paradigm for omnimodal understanding and controllable, personalised long-horizon speech generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25131</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:48:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Era of Real-World Human Interaction: RL from User Conversations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25137</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25137.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chuanyang Jin, Jing Xu, Bo Liu, Leitian Tao, Olga Golovneva, Tianmin Shu, Wenting Zhao, Xian Li, Jason Weston&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We posit that to achieve continual model improvement and multifaceted alignment, future models must learn from natural human interaction. Current conversational models are aligned using pre-annotated, expert-generated human feedback. In this work, we introduce Reinforcement Learning from Human Interaction (RLHI), a paradigm that learns directly from in-the-wild user conversations. We develop two complementary methods: (1) RLHI with User-Guided Rewrites, which revises unsatisfactory model outputs based on users' natural-language follow-up responses, (2) RLHI with User-Based Rewards, which learns via a reward model conditioned on knowledge of the user's long-term interaction history (termed persona). Together, these methods link long-term user personas to turn-level preferences via persona-conditioned preference optimization. Trained on conversations derived from WildChat, both RLHI variants outperform strong baselines in personalization and instruction-following, and similar feedback enhances performance on reasoning benchmarks. These results suggest organic human interaction offers scalable, effective supervision for personalized alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25137</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:50:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pretraining Large Language Models with NVFP4</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25149</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25149.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NVIDIA, Felix Abecassis, Anjulie Agrusa, Dong Ahn, Jonah Alben, Stefania Alborghetti, Michael Andersch, Sivakumar Arayandi, Alexis Bjorlin, Aaron Blakeman, Evan Briones, Ian Buck, Bryan Catanzaro, Jinhang Choi, Mike Chrzanowski, Eric Chung, Victor Cui, Steve Dai, Bita Darvish Rouhani, Carlo del Mundo, Deena Donia, Burc Eryilmaz, Henry Estela, Abhinav Goel, Oleg Goncharov, Yugi Guvvala, Robert Hesse, Russell Hewett, Herbert Hum, Ujval Kapasi, Brucek Khailany, Mikail Khona, Nick Knight, Alex Kondratenko, Ronny Krashinsky, Ben Lanir, Simon Layton, Michael Lightstone, Daniel Lo, Paulius Micikevicius, Asit Mishra, Tim Moon, Deepak Narayanan, Chao Ni, Abhijit Paithankar, Satish Pasumarthi, Ankit Patel, Mostofa Patwary, Ashwin Poojary, Gargi Prasad, Sweta Priyadarshi, Yigong Qin, Xiaowei Ren, Oleg Rybakov, Charbel Sakr, Sanjeev Satheesh, Stas Sergienko, Pasha Shamis, Kirthi Shankar, Nishant Sharma, Mohammad Shoeybi, Michael Siu, Misha Smelyanskiy, Darko Stosic, Dusan Stosic, Bor-Yiing Su, Frank Sun, Nima Tajbakhsh, Shelby Thomas, Przemek Tredak, Evgeny Tsykunov, Gandhi Vaithilingam, Aditya Vavre, Rangharajan Venkatesan, Roger Waleffe, Qiyu Wan, Hexin Wang, Mengdi Wang, Lizzie Wei, Hao Wu, Evan Wu, Keith Wyss, Ning Xu, Jinze Xue, Charlene Yang, Yujia Zhai, Ruoxi Zhang, Jingyang Zhu, Zhongbo Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) today are powerful problem solvers across many domains, and they continue to get stronger as they scale in model size, training set size, and training set quality, as shown by extensive research and experimentation across the industry. Training a frontier model today requires on the order of tens to hundreds of yottaflops, which is a massive investment of time, compute, and energy. Improving pretraining efficiency is therefore essential to enable the next generation of even more capable LLMs. While 8-bit floating point (FP8) training is now widely adopted, transitioning to even narrower precision, such as 4-bit floating point (FP4), could unlock additional improvements in computational speed and resource utilization. However, quantization at this level poses challenges to training stability, convergence, and implementation, notably for large-scale models trained on long token horizons.   In this study, we introduce a novel approach for stable and accurate training of large language models (LLMs) using the NVFP4 format. Our method integrates Random Hadamard transforms (RHT) to bound block-level outliers, employs a two-dimensional quantization scheme for consistent representations across both the forward and backward passes, utilizes stochastic rounding for unbiased gradient estimation, and incorporates selective high-precision layers. We validate our approach by training a 12-billion-parameter model on 10 trillion tokens -- the longest publicly documented training run in 4-bit precision to date. Our results show that the model trained with our NVFP4-based pretraining technique achieves training loss and downstream task accuracies comparable to an FP8 baseline. These findings highlight that NVFP4, when combined with our training approach, represents a major step forward in narrow-precision LLM training algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25149</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:53:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GSM8K-V: Can Vision Language Models Solve Grade School Math Word   Problems in Visual Contexts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25160</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25160.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fan Yuan, Yuchen Yan, Yifan Jiang, Haoran Zhao, Tao Feng, Jinyan Chen, Yanwei Lou, Wenqi Zhang, Yongliang Shen, Weiming Lu, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision language models (VLMs) achieve unified modeling of images and text, enabling them to accomplish complex real-world tasks through perception, planning, and reasoning. Among these tasks, reasoning is particularly representative, with mathematical reasoning serving as a prominent example. It highlights the high-level capability of VLMs to comprehend mathematical information in images and to perform sophisticated reasoning. Recently, numerous visual mathematical reasoning benchmarks have been proposed, but they are often restricted to geometry, lack coverage of math word problems, and rarely assess reasoning across multiple images. To address these gaps, we introduce GSM8K-V, a purely visual multi-image mathematical reasoning benchmark. GSM8K-V is built by systematically mapping each sample from the widely used text-based GSM8K into visual form. Through a carefully designed automated image-generation pipeline combined with meticulous human annotation, we curate 1,319 high-quality samples. We evaluate a wide range of open-source and closed-source models on GSM8K-V. Results show that although existing VLMs have nearly saturated performance on text-based GSM8K, there remains substantial room for improvement on GSM8K-V. For example, the best-performing model, Gemini-2.5-Pro, achieves 95.22% accuracy on GSM8K but only 46.93% on GSM8K-V. We conduct a comprehensive analysis of GSM8K-V, examining the limitations of current models as well as potential directions for improvement. GSM8K-V offers a new perspective on visual mathematical reasoning and establishes a benchmark to guide the development of more robust and generalizable VLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25160</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:57:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rolling Forcing: Autoregressive Long Video Diffusion in Real Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25161</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25161.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kunhao Liu, Wenbo Hu, Jiale Xu, Ying Shan, Shijian Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Streaming video generation, as one fundamental component in interactive world models and neural game engines, aims to generate high-quality, low-latency, and temporally coherent long video streams. However, most existing work suffers from severe error accumulation that often significantly degrades the generated stream videos over long horizons. We design Rolling Forcing, a novel video generation technique that enables streaming long videos with minimal error accumulation. Rolling Forcing comes with three novel designs. First, instead of iteratively sampling individual frames, which accelerates error propagation, we design a joint denoising scheme that simultaneously denoises multiple frames with progressively increasing noise levels. This design relaxes the strict causality across adjacent frames, effectively suppressing error growth. Second, we introduce the attention sink mechanism into the long-horizon stream video generation task, which allows the model to keep key value states of initial frames as a global context anchor and thereby enhances long-term global consistency. Third, we design an efficient training algorithm that enables few-step distillation over largely extended denoising windows. This algorithm operates on non-overlapping windows and mitigates exposure bias conditioned on self-generated histories. Extensive experiments show that Rolling Forcing enables real-time streaming generation of multi-minute videos on a single GPU, with substantially reduced error accumulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25161</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:57:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TR2-D2: Tree Search Guided Trajectory-Aware Fine-Tuning for Discrete   Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25171</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25171.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sophia Tang, Yuchen Zhu, Molei Tao, Pranam Chatterjee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning with stochastic optimal control offers a promising framework for diffusion fine-tuning, where a pre-trained diffusion model is optimized to generate paths that lead to a reward-tilted distribution. While these approaches enable optimization without access to explicit samples from the optimal distribution, they require training on rollouts under the current fine-tuned model, making them susceptible to reinforcing sub-optimal trajectories that yield poor rewards. To overcome this challenge, we introduce TRee Search Guided TRajectory-Aware Fine-Tuning for Discrete Diffusion (TR2-D2), a novel framework that optimizes reward-guided discrete diffusion trajectories with tree search to construct replay buffers for trajectory-aware fine-tuning. These buffers are generated using Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS) and subsequently used to fine-tune a pre-trained discrete diffusion model under a stochastic optimal control objective. We validate our framework on single- and multi-objective fine-tuning of biological sequence diffusion models, highlighting the overall effectiveness of TR2-D2 for reliable reward-guided fine-tuning in discrete sequence generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25171</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EasySteer: A Unified Framework for High-Performance and Extensible LLM   Steering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25175</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25175.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haolei Xu, Xinyu Mei, Yuchen Yan, Rui Zhou, Wenqi Zhang, Weiming Lu, Yueting Zhuang, Yongliang Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM) steering has emerged as a promising paradigm for controlling model behavior at inference time through targeted manipulation of hidden states, offering a lightweight alternative to expensive retraining. However, existing steering frameworks suffer from critical limitations: computational inefficiency, limited extensibility, and restricted functionality that hinder both research progress and practical deployment. We present EasySteer, a unified framework for high-performance, extensible LLM steering built on vLLM. Our system features modular architecture with pluggable interfaces for both analysis-based and learning-based methods, fine-grained parameter control, pre-computed steering vectors for eight application domains, and an interactive demonstration system. Through deep integration with vLLM's optimized inference engine, EasySteer achieves 5.5-11.4times speedup over existing frameworks. Extensive experiments demonstrate its effectiveness in overthinking mitigation, hallucination reduction, and other key applications. EasySteer transforms steering from research technique to production-ready capability, establishing critical infrastructure for deployable, controllable language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25175</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SIRI: Scaling Iterative Reinforcement Learning with Interleaved   Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25176</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25176.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoming Wen, Yushi Bai, Juanzi Li, Jie Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SIRI, Scaling Iterative Reinforcement Learning with Interleaved Compression, a simple yet effective RL approach for Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) that enables more efficient and accurate reasoning. Existing studies have observed repetitive thinking patterns in LRMs, and attempts to reduce them often come at the cost of performance. In this paper, we show that this trade-off can be overcome through a training regime that iteratively alternates between compressing and expanding the reasoning budget, by dynamically adjusting the maximum rollout length during training. The compression phase cuts the rollout length, forcing the model to make precise and valuable decisions within a limited context, which effectively reduces redundant tokens and increases reasoning density. The expansion phase then relaxes the length limit, providing space for the model to explore and plan in long-horizon settings. Remarkably, we find that after each compression-expansion cycle, the model's performance improves even as its output length decreases, steadily pushing it closer to the Pareto frontier in the performance-efficiency trade-off. Training on DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-1.5B, SIRI-low improves performance on AIME24 by 43.2% while reducing token usage by 46.9% after three iterations, and SIRI-high achieves the highest accuracy compared to all other methods (Figure 1). Our findings shed light on the potential of periodically oscillating the LRM's output truncation length during training to dynamically balance exploration and efficiency in reasoning, converging towards an optimal "sweet spot" between the two. Our models are publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25176</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PixelCraft: A Multi-Agent System for High-Fidelity Visual Reasoning on   Structured Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25185</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25185.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuoshuo Zhang, Zijian Li, Yizhen Zhang, Jingjing Fu, Lei Song, Jiang Bian, Jun Zhang, Yujiu Yang, Rui Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Structured images (e.g., charts and geometric diagrams) remain challenging for multimodal large language models (MLLMs), as perceptual slips can cascade into erroneous conclusions. Intermediate visual cues can steer reasoning; however, existing cue-based methods are constrained with low-fidelity image processing and linear, rigid reasoning patterns, limiting their effectiveness on complex structured-image tasks. In this paper, we propose PixelCraft, a novel multi-agent system for high-fidelity image processing and flexible visual reasoning on structured images. The system comprises a dispatcher, a planner, a reasoner, critics, and a set of visual tool agents. To achieve high-fidelity processing, we construct a high-quality corpus and fine-tune an MLLM into a grounding model, whose pixel-level localizations are integrated with traditional computer vision (CV) algorithms in tool agents. Building on this foundation, PixelCraft facilitates flexible visual reasoning through a dynamic three-stage workflow of tool selection, agent discussion, and self-criticism. Moreover, unlike prior linear reasoning patterns that simply append historical images, PixelCraft maintains an image memory to allow the planner to adaptively revisit earlier visual steps, explore alternative reasoning branches, and dynamically adjust the reasoning trajectory during discussion. Extensive experiments on challenging chart and geometry benchmarks demonstrate that PixelCraft significantly improves visual reasoning performance for advanced MLLMs, setting a new standard for structured image reasoning. Our code will be available at https://github.com/microsoft/PixelCraft.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25185</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Jigsaw Post-Training Improves MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25190</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25190.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Penghao Wu, Yushan Zhang, Haiwen Diao, Bo Li, Lewei Lu, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning based post-training has recently emerged as a powerful paradigm for enhancing the alignment and reasoning capabilities of multimodal large language models (MLLMs). While vision-centric post-training is crucial for enhancing MLLMs' intrinsic understanding of visual signals, current post-training paradigms are predominantly text-centric, where dense visual inputs are only leveraged to extract sparse cues for text-based reasoning. There exist a few approaches in this direction, however, they often still rely on text as an intermediate mediator or introduce additional visual generative designs. In this work, we introduce Visual Jigsaw, a generic self-supervised post-training framework designed to strengthen visual understanding in MLLMs. Visual Jigsaw is formulated as a general ordering task: visual inputs are partitioned, shuffled, and the model must reconstruct the visual information by producing the correct permutation in natural language. This naturally aligns with reinforcement learning from verifiable rewards (RLVR), requires no additional visual generative components, and derives its supervisory signal automatically without any annotations. We instantiate Visual Jigsaw across three visual modalities, including images, videos, and 3D data. Extensive experiments demonstrate substantial improvements in fine-grained perception, temporal reasoning, and 3D spatial understanding. Our findings highlight the potential of self-supervised vision-centric tasks in post-training MLLMs and aim to inspire further research on vision-centric pretext designs. Project Page: https://penghao-wu.github.io/visual_jigsaw/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25190</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VGGT-X: When VGGT Meets Dense Novel View Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25191</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25191.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Liu, Chuanchen Luo, Zimo Tang, Junran Peng, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We study the problem of applying 3D Foundation Models (3DFMs) to dense Novel View Synthesis (NVS). Despite significant progress in Novel View Synthesis powered by NeRF and 3DGS, current approaches remain reliant on accurate 3D attributes (e.g., camera poses and point clouds) acquired from Structure-from-Motion (SfM), which is often slow and fragile in low-texture or low-overlap captures. Recent 3DFMs showcase orders of magnitude speedup over the traditional pipeline and great potential for online NVS. But most of the validation and conclusions are confined to sparse-view settings. Our study reveals that naively scaling 3DFMs to dense views encounters two fundamental barriers: dramatically increasing VRAM burden and imperfect outputs that degrade initialization-sensitive 3D training. To address these barriers, we introduce VGGT-X, incorporating a memory-efficient VGGT implementation that scales to 1,000+ images, an adaptive global alignment for VGGT output enhancement, and robust 3DGS training practices. Extensive experiments show that these measures substantially close the fidelity gap with COLMAP-initialized pipelines, achieving state-of-the-art results in dense COLMAP-free NVS and pose estimation. Additionally, we analyze the causes of remaining gaps with COLMAP-initialized rendering, providing insights for the future development of 3D foundation models and dense NVS. Our project page is available at https://dekuliutesla.github.io/vggt-x.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25191</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
