<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:13:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Dens3R: A Foundation Model for 3D Geometry Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16290</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16290.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xianze Fang, Jingnan Gao, Zhe Wang, Zhuo Chen, Xingyu Ren, Jiangjing Lyu, Qiaomu Ren, Zhonglei Yang, Xiaokang Yang, Yichao Yan, Chengfei Lyu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in dense 3D reconstruction have led to significant progress, yet achieving accurate unified geometric prediction remains a major challenge. Most existing methods are limited to predicting a single geometry quantity from input images. However, geometric quantities such as depth, surface normals, and point maps are inherently correlated, and estimating them in isolation often fails to ensure consistency, thereby limiting both accuracy and practical applicability. This motivates us to explore a unified framework that explicitly models the structural coupling among different geometric properties to enable joint regression. In this paper, we present Dens3R, a 3D foundation model designed for joint geometric dense prediction and adaptable to a wide range of downstream tasks. Dens3R adopts a two-stage training framework to progressively build a pointmap representation that is both generalizable and intrinsically invariant. Specifically, we design a lightweight shared encoder-decoder backbone and introduce position-interpolated rotary positional encoding to maintain expressive power while enhancing robustness to high-resolution inputs. By integrating image-pair matching features with intrinsic invariance modeling, Dens3R accurately regresses multiple geometric quantities such as surface normals and depth, achieving consistent geometry perception from single-view to multi-view inputs. Additionally, we propose a post-processing pipeline that supports geometrically consistent multi-view inference. Extensive experiments demonstrate the superior performance of Dens3R across various dense 3D prediction tasks and highlight its potential for broader applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16290</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 07:22:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InstructVLA: Vision-Language-Action Instruction Tuning from   Understanding to Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17520</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.17520.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuai Yang, Hao Li, Yilun Chen, Bin Wang, Yang Tian, Tai Wang, Hanqing Wang, Feng Zhao, Yiyi Liao, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; To operate effectively in the real world, robots must integrate multimodal reasoning with precise action generation. However, existing vision-language-action (VLA) models often sacrifice one for the other, narrow their abilities to task-specific manipulation data, and suffer catastrophic forgetting of pre-trained vision-language capabilities. To bridge this gap, we introduce InstructVLA, an end-to-end VLA model that preserves the flexible reasoning of large vision-language models (VLMs) while delivering leading manipulation performance. InstructVLA introduces a novel training paradigm, Vision-Language-Action Instruction Tuning (VLA-IT), which employs multimodal training with mixture-of-experts adaptation to jointly optimize textual reasoning and action generation on both standard VLM corpora and a curated 650K-sample VLA-IT dataset. On in-domain SimplerEnv tasks, InstructVLA achieves 30.5% improvement over SpatialVLA. To evaluate generalization, we introduce SimplerEnv-Instruct, an 80-task benchmark requiring closed-loop control and high-level instruction understanding, where it outperforms a fine-tuned OpenVLA by 92% and an action expert aided by GPT-4o by 29%. Additionally, InstructVLA surpasses baseline VLMs on multimodal tasks and exhibits inference-time scaling by leveraging textual reasoning to boost manipulation performance in both simulated and real-world settings. These results demonstrate InstructVLA's potential for bridging intuitive and steerable human-robot interaction with efficient policy learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17520</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 13:57:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Agents: Building Effective Agents While Reducing Cost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02694</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02694.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ningning Wang, Xavier Hu, Pai Liu, He Zhu, Yue Hou, Heyuan Huang, Shengyu Zhang, Jian Yang, Jiaheng Liu, Ge Zhang, Changwang Zhang, Jun Wang, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The remarkable capabilities of Large Language Model (LLM)-driven agents have enabled sophisticated systems to tackle complex, multi-step tasks, but their escalating costs threaten scalability and accessibility. This work presents the first systematic study of the efficiency-effectiveness trade-off in modern agent systems, addressing the critical need for cost-effective designs without sacrificing performance. We investigate three key questions: (1) How much complexity do agentic tasks inherently require? (2) When do additional modules yield diminishing returns? (3) How much efficiency can be gained through the design of efficient agent frameworks? Through an empirical analysis on the GAIA benchmark, we evaluate the impact of LLM backbone selection, agent framework designs, and test-time scaling strategies. Using the cost-of-pass metric, we quantify the efficiency-performance trade-off across these dimensions. Our findings inform the development of Efficient Agents , a novel agent framework that has an optimal complexity to task requirements. Efficient Agents retains 96.7% of the performance of OWL, one leading open-source agent framework, while reducing operational costs from 0.398 to 0.228, resulting in a 28.4% improvement in cost-of-pass. Our work provides actionable insights for designing efficient, high-performing agent systems, advancing the accessibility and sustainability of AI-driven solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02694</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 17:56:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MCIF: Multimodal Crosslingual Instruction-Following Benchmark from   Scientific Talks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19634</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.19634.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sara Papi, Maike Züfle, Marco Gaido, Beatrice Savoldi, Danni Liu, Ioannis Douros, Luisa Bentivogli, Jan Niehues&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models have catalyzed the development of multimodal LLMs (MLLMs) that integrate text, speech, and vision within unified frameworks. As MLLMs evolve from narrow, monolingual, task-specific systems to general-purpose instruction-following models, a key frontier lies in evaluating their multilingual and multimodal capabilities over both long and short contexts. However, existing benchmarks fall short in evaluating these dimensions jointly: they are often limited to English, mostly focus on one single modality at a time, rely on short-form contexts, or lack human annotations -- hindering comprehensive assessment of model performance across languages, modalities, and task complexity. To address these gaps, we introduce MCIF (Multimodal Crosslingual Instruction Following), the first multilingual human-annotated benchmark based on scientific talks that is designed to evaluate instruction-following in crosslingual, multimodal settings over both short- and long-form inputs. MCIF spans three core modalities -- speech, vision, and text -- and four diverse languages (English, German, Italian, and Chinese), enabling a comprehensive evaluation of MLLMs' abilities to interpret instructions across languages and combine them with multimodal contextual information. MCIF is released under a CC-BY 4.0 license to encourage open research and progress in MLLMs development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19634</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 19:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AgentTTS: Large Language Model Agent for Test-time Compute-optimal   Scaling Strategy in Complex Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00890</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00890.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fali Wang, Hui Liu, Zhenwei Dai, Jingying Zeng, Zhiwei Zhang, Zongyu Wu, Chen Luo, Zhen Li, Xianfeng Tang, Qi He, Suhang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Test-time scaling (TTS) enhances the performance of large language models (LLMs) by allocating additional compute resources during inference. However, existing research primarily investigates TTS in single-stage tasks; while many real-world problems are multi-stage complex tasks, composed of a sequence of heterogeneous subtasks with each subtask requires LLM of specific capability. Therefore, we study a novel problem: the test-time compute-optimal scaling in multi-stage complex tasks, aiming to select suitable models and allocate budgets per subtask to maximize overall performance. TTS in multi-stage tasks introduces two fundamental challenges: (i) The combinatorial search space of model and budget allocations, combined with the high cost of inference, makes brute-force search impractical. (ii) The optimal model and budget allocations across subtasks are interdependent, increasing the complexity of the compute-optimal search. To address this gap, we conduct extensive pilot experiments on four tasks across six datasets, deriving three empirical insights characterizing the behavior of LLMs in multi-stage complex tasks. Informed by these insights, we propose AgentTTS, an LLM-agent-based framework that autonomously searches for compute-optimal allocations through iterative feedback-driven interactions with the execution environment. Experimental results demonstrate that AgentTTS significantly outperforms traditional and other LLM-based baselines in search efficiency, and shows improved robustness to varying training set sizes and enhanced interpretability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00890</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 19:21:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embedding-Aware Quantum-Classical SVMs for Scalable Quantum Machine   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00024</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00024.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sebastián Andrés Cajas Ordóñez, Luis Fernando Torres Torres, Mario Bifulco, Carlos Andrés Durán, Cristian Bosch, Ricardo Simón Carbajo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Quantum Support Vector Machines face scalability challenges due to high-dimensional quantum states and hardware limitations. We propose an embedding-aware quantum-classical pipeline combining class-balanced k-means distillation with pretrained Vision Transformer embeddings. Our key finding: ViT embeddings uniquely enable quantum advantage, achieving up to 8.02% accuracy improvements over classical SVMs on Fashion-MNIST and 4.42% on MNIST, while CNN features show performance degradation. Using 16-qubit tensor network simulation via cuTensorNet, we provide the first systematic evidence that quantum kernel advantage depends critically on embedding choice, revealing fundamental synergy between transformer attention and quantum feature spaces. This provides a practical pathway for scalable quantum machine learning that leverages modern neural architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00024</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 21:23:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Language Models for Root Cause Analysis in 5G Wireless   Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21974</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.21974.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohamed Sana, Nicola Piovesan, Antonio De Domenico, Yibin Kang, Haozhe Zhang, Merouane Debbah, Fadhel Ayed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Root Cause Analysis (RCA) in mobile networks remains a challenging task due to the need for interpretability, domain expertise, and causal reasoning. In this work, we propose a lightweight framework that leverages Large Language Models (LLMs) for RCA. To do so, we introduce TeleLogs, a curated dataset of annotated troubleshooting problems designed to benchmark RCA capabilities. Our evaluation reveals that existing open-source reasoning LLMs struggle with these problems, underscoring the need for domain-specific adaptation. To address this issue, we propose a two-stage training methodology that combines supervised fine-tuning with reinforcement learning to improve the accuracy and reasoning quality of LLMs. The proposed approach fine-tunes a series of RCA models to integrate domain knowledge and generate structured, multi-step diagnostic explanations, improving both interpretability and effectiveness. Extensive experiments across multiple LLM sizes show significant performance gains over state-of-the-art reasoning and non-reasoning models, including strong generalization to randomized test variants. These results demonstrate the promise of domain-adapted, reasoning-enhanced LLMs for practical and explainable RCA in network operation and management.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21974</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 16:21:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyber-Zero: Training Cybersecurity Agents without Runtime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00910</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00910.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Terry Yue Zhuo, Dingmin Wang, Hantian Ding, Varun Kumar, Zijian Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have achieved remarkable success in software engineering tasks when trained with executable runtime environments, particularly in resolving GitHub issues. However, such runtime environments are often unavailable in other domains, especially cybersecurity, where challenge configurations and execution contexts are ephemeral or restricted. We present Cyber-Zero, the first runtime-free framework for synthesizing high-quality agent trajectories to train cybersecurity LLMs. Cyber-Zero leverages publicly available CTF writeups and employs persona-driven LLM simulation to reverse-engineer runtime behaviors and generate realistic, long-horizon interaction sequences without actual environments. Using trajectories synthesized by Cyber-Zero, we train LLM-based agents that achieve up to 13.1% absolute performance gains over baseline models on three prominent CTF benchmarks: InterCode-CTF, NYU CTF Bench, and Cybench. Our best model, Cyber-Zero-32B, establishes new state-of-the-art performance among open-weight models, matching the capabilities of proprietary systems like DeepSeek-V3-0324 and Claude-3.5-Sonnet while offering superior cost-effectiveness, and demonstrating that runtime-free trajectory synthesis can effectively democratize the development of state-of-the-art cybersecurity agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00910</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 18:10:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Hallucination in Conversations for Low Resource Languages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22720</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.22720.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amit Das, Md. Najib Hasan, Souvika Sarkar, Zheng Zhang, Fatemeh Jamshidi, Tathagata Bhattacharya, Nilanjana Raychawdhury, Dongji Feng, Vinija Jain, Aman Chadha&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable proficiency in generating text that closely resemble human writing. However, they often generate factually incorrect statements, a problem typically referred to as 'hallucination'. Addressing hallucination is crucial for enhancing the reliability and effectiveness of LLMs. While much research has focused on hallucinations in English, our study extends this investigation to conversational data in three languages: Hindi, Farsi, and Mandarin. We offer a comprehensive analysis of a dataset to examine both factual and linguistic errors in these languages for GPT-3.5, GPT-4o, Llama-3.1, Gemma-2.0, DeepSeek-R1 and Qwen-3. We found that LLMs produce very few hallucinated responses in Mandarin but generate a significantly higher number of hallucinations in Hindi and Farsi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22720</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 14:39:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PixNerd: Pixel Neural Field Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23268</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23268.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuai Wang, Ziteng Gao, Chenhui Zhu, Weilin Huang, Limin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The current success of diffusion transformers heavily depends on the compressed latent space shaped by the pre-trained variational autoencoder(VAE). However, this two-stage training paradigm inevitably introduces accumulated errors and decoding artifacts. To address the aforementioned problems, researchers return to pixel space at the cost of complicated cascade pipelines and increased token complexity. In contrast to their efforts, we propose to model the patch-wise decoding with neural field and present a single-scale, single-stage, efficient, end-to-end solution, coined as pixel neural field diffusion~(PixelNerd). Thanks to the efficient neural field representation in PixNerd, we directly achieved 2.15 FID on ImageNet 256times256 and 2.84 FID on ImageNet 512times512 without any complex cascade pipeline or VAE. We also extend our PixNerd framework to text-to-image applications. Our PixNerd-XXL/16 achieved a competitive 0.73 overall score on the GenEval benchmark and 80.9 overall score on the DPG benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23268</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 06:07:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-Debate: Competitive Multi-Agent Debate for Software Issue Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23348</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23348.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Han Li, Yuling Shi, Shaoxin Lin, Xiaodong Gu, Heng Lian, Xin Wang, Yantao Jia, Tao Huang, Qianxiang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Issue resolution has made remarkable progress thanks to the advanced reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). Recently, agent-based frameworks such as SWE-agent have further advanced this progress by enabling autonomous, tool-using agents to tackle complex software engineering tasks. While existing agent-based issue resolution approaches are primarily based on agents' independent explorations, they often get stuck in local solutions and fail to identify issue patterns that span across different parts of the codebase. To address this limitation, we propose SWE-Debate, a competitive multi-agent debate framework that encourages diverse reasoning paths and achieves more consolidated issue localization. SWE-Debate first creates multiple fault propagation traces as localization proposals by traversing a code dependency graph. Then, it organizes a three-round debate among specialized agents, each embodying distinct reasoning perspectives along the fault propagation trace. This structured competition enables agents to collaboratively converge on a consolidated fix plan. Finally, this consolidated fix plan is integrated into an MCTS-based code modification agent for patch generation. Experiments on the SWE-bench benchmark show that SWE-Debate achieves new state-of-the-art results in open-source agent frameworks and outperforms baselines by a large margin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23348</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 08:54:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-Exp: Experience-Driven Software Issue Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23361</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23361.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Silin Chen, Shaoxin Lin, Xiaodong Gu, Yuling Shi, Heng Lian, Longfei Yun, Dong Chen, Weiguo Sun, Lin Cao, Qianxiang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language model (LLM) agents have shown remarkable progress in software issue resolution, leveraging advanced techniques such as multi-agent collaboration and Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS). However, current agents act as memoryless explorers - treating each problem separately without retaining or reusing knowledge from previous repair experiences. This leads to redundant exploration of failed trajectories and missed chances to adapt successful issue resolution methods to similar problems. To address this problem, we introduce SWE-Exp, an experience - enhanced approach that distills concise and actionable experience from prior agent trajectories, enabling continuous learning across issues. Our method introduces a multi-faceted experience bank that captures both successful and failed repair attempts. Specifically, it extracts reusable issue resolution knowledge at different levels - from high-level problem comprehension to specific code changes. Experiments show that SWE-Exp achieves state-of-the-art resolution rate (41.6% Pass@1) on SWE-bench-Verified under open-source agent frameworks. Our approach establishes a new paradigm in which automated software engineering agents systematically accumulate and leverage repair expertise, fundamentally shifting from trial-and-error exploration to strategic, experience-driven issue resolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23361</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 09:13:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D-R1: Enhancing Reasoning in 3D VLMs for Unified Scene Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23478</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23478.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ting Huang, Zeyu Zhang, Hao Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large vision-language models (VLMs) have made significant strides in 2D visual understanding tasks, sparking interest in extending these capabilities to 3D scene understanding. However, current 3D VLMs often struggle with robust reasoning and generalization due to limitations in high-quality spatial data and the static nature of viewpoint assumptions. To address these challenges, we propose 3D-R1, a foundation model that enhances the reasoning capabilities of 3D VLMs. Specifically, we first construct a high-quality synthetic dataset with CoT, named Scene-30K, leveraging existing 3D-VL datasets and a data engine based on Gemini 2.5 Pro. It serves as cold-start initialization data for 3D-R1. Moreover, we leverage RLHF policy such as GRPO in the reinforcement learning training process to enhance reasoning capabilities and introduce three reward functions: a perception reward, a semantic similarity reward and a format reward to maintain detection accuracy and answer semantic precision. Furthermore, we introduce a dynamic view selection strategy that adaptively chooses the most informative perspectives for 3D scene understanding. Extensive experiments demonstrate that 3D-R1 delivers an average improvement of 10% across various 3D scene benchmarks, highlighting its effectiveness in enhancing reasoning and generalization in 3D scene understanding. Code: https://github.com/AIGeeksGroup/3D-R1. Website: https://aigeeksgroup.github.io/3D-R1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23478</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 11:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian Variation Field Diffusion for High-fidelity Video-to-4D   Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23785</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23785.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bowen Zhang, Sicheng Xu, Chuxin Wang, Jiaolong Yang, Feng Zhao, Dong Chen, Baining Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we present a novel framework for video-to-4D generation that creates high-quality dynamic 3D content from single video inputs. Direct 4D diffusion modeling is extremely challenging due to costly data construction and the high-dimensional nature of jointly representing 3D shape, appearance, and motion. We address these challenges by introducing a Direct 4DMesh-to-GS Variation Field VAE that directly encodes canonical Gaussian Splats (GS) and their temporal variations from 3D animation data without per-instance fitting, and compresses high-dimensional animations into a compact latent space. Building upon this efficient representation, we train a Gaussian Variation Field diffusion model with temporal-aware Diffusion Transformer conditioned on input videos and canonical GS. Trained on carefully-curated animatable 3D objects from the Objaverse dataset, our model demonstrates superior generation quality compared to existing methods. It also exhibits remarkable generalization to in-the-wild video inputs despite being trained exclusively on synthetic data, paving the way for generating high-quality animated 3D content. Project page: https://gvfdiffusion.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23785</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 17:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FACTORY: A Challenging Human-Verified Prompt Set for Long-Form   Factuality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00109</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00109.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingda Chen, Yang Li, Xilun Chen, Adina Williams, Gargi Ghosh, Scott Yih&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-form factuality evaluation assesses the ability of models to generate accurate, comprehensive responses to short prompts. Existing benchmarks often lack human verification, leading to potential quality issues. To address this limitation, we introduce FACTORY, a large-scale, human-verified prompt set. Developed using a model-in-the-loop approach and refined by humans, FACTORY includes challenging prompts that are fact-seeking, answerable, and unambiguous. We conduct human evaluations on 6 state-of-the-art language models using FACTORY and existing datasets. Our results show that FACTORY is a challenging benchmark: approximately 40% of the claims made in the responses of SOTA models are not factual, compared to only 10% for other datasets. Our analysis identifies the strengths of FACTORY over prior benchmarks, emphasizing its reliability and the necessity for models to reason across long-tailed facts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00109</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 19:00:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RL-PLUS: Countering Capability Boundary Collapse of LLMs in   Reinforcement Learning with Hybrid-policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00222</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00222.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yihong Dong, Xue Jiang, Yongding Tao, Huanyu Liu, Kechi Zhang, Lili Mou, Rongyu Cao, Yingwei Ma, Jue Chen, Binhua Li, Zhi Jin, Fei Huang, Yongbin Li, Ge Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Reward (RLVR) has significantly advanced the complex reasoning abilities of Large Language Models (LLMs). However, it struggles to break through the inherent capability boundaries of the base LLM, due to its essentially on-policy strategy coupled with LLM's immense action space and sparse reward. Critically, RLVR can lead to the capability boundary collapse, narrowing the LLM's problem-solving scope. To address this problem, we propose RL-PLUS, a novel hybrid-policy optimization approach for LLMs that synergizes internal exploitation with external data to achieve stronger reasoning capabilities and surpass the boundaries of base models. RL-PLUS integrates two core components, i.e., Multiple Importance Sampling to address distributional mismatch from external data, and Exploration-Based Advantage Function to guide the model towards high-value, unexplored reasoning paths. We provide both theoretical analysis and extensive experiments to demonstrate the superiority and generalizability of our approach. Compared with existing RLVR methods, RL-PLUS achieves 1) state-of-the-art performance on six math reasoning benchmarks; 2) superior performance on six out-of-distribution reasoning tasks; 3) consistent and significant gains across diverse model families, with average relative improvements up to 69.2\%. Moreover, the analysis of Pass@k curves indicates that RL-PLUS effectively resolves the capability boundary collapse problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00222</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 23:55:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Referring Segmentation: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00265</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00265.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Henghui Ding, Song Tang, Shuting He, Chang Liu, Zuxuan Wu, Yu-Gang Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal referring segmentation aims to segment target objects in visual scenes, such as images, videos, and 3D scenes, based on referring expressions in text or audio format. This task plays a crucial role in practical applications requiring accurate object perception based on user instructions. Over the past decade, it has gained significant attention in the multimodal community, driven by advances in convolutional neural networks, transformers, and large language models, all of which have substantially improved multimodal perception capabilities. This paper provides a comprehensive survey of multimodal referring segmentation. We begin by introducing this field's background, including problem definitions and commonly used datasets. Next, we summarize a unified meta architecture for referring segmentation and review representative methods across three primary visual scenes, including images, videos, and 3D scenes. We further discuss Generalized Referring Expression (GREx) methods to address the challenges of real-world complexity, along with related tasks and practical applications. Extensive performance comparisons on standard benchmarks are also provided. We continually track related works at https://github.com/henghuiding/Awesome-Multimodal-Referring-Segmentation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00265</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 02:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representation Shift: Unifying Token Compression with FlashAttention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00367</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00367.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Joonmyung Choi, Sanghyeok Lee, Byungoh Ko, Eunseo Kim, Jihyung Kil, Hyunwoo J. Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Transformers have demonstrated remarkable success across vision, language, and video. Yet, increasing task complexity has led to larger models and more tokens, raising the quadratic cost of self-attention and the overhead of GPU memory access. To reduce the computation cost of self-attention, prior work has proposed token compression techniques that drop redundant or less informative tokens. Meanwhile, fused attention kernels such as FlashAttention have been developed to alleviate memory overhead by avoiding attention map construction and its associated I/O to HBM. This, however, makes it incompatible with most training-free token compression methods, which rely on attention maps to determine token importance. Here, we propose Representation Shift, a training-free, model-agnostic metric that measures the degree of change in each token's representation. This seamlessly integrates token compression with FlashAttention, without attention maps or retraining. Our method further generalizes beyond Transformers to CNNs and state space models. Extensive experiments show that Representation Shift enables effective token compression compatible with FlashAttention, yielding significant speedups of up to 5.5% and 4.4% in video-text retrieval and video QA, respectively. Code is available at https://github.com/mlvlab/Representation-Shift.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00367</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 06:53:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive Kernel-Pro: A Framework for Deep Research Agents and Agent   Foundation Models Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00414</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00414.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianqing Fang, Zhisong Zhang, Xiaoyang Wang, Rui Wang, Can Qin, Yuxuan Wan, Jun-Yu Ma, Ce Zhang, Jiaqi Chen, Xiyun Li, Hongming Zhang, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 81&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; General AI Agents are increasingly recognized as foundational frameworks for the next generation of artificial intelligence, enabling complex reasoning, web interaction, coding, and autonomous research capabilities. However, current agent systems are either closed-source or heavily reliant on a variety of paid APIs and proprietary tools, limiting accessibility and reproducibility for the research community. In this work, we present Cognitive Kernel-Pro, a fully open-source and (to the maximum extent) free multi-module agent framework designed to democratize the development and evaluation of advanced AI agents. Within Cognitive Kernel-Pro, we systematically investigate the curation of high-quality training data for Agent Foundation Models, focusing on the construction of queries, trajectories, and verifiable answers across four key domains: web, file, code, and general reasoning. Furthermore, we explore novel strategies for agent test-time reflection and voting to enhance agent robustness and performance. We evaluate Cognitive Kernel-Pro on GAIA, achieving state-of-the-art results among open-source and free agents. Notably, our 8B-parameter open-source model surpasses previous leading systems such as WebDancer and WebSailor, establishing a new performance standard for accessible, high-capability AI agents. Code is available at https://github.com/Tencent/CognitiveKernel-Pro&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00414</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 08:11:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sel3DCraft: Interactive Visual Prompts for User-Friendly Text-to-3D   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00428</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00428.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nan Xiang, Tianyi Liang, Haiwen Huang, Shiqi Jiang, Hao Huang, Yifei Huang, Liangyu Chen, Changbo Wang, Chenhui Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-3D (T23D) generation has transformed digital content creation, yet remains bottlenecked by blind trial-and-error prompting processes that yield unpredictable results. While visual prompt engineering has advanced in text-to-image domains, its application to 3D generation presents unique challenges requiring multi-view consistency evaluation and spatial understanding. We present Sel3DCraft, a visual prompt engineering system for T23D that transforms unstructured exploration into a guided visual process. Our approach introduces three key innovations: a dual-branch structure combining retrieval and generation for diverse candidate exploration; a multi-view hybrid scoring approach that leverages MLLMs with innovative high-level metrics to assess 3D models with human-expert consistency; and a prompt-driven visual analytics suite that enables intuitive defect identification and refinement. Extensive testing and user studies demonstrate that Sel3DCraft surpasses other T23D systems in supporting creativity for designers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00428</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 08:36:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning an Efficient Multi-Turn Dialogue Evaluator from Multiple Judges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00454</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00454.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqi Tang, Kehua Feng, Yunfeng Wang, Zhiwen Chen, Chengfei Lv, Gang Yu, Qiang Zhang, Keyan Ding&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating the conversational abilities of large language models (LLMs) remains a challenging task. Current mainstream approaches primarily rely on the ``LLM-as-a-judge" paradigm, where an LLM is prompted to serve as an evaluator to assess dialogue quality. However, such methods often suffer from various biases, which undermine the reliability and consistency of the evaluation results. To mitigate these biases, recent methods employ multiple LLMs as judges and aggregate their judgments to select the optimal assessment. Although effective, this multi-judge approach incurs significant computational overhead during inference. In this paper, we propose an efficient multi-turn dialogue evaluator that captures the collective wisdom of multiple LLM judges by aggregating their preference knowledge into a single model. Our approach preserves the advantages of diverse multi-judge feedback while drastically reducing the evaluation cost, enabling fast and flexible dialogue quality assessment. Extensive experiments on seven single rating and pairwise comparison dialogue evaluation benchmarks demonstrate that our method outperforms existing baselines across diverse scenarios, showcasing its efficiency and robustness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00454</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 09:26:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LAMIC: Layout-Aware Multi-Image Composition via Scalability of   Multimodal Diffusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00477</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00477.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuzhuo Chen, Zehua Ma, Jianhua Wang, Kai Kang, Shunyu Yao, Weiming Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In controllable image synthesis, generating coherent and consistent images from multiple references with spatial layout awareness remains an open challenge. We present LAMIC, a Layout-Aware Multi-Image Composition framework that, for the first time, extends single-reference diffusion models to multi-reference scenarios in a training-free manner. Built upon the MMDiT model, LAMIC introduces two plug-and-play attention mechanisms: 1) Group Isolation Attention (GIA) to enhance entity disentanglement; and 2) Region-Modulated Attention (RMA) to enable layout-aware generation. To comprehensively evaluate model capabilities, we further introduce three metrics: 1) Inclusion Ratio (IN-R) and Fill Ratio (FI-R) for assessing layout control; and 2) Background Similarity (BG-S) for measuring background consistency. Extensive experiments show that LAMIC achieves state-of-the-art performance across most major metrics: it consistently outperforms existing multi-reference baselines in ID-S, BG-S, IN-R and AVG scores across all settings, and achieves the best DPG in complex composition tasks. These results demonstrate LAMIC's superior abilities in identity keeping, background preservation, layout control, and prompt-following, all achieved without any training or fine-tuning, showcasing strong zero-shot generalization ability. By inheriting the strengths of advanced single-reference models and enabling seamless extension to multi-image scenarios, LAMIC establishes a new training-free paradigm for controllable multi-image composition. As foundation models continue to evolve, LAMIC's performance is expected to scale accordingly. Our implementation is available at: https://github.com/Suchenl/LAMIC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00477</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 09:51:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DPoser-X: Diffusion Model as Robust 3D Whole-body Human Pose Prior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00599</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00599.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junzhe Lu, Jing Lin, Hongkun Dou, Ailing Zeng, Yue Deng, Xian Liu, Zhongang Cai, Lei Yang, Yulun Zhang, Haoqian Wang, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present DPoser-X, a diffusion-based prior model for 3D whole-body human poses. Building a versatile and robust full-body human pose prior remains challenging due to the inherent complexity of articulated human poses and the scarcity of high-quality whole-body pose datasets. To address these limitations, we introduce a Diffusion model as body Pose prior (DPoser) and extend it to DPoser-X for expressive whole-body human pose modeling. Our approach unifies various pose-centric tasks as inverse problems, solving them through variational diffusion sampling. To enhance performance on downstream applications, we introduce a novel truncated timestep scheduling method specifically designed for pose data characteristics. We also propose a masked training mechanism that effectively combines whole-body and part-specific datasets, enabling our model to capture interdependencies between body parts while avoiding overfitting to specific actions. Extensive experiments demonstrate DPoser-X's robustness and versatility across multiple benchmarks for body, hand, face, and full-body pose modeling. Our model consistently outperforms state-of-the-art alternatives, establishing a new benchmark for whole-body human pose prior modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00599</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 12:56:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Agent Game Generation and Evaluation via Audio-Visual Recordings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00632</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00632.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexia Jolicoeur-Martineau&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While AI excels at generating text, audio, images, and videos, creating interactive audio-visual content such as video games remains challenging. Current LLMs can generate JavaScript games and animations, but lack automated evaluation metrics and struggle with complex content that normally requires teams of humans working for many months (multi-shot, multi-agents) using assets made by artists. To tackle these issues, we built a new metric and a multi-agent system.   We propose AVR-Eval, a relative metric for multimedia content quality using Audio-Visual Recordings (AVRs). An omni-modal model (processing text, video, and audio) compares the AVRs of two contents, with a text model reviewing evaluations to determine superiority. We show that AVR-Eval properly identifies good from broken or mismatched content.   We built AVR-Agent, a multi-agent system generating JavaScript code from a bank of multimedia assets (audio, images, 3D models). The coding agent selects relevant assets, generates multiple initial codes, uses AVR-Eval to identify the best version, and iteratively improves it through omni-modal agent feedback from the AVR.   We run experiments on games and animations with AVR-Eval (win rate of content A against B). We find that content generated by AVR-Agent has a significantly higher win rate against content made through one-shot generation. However, models struggle to leverage custom assets and AVR feedback effectively, showing no higher win rate. This reveals a critical gap: while humans benefit from high-quality assets and audio-visual feedback, current coding models do not seem to utilize these resources as effectively, highlighting fundamental differences between human and machine content creation approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00632</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 13:45:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpA2V: Harnessing Spatial Auditory Cues for Audio-driven Spatially-aware   Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00782</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00782.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kien T. Pham, Yingqing He, Yazhou Xing, Qifeng Chen, Long Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Audio-driven video generation aims to synthesize realistic videos that align with input audio recordings, akin to the human ability to visualize scenes from auditory input. However, existing approaches predominantly focus on exploring semantic information, such as the classes of sounding sources present in the audio, limiting their ability to generate videos with accurate content and spatial composition. In contrast, we humans can not only naturally identify the semantic categories of sounding sources but also determine their deeply encoded spatial attributes, including locations and movement directions. This useful information can be elucidated by considering specific spatial indicators derived from the inherent physical properties of sound, such as loudness or frequency. As prior methods largely ignore this factor, we present SpA2V, the first framework explicitly exploits these spatial auditory cues from audios to generate videos with high semantic and spatial correspondence. SpA2V decomposes the generation process into two stages: 1) Audio-guided Video Planning: We meticulously adapt a state-of-the-art MLLM for a novel task of harnessing spatial and semantic cues from input audio to construct Video Scene Layouts (VSLs). This serves as an intermediate representation to bridge the gap between the audio and video modalities. 2) Layout-grounded Video Generation: We develop an efficient and effective approach to seamlessly integrate VSLs as conditional guidance into pre-trained diffusion models, enabling VSL-grounded video generation in a training-free manner. Extensive experiments demonstrate that SpA2V excels in generating realistic videos with semantic and spatial alignment to the input audios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00782</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 17:05:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Fixed: Variable-Length Denoising for Diffusion Large Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00819</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00819.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinsong Li, Xiaoyi Dong, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Jiaqi Wang, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Large Language Models (DLLMs) are emerging as a powerful alternative to the dominant Autoregressive Large Language Models, offering efficient parallel generation and capable global context modeling. However, the practical application of DLLMs is hindered by a critical architectural constraint: the need for a statically predefined generation length. This static length allocation leads to a problematic trade-off: insufficient lengths cripple performance on complex tasks, while excessive lengths incur significant computational overhead and sometimes result in performance degradation. While the inference framework is rigid, we observe that the model itself possesses internal signals that correlate with the optimal response length for a given task. To bridge this gap, we leverage these latent signals and introduce DAEDAL, a novel training-free denoising strategy that enables Dynamic Adaptive Length Expansion for Diffusion Large Language Models. DAEDAL operates in two phases: 1) Before the denoising process, DAEDAL starts from a short initial length and iteratively expands it to a coarse task-appropriate length, guided by a sequence completion metric. 2) During the denoising process, DAEDAL dynamically intervenes by pinpointing and expanding insufficient generation regions through mask token insertion, ensuring the final output is fully developed. Extensive experiments on DLLMs demonstrate that DAEDAL achieves performance comparable, and in some cases superior, to meticulously tuned fixed-length baselines, while simultaneously enhancing computational efficiency by achieving a higher effective token ratio. By resolving the static length constraint, DAEDAL unlocks new potential for DLLMs, bridging a critical gap with their Autoregressive counterparts and paving the way for more efficient and capable generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00819</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 17:56:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IGL-Nav: Incremental 3D Gaussian Localization for Image-goal Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00823</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00823.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenxuan Guo, Xiuwei Xu, Hang Yin, Ziwei Wang, Jianjiang Feng, Jie Zhou, Jiwen Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual navigation with an image as goal is a fundamental and challenging problem. Conventional methods either rely on end-to-end RL learning or modular-based policy with topological graph or BEV map as memory, which cannot fully model the geometric relationship between the explored 3D environment and the goal image. In order to efficiently and accurately localize the goal image in 3D space, we build our navigation system upon the renderable 3D gaussian (3DGS) representation. However, due to the computational intensity of 3DGS optimization and the large search space of 6-DoF camera pose, directly leveraging 3DGS for image localization during agent exploration process is prohibitively inefficient. To this end, we propose IGL-Nav, an Incremental 3D Gaussian Localization framework for efficient and 3D-aware image-goal navigation. Specifically, we incrementally update the scene representation as new images arrive with feed-forward monocular prediction. Then we coarsely localize the goal by leveraging the geometric information for discrete space matching, which can be equivalent to efficient 3D convolution. When the agent is close to the goal, we finally solve the fine target pose with optimization via differentiable rendering. The proposed IGL-Nav outperforms existing state-of-the-art methods by a large margin across diverse experimental configurations. It can also handle the more challenging free-view image-goal setting and be deployed on real-world robotic platform using a cellphone to capture goal image at arbitrary pose. Project page: https://gwxuan.github.io/IGL-Nav/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00823</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Llama-3.1-FoundationAI-SecurityLLM-8B-Instruct Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01059</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01059.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sajana Weerawardhena, Paul Kassianik, Blaine Nelson, Baturay Saglam, Anu Vellore, Aman Priyanshu, Supriti Vijay, Massimo Aufiero, Arthur Goldblatt, Fraser Burch, Ed Li, Jianliang He, Dhruv Kedia, Kojin Oshiba, Zhouran Yang, Yaron Singer, Amin Karbasi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable success across many domains, yet their integration into cybersecurity applications remains limited due to a lack of general-purpose cybersecurity data, representational complexity, and safety and regulatory concerns. To address this gap, we previously introduced Foundation-Sec-8B, a cybersecurity-focused LLM suitable for fine-tuning on downstream tasks. That model, however, was not designed for chat-style interactions or instruction-following. In this report, we release Foundation-Sec-8B-Instruct: a model specifically trained for general-purpose cybersecurity dialogue. Built on Foundation-Sec-8B, it combines domain-specific knowledge with instruction-following, conversational capabilities, and alignment with human preferences to produce high-quality, relevant responses. Comprehensive evaluations show that Foundation-Sec-8B-Instruct outperforms Llama 3.1-8B-Instruct on a range of cybersecurity tasks while matching its instruction-following performance. It is also competitive with GPT-4o-mini on cyber threat intelligence and instruction-following tasks. We envision Foundation-Sec-8B-Instruct becoming an indispensable assistant in the daily workflows of cybersecurity professionals. We release the model publicly at https://huggingface.co/fdtn-ai/Foundation-Sec-8B-Instruct.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01059</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 20:25:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Promise of RL for Autoregressive Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01119</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01119.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Saba Ahmadi, Rabiul Awal, Ankur Sikarwar, Amirhossein Kazemnejad, Ge Ya Luo, Juan A. Rodriguez, Sai Rajeswar, Siva Reddy, Christopher Pal, Benno Krojer, Aishwarya Agrawal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We explore three strategies to enhance performance on a wide range of image editing tasks: supervised fine-tuning (SFT), reinforcement learning (RL), and Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning. In order to study all these components in one consistent framework, we adopt an autoregressive multimodal model that processes textual and visual tokens in a unified manner. We find RL combined with a large multi-modal LLM verifier to be the most effective of these strategies. As a result, we release EARL: Editing with Autoregression and RL, a strong RL-based image editing model that performs competitively on a diverse range of edits compared to strong baselines, despite using much less training data. Thus, EARL pushes the frontier of autoregressive multimodal models on image editing. We release our code, training data, and trained models at https://github.com/mair-lab/EARL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01119</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 23:47:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniEgoMotion: A Unified Model for Egocentric Motion Reconstruction,   Forecasting, and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01126</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01126.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaitanya Patel, Hiroki Nakamura, Yuta Kyuragi, Kazuki Kozuka, Juan Carlos Niebles, Ehsan Adeli&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Egocentric human motion generation and forecasting with scene-context is crucial for enhancing AR/VR experiences, improving human-robot interaction, advancing assistive technologies, and enabling adaptive healthcare solutions by accurately predicting and simulating movement from a first-person perspective. However, existing methods primarily focus on third-person motion synthesis with structured 3D scene contexts, limiting their effectiveness in real-world egocentric settings where limited field of view, frequent occlusions, and dynamic cameras hinder scene perception. To bridge this gap, we introduce Egocentric Motion Generation and Egocentric Motion Forecasting, two novel tasks that utilize first-person images for scene-aware motion synthesis without relying on explicit 3D scene. We propose UniEgoMotion, a unified conditional motion diffusion model with a novel head-centric motion representation tailored for egocentric devices. UniEgoMotion's simple yet effective design supports egocentric motion reconstruction, forecasting, and generation from first-person visual inputs in a unified framework. Unlike previous works that overlook scene semantics, our model effectively extracts image-based scene context to infer plausible 3D motion. To facilitate training, we introduce EE4D-Motion, a large-scale dataset derived from EgoExo4D, augmented with pseudo-ground-truth 3D motion annotations. UniEgoMotion achieves state-of-the-art performance in egocentric motion reconstruction and is the first to generate motion from a single egocentric image. Extensive evaluations demonstrate the effectiveness of our unified framework, setting a new benchmark for egocentric motion modeling and unlocking new possibilities for egocentric applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01126</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 00:41:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Personalized Safety Alignment for Text-to-Image Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01151</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01151.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Lei, Jinbin Bai, Qingyu Shi, Aosong Feng, Kaidong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-image diffusion models have revolutionized visual content generation, but current safety mechanisms apply uniform standards that often fail to account for individual user preferences. These models overlook the diverse safety boundaries shaped by factors like age, mental health, and personal beliefs. To address this, we propose Personalized Safety Alignment (PSA), a framework that allows user-specific control over safety behaviors in generative models. PSA integrates personalized user profiles into the diffusion process, adjusting the model's behavior to match individual safety preferences while preserving image quality. We introduce a new dataset, Sage, which captures user-specific safety preferences and incorporates these profiles through a cross-attention mechanism. Experiments show that PSA outperforms existing methods in harmful content suppression and aligns generated content better with user constraints, achieving higher Win Rate and Pass Rate scores. Our code, data, and models are publicly available at https://torpedo2648.github.io/PSAlign/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01151</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 02:23:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Chain-of-Thought Reasoning of LLMs a Mirage? A Data Distribution Lens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01191</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01191.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chengshuai Zhao, Zhen Tan, Pingchuan Ma, Dawei Li, Bohan Jiang, Yancheng Wang, Yingzhen Yang, Huan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 184&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-Thought (CoT) prompting has been shown to improve Large Language Model (LLM) performance on various tasks. With this approach, LLMs appear to produce human-like reasoning steps before providing answers (a.k.a., CoT reasoning), which often leads to the perception that they engage in deliberate inferential processes. However, some initial findings suggest that CoT reasoning may be more superficial than it appears, motivating us to explore further. In this paper, we study CoT reasoning via a data distribution lens and investigate if CoT reasoning reflects a structured inductive bias learned from in-distribution data, allowing the model to conditionally generate reasoning paths that approximate those seen during training. Thus, its effectiveness is fundamentally bounded by the degree of distribution discrepancy between the training data and the test queries. With this lens, we dissect CoT reasoning via three dimensions: task, length, and format. To investigate each dimension, we design DataAlchemy, an isolated and controlled environment to train LLMs from scratch and systematically probe them under various distribution conditions. Our results reveal that CoT reasoning is a brittle mirage that vanishes when it is pushed beyond training distributions. This work offers a deeper understanding of why and when CoT reasoning fails, emphasizing the ongoing challenge of achieving genuine and generalizable reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01191</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 04:37:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Coarse-to-Fine Approach to Multi-Modality 3D Occupancy Grounding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01197</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01197.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhan Shi, Song Wang, Junbo Chen, Jianke Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual grounding aims to identify objects or regions in a scene based on natural language descriptions, essential for spatially aware perception in autonomous driving. However, existing visual grounding tasks typically depend on bounding boxes that often fail to capture fine-grained details. Not all voxels within a bounding box are occupied, resulting in inaccurate object representations. To address this, we introduce a benchmark for 3D occupancy grounding in challenging outdoor scenes. Built on the nuScenes dataset, it integrates natural language with voxel-level occupancy annotations, offering more precise object perception compared to the traditional grounding task. Moreover, we propose GroundingOcc, an end-to-end model designed for 3D occupancy grounding through multi-modal learning. It combines visual, textual, and point cloud features to predict object location and occupancy information from coarse to fine. Specifically, GroundingOcc comprises a multimodal encoder for feature extraction, an occupancy head for voxel-wise predictions, and a grounding head to refine localization. Additionally, a 2D grounding module and a depth estimation module enhance geometric understanding, thereby boosting model performance. Extensive experiments on the benchmark demonstrate that our method outperforms existing baselines on 3D occupancy grounding. The dataset is available at https://github.com/RONINGOD/GroundingOcc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01197</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 05:05:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploitation Is All You Need... for Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01287</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01287.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Micah Rentschler, Jesse Roberts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Ensuring sufficient exploration is a central challenge when training meta-reinforcement learning (meta-RL) agents to solve novel environments. Conventional solutions to the exploration-exploitation dilemma inject explicit incentives such as randomization, uncertainty bonuses, or intrinsic rewards to encourage exploration. In this work, we hypothesize that an agent trained solely to maximize a greedy (exploitation-only) objective can nonetheless exhibit emergent exploratory behavior, provided three conditions are met: (1) Recurring Environmental Structure, where the environment features repeatable regularities that allow past experience to inform future choices; (2) Agent Memory, enabling the agent to retain and utilize historical interaction data; and (3) Long-Horizon Credit Assignment, where learning propagates returns over a time frame sufficient for the delayed benefits of exploration to inform current decisions. Through experiments in stochastic multi-armed bandits and temporally extended gridworlds, we observe that, when both structure and memory are present, a policy trained on a strictly greedy objective exhibits information-seeking exploratory behavior. We further demonstrate, through controlled ablations, that emergent exploration vanishes if either environmental structure or agent memory is absent (Conditions 1 &amp; 2). Surprisingly, removing long-horizon credit assignment (Condition 3) does not always prevent emergent exploration-a result we attribute to the pseudo-Thompson Sampling effect. These findings suggest that, under the right prerequisites, exploration and exploitation need not be treated as orthogonal objectives but can emerge from a unified reward-maximization process.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01287</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 09:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence and Misinformation in Art: Can Vision Language   Models Judge the Hand or the Machine Behind the Canvas?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01408</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01408.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tarian Fu, Javier Conde, Gonzalo Martínez, Pedro Reviriego, Elena Merino-Gómez, Fernando Moral&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The attribution of artworks in general and of paintings in particular has always been an issue in art. The advent of powerful artificial intelligence models that can generate and analyze images creates new challenges for painting attribution. On the one hand, AI models can create images that mimic the style of a painter, which can be incorrectly attributed, for example, by other AI models. On the other hand, AI models may not be able to correctly identify the artist for real paintings, inducing users to incorrectly attribute paintings. In this paper, both problems are experimentally studied using state-of-the-art AI models for image generation and analysis on a large dataset with close to 40,000 paintings from 128 artists. The results show that vision language models have limited capabilities to: 1) perform canvas attribution and 2) to identify AI generated images. As users increasingly rely on queries to AI models to get information, these results show the need to improve the capabilities of VLMs to reliably perform artist attribution and detection of AI generated images to prevent the spread of incorrect information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01408</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 15:27:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboMemory: A Brain-inspired Multi-memory Agentic Framework for Lifelong   Learning in Physical Embodied Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01415</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01415.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingcong Lei, Honghao Cai, Zezhou Cui, Liangchen Tan, Junkun Hong, Gehan Hu, Shuangyu Zhu, Yimou Wu, Shaohan Jiang, Ge Wang, Zhen Li, Shuguang Cui, Yiming Zhao, Yatong Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present RoboMemory, a brain-inspired multi-memory framework for lifelong learning in physical embodied systems, addressing critical challenges in real-world environments: continuous learning, multi-module memory latency, task correlation capture, and infinite-loop mitigation in closed-loop planning. Grounded in cognitive neuroscience, it integrates four core modules: the Information Preprocessor (thalamus-like), the Lifelong Embodied Memory System (hippocampus-like), the Closed-Loop Planning Module (prefrontal lobe-like), and the Low-Level Executer (cerebellum-like) to enable long-term planning and cumulative learning. The Lifelong Embodied Memory System, central to the framework, alleviates inference speed issues in complex memory frameworks via parallelized updates/retrieval across Spatial, Temporal, Episodic, and Semantic submodules. It incorporates a dynamic Knowledge Graph (KG) and consistent architectural design to enhance memory consistency and scalability. Evaluations on EmbodiedBench show RoboMemory outperforms the open-source baseline (Qwen2.5-VL-72B-Ins) by 25% in average success rate and surpasses the closed-source State-of-the-Art (SOTA) (Claude3.5-Sonnet) by 5%, establishing new SOTA. Ablation studies validate key components (critic, spatial memory, long-term memory), while real-world deployment confirms its lifelong learning capability with significantly improved success rates across repeated tasks. RoboMemory alleviates high latency challenges with scalability, serving as a foundational reference for integrating multi-modal memory systems in physical robots.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01415</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 15:39:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Glimpse to Compress: Dynamic Visual Token Pruning for Large   Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01548</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01548.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Quan-Sheng Zeng, Yunheng Li, Qilong Wang, Peng-Tao Jiang, Zuxuan Wu, Ming-Ming Cheng, Qibin Hou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual token compression is critical for Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs) to efficiently process high-resolution inputs. Existing methods that typically adopt fixed compression ratios cannot adapt to scenes of varying complexity, often causing imprecise pruning that discards informative visual tokens and results in degraded model performance. To address this issue, we introduce a dynamic pruning framework, GlimpsePrune, inspired by human cognition. It takes a data-driven ''glimpse'' and prunes irrelevant visual tokens in a single forward pass before answer generation. This approach prunes 92.6% of visual tokens while on average fully retaining the baseline performance on free-form VQA tasks. The reduced computational cost also enables more effective fine-tuning: an enhanced GlimpsePrune+ achieves 110% of the baseline performance while maintaining a similarly high pruning rate. Our work paves a new way for building more powerful and efficient LVLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01548</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 02:15:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenMed NER: Open-Source, Domain-Adapted State-of-the-Art Transformers   for Biomedical NER Across 12 Public Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01630</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01630.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Maziyar Panahi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Named-entity recognition (NER) is fundamental to extracting structured information from the &gt;80% of healthcare data that resides in unstructured clinical notes and biomedical literature. Despite recent advances with large language models, achieving state-of-the-art performance across diverse entity types while maintaining computational efficiency remains a significant challenge. We introduce OpenMed NER, a suite of open-source, domain-adapted transformer models that combine lightweight domain-adaptive pre-training (DAPT) with parameter-efficient Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA). Our approach performs cost-effective DAPT on a 350k-passage corpus compiled from ethically sourced, publicly available research repositories and de-identified clinical notes (PubMed, arXiv, and MIMIC-III) using DeBERTa-v3, PubMedBERT, and BioELECTRA backbones. This is followed by task-specific fine-tuning with LoRA, which updates less than 1.5% of model parameters. We evaluate our models on 12 established biomedical NER benchmarks spanning chemicals, diseases, genes, and species. OpenMed NER achieves new state-of-the-art micro-F1 scores on 10 of these 12 datasets, with substantial gains across diverse entity types. Our models advance the state-of-the-art on foundational disease and chemical benchmarks (e.g., BC5CDR-Disease, +2.70 pp), while delivering even larger improvements of over 5.3 and 9.7 percentage points on more specialized gene and clinical cell line corpora. This work demonstrates that strategically adapted open-source models can surpass closed-source solutions. This performance is achieved with remarkable efficiency: training completes in under 12 hours on a single GPU with a low carbon footprint (&lt; 1.2 kg CO2e), producing permissively licensed, open-source checkpoints designed to help practitioners facilitate compliance with emerging data protection and AI regulations, such as the EU AI Act.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01630</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 07:33:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StrandDesigner: Towards Practical Strand Generation with Sketch Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01650</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01650.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Na Zhang, Moran Li, Chengming Xu, Han Feng, Xiaobin Hu, Jiangning Zhang, Weijian Cao, Chengjie Wang, Yanwei Fu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Realistic hair strand generation is crucial for applications like computer graphics and virtual reality. While diffusion models can generate hairstyles from text or images, these inputs lack precision and user-friendliness. Instead, we propose the first sketch-based strand generation model, which offers finer control while remaining user-friendly. Our framework tackles key challenges, such as modeling complex strand interactions and diverse sketch patterns, through two main innovations: a learnable strand upsampling strategy that encodes 3D strands into multi-scale latent spaces, and a multi-scale adaptive conditioning mechanism using a transformer with diffusion heads to ensure consistency across granularity levels. Experiments on several benchmark datasets show our method outperforms existing approaches in realism and precision. Qualitative results further confirm its effectiveness. Code will be released at [GitHub](https://github.com/fighting-Zhang/StrandDesigner).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01650</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 08:17:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voxlect: A Speech Foundation Model Benchmark for Modeling Dialects and   Regional Languages Around the Globe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01691</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01691.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tiantian Feng, Kevin Huang, Anfeng Xu, Xuan Shi, Thanathai Lertpetchpun, Jihwan Lee, Yoonjeong Lee, Dani Byrd, Shrikanth Narayanan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Voxlect, a novel benchmark for modeling dialects and regional languages worldwide using speech foundation models. Specifically, we report comprehensive benchmark evaluations on dialects and regional language varieties in English, Arabic, Mandarin and Cantonese, Tibetan, Indic languages, Thai, Spanish, French, German, Brazilian Portuguese, and Italian. Our study used over 2 million training utterances from 30 publicly available speech corpora that are provided with dialectal information. We evaluate the performance of several widely used speech foundation models in classifying speech dialects. We assess the robustness of the dialectal models under noisy conditions and present an error analysis that highlights modeling results aligned with geographic continuity. In addition to benchmarking dialect classification, we demonstrate several downstream applications enabled by Voxlect. Specifically, we show that Voxlect can be applied to augment existing speech recognition datasets with dialect information, enabling a more detailed analysis of ASR performance across dialectal variations. Voxlect is also used as a tool to evaluate the performance of speech generation systems. Voxlect is publicly available with the license of the RAIL family at: https://github.com/tiantiaf0627/voxlect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01691</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 09:51:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiveMCPBench: Can Agents Navigate an Ocean of MCP Tools?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01780</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01780.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guozhao Mo, Wenliang Zhong, Jiawei Chen, Xuanang Chen, Yaojie Lu, Hongyu Lin, Ben He, Xianpei Han, Le Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the rapid development of Model Context Protocol (MCP), the number of MCP servers has surpassed 10,000. However, existing MCP benchmarks are limited to single-server settings with only a few tools, hindering effective evaluation of agent capabilities in large-scale, real-world scenarios. To address this limitation, we present LiveMCPBench, the first comprehensive benchmark comprising 95 real-world tasks grounded in the MCP ecosystem, designed to evaluate LLM agents at scale across diverse servers. To support a scalable and reproducible evaluation pipeline in large-scale MCP environments, we curate LiveMCPTool, a diverse and readily deployable collection of 70 MCP servers and 527 tools. Furthermore, we introduce LiveMCPEval, an LLM-as-a-Judge framework that enables automated and adaptive evaluation in dynamic, time-varying task environments, achieving 81% agreement with human reviewers. Finally, we propose the MCP Copilot Agent, a multi-step agent that routes tools for dynamic planning and executes tools for API interaction across the entire LiveMCPTool suite. Our evaluation covers 10 leading models, with the best-performing model (Claude-Sonnet-4) reaching a 78.95% success rate. However, we observe large performance variance across models, and several widely-used models perform poorly in LiveMCPBench's complex, tool-rich environments. Overall, LiveMCPBench offers the first unified framework for benchmarking LLM agents in realistic, tool-rich, and dynamic MCP environments, laying a solid foundation for scalable and reproducible research on agent capabilities. Our code and data will be publicly available at https://icip-cas.github.io/LiveMCPBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01780</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 14:36:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Web-CogReasoner: Towards Knowledge-Induced Cognitive Reasoning for Web   Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01858</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01858.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhan Guo, Cong Guo, Aiwen Sun, Hongliang He, Xinyu Yang, Yue Lu, Yingji Zhang, Xuntao Guo, Dong Zhang, Jianzhuang Liu, Jiang Duan, Yijia Xiao, Liangjian Wen, Hai-Ming Xu, Yong Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large-scale models have significantly advanced the development of web agents, enabling perception and interaction with digital environments akin to human cognition. In this paper, we argue that web agents must first acquire sufficient knowledge to effectively engage in cognitive reasoning. Therefore, we decompose a web agent's capabilities into two essential stages: knowledge content learning and cognitive processes. To formalize this, we propose Web-CogKnowledge Framework, categorizing knowledge as Factual, Conceptual, and Procedural. In this framework, knowledge content learning corresponds to the agent's processes of Memorizing and Understanding, which rely on the first two knowledge types, representing the "what" of learning. Conversely, cognitive processes correspond to Exploring, grounded in Procedural knowledge, defining the "how" of reasoning and action. To facilitate knowledge acquisition, we construct the Web-CogDataset, a structured resource curated from 14 real-world websites, designed to systematically instill core knowledge necessary for web agent. This dataset serves as the agent's conceptual grounding-the "nouns" upon which comprehension is built-as well as the basis for learning how to reason and act. Building on this foundation, we operationalize these processes through a novel knowledge-driven Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning framework, developing and training our proposed agent, the Web-CogReasoner. Extensive experimentation reveals its significant superiority over existing models, especially in generalizing to unseen tasks where structured knowledge is decisive. To enable rigorous evaluation, we introduce the Web-CogBench, a comprehensive evaluation suite designed to assess and compare agent performance across the delineated knowledge domains and cognitive capabilities. Our code and data is open sourced at https://github.com/Gnonymous/Web-CogReasoner&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01858</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 17:17:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IAUNet: Instance-Aware U-Net</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01928</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01928.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yaroslav Prytula, Illia Tsiporenko, Ali Zeynalli, Dmytro Fishman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instance segmentation is critical in biomedical imaging to accurately distinguish individual objects like cells, which often overlap and vary in size. Recent query-based methods, where object queries guide segmentation, have shown strong performance. While U-Net has been a go-to architecture in medical image segmentation, its potential in query-based approaches remains largely unexplored. In this work, we present IAUNet, a novel query-based U-Net architecture. The core design features a full U-Net architecture, enhanced by a novel lightweight convolutional Pixel decoder, making the model more efficient and reducing the number of parameters. Additionally, we propose a Transformer decoder that refines object-specific features across multiple scales. Finally, we introduce the 2025 Revvity Full Cell Segmentation Dataset, a unique resource with detailed annotations of overlapping cell cytoplasm in brightfield images, setting a new benchmark for biomedical instance segmentation. Experiments on multiple public datasets and our own show that IAUNet outperforms most state-of-the-art fully convolutional, transformer-based, and query-based models and cell segmentation-specific models, setting a strong baseline for cell instance segmentation tasks. Code is available at https://github.com/SlavkoPrytula/IAUNet&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01928</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 21:36:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SitEmb-v1.5: Improved Context-Aware Dense Retrieval for Semantic   Association and Long Story Comprehension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01959</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01959.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junjie Wu, Jiangnan Li, Yuqing Li, Lemao Liu, Liyan Xu, Jiwei Li, Dit-Yan Yeung, Jie Zhou, Mo Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) over long documents typically involves splitting the text into smaller chunks, which serve as the basic units for retrieval. However, due to dependencies across the original document, contextual information is often essential for accurately interpreting each chunk. To address this, prior work has explored encoding longer context windows to produce embeddings for longer chunks. Despite these efforts, gains in retrieval and downstream tasks remain limited. This is because (1) longer chunks strain the capacity of embedding models due to the increased amount of information they must encode, and (2) many real-world applications still require returning localized evidence due to constraints on model or human bandwidth.   We propose an alternative approach to this challenge by representing short chunks in a way that is conditioned on a broader context window to enhance retrieval performance -- i.e., situating a chunk's meaning within its context. We further show that existing embedding models are not well-equipped to encode such situated context effectively, and thus introduce a new training paradigm and develop the situated embedding models (SitEmb). To evaluate our method, we curate a book-plot retrieval dataset specifically designed to assess situated retrieval capabilities. On this benchmark, our SitEmb-v1 model based on BGE-M3 substantially outperforms state-of-the-art embedding models, including several with up to 7-8B parameters, with only 1B parameters. Our 8B SitEmb-v1.5 model further improves performance by over 10% and shows strong results across different languages and several downstream applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01959</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 23:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marco-Voice Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02038</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02038.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fengping Tian, Chenyang Lyu, Xuanfan Ni, Haoqin Sun, Qingjuan Li, Zhiqiang Qian, Haijun Li, Longyue Wang, Zhao Xu, Weihua Luo, Kaifu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents a multifunctional speech synthesis system that integrates voice cloning and emotion control speech synthesis within a unified framework. The goal of this work is to address longstanding challenges in achieving highly expressive, controllable, and natural speech generation that faithfully preserves speaker identity across diverse linguistic and emotional contexts. Our approach introduces an effective speaker-emotion disentanglement mechanism with in-batch contrastive learning, enabling independent manipulation of speaker identity and eemotional style, as well as rotational emotional embedding integration method for smooth emotion control. To support comprehensive training and evaluation, we construct CSEMOTIONS, a high-quality emotional speech dataset containing 10 hours of Mandarin speech from six professional speakers across seven emotional categories. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our system, Marco-Voice, achieves substantial improvements in both objective and subjective metrics. Comprehensive evaluations and analysis were conducted, results show that MarcoVoice delivers competitive performance in terms of speech clarity and emotional richness, representing a substantial advance in the field of expressive neural speech synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02038</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 04:08:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AlignGuard-LoRA: Alignment-Preserving Fine-Tuning via Fisher-Guided   Decomposition and Riemannian-Geodesic Collision Regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02079</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02079.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amitava Das, Abhilekh Borah, Vinija Jain, Aman Chadha&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Low-rank adaptation (LoRA) has become a standard tool for efficiently fine-tuning large language models (LLMs). Yet, even minor LoRA updates can induce alignment drift, weakening safety and behavioral constraints through entangled parameter changes. To address this, we propose AlignGuard-LoRA (AGL), a principled framework for preserving alignment during finetuning. AGL introduces several key components: a primary task loss for supervision, Fisher Information Matrix-based regularization to restrict updates in alignment-sensitive subspaces, and task-specific regularization to stabilize the integration of new knowledge. We further introduce collision-aware regularization, blending Riemannian overlap -- which penalizes coordinate-wise interference -- and geodesic separation -- which encourages disjoint update geometry. We curate DriftCaps, a targeted diagnostic benchmark of safe and unsafe prompts designed to quantify alignment drift and safety degradation. Empirical evaluations show that AGL mitigates alignment drift by up to 50% on safety-critical benchmarks without degrading downstream task performance. Comprehensive ablation confirms that each component contributes distinctly to preserving latent safety behaviors. Finally, we derive and validate a scaling law for catastrophic forgetting, revealing that AGL flattens post-finetuning loss escalation while preserving adaptation dynamics. AGL is a structurally grounded refinement of LoRA, ensuring alignment preservation with minimal trade-offs. To encourage further exploration and development, we open-source our implementation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02079</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 05:45:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CRINN: Contrastive Reinforcement Learning for Approximate Nearest   Neighbor Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02091</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02091.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoya Li, Xiaofei Sun, Albert Wang, Chris Shum, Jiwei Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Approximate nearest-neighbor search (ANNS) algorithms have become increasingly critical for recent AI applications, particularly in retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) and agent-based LLM applications. In this paper, we present CRINN, a new paradigm for ANNS algorithms. CRINN treats ANNS optimization as a reinforcement learning problem where execution speed serves as the reward signal. This approach enables the automatic generation of progressively faster ANNS implementations while maintaining accuracy constraints. Our experimental evaluation demonstrates CRINN's effectiveness across six widely-used NNS benchmark datasets. When compared against state-of-the-art open-source ANNS algorithms, CRINN achieves best performance on three of them (GIST-960-Euclidean, MNIST-784-Euclidean, and GloVe-25-angular), and tied for first place on two of them (SIFT-128-Euclidean and GloVe-25-angular). The implications of CRINN's success reach well beyond ANNS optimization: It validates that LLMs augmented with reinforcement learning can function as an effective tool for automating sophisticated algorithmic optimizations that demand specialized knowledge and labor-intensive manual refinement.Code can be found at https://github.com/deepreinforce-ai/CRINN&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02091</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 05:57:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Overthink It: A Survey of Efficient R1-style Large Reasoning   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02120</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02120.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Linan Yue, Yichao Du, Yizhi Wang, Weibo Gao, Fangzhou Yao, Li Wang, Ye Liu, Ziyu Xu, Qi Liu, Shimin Di, Min-Ling Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have gradually become a research hotspot due to their outstanding performance in handling complex tasks. Among them, DeepSeek R1 has garnered significant attention for its exceptional performance and open-source nature, driving advancements in the research of R1-style LRMs. Unlike traditional Large Language Models (LLMs), these models enhance logical deduction and decision-making capabilities during reasoning by incorporating mechanisms such as long chain-of-thought and self-reflection through reinforcement learning. However, with the widespread application of these models, the problem of overthinking has gradually emerged. Specifically, when generating answers, these models often construct excessively long reasoning chains with redundant or repetitive steps, which leads to reduced reasoning efficiency and may affect the accuracy of the final answer. To this end, various efficient reasoning methods have been proposed, aiming to reduce the length of reasoning paths without compromising model performance and reasoning capability. By reviewing the current research advancements in the field of efficient reasoning methods systematically, we categorize existing works into two main directions based on the lens of single-model optimization versus model collaboration: (1) Efficient Reasoning with Single Model, which focuses on improving the reasoning efficiency of individual models; and (2) Efficient Reasoning with Model Collaboration, which explores optimizing reasoning paths through collaboration among multiple models. Besides, we maintain a public GitHub repository that tracks the latest progress in efficient reasoning methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02120</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 06:54:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trainable Dynamic Mask Sparse Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02124</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02124.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingze Shi, Yifan Wu, Bingheng Wu, Yiran Peng, Liangdong Wang, Guang Liu, Yuyu Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In large language models, the demand for modeling long contexts is constantly increasing, but the quadratic complexity of the standard self-attention mechanism often becomes a bottleneck. Although existing sparse attention mechanisms have improved efficiency, they may still encounter issues such as static patterns or information loss. We introduce a trainable dynamic mask sparse attention mechanism, Dynamic Mask Attention, which effectively utilizes content-aware and position-aware sparsity. DMA achieves this through two key innovations: First, it dynamically generates content-aware sparse masks from value representations, enabling the model to identify and focus on critical information adaptively. Second, it implements position-aware sparse attention computation that effectively skips unnecessary calculation regions. This dual-sparsity design allows the model to significantly reduce the computational complexity of important information while retaining complete information, achieving an excellent balance between information fidelity and computational efficiency. We have verified the performance of DMA through comprehensive experiments. Comparative studies show that DMA outperforms multi-head attention, sliding window attention, multi-head latent attention, and native sparse attention in terms of perplexity under Chinchilla Scaling Law settings. Moreover, in challenging multi-query associative recall tasks, DMA also demonstrates superior performance and efficiency compared to these methods. Crucially, in the evaluation of a 1.7B parameter model, DMA significantly outperforms multi-head attention in both standard benchmark performance and the challenging needle-in-a-haystack task. These experimental results highlight its capability to balance model efficiency and long-context modeling ability effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02124</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 07:05:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fitness aligned structural modeling enables scalable virtual screening   with AuroBind</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02137</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02137.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongyue Zhang, Jiahua Rao, Jie Zhong, Weiqiang Bai, Dongxue Wang, Shaobo Ning, Lifeng Qiao, Sheng Xu, Runze Ma, Will Hua, Jack Xiaoyu Chen, Odin Zhang, Wei Lu, Hanyi Feng, He Yang, Xinchao Shi, Rui Li, Wanli Ouyang, Xinzhu Ma, Jiahao Wang, Jixian Zhang, Jia Duan, Siqi Sun, Jian Zhang, Shuangjia Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Most human proteins remain undrugged, over 96% of human proteins remain unexploited by approved therapeutics. While structure-based virtual screening promises to expand the druggable proteome, existing methods lack atomic-level precision and fail to predict binding fitness, limiting translational impact. We present AuroBind, a scalable virtual screening framework that fine-tunes a custom atomic-level structural model on million-scale chemogenomic data. AuroBind integrates direct preference optimization, self-distillation from high-confidence complexes, and a teacher-student acceleration strategy to jointly predict ligand-bound structures and binding fitness. The proposed models outperform state-of-the-art models on structural and functional benchmarks while enabling 100,000-fold faster screening across ultra-large compound libraries. In a prospective screen across ten disease-relevant targets, AuroBind achieved experimental hit rates of 7-69%, with top compounds reaching sub-nanomolar to picomolar potency. For the orphan GPCRs GPR151 and GPR160, AuroBind identified both agonists and antagonists with success rates of 16-30%, and functional assays confirmed GPR160 modulation in liver and prostate cancer models. AuroBind offers a generalizable framework for structure-function learning and high-throughput molecular screening, bridging the gap between structure prediction and therapeutic discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02137</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 07:34:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Trade-off: Self-Supervised Reinforcement Learning for   Reasoning Models' Instruction Following</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02150</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02150.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qingyu Ren, Qianyu He, Bowei Zhang, Jie Zeng, Jiaqing Liang, Yanghua Xiao, Weikang Zhou, Zeye Sun, Fei Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning models excel in complex problem solving but exhibit a concerning trade off between reasoning capabilities and instruction following abilities. Existing approaches for improving instruction following rely on stronger external models, creating methodological bottlenecks and practical limitations including increased costs and accessibility constraints. We propose a self-supervised RL framework that leverages reasoning models' own internal signals to improve instruction following capabilities without external supervision. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our framework significantly improves instruction following capabilities while maintaining reasoning performance, offering a scalable and cost-effective approach to enhance instruction following in reasoning models. The data and code are publicly available at https://github.com/Rainier-rq/verl-if.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02150</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 07:48:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seed Diffusion: A Large-Scale Diffusion Language Model with High-Speed   Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02193</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02193.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxuan Song, Zheng Zhang, Cheng Luo, Pengyang Gao, Fan Xia, Hao Luo, Zheng Li, Yuehang Yang, Hongli Yu, Xingwei Qu, Yuwei Fu, Jing Su, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Mingxuan Wang, Lin Yan, Xiaoying Jia, Jingjing Liu, Wei-Ying Ma, Ya-Qin Zhang, Yonghui Wu, Hao Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 104&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Seed Diffusion Preview, a large-scale language model based on discrete-state diffusion, offering remarkably fast inference speed. Thanks to non-sequential, parallel generation, discrete diffusion models provide a notable speedup to mitigate the inherent latency of token-by-token decoding, as demonstrated recently (e.g., Mercury Coder, Gemini Diffusion). Seed Diffusion Preview achieves an inference speed of 2,146 token/s over H20 GPUs while maintaining competitive performance across a sweep of standard code evaluation benchmarks, significantly faster than contemporary Mercury and Gemini Diffusion, establishing new state of the art on the speed-quality Pareto frontier for code models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02193</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 08:43:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LeanK: Learnable K Cache Channel Pruning for Efficient Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02215</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02215.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yike Zhang, Zhiyuan He, Huiqiang Jiang, Chengruidong Zhang, Yuqing Yang, Jianyong Wang, Lili Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) enable long-context tasks but face efficiency challenges due to the growing key-value (KV) cache. We propose LeanK, a learning-based method that prunes unimportant key (K) cache channels by leveraging static channel sparsity. With a novel two-stage training process, LeanK learns channel-wise static mask that could satisfy specific sparsity ratio and hardware alignment requirement. LeanK reduces GPU memory and accelerates decoding without sacrificing accuracy. Experiments demonstrate up to 70% K cache and 16%-18% V cache memory reduction. Custom decoding kernel enables 1.3x speedup for attention computation. We also provide insights into model channels and attention heads during long-context inference by analyzing the learned importance distribution. Our code is available at https://aka.ms/LeanK.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02215</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 09:08:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I2CR: Intra- and Inter-modal Collaborative Reflections for Multimodal   Entity Linking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02243</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02243.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyan Liu, Junwen Li, Kaiwen Li, Tong Ruan, Chao Wang, Xinyan He, Zongyu Wang, Xuezhi Cao, Jingping Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal entity linking plays a crucial role in a wide range of applications. Recent advances in large language model-based methods have become the dominant paradigm for this task, effectively leveraging both textual and visual modalities to enhance performance. Despite their success, these methods still face two challenges, including unnecessary incorporation of image data in certain scenarios and the reliance only on a one-time extraction of visual features, which can undermine their effectiveness and accuracy. To address these challenges, we propose a novel LLM-based framework for the multimodal entity linking task, called Intra- and Inter-modal Collaborative Reflections. This framework prioritizes leveraging text information to address the task. When text alone is insufficient to link the correct entity through intra- and inter-modality evaluations, it employs a multi-round iterative strategy that integrates key visual clues from various aspects of the image to support reasoning and enhance matching accuracy. Extensive experiments on three widely used public datasets demonstrate that our framework consistently outperforms current state-of-the-art methods in the task, achieving improvements of 3.2%, 5.1%, and 1.6%, respectively. Our code is available at https://github.com/ziyan-xiaoyu/I2CR/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02243</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 09:43:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SHAMI-MT: A Syrian Arabic Dialect to Modern Standard Arabic   Bidirectional Machine Translation System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02268</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02268.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Serry Sibaee, Omer Nacar, Yasser Al-Habashi, Adel Ammar, Wadii Boulila&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rich linguistic landscape of the Arab world is characterized by a significant gap between Modern Standard Arabic (MSA), the language of formal communication, and the diverse regional dialects used in everyday life. This diglossia presents a formidable challenge for natural language processing, particularly machine translation. This paper introduces SHAMI-MT, a bidirectional machine translation system specifically engineered to bridge the communication gap between MSA and the Syrian dialect. We present two specialized models, one for MSA-to-Shami and another for Shami-to-MSA translation, both built upon the state-of-the-art AraT5v2-base-1024 architecture. The models were fine-tuned on the comprehensive Nabra dataset and rigorously evaluated on unseen data from the MADAR corpus. Our MSA-to-Shami model achieved an outstanding average quality score of 4.01 out of 5.0 when judged by OPENAI model GPT-4.1, demonstrating its ability to produce translations that are not only accurate but also dialectally authentic. This work provides a crucial, high-fidelity tool for a previously underserved language pair, advancing the field of dialectal Arabic translation and offering significant applications in content localization, cultural heritage, and intercultural communication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02268</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:21:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynaword: From One-shot to Continuously Developed Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02271</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02271.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kenneth Enevoldsen, Kristian Nørgaard Jensen, Jan Kostkan, Balázs Szabó, Márton Kardos, Kirten Vad, Andrea Blasi Núñez, Gianluca Barmina, Jacob Nielsen, Rasmus Larsen, Peter Vahlstrup, Per Møldrup Dalum, Desmond Elliott, Lukas Galke, Peter Schneider-Kamp, Kristoffer Nielbo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large-scale datasets are foundational for research and development in natural language processing. However, current approaches face three key challenges: (1) reliance on ambiguously licensed sources restricting use, sharing, and derivative works; (2) static dataset releases that prevent community contributions and diminish longevity; and (3) quality assurance processes restricted to publishing teams rather than leveraging community expertise.   To address these limitations, we introduce two contributions: the Dynaword approach and Danish Dynaword. The Dynaword approach is a framework for creating large-scale, open datasets that can be continuously updated through community collaboration. Danish Dynaword is a concrete implementation that validates this approach and demonstrates its potential. Danish Dynaword contains over four times as many tokens as comparable releases, is exclusively openly licensed, and has received multiple contributions across industry and research. The repository includes light-weight tests to ensure data formatting, quality, and documentation, establishing a sustainable framework for ongoing community contributions and dataset evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02271</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:30:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CellForge: Agentic Design of Virtual Cell Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02276</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02276.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangru Tang, Zhuoyun Yu, Jiapeng Chen, Yan Cui, Daniel Shao, Weixu Wang, Fang Wu, Yuchen Zhuang, Wenqi Shi, Zhi Huang, Arman Cohan, Xihong Lin, Fabian Theis, Smita Krishnaswamy, Mark Gerstein&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Virtual cell modeling represents an emerging frontier at the intersection of artificial intelligence and biology, aiming to predict quantities such as responses to diverse perturbations quantitatively. However, autonomously building computational models for virtual cells is challenging due to the complexity of biological systems, the heterogeneity of data modalities, and the need for domain-specific expertise across multiple disciplines. Here, we introduce CellForge, an agentic system that leverages a multi-agent framework that transforms presented biological datasets and research objectives directly into optimized computational models for virtual cells. More specifically, given only raw single-cell multi-omics data and task descriptions as input, CellForge outputs both an optimized model architecture and executable code for training virtual cell models and inference. The framework integrates three core modules: Task Analysis for presented dataset characterization and relevant literature retrieval, Method Design, where specialized agents collaboratively develop optimized modeling strategies, and Experiment Execution for automated generation of code. The agents in the Design module are separated into experts with differing perspectives and a central moderator, and have to collaboratively exchange solutions until they achieve a reasonable consensus. We demonstrate CellForge's capabilities in single-cell perturbation prediction, using six diverse datasets that encompass gene knockouts, drug treatments, and cytokine stimulations across multiple modalities. CellForge consistently outperforms task-specific state-of-the-art methods. Overall, CellForge demonstrates how iterative interaction between LLM agents with differing perspectives provides better solutions than directly addressing a modeling challenge. Our code is publicly available at https://github.com/gersteinlab/CellForge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02276</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:43:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VeOmni: Scaling Any Modality Model Training with Model-Centric   Distributed Recipe Zoo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qianli Ma, Yaowei Zheng, Zhelun Shi, Zhongkai Zhao, Bin Jia, Ziyue Huang, Zhiqi Lin, Youjie Li, Jiacheng Yang, Yanghua Peng, Zhi Zhang, Xin Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have driven impressive progress in omni-modal understanding and generation. However, training omni-modal LLMs remains a significant challenge due to the heterogeneous model architectures required to process diverse modalities, necessitating sophisticated system design for efficient large-scale training. Existing frameworks typically entangle model definition with parallel logic, incurring limited scalability and substantial engineering overhead for end-to-end omni-modal training. % We present \veomni, a modular and efficient training framework to accelerate the development of omni-modal LLMs. \veomni introduces model-centric distributed recipes that decouples communication from computation, enabling efficient 3D parallelism on omni-modal LLMs. \veomni also features a flexible configuration interface supporting seamless integration of new modalities with minimal code change. % Using \veomni, a omni-modal mixture-of-experts (MoE) model with 30B parameters can be trained with over 2,800 tokens/sec/GPU throughput and scale to 160K context lengths via 3D parallelism on 128 GPUs, showcasing its superior efficiency and scalability for training large omni-modal LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02317</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 11:33:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qwen-Image Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02324</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02324.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenfei Wu, Jiahao Li, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin, Kaiyuan Gao, Kun Yan, Sheng-ming Yin, Shuai Bai, Xiao Xu, Yilei Chen, Yuxiang Chen, Zecheng Tang, Zekai Zhang, Zhengyi Wang, An Yang, Bowen Yu, Chen Cheng, Dayiheng Liu, Deqing Li, Hang Zhang, Hao Meng, Hu Wei, Jingyuan Ni, Kai Chen, Kuan Cao, Liang Peng, Lin Qu, Minggang Wu, Peng Wang, Shuting Yu, Tingkun Wen, Wensen Feng, Xiaoxiao Xu, Yi Wang, Yichang Zhang, Yongqiang Zhu, Yujia Wu, Yuxuan Cai, Zenan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 164&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Qwen-Image, an image generation foundation model in the Qwen series that achieves significant advances in complex text rendering and precise image editing. To address the challenges of complex text rendering, we design a comprehensive data pipeline that includes large-scale data collection, filtering, annotation, synthesis, and balancing. Moreover, we adopt a progressive training strategy that starts with non-text-to-text rendering, evolves from simple to complex textual inputs, and gradually scales up to paragraph-level descriptions. This curriculum learning approach substantially enhances the model's native text rendering capabilities. As a result, Qwen-Image not only performs exceptionally well in alphabetic languages such as English, but also achieves remarkable progress on more challenging logographic languages like Chinese. To enhance image editing consistency, we introduce an improved multi-task training paradigm that incorporates not only traditional text-to-image (T2I) and text-image-to-image (TI2I) tasks but also image-to-image (I2I) reconstruction, effectively aligning the latent representations between Qwen2.5-VL and MMDiT. Furthermore, we separately feed the original image into Qwen2.5-VL and the VAE encoder to obtain semantic and reconstructive representations, respectively. This dual-encoding mechanism enables the editing module to strike a balance between preserving semantic consistency and maintaining visual fidelity. Qwen-Image achieves state-of-the-art performance, demonstrating its strong capabilities in both image generation and editing across multiple benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02324</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 11:49:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse-dLLM: Accelerating Diffusion LLMs with Dynamic Cache Eviction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02558</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02558.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuerong Song, Xiaoran Liu, Ruixiao Li, Zhigeng Liu, Zengfeng Huang, Qipeng Guo, Ziwei He, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Large Language Models (dLLMs) enable breakthroughs in reasoning and parallel decoding but suffer from prohibitive quadratic computational complexity and memory overhead during inference. Current caching techniques accelerate decoding by storing full-layer states, yet impose substantial memory usage that limit long-context applications. Our analysis of attention patterns in dLLMs reveals persistent cross-layer sparsity, with pivotal tokens remaining salient across decoding steps and low-relevance tokens staying unimportant, motivating selective cache eviction. We propose Sparse-dLLM, the first training-free framework integrating dynamic cache eviction with sparse attention via delayed bidirectional sparse caching. By leveraging the stability of token saliency over steps, it retains critical tokens and dynamically evicts unimportant prefix/suffix entries using an attention-guided strategy. Extensive experiments on LLaDA and Dream series demonstrate Sparse-dLLM achieves up to 10times higher throughput than vanilla dLLMs, with comparable performance and similar peak memory costs, outperforming previous methods in efficiency and effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02558</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 16:14:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReMoMask: Retrieval-Augmented Masked Motion Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02605</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02605.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengdao Li, Siheng Wang, Zeyu Zhang, Hao Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-Motion (T2M) generation aims to synthesize realistic and semantically aligned human motion sequences from natural language descriptions. However, current approaches face dual challenges: Generative models (e.g., diffusion models) suffer from limited diversity, error accumulation, and physical implausibility, while Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) methods exhibit diffusion inertia, partial-mode collapse, and asynchronous artifacts. To address these limitations, we propose ReMoMask, a unified framework integrating three key innovations: 1) A Bidirectional Momentum Text-Motion Model decouples negative sample scale from batch size via momentum queues, substantially improving cross-modal retrieval precision; 2) A Semantic Spatio-temporal Attention mechanism enforces biomechanical constraints during part-level fusion to eliminate asynchronous artifacts; 3) RAG-Classier-Free Guidance incorporates minor unconditional generation to enhance generalization. Built upon MoMask's RVQ-VAE, ReMoMask efficiently generates temporally coherent motions in minimal steps. Extensive experiments on standard benchmarks demonstrate the state-of-the-art performance of ReMoMask, achieving a 3.88% and 10.97% improvement in FID scores on HumanML3D and KIT-ML, respectively, compared to the previous SOTA method RAG-T2M. Code: https://github.com/AIGeeksGroup/ReMoMask. Website: https://aigeeksgroup.github.io/ReMoMask.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02605</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 16:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HyCodePolicy: Hybrid Language Controllers for Multimodal Monitoring and   Decision in Embodied Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02629</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02629.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yibin Liu, Zhixuan Liang, Zanxin Chen, Tianxing Chen, Mengkang Hu, Wanxi Dong, Congsheng Xu, Zhaoming Han, Yusen Qin, Yao Mu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have enabled richer perceptual grounding for code policy generation in embodied agents. However, most existing systems lack effective mechanisms to adaptively monitor policy execution and repair codes during task completion. In this work, we introduce HyCodePolicy, a hybrid language-based control framework that systematically integrates code synthesis, geometric grounding, perceptual monitoring, and iterative repair into a closed-loop programming cycle for embodied agents. Technically, given a natural language instruction, our system first decomposes it into subgoals and generates an initial executable program grounded in object-centric geometric primitives. The program is then executed in simulation, while a vision-language model (VLM) observes selected checkpoints to detect and localize execution failures and infer failure reasons. By fusing structured execution traces capturing program-level events with VLM-based perceptual feedback, HyCodePolicy infers failure causes and repairs programs. This hybrid dual feedback mechanism enables self-correcting program synthesis with minimal human supervision. Our results demonstrate that HyCodePolicy significantly improves the robustness and sample efficiency of robot manipulation policies, offering a scalable strategy for integrating multimodal reasoning into autonomous decision-making pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02629</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 17:18:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Is Your AI Agent Buying? Evaluation, Implications and Emerging   Questions for Agentic E-Commerce</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02630</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02630.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amine Allouah, Omar Besbes, Josué D Figueroa, Yash Kanoria, Akshit Kumar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Online marketplaces will be transformed by autonomous AI agents acting on behalf of consumers. Rather than humans browsing and clicking, vision-language-model (VLM) agents can parse webpages, evaluate products, and transact. This raises a fundamental question: what do AI agents buy, and why? We develop ACES, a sandbox environment that pairs a platform-agnostic VLM agent with a fully programmable mock marketplace to study this question. We first conduct basic rationality checks in the context of simple tasks, and then, by randomizing product positions, prices, ratings, reviews, sponsored tags, and platform endorsements, we obtain causal estimates of how frontier VLMs actually shop. Models show strong but heterogeneous position effects: all favor the top row, yet different models prefer different columns, undermining the assumption of a universal "top" rank. They penalize sponsored tags and reward endorsements. Sensitivities to price, ratings, and reviews are directionally human-like but vary sharply in magnitude across models. Motivated by scenarios where sellers use AI agents to optimize product listings, we show that a seller-side agent that makes minor tweaks to product descriptions, targeting AI buyer preferences, can deliver substantial market-share gains if AI-mediated shopping dominates. We also find that modal product choices can differ across models and, in some cases, demand may concentrate on a few select products, raising competition questions. Together, our results illuminate how AI agents may behave in e-commerce settings and surface concrete seller strategy, platform design, and regulatory questions in an AI-mediated ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02630</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 17:19:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamVVT: Mastering Realistic Video Virtual Try-On in the Wild via a   Stage-Wise Diffusion Transformer Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02807</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02807.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tongchun Zuo, Zaiyu Huang, Shuliang Ning, Ente Lin, Chao Liang, Zerong Zheng, Jianwen Jiang, Yuan Zhang, Mingyuan Gao, Xin Dong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video virtual try-on (VVT) technology has garnered considerable academic interest owing to its promising applications in e-commerce advertising and entertainment. However, most existing end-to-end methods rely heavily on scarce paired garment-centric datasets and fail to effectively leverage priors of advanced visual models and test-time inputs, making it challenging to accurately preserve fine-grained garment details and maintain temporal consistency in unconstrained scenarios. To address these challenges, we propose DreamVVT, a carefully designed two-stage framework built upon Diffusion Transformers (DiTs), which is inherently capable of leveraging diverse unpaired human-centric data to enhance adaptability in real-world scenarios. To further leverage prior knowledge from pretrained models and test-time inputs, in the first stage, we sample representative frames from the input video and utilize a multi-frame try-on model integrated with a vision-language model (VLM), to synthesize high-fidelity and semantically consistent keyframe try-on images. These images serve as complementary appearance guidance for subsequent video generation. In the second stage, skeleton maps together with fine-grained motion and appearance descriptions are extracted from the input content, and these along with the keyframe try-on images are then fed into a pretrained video generation model enhanced with LoRA adapters. This ensures long-term temporal coherence for unseen regions and enables highly plausible dynamic motions. Extensive quantitative and qualitative experiments demonstrate that DreamVVT surpasses existing methods in preserving detailed garment content and temporal stability in real-world scenarios. Our project page https://virtu-lab.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02807</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 18:27:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tool-integrated Reinforcement Learning for Repo Deep Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03012</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03012.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zexiong Ma, Chao Peng, Qunhong Zeng, Pengfei Gao, Yanzhen Zou, Bing Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Issue localization, the process of identifying code locations that need modification to resolve software issues, is a critical yet challenging task in software development. The semantic gap between natural language issue descriptions and faulty code requires complex multi-hop reasoning through code dependencies. Existing LLM-based agents attempt to address this by integrating repository retrieval tools. However, this transforms issue localization into a demanding task we call Repo Deep Search, which requires the LLM to effectively utilize various repository retrieval tools throughout a multi-step reasoning and navigation process. To tackle this challenge, we present ToolTrain, a two-stage tool-integrated training framework combining rejection-sampled supervised fine-tuning and tool-integrated reinforcement learning to enhance LLMs' ability to use retrieval tools for issue localization. Experimental results show that ToolTrain-trained models achieve state-of-the-art performance, with our 32B model even surpassing Claude-3.7 on function-level localization. The results also show that improved localization performance translates to better end-to-end issue resolution performance. This further demonstrates that training for issue localization is a viable and effective strategy for improving automated software development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03012</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 02:44:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-human Interactive Talking Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03050</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03050.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeyu Zhu, Weijia Wu, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing studies on talking video generation have predominantly focused on single-person monologues or isolated facial animations, limiting their applicability to realistic multi-human interactions. To bridge this gap, we introduce MIT, a large-scale dataset specifically designed for multi-human talking video generation. To this end, we develop an automatic pipeline that collects and annotates multi-person conversational videos. The resulting dataset comprises 12 hours of high-resolution footage, each featuring two to four speakers, with fine-grained annotations of body poses and speech interactions. It captures natural conversational dynamics in multi-speaker scenario, offering a rich resource for studying interactive visual behaviors. To demonstrate the potential of MIT, we furthur propose CovOG, a baseline model for this novel task. It integrates a Multi-Human Pose Encoder (MPE) to handle varying numbers of speakers by aggregating individual pose embeddings, and an Interactive Audio Driver (IAD) to modulate head dynamics based on speaker-specific audio features. Together, these components showcase the feasibility and challenges of generating realistic multi-human talking videos, establishing MIT as a valuable benchmark for future research. The code is avalibale at: https://github.com/showlab/Multi-human-Talking-Video-Dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03050</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 03:54:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoTox: Chain-of-Thought-Based Molecular Toxicity Reasoning and   Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03159</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03159.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jueon Park, Yein Park, Minju Song, Soyon Park, Donghyeon Lee, Seungheun Baek, Jaewoo Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Drug toxicity remains a major challenge in pharmaceutical development. Recent machine learning models have improved in silico toxicity prediction, but their reliance on annotated data and lack of interpretability limit their applicability. This limits their ability to capture organ-specific toxicities driven by complex biological mechanisms. Large language models (LLMs) offer a promising alternative through step-by-step reasoning and integration of textual data, yet prior approaches lack biological context and transparent rationale. To address this issue, we propose CoTox, a novel framework that integrates LLM with chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning for multi-toxicity prediction. CoTox combines chemical structure data, biological pathways, and gene ontology (GO) terms to generate interpretable toxicity predictions through step-by-step reasoning. Using GPT-4o, we show that CoTox outperforms both traditional machine learning and deep learning model. We further examine its performance across various LLMs to identify where CoTox is most effective. Additionally, we find that representing chemical structures with IUPAC names, which are easier for LLMs to understand than SMILES, enhances the model's reasoning ability and improves predictive performance. To demonstrate its practical utility in drug development, we simulate the treatment of relevant cell types with drug and incorporated the resulting biological context into the CoTox framework. This approach allow CoTox to generate toxicity predictions aligned with physiological responses, as shown in case study. This result highlights the potential of LLM-based frameworks to improve interpretability and support early-stage drug safety assessment. The code and prompt used in this work are available at https://github.com/dmis-lab/CoTox.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03159</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 07:04:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChartCap: Mitigating Hallucination of Dense Chart Captioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03164</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03164.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyoung Lim, Jaewoo Ahn, Gunhee Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating accurate, informative, and hallucination-free captions for charts remains challenging for vision language models, primarily due to the lack of large-scale, high-quality datasets of real-world charts. However, existing real-world chart datasets suffer from the inclusion of extraneous information that cannot be inferred from the chart and failure to sufficiently capture structural elements and key insights. Therefore, we introduce ChartCap, a large-scale dataset of 565K real-world chart images paired with type-specific, dense captions that exclude extraneous information and highlight both structural elements and key insights in detail. To build ChartCap, we design a four-stage pipeline that generates captions using only the discernible data from the chart and employ a cycle consistency-based human verification, which accelerates quality control without sacrificing accuracy. Additionally, we propose a novel metric, the Visual Consistency Score, which evaluates caption quality by measuring the similarity between the chart regenerated from a caption and the original chart, independent of reference captions. Extensive experiments confirms that models fine-tuned on ChartCap consistently generate more accurate and informative captions with reduced hallucinations, surpassing both open-source and proprietary models and even human-annotated captions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03164</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 07:09:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light-IF: Endowing LLMs with Generalizable Reasoning via Preview and   Self-Checking for Complex Instruction Following</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03178</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03178.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenyang Wang, Liang Wen, Shousheng Jia, Xiangzheng Zhang, Liang Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While advancements in the reasoning abilities of LLMs have significantly enhanced their performance in solving mathematical problems, coding tasks, and general puzzles, their effectiveness in accurately adhering to instructions remains inconsistent, particularly with more complex directives. Our investigation identifies lazy reasoning during the thinking stage as the primary factor contributing to poor instruction adherence. To mitigate this issue, we propose a comprehensive framework designed to enable rigorous reasoning processes involving preview and self-checking, essential for satisfying strict instruction constraints. Specifically, we first generate instructions with complex constraints and apply a filtering process to obtain valid prompts, resulting in three distinct prompt datasets categorized as hard, easy, and pass. Then, we employ rejection sampling on the pass prompts to curate a small yet high-quality dataset, enabling a cold-start initialization of the model and facilitating its adaptation to effective reasoning patterns. Subsequently, we employ an entropy-preserving supervised fine-tuning (Entropy-SFT) strategy coupled with token-wise entropy-adaptive (TEA-RL) reinforcement learning guided by rule-based dense rewards. This approach encourages the model to transform its reasoning mechanism, ultimately fostering generalizable reasoning abilities that encompass preview and self-checking. Extensive experiments conducted on instruction-following benchmarks demonstrate remarkable performance improvements across various model scales. Notably, our Light-IF-32B model surpasses both larger open-source models such as DeepSeek-R1 and closed-source models like Doubao-1.6.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03178</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 07:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork UniPic: Unified Autoregressive Modeling for Visual Understanding   and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03320</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03320.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peiyu Wang, Yi Peng, Yimeng Gan, Liang Hu, Tianyidan Xie, Xiaokun Wang, Yichen Wei, Chuanxin Tang, Bo Zhu, Changshi Li, Hongyang Wei, Eric Li, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Skywork UniPic, a 1.5 billion-parameter autoregressive model that unifies image understanding, text-to-image generation, and image editing within a single architecture-eliminating the need for task-specific adapters or inter-module connectors-and demonstrate that compact multimodal systems can achieve state-of-the-art performance on commodity hardware. Skywork UniPic achieves a GenEval score of 0.86, surpassing most existing unified models; sets a new DPG-Bench complex-generation record of 85.5; attains 5.83 on GEditBench-EN and 3.49 on ImgEdit-Bench for image editing; and generates 1024 x 1024 images with under 15 GB of GPU memory (e.g., RTX 4090). (1) a decoupled encoding strategy that leverages a masked autoregressive encoder for synthesis and a SigLIP2 encoder for understanding, all feeding a shared autoregressive decoder; (2) a progressive, resolution-aware training schedule scaling from 256 x 256 to 1024 x 1024 while dynamically unfreezing parameters to balance capacity and stability; and (3) meticulously curated, 100 million-scale datasets augmented with task-specific reward models to refine generation and editing objectives. By demonstrating that high-fidelity multimodal integration need not incur prohibitive resource demands, Skywork UniPic establishes a practical paradigm for deployable, high-fidelity multimodal AI. Code and weights are publicly available at https://huggingface.co/Skywork/Skywork-UniPic-1.5B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03320</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 10:59:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Document Understanding and Question Answering: A Multi-Agent   Collaboration Framework with Test-Time Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03404</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03404.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinlei Yu, Zhangquan Chen, Yudong Zhang, Shilin Lu, Ruolin Shen, Jiangning Zhang, Xiaobin Hu, Yanwei Fu, Shuicheng Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing vision-language models (VLMs), whether generalists or specialists, remain constrained by their parameter scale, lack robust self-correction capabilities, and underperform in tasks involving long visual contexts and complex reasoning, resulting in suboptimal performance on document-based tasks. To address this, we propose MACT, a Multi-Agent Collaboration framework with Test-Time scaling, tailored for visual document understanding and visual question answering (VQA). It comprises four distinct small-scale agents, i.e., planning, execution, judgment, and answer agents, with clearly defined roles and effective collaboration. Notably, the judgment agent exclusively verifies correctness and redirects to prior agents for revisions, outperforming conventional correction strategies. To further expand the capability boundaries of the framework, we propose mixed reward modeling that balances agent-specific abilities and global collaboration, as well as agent-wise hybrid test-time scaling, which customizes different scaling strategies for each agent based on their functions. Evaluated on benchmarks spanning both document-based and non-document-based settings, our MACT shows superior performance with a smaller parameter scale without sacrificing the ability of general and mathematical tasks. Especially, it stands out in benchmarks involving long visual contexts and complicated reasoning. The three variants of MACT consistently hold the top three positions in average scores, leading in 13 of the 15 benchmarks. Code will be available at: https://github.com/YU-deep/MACT.git.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03404</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 12:52:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training Long-Context, Multi-Turn Software Engineering Agents with   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03501</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03501.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Golubev, Maria Trofimova, Sergei Polezhaev, Ibragim Badertdinov, Maksim Nekrashevich, Anton Shevtsov, Simon Karasik, Sergey Abramov, Andrei Andriushchenko, Filipp Fisin, Sergei Skvortsov, Boris Yangel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Research on applications of Reinforcement Learning (RL) to Large Language Models (LLMs) has mostly been focused on single-turn problems, such as mathematical reasoning or single-shot code generation. While these problems can be viewed as token-level multi-turn MDPs, this view corresponds to a degenerate case of multi-turn interaction where the environment provides no feedback. This contrasts with many real-world domains, such as software engineering (SWE), which require rich multi-turn interactions with a stateful environment that responds to each action with a non-trivial observation.   To bridge this gap, we demonstrate the successful application of RL to this general regime. Using a modified Decoupled Advantage Policy Optimization (DAPO) algorithm, we train an agent based on Qwen2.5-72B-Instruct to solve real-world software engineering tasks. Our approach increases the agent's success rate on the SWE-bench Verified benchmark from a 20% rejection fine-tuned baseline to 39%, without relying on any teacher models. On SWE-rebench, our agent matches or outperforms leading open-weight models such as DeepSeek-V3-0324 and Qwen3-235B-A22B using an identical scaffolding, offering a viable path toward building more capable autonomous agents for complex real-world problems based on open models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03501</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 14:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LaTCoder: Converting Webpage Design to Code with Layout-as-Thought</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03560</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03560.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Gui, Zhen Li, Zhongyi Zhang, Guohao Wang, Tianpeng Lv, Gaoyang Jiang, Yi Liu, Dongping Chen, Yao Wan, Hongyu Zhang, Wenbin Jiang, Xuanhua Shi, Hai Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Converting webpage designs into code (design-to-code) plays a vital role in User Interface (UI) development for front-end developers, bridging the gap between visual design and functional implementation. While recent Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have shown significant potential in design-to-code tasks, they often fail to accurately preserve the layout during code generation. To this end, we draw inspiration from the Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning in human cognition and propose LaTCoder, a novel approach that enhances layout preservation in webpage design during code generation with Layout-as-Thought (LaT). Specifically, we first introduce a simple yet efficient algorithm to divide the webpage design into image blocks. Next, we prompt MLLMs using a CoTbased approach to generate code for each block. Finally, we apply two assembly strategies-absolute positioning and an MLLM-based method-followed by dynamic selection to determine the optimal output. We evaluate the effectiveness of LaTCoder using multiple backbone MLLMs (i.e., DeepSeek-VL2, Gemini, and GPT-4o) on both a public benchmark and a newly introduced, more challenging benchmark (CC-HARD) that features complex layouts. The experimental results on automatic metrics demonstrate significant improvements. Specifically, TreeBLEU scores increased by 66.67% and MAE decreased by 38% when using DeepSeek-VL2, compared to direct prompting. Moreover, the human preference evaluation results indicate that annotators favor the webpages generated by LaTCoder in over 60% of cases, providing strong evidence of the effectiveness of our method.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03560</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 15:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Goedel-Prover-V2: Scaling Formal Theorem Proving with Scaffolded Data   Synthesis and Self-Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03613</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03613.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yong Lin, Shange Tang, Bohan Lyu, Ziran Yang, Jui-Hui Chung, Haoyu Zhao, Lai Jiang, Yihan Geng, Jiawei Ge, Jingruo Sun, Jiayun Wu, Jiri Gesi, Ximing Lu, David Acuna, Kaiyu Yang, Hongzhou Lin, Yejin Choi, Danqi Chen, Sanjeev Arora, Chi Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Goedel-Prover-V2, a series of open-source language models that set a new state-of-the-art in automated theorem proving. Built on the standard expert iteration and reinforcement learning pipeline, our approach incorporates three key innovations: (1) Scaffolded data synthesis: We generate synthetic tasks of increasing difficulty to train the model to master increasingly complex theorems; (2) Verifier-guided self-correction: We enable the model to iteratively revise its proofs by leveraging feedback from the Lean compiler; (3) Model averaging: We merge model checkpoints to mitigate the decrease in model output diversity in later stages of training. Our small model, Goedel-Prover-V2-8B, reaches 84.6% pass@32 on MiniF2F and outperforms DeepSeek-Prover-V2-671B under the same metric, despite being 80X smaller. Our flagship model, Goedel-Prover-V2-32B, achieves 88.1% on MiniF2F at pass@32 in standard mode and 90.4% in self-correction mode, outperforming prior SOTA by a large margin. Additionally, our flagship model solves 86 problems on PutnamBench at pass@184, securing the first place among open-source models on the leaderboard, surpassing DeepSeek-Prover-V2-671B's record of solving 47 problems by pass@1024 with a significantly smaller model size and compute budget. At the time of its release (July-August 2025), Goedel-Prover-V2 achieves the strongest overall performance among all open-source theorem provers. It also ranks among the top-performing models--including closed-source systems with publicly reported performance--under a constrained test-time compute budget. Our models, code, and data are released at https://github.com/Goedel-LM/Goedel-Prover-V2.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03613</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 16:28:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are We on the Right Way for Assessing Document Retrieval-Augmented   Generation?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03644</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03644.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenxuan Shen, Mingjia Wang, Yaochen Wang, Dongping Chen, Junjie Yang, Yao Wan, Weiwei Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) systems using Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) show great promise for complex document understanding, yet their development is critically hampered by inadequate evaluation. Current benchmarks often focus on specific part of document RAG system and use synthetic data with incomplete ground truth and evidence labels, therefore failing to reflect real-world bottlenecks and challenges. To overcome these limitations, we introduce Double-Bench: a new large-scale, multilingual, and multimodal evaluation system that is able to produce fine-grained assessment to each component within document RAG systems. It comprises 3,276 documents (72,880 pages) and 5,168 single- and multi-hop queries across 6 languages and 4 document types with streamlined dynamic update support for potential data contamination issues. Queries are grounded in exhaustively scanned evidence pages and verified by human experts to ensure maximum quality and completeness. Our comprehensive experiments across 9 state-of-the-art embedding models, 4 MLLMs and 4 end-to-end document RAG frameworks demonstrate the gap between text and visual embedding models is narrowing, highlighting the need in building stronger document retrieval models. Our findings also reveal the over-confidence dilemma within current document RAG frameworks that tend to provide answer even without evidence support. We hope our fully open-source Double-Bench provide a rigorous foundation for future research in advanced document RAG systems. We plan to retrieve timely corpus and release new benchmarks on an annual basis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03644</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 16:55:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HPSv3: Towards Wide-Spectrum Human Preference Score</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03789</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03789.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhang Ma, Xiaoshi Wu, Keqiang Sun, Hongsheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating text-to-image generation models requires alignment with human perception, yet existing human-centric metrics are constrained by limited data coverage, suboptimal feature extraction, and inefficient loss functions. To address these challenges, we introduce Human Preference Score v3 (HPSv3). (1) We release HPDv3, the first wide-spectrum human preference dataset integrating 1.08M text-image pairs and 1.17M annotated pairwise comparisons from state-of-the-art generative models and low to high-quality real-world images. (2) We introduce a VLM-based preference model trained using an uncertainty-aware ranking loss for fine-grained ranking. Besides, we propose Chain-of-Human-Preference (CoHP), an iterative image refinement method that enhances quality without extra data, using HPSv3 to select the best image at each step. Extensive experiments demonstrate that HPSv3 serves as a robust metric for wide-spectrum image evaluation, and CoHP offers an efficient and human-aligned approach to improve image generation quality. The code and dataset are available at the HPSv3 Homepage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03789</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 17:17:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent Lightning: Train ANY AI Agents with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03680</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03680.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xufang Luo, Yuge Zhang, Zhiyuan He, Zilong Wang, Siyun Zhao, Dongsheng Li, Luna K. Qiu, Yuqing Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Agent Lightning, a flexible and extensible framework that enables Reinforcement Learning (RL)-based training of Large Language Models (LLMs) for any AI agent. Unlike existing methods that tightly couple RL training with agent or rely on sequence concatenation with masking, Agent Lightning achieves complete decoupling between agent execution and training, allowing seamless integration with existing agents developed via diverse ways (e.g., using frameworks like LangChain, OpenAI Agents SDK, AutoGen, and building from scratch) with almost ZERO code modifications. By formulating agent execution as Markov decision process, we define an unified data interface and propose a hierarchical RL algorithm, LightningRL, which contains a credit assignment module, allowing us to decompose trajectories generated by ANY agents into training transition. This enables RL to handle complex interaction logic, such as multi-agent scenarios and dynamic workflows. For the system design, we introduce a Training-Agent Disaggregation architecture, and brings agent observability frameworks into agent runtime, providing a standardized agent finetuning interface. Experiments across text-to-SQL, retrieval-augmented generation, and math tool-use tasks demonstrate stable, continuous improvements, showcasing the framework's potential for real-world agent training and deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03680</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 17:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CompassVerifier: A Unified and Robust Verifier for LLMs Evaluation and   Outcome Reward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03686</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03686.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shudong Liu, Hongwei Liu, Junnan Liu, Linchen Xiao, Songyang Gao, Chengqi Lyu, Yuzhe Gu, Wenwei Zhang, Derek F. Wong, Songyang Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Answer verification is crucial not only for evaluating large language models (LLMs) by matching their unstructured outputs against standard answers, but also serves as the reward model to guide LLM optimization. Most evaluation frameworks rely on regularized matching or employ general LLMs for answer verification, which demands extensive, repetitive customization for regex rules or evaluation prompts. Two fundamental limitations persist in current methodologies: 1) the absence of comprehensive benchmarks that systematically evaluate verification capabilities across different LLMs; and 2) the nascent stage of verifier development, where existing approaches lack both the robustness to handle complex edge cases and the generalizability across different domains. In this work, we develop CompassVerifier, an accurate and robust lightweight verifier model for evaluation and outcome reward. It demonstrates multi-domain competency spanning math, knowledge, and diverse reasoning tasks, with the capability to process various answer types, including multi-subproblems, formulas, and sequence answers, while effectively identifying abnormal/invalid responses. We introduce VerifierBench benchmark comprising model outputs collected from multiple data sources, augmented through manual analysis of metaerror patterns to enhance CompassVerifier. We anticipate that CompassVerifier and VerifierBench will facilitate answer verification, evaluation protocols, and reinforcement learning research. Code and dataset are available at https://github.com/open-compass/CompassVerifier.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03686</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 17:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongVie: Multimodal-Guided Controllable Ultra-Long Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03694</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03694.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianxiong Gao, Zhaoxi Chen, Xian Liu, Jianfeng Feng, Chenyang Si, Yanwei Fu, Yu Qiao, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Controllable ultra-long video generation is a fundamental yet challenging task. Although existing methods are effective for short clips, they struggle to scale due to issues such as temporal inconsistency and visual degradation. In this paper, we initially investigate and identify three key factors: separate noise initialization, independent control signal normalization, and the limitations of single-modality guidance. To address these issues, we propose LongVie, an end-to-end autoregressive framework for controllable long video generation. LongVie introduces two core designs to ensure temporal consistency: 1) a unified noise initialization strategy that maintains consistent generation across clips, and 2) global control signal normalization that enforces alignment in the control space throughout the entire video. To mitigate visual degradation, LongVie employs 3) a multi-modal control framework that integrates both dense (e.g., depth maps) and sparse (e.g., keypoints) control signals, complemented by 4) a degradation-aware training strategy that adaptively balances modality contributions over time to preserve visual quality. We also introduce LongVGenBench, a comprehensive benchmark consisting of 100 high-resolution videos spanning diverse real-world and synthetic environments, each lasting over one minute. Extensive experiments show that LongVie achieves state-of-the-art performance in long-range controllability, consistency, and quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03694</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sotopia-RL: Reward Design for Social Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03905</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03905.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haofei Yu, Zhengyang Qi, Yining Zhao, Kolby Nottingham, Keyang Xuan, Bodhisattwa Prasad Majumder, Hao Zhu, Paul Pu Liang, Jiaxuan You&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Social intelligence has become a critical capability for large language models (LLMs), enabling them to engage effectively in real-world social tasks such as accommodation, persuasion, collaboration, and negotiation. Reinforcement learning (RL) is a natural fit for training socially intelligent agents because it allows models to learn sophisticated strategies directly through social interactions. However, social interactions have two key characteristics that set barriers for RL training: (1) partial observability, where utterances have indirect and delayed effects that complicate credit assignment, and (2) multi-dimensionality, where behaviors such as rapport-building or knowledge-seeking contribute indirectly to goal achievement. These characteristics make Markov decision process (MDP)-based RL with single-dimensional episode-level rewards inefficient and unstable. To address these challenges, we propose Sotopia-RL, a novel framework that refines coarse episode-level feedback into utterance-level, multi-dimensional rewards. Utterance-level credit assignment mitigates partial observability by attributing outcomes to individual utterances, while multi-dimensional rewards capture the full richness of social interactions and reduce reward hacking. Experiments in Sotopia, an open-ended social learning environment, demonstrate that Sotopia-RL achieves state-of-the-art social goal completion scores (7.17 on Sotopia-hard and 8.31 on Sotopia-full), significantly outperforming existing approaches. Ablation studies confirm the necessity of both utterance-level credit assignment and multi-dimensional reward design for RL training. Our implementation is publicly available at: https://github.com/sotopia-lab/sotopia-rl.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03905</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 20:43:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoAct-1: Computer-using Agents with Coding as Actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03923</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03923.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Linxin Song, Yutong Dai, Viraj Prabhu, Jieyu Zhang, Taiwei Shi, Li Li, Junnan Li, Silvio Savarese, Zeyuan Chen, Jieyu Zhao, Ran Xu, Caiming Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autonomous agents that operate computers via Graphical User Interfaces (GUIs) often struggle with efficiency and reliability on complex, long-horizon tasks. While augmenting these agents with planners can improve task decomposition, they remain constrained by the inherent limitations of performing all actions through GUI manipulation, leading to brittleness and inefficiency. In this work, we introduce a more robust and flexible paradigm: enabling agents to use coding as a enhanced action. We present CoAct-1, a novel multi-agent system that synergistically combines GUI-based control with direct programmatic execution. CoAct-1 features an Orchestrator that dynamically delegates subtasks to either a conventional GUI Operator or a specialized Programmer agent, which can write and execute Python or Bash scripts. This hybrid approach allows the agent to bypass inefficient GUI action sequences for tasks like file management and data processing, while still leveraging visual interaction when necessary. We evaluate our system on the challenging OSWorld benchmark, where CoAct-1 achieves a new state-of-the-art success rate of 60.76%, significantly outperforming prior methods. Furthermore, our approach dramatically improves efficiency, reducing the average number of steps required to complete a task to just 10.15, compared to 15 for leading GUI agents. Our results demonstrate that integrating coding as a core action provides a more powerful, efficient, and scalable path toward generalized computer automation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03923</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 21:33:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiDashengLM: Efficient Audio Understanding with General Audio Captions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03983</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03983.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Heinrich Dinkel, Gang Li, Jizhong Liu, Jian Luan, Yadong Niu, Xingwei Sun, Tianzi Wang, Qiyang Xiao, Junbo Zhang, Jiahao Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current approaches for large audio language models (LALMs) often rely on closed data sources or proprietary models, limiting their generalization and accessibility. This paper introduces MiDashengLM, a novel open audio-language model designed for efficient and comprehensive audio understanding through the use of general audio captions using our novel ACAVCaps training dataset. MiDashengLM exclusively relies on publicly available pretraining and supervised fine-tuning (SFT) datasets, ensuring full transparency and reproducibility. At its core, MiDashengLM integrates Dasheng, an open-source audio encoder, specifically engineered to process diverse auditory information effectively. Unlike previous works primarily focused on Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) based audio-text alignment, our strategy centers on general audio captions, fusing speech, sound and music information into one textual representation, enabling a holistic textual representation of complex audio scenes. Lastly, MiDashengLM provides an up to 4x speedup in terms of time-to-first-token (TTFT) and up to 20x higher throughput than comparable models. Checkpoints are available online at https://huggingface.co/mispeech/midashenglm-7b and https://github.com/xiaomi-research/dasheng-lm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03983</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:30:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Today's LLMs Ready to Explain Well-Being Concepts?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03990</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03990.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bohan Jiang, Dawei Li, Zhen Tan, Chengshuai Zhao, Huan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Well-being encompasses mental, physical, and social dimensions essential to personal growth and informed life decisions. As individuals increasingly consult Large Language Models (LLMs) to understand well-being, a key challenge emerges: Can LLMs generate explanations that are not only accurate but also tailored to diverse audiences? High-quality explanations require both factual correctness and the ability to meet the expectations of users with varying expertise. In this work, we construct a large-scale dataset comprising 43,880 explanations of 2,194 well-being concepts, generated by ten diverse LLMs. We introduce a principle-guided LLM-as-a-judge evaluation framework, employing dual judges to assess explanation quality. Furthermore, we show that fine-tuning an open-source LLM using Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) and Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) can significantly enhance the quality of generated explanations. Our results reveal: (1) The proposed LLM judges align well with human evaluations; (2) explanation quality varies significantly across models, audiences, and categories; and (3) DPO- and SFT-finetuned models outperform their larger counterparts, demonstrating the effectiveness of preference-based learning for specialized explanation tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03990</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:45:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HarmonyGuard: Toward Safety and Utility in Web Agents via Adaptive   Policy Enhancement and Dual-Objective Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04010</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04010.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yurun Chen, Xavier Hu, Yuhan Liu, Keting Yin, Juncheng Li, Zhuosheng Zhang, Shengyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models enable agents to autonomously perform tasks in open web environments. However, as hidden threats within the web evolve, web agents face the challenge of balancing task performance with emerging risks during long-sequence operations. Although this challenge is critical, current research remains limited to single-objective optimization or single-turn scenarios, lacking the capability for collaborative optimization of both safety and utility in web environments. To address this gap, we propose HarmonyGuard, a multi-agent collaborative framework that leverages policy enhancement and objective optimization to jointly improve both utility and safety. HarmonyGuard features a multi-agent architecture characterized by two fundamental capabilities: (1) Adaptive Policy Enhancement: We introduce the Policy Agent within HarmonyGuard, which automatically extracts and maintains structured security policies from unstructured external documents, while continuously updating policies in response to evolving threats. (2) Dual-Objective Optimization: Based on the dual objectives of safety and utility, the Utility Agent integrated within HarmonyGuard performs the Markovian real-time reasoning to evaluate the objectives and utilizes metacognitive capabilities for their optimization. Extensive evaluations on multiple benchmarks show that HarmonyGuard improves policy compliance by up to 38% and task completion by up to 20% over existing baselines, while achieving over 90% policy compliance across all tasks. Our project is available here: https://github.com/YurunChen/HarmonyGuard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04010</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 01:49:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Large Multimodal Models Actively Recognize Faulty Inputs? A   Systematic Evaluation Framework of Their Input Scrutiny Ability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04017</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04017.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haiqi Yang, Jinzhe Li, Gengxu Li, Yi Chang, Yuan Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) have witnessed remarkable growth, showcasing formidable capabilities in handling intricate multimodal tasks with exceptional performance. Recent research has underscored the inclination of large language models to passively accept defective inputs, often resulting in futile reasoning on invalid prompts. However, the same critical question of whether LMMs can actively detect and scrutinize erroneous inputs still remains unexplored. To address this gap, we introduce the Input Scrutiny Ability Evaluation Framework (ISEval), which encompasses seven categories of flawed premises and three evaluation metrics. Our extensive evaluation of ten advanced LMMs has identified key findings. Most models struggle to actively detect flawed textual premises without guidance, which reflects a strong reliance on explicit prompts for premise error identification. Error type affects performance: models excel at identifying logical fallacies but struggle with surface-level linguistic errors and certain conditional flaws. Modality trust varies-Gemini 2.5 pro and Claude Sonnet 4 balance visual and textual info, while aya-vision-8b over-rely on text in conflicts. These insights underscore the urgent need to enhance LMMs' proactive verification of input validity and shed novel insights into mitigating the problem. The code is available at https://github.com/MLGroupJLU/LMM_ISEval.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04017</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 02:13:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VeriGUI: Verifiable Long-Chain GUI Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04026</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04026.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shunyu Liu, Minghao Liu, Huichi Zhou, Zhenyu Cui, Yang Zhou, Yuhao Zhou, Wendong Fan, Ge Zhang, Jiajun Shi, Weihao Xuan, Jiaxing Huang, Shuang Luo, Fang Wu, Heli Qi, Qingcheng Zeng, Ziqi Ren, Jialiang Gao, Jindi Lv, Junjie Wang, Aosong Feng, Heng Zhou, Wangchunshu Zhou, Zhenfei Yin, Wenlong Zhang, Guohao Li, Wenhao Yu, Irene Li, Lei Ma, Lei Bai, Qunshu Lin, Mingli Song, Dacheng Tao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 131&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have delved into constructing autonomous agents capable of performing complex Graphical User Interface (GUI)-based computer tasks, with the potential to revolutionize human-computer interaction. Despite encouraging results, existing efforts mainly focus on short-term interactions and rely on outcome-only verification, thereby limiting their scalability in real-world GUI applications that demand long-horizon task decomposition and execution. In this work, we introduce VeriGUI, a novel verifiable long-chain GUI dataset designed to facilitate the development and evaluation of generalist GUI agents operating in realistic computer environments. Our dataset emphasizes two critical dimensions: (1) long-chain complexity, with tasks decomposed into a sequence of interdependent subtasks spanning hundreds of steps, explicitly designed to allow any subtask to serve as a valid starting point; and (2) subtask-level verifiability, which enables diverse exploration strategies within each subtask, while ensuring that each subtask-level goal remains verifiable and consistent. The dataset consists of GUI task trajectories across both desktop and web, annotated by human experts. Extensive experiments on VeriGUI using various agents with different foundation models reveal significant performance gaps in handling long-horizon tasks, highlighting the need for more robust planning and decision-making capabilities in GUI agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04026</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 02:38:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking the Potential of MLLMs in Referring Expression Segmentation   via a Light-weight Mask Decode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04107</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04107.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingchao Wang, Zhijian Wu, Dingjiang Huang, Yefeng Zheng, Hong Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reference Expression Segmentation (RES) aims to segment image regions specified by referring expressions and has become popular with the rise of multimodal large models (MLLMs). While MLLMs excel in semantic understanding, their token-generation paradigm struggles with pixel-level dense prediction. Existing RES methods either couple MLLMs with the parameter-heavy Segment Anything Model (SAM) with 632M network parameters or adopt SAM-free lightweight pipelines that sacrifice accuracy. To address the trade-off between performance and cost, we specifically propose MLLMSeg, a novel framework that fully exploits the inherent visual detail features encoded in the MLLM vision encoder without introducing an extra visual encoder. Besides, we propose a detail-enhanced and semantic-consistent feature fusion module (DSFF) that fully integrates the detail-related visual feature with the semantic-related feature output by the large language model (LLM) of MLLM. Finally, we establish a light-weight mask decoder with only 34M network parameters that optimally leverages detailed spatial features from the visual encoder and semantic features from the LLM to achieve precise mask prediction. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method generally surpasses both SAM-based and SAM-free competitors, striking a better balance between performance and cost. Code is available at https://github.com/jcwang0602/MLLMSeg.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04107</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 06:06:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RPCANet++: Deep Interpretable Robust PCA for Sparse Object Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04190</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04190.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fengyi Wu, Yimian Dai, Tianfang Zhang, Yixuan Ding, Jian Yang, Ming-Ming Cheng, Zhenming Peng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Robust principal component analysis (RPCA) decomposes an observation matrix into low-rank background and sparse object components. This capability has enabled its application in tasks ranging from image restoration to segmentation. However, traditional RPCA models suffer from computational burdens caused by matrix operations, reliance on finely tuned hyperparameters, and rigid priors that limit adaptability in dynamic scenarios. To solve these limitations, we propose RPCANet++, a sparse object segmentation framework that fuses the interpretability of RPCA with efficient deep architectures. Our approach unfolds a relaxed RPCA model into a structured network comprising a Background Approximation Module (BAM), an Object Extraction Module (OEM), and an Image Restoration Module (IRM). To mitigate inter-stage transmission loss in the BAM, we introduce a Memory-Augmented Module (MAM) to enhance background feature preservation, while a Deep Contrast Prior Module (DCPM) leverages saliency cues to expedite object extraction. Extensive experiments on diverse datasets demonstrate that RPCANet++ achieves state-of-the-art performance under various imaging scenarios. We further improve interpretability via visual and numerical low-rankness and sparsity measurements. By combining the theoretical strengths of RPCA with the efficiency of deep networks, our approach sets a new baseline for reliable and interpretable sparse object segmentation. Codes are available at our Project Webpage https://fengyiwu98.github.io/rpcanetx.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04190</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 08:19:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Vision-Language Model Training with Reinforcement Learning in   Synthetic Worlds for Real-World Success</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04280</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04280.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; George Bredis, Stanislav Dereka, Viacheslav Sinii, Ruslan Rakhimov, Daniil Gavrilov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Interactive multimodal agents must convert raw visual observations into coherent sequences of language-conditioned actions -- a capability that current vision-language models (VLMs) still lack. Earlier reinforcement-learning (RL) efforts could, in principle, endow VLMs with such skills, but they have seldom tested whether the learned behaviours generalize beyond their training simulators, and they depend either on brittle hyperparameter tuning or on dense-reward environments with low state variability. We introduce Vision-Language Decoupled Actor-Critic (VL-DAC), a lightweight, hyperparameter-free RL algorithm. VL-DAC applies PPO updates to action tokens while learning value only at the environment-step level: an arrangement, to our knowledge, not previously explored for large VLMs or LLMs. This simple decoupling removes unstable weighting terms and yields faster, more reliable convergence. Training a single VLM with VL-DAC in one inexpensive simulator at a time (MiniWorld, Gym-Cards, ALFWorld, or WebShop) already produces policies that generalize widely: +50\% relative on BALROG (game-centric agentic control), +5\% relative on the hardest part of VSI-Bench (spatial planning), and +2\% on VisualWebBench (web navigation), all without degrading general image understanding accuracy. These results provide the first evidence that a simple RL algorithm can train VLMs entirely in cheap synthetic worlds while delivering measurable gains on real-image agentic, spatial-reasoning, and web-navigation benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04280</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 10:08:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EVOC2RUST: A Skeleton-guided Framework for Project-Level C-to-Rust   Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04295</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04295.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaofan Wang, Tingrui Yu, Jie Wang, Dong Chen, Wenrui Zhang, Yuling Shi, Xiaodong Gu, Beijun Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Rust's compile-time safety guarantees make it ideal for safety-critical systems, creating demand for translating legacy C codebases to Rust. While various approaches have emerged for this task, they face inherent trade-offs: rule-based solutions face challenges in meeting code safety and idiomaticity requirements, while LLM-based solutions often fail to generate semantically equivalent Rust code, due to the heavy dependencies of modules across the entire codebase. Recent studies have revealed that both solutions are limited to small-scale programs. In this paper, we propose EvoC2Rust, an automated framework for converting entire C projects to equivalent Rust ones. EvoC2Rust employs a skeleton-guided translation strategy for project-level translation. The pipeline consists of three evolutionary stages: 1) it first decomposes the C project into functional modules, employs a feature-mapping-enhanced LLM to transform definitions and macros and generates type-checked function stubs, which form a compilable Rust skeleton; 2) it then incrementally translates the function, replacing the corresponding stub placeholder; 3) finally, it repairs compilation errors by integrating LLM and static analysis. Through evolutionary augmentation, EvoC2Rust combines the advantages of both rule-based and LLM-based solutions. Our evaluation on open-source benchmarks and six industrial projects demonstrates EvoC2Rust's superior performance in project-level C-to-Rust translation. On average, it achieves 17.24% and 14.32% improvements in syntax and semantic accuracy over the LLM-based approaches, along with a 96.79% higher code safety rate than the rule-based tools. At the module level, EvoC2Rust reaches 92.25% compilation and 89.53% test pass rates on industrial projects, even for complex codebases and long functions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04295</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 10:31:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating, Synthesizing, and Enhancing for Customer Support   Conversation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04423</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04423.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jie Zhu, Huaixia Dou, Junhui Li, Lifan Guo, Feng Chen, Chi Zhang, Fang Kong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Effective customer support requires not only accurate problem solving but also structured and empathetic communication aligned with professional standards. However, existing dialogue datasets often lack strategic guidance, and real-world service data is difficult to access and annotate. To address this, we introduce the task of Customer Support Conversation (CSC), aimed at training customer service agents to respond using well-defined support strategies. We propose a structured CSC framework grounded in COPC guidelines, defining five conversational stages and twelve strategies to guide high-quality interactions. Based on this, we construct CSConv, an evaluation dataset of 1,855 real-world customer-agent conversations rewritten using LLMs to reflect deliberate strategy use, and annotated accordingly. Additionally, we develop a role-playing approach that simulates strategy-rich conversations using LLM-powered roles aligned with the CSC framework, resulting in the training dataset RoleCS. Experiments show that fine-tuning strong LLMs on RoleCS significantly improves their ability to generate high-quality, strategy-aligned responses on CSConv. Human evaluations further confirm gains in problem resolution. All code and data will be made publicly available at https://github.com/aliyun/qwen-dianjin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04423</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 13:11:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StepFun-Formalizer: Unlocking the Autoformalization Potential of LLMs   through Knowledge-Reasoning Fusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04440</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04440.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yutong Wu, Di Huang, Ruosi Wan, Yue Peng, Shijie Shang, Chenrui Cao, Lei Qi, Rui Zhang, Zidong Du, Jie Yan, Xing Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoformalization aims to translate natural-language mathematical statements into a formal language. While LLMs have accelerated progress in this area, existing methods still suffer from low accuracy. We identify two key abilities for effective autoformalization: comprehensive mastery of formal-language domain knowledge, and reasoning capability of natural language problem understanding and informal-formal alignment. Without the former, a model cannot identify the correct formal objects; without the latter, it struggles to interpret real-world contexts and map them precisely into formal expressions. To address these gaps, we introduce ThinkingF, a data synthesis and training pipeline that improves both abilities. First, we construct two datasets: one by distilling and selecting large-scale examples rich in formal knowledge, and another by generating informal-to-formal reasoning trajectories guided by expert-designed templates. We then apply SFT and RLVR with these datasets to further fuse and refine the two abilities. The resulting 7B and 32B models exhibit both comprehensive formal knowledge and strong informal-to-formal reasoning. Notably, StepFun-Formalizer-32B achieves SOTA BEq@1 scores of 40.5% on FormalMATH-Lite and 26.7% on ProverBench, surpassing all prior general-purpose and specialized models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04440</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 13:28:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Position: The Current AI Conference Model is Unsustainable! Diagnosing   the Crisis of Centralized AI Conference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04586</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04586.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nuo Chen, Moming Duan, Andre Huikai Lin, Qian Wang, Jiaying Wu, Bingsheng He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Artificial Intelligence (AI) conferences are essential for advancing research, sharing knowledge, and fostering academic community. However, their rapid expansion has rendered the centralized conference model increasingly unsustainable. This paper offers a data-driven diagnosis of a structural crisis that threatens the foundational goals of scientific dissemination, equity, and community well-being. We identify four key areas of strain: (1) scientifically, with per-author publication rates more than doubling over the past decade to over 4.5 papers annually; (2) environmentally, with the carbon footprint of a single conference exceeding the daily emissions of its host city; (3) psychologically, with 71% of online community discourse reflecting negative sentiment and 35% referencing mental health concerns; and (4) logistically, with attendance at top conferences such as NeurIPS 2024 beginning to outpace venue capacity. These pressures point to a system that is misaligned with its core mission. In response, we propose the Community-Federated Conference (CFC) model, which separates peer review, presentation, and networking into globally coordinated but locally organized components, offering a more sustainable, inclusive, and resilient path forward for AI research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04586</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 16:08:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sculptor: Empowering LLMs with Cognitive Agency via Active Context   Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04664</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04664.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mo Li, L. H. Xu, Qitai Tan, Ting Cao, Yunxin Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) suffer from significant performance degradation when processing long contexts due to proactive interference, where irrelevant information in earlier parts of the context disrupts reasoning and memory recall. While most research focuses on external memory systems to augment LLMs' capabilities, we propose a complementary approach: empowering LLMs with Active Context Management (ACM) tools to actively sculpt their internal working memory. We introduce Sculptor, a framework that equips LLMs with three categories of tools: (1) context fragmentation, (2) summary, hide, and restore, and (3) intelligent search. Our approach enables LLMs to proactively manage their attention and working memory, analogous to how humans selectively focus on relevant information while filtering out distractions. Experimental evaluation on information-sparse benchmarks-PI-LLM (proactive interference) and NeedleBench Multi-Needle Reasoning-demonstrates that Sculptor significantly improves performance even without specific training, leveraging LLMs' inherent tool calling generalization capabilities. By enabling Active Context Management, Sculptor not only mitigates proactive interference but also provides a cognitive foundation for more reliable reasoning across diverse long-context tasks-highlighting that explicit context-control strategies, rather than merely larger token windows, are key to robustness at scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04664</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 17:32:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SEAgent: Self-Evolving Computer Use Agent with Autonomous Learning from   Experience</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04700</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04700.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeyi Sun, Ziyu Liu, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Xiaoyi Dong, Tong Wu, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Repurposing large vision-language models (LVLMs) as computer use agents (CUAs) has led to substantial breakthroughs, primarily driven by human-labeled data. However, these models often struggle with novel and specialized software, particularly in scenarios lacking human annotations. To address this challenge, we propose SEAgent, an agentic self-evolving framework enabling CUAs to autonomously evolve through interactions with unfamiliar software. Specifically, SEAgent empowers computer-use agents to autonomously master novel software environments via experiential learning, where agents explore new software, learn through iterative trial-and-error, and progressively tackle auto-generated tasks organized from simple to complex. To achieve this goal, we design a World State Model for step-wise trajectory assessment, along with a Curriculum Generator that generates increasingly diverse and challenging tasks. The agent's policy is updated through experiential learning, comprised of adversarial imitation of failure actions and Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) on successful ones. Furthermore, we introduce a specialist-to-generalist training strategy that integrates individual experiential insights from specialist agents, facilitating the development of a stronger generalist CUA capable of continuous autonomous evolution. This unified agent ultimately achieves performance surpassing ensembles of individual specialist agents on their specialized software. We validate the effectiveness of SEAgent across five novel software environments within OS-World. Our approach achieves a significant improvement of 23.2% in success rate, from 11.3% to 34.5%, over a competitive open-source CUA, i.e., UI-TARS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04700</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 17:58:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REINA: Regularized Entropy Information-Based Loss for Efficient   Simultaneous Speech Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04946</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04946.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nameer Hirschkind, Joseph Liu, Mahesh Kumar Nandwana, Xiao Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Simultaneous Speech Translation (SimulST) systems stream in audio while simultaneously emitting translated text or speech. Such systems face the significant challenge of balancing translation quality and latency. We introduce a strategy to optimize this tradeoff: wait for more input only if you gain information by doing so. Based on this strategy, we present Regularized Entropy INformation Adaptation (REINA), a novel loss to train an adaptive policy using an existing non-streaming translation model. We derive REINA from information theory principles and show that REINA helps push the reported Pareto frontier of the latency/quality tradeoff over prior works. Utilizing REINA, we train a SimulST model on French, Spanish and German, both from and into English. Training on only open source or synthetically generated data, we achieve state-of-the-art (SOTA) streaming results for models of comparable size. We also introduce a metric for streaming efficiency, quantitatively showing REINA improves the latency/quality trade-off by as much as 21% compared to prior approaches, normalized against non-streaming baseline BLEU scores.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04946</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 00:25:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steering One-Step Diffusion Model with Fidelity-Rich Decoder for Fast   Image Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04979</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04979.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zheng Chen, Mingde Zhou, Jinpei Guo, Jiale Yuan, Yifei Ji, Yulun Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion-based image compression has demonstrated impressive perceptual performance. However, it suffers from two critical drawbacks: (1) excessive decoding latency due to multi-step sampling, and (2) poor fidelity resulting from over-reliance on generative priors. To address these issues, we propose SODEC, a novel single-step diffusion image compression model. We argue that in image compression, a sufficiently informative latent renders multi-step refinement unnecessary. Based on this insight, we leverage a pre-trained VAE-based model to produce latents with rich information, and replace the iterative denoising process with a single-step decoding. Meanwhile, to improve fidelity, we introduce the fidelity guidance module, encouraging output that is faithful to the original image. Furthermore, we design the rate annealing training strategy to enable effective training under extremely low bitrates. Extensive experiments show that SODEC significantly outperforms existing methods, achieving superior rate-distortion-perception performance. Moreover, compared to previous diffusion-based compression models, SODEC improves decoding speed by more than 20times. Code is released at: https://github.com/zhengchen1999/SODEC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04979</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 02:24:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R-Zero: Self-Evolving Reasoning LLM from Zero Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05004</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05004.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chengsong Huang, Wenhao Yu, Xiaoyang Wang, Hongming Zhang, Zongxia Li, Ruosen Li, Jiaxin Huang, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 84&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-evolving Large Language Models (LLMs) offer a scalable path toward super-intelligence by autonomously generating, refining, and learning from their own experiences. However, existing methods for training such models still rely heavily on vast human-curated tasks and labels, typically via fine-tuning or reinforcement learning, which poses a fundamental bottleneck to advancing AI systems toward capabilities beyond human intelligence. To overcome this limitation, we introduce R-Zero, a fully autonomous framework that generates its own training data from scratch. Starting from a single base LLM, R-Zero initializes two independent models with distinct roles, a Challenger and a Solver. These models are optimized separately and co-evolve through interaction: the Challenger is rewarded for proposing tasks near the edge of the Solver capability, and the Solver is rewarded for solving increasingly challenging tasks posed by the Challenger. This process yields a targeted, self-improving curriculum without any pre-existing tasks and labels. Empirically, R-Zero substantially improves reasoning capability across different backbone LLMs, e.g., boosting the Qwen3-4B-Base by +6.49 on math-reasoning benchmarks and +7.54 on general-domain reasoning benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05004</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 03:38:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepPHY: Benchmarking Agentic VLMs on Physical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05405</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05405.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinrun Xu, Pi Bu, Ye Wang, Börje F. Karlsson, Ziming Wang, Tengtao Song, Qi Zhu, Jun Song, Zhiming Ding, Bo Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although Vision Language Models (VLMs) exhibit strong perceptual abilities and impressive visual reasoning, they struggle with attention to detail and precise action planning in complex, dynamic environments, leading to subpar performance. Real-world tasks typically require complex interactions, advanced spatial reasoning, long-term planning, and continuous strategy refinement, usually necessitating understanding the physics rules of the target scenario. However, evaluating these capabilities in real-world scenarios is often prohibitively expensive. To bridge this gap, we introduce DeepPHY, a novel benchmark framework designed to systematically evaluate VLMs' understanding and reasoning about fundamental physical principles through a series of challenging simulated environments. DeepPHY integrates multiple physical reasoning environments of varying difficulty levels and incorporates fine-grained evaluation metrics. Our evaluation finds that even state-of-the-art VLMs struggle to translate descriptive physical knowledge into precise, predictive control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05405</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 13:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfiAlign: A Scalable and Sample-Efficient Framework for Aligning LLMs   to Enhance Reasoning Capabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05496</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05496.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuo Cai, Su Lu, Qi Zhou, Kejing Yang, Zhijie Sang, Congkai Xie, Hongxia Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have exhibited impressive reasoning abilities on a wide range of complex tasks. However, enhancing these capabilities through post-training remains resource intensive, particularly in terms of data and computational cost. Although recent efforts have sought to improve sample efficiency through selective data curation, existing methods often rely on heuristic or task-specific strategies that hinder scalability. In this work, we introduce InfiAlign, a scalable and sample-efficient post-training framework that integrates supervised fine-tuning (SFT) with Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) to align LLMs for enhanced reasoning. At the core of InfiAlign is a robust data selection pipeline that automatically curates high-quality alignment data from open-source reasoning datasets using multidimensional quality metrics. This pipeline enables significant performance gains while drastically reducing data requirements and remains extensible to new data sources. When applied to the Qwen2.5-Math-7B-Base model, our SFT model achieves performance on par with DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-7B, while using only approximately 12% of the training data, and demonstrates strong generalization across diverse reasoning tasks. Additional improvements are obtained through the application of DPO, with particularly notable gains in mathematical reasoning tasks. The model achieves an average improvement of 3.89% on AIME 24/25 benchmarks. Our results highlight the effectiveness of combining principled data selection with full-stage post-training, offering a practical solution for aligning large reasoning models in a scalable and data-efficient manner. The model checkpoints are available at https://huggingface.co/InfiX-ai/InfiAlign-Qwen-7B-SFT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05496</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 15:34:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hi3DEval: Advancing 3D Generation Evaluation with Hierarchical Validity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05609</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05609.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhan Zhang, Long Zhuo, Ziyang Chu, Tong Wu, Zhibing Li, Liang Pan, Dahua Lin, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite rapid advances in 3D content generation, quality assessment for the generated 3D assets remains challenging. Existing methods mainly rely on image-based metrics and operate solely at the object level, limiting their ability to capture spatial coherence, material authenticity, and high-fidelity local details. 1) To address these challenges, we introduce Hi3DEval, a hierarchical evaluation framework tailored for 3D generative content. It combines both object-level and part-level evaluation, enabling holistic assessments across multiple dimensions as well as fine-grained quality analysis. Additionally, we extend texture evaluation beyond aesthetic appearance by explicitly assessing material realism, focusing on attributes such as albedo, saturation, and metallicness. 2) To support this framework, we construct Hi3DBench, a large-scale dataset comprising diverse 3D assets and high-quality annotations, accompanied by a reliable multi-agent annotation pipeline. We further propose a 3D-aware automated scoring system based on hybrid 3D representations. Specifically, we leverage video-based representations for object-level and material-subject evaluations to enhance modeling of spatio-temporal consistency and employ pretrained 3D features for part-level perception. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach outperforms existing image-based metrics in modeling 3D characteristics and achieves superior alignment with human preference, providing a scalable alternative to manual evaluations. The project page is available at https://zyh482.github.io/Hi3DEval/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05609</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 17:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Reason for Factuality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xilun Chen, Ilia Kulikov, Vincent-Pierre Berges, Barlas Oğuz, Rulin Shao, Gargi Ghosh, Jason Weston, Wen-tau Yih&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning Large Language Models (R-LLMs) have significantly advanced complex reasoning tasks but often struggle with factuality, generating substantially more hallucinations than their non-reasoning counterparts on long-form factuality benchmarks. However, extending online Reinforcement Learning (RL), a key component in recent R-LLM advancements, to the long-form factuality setting poses several unique challenges due to the lack of reliable verification methods. Previous work has utilized automatic factuality evaluation frameworks such as FActScore to curate preference data in the offline RL setting, yet we find that directly leveraging such methods as the reward in online RL leads to reward hacking in multiple ways, such as producing less detailed or relevant responses. We propose a novel reward function that simultaneously considers the factual precision, response detail level, and answer relevance, and applies online RL to learn high quality factual reasoning. Evaluated on six long-form factuality benchmarks, our factual reasoning model achieves an average reduction of 23.1 percentage points in hallucination rate, a 23% increase in answer detail level, and no degradation in the overall response helpfulness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05618</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 17:57:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Generalization of SFT: A Reinforcement Learning Perspective with   Reward Rectification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05629</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05629.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yongliang Wu, Yizhou Zhou, Zhou Ziheng, Yingzhe Peng, Xinyu Ye, Xinting Hu, Wenbo Zhu, Lu Qi, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Xu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 103&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present a simple yet theoretically motivated improvement to Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) for the Large Language Model (LLM), addressing its limited generalization compared to reinforcement learning (RL). Through mathematical analysis, we reveal that standard SFT gradients implicitly encode a problematic reward structure that may severely restrict the generalization capabilities of model. To rectify this, we propose Dynamic Fine-Tuning (DFT), stabilizing gradient updates for each token by dynamically rescaling the objective function with the probability of this token. Remarkably, this single-line code change significantly outperforms standard SFT across multiple challenging benchmarks and base models, demonstrating greatly improved generalization. Additionally, our approach shows competitive results in offline RL settings, offering an effective yet simpler alternative. This work bridges theoretical insight and practical solutions, substantially advancing SFT performance. The code will be available at https://github.com/yongliang-wu/DFT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05629</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 17:59:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOSEv2: A More Challenging Dataset for Video Object Segmentation in   Complex Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05630</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05630.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Henghui Ding, Kaining Ying, Chang Liu, Shuting He, Xudong Jiang, Yu-Gang Jiang, Philip H. S. Torr, Song Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video object segmentation (VOS) aims to segment specified target objects throughout a video. Although state-of-the-art methods have achieved impressive performance (e.g., 90+% J&amp;F) on existing benchmarks such as DAVIS and YouTube-VOS, these datasets primarily contain salient, dominant, and isolated objects, limiting their generalization to real-world scenarios. To advance VOS toward more realistic environments, coMplex video Object SEgmentation (MOSEv1) was introduced to facilitate VOS research in complex scenes. Building on the strengths and limitations of MOSEv1, we present MOSEv2, a significantly more challenging dataset designed to further advance VOS methods under real-world conditions. MOSEv2 consists of 5,024 videos and over 701,976 high-quality masks for 10,074 objects across 200 categories. Compared to its predecessor, MOSEv2 introduces significantly greater scene complexity, including more frequent object disappearance and reappearance, severe occlusions and crowding, smaller objects, as well as a range of new challenges such as adverse weather (e.g., rain, snow, fog), low-light scenes (e.g., nighttime, underwater), multi-shot sequences, camouflaged objects, non-physical targets (e.g., shadows, reflections), scenarios requiring external knowledge, etc. We benchmark 20 representative VOS methods under 5 different settings and observe consistent performance drops. For example, SAM2 drops from 76.4% on MOSEv1 to only 50.9% on MOSEv2. We further evaluate 9 video object tracking methods and find similar declines, demonstrating that MOSEv2 presents challenges across tasks. These results highlight that despite high accuracy on existing datasets, current VOS methods still struggle under real-world complexities. MOSEv2 is publicly available at https://MOSE.video.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05630</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 17:59:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genie Envisioner: A Unified World Foundation Platform for Robotic   Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05635</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05635.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yue Liao, Pengfei Zhou, Siyuan Huang, Donglin Yang, Shengcong Chen, Yuxin Jiang, Yue Hu, Jingbin Cai, Si Liu, Jianlan Luo, Liliang Chen, Shuicheng Yan, Maoqing Yao, Guanghui Ren&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Genie Envisioner (GE), a unified world foundation platform for robotic manipulation that integrates policy learning, evaluation, and simulation within a single video-generative framework. At its core, GE-Base is a large-scale, instruction-conditioned video diffusion model that captures the spatial, temporal, and semantic dynamics of real-world robotic interactions in a structured latent space. Built upon this foundation, GE-Act maps latent representations to executable action trajectories through a lightweight, flow-matching decoder, enabling precise and generalizable policy inference across diverse embodiments with minimal supervision. To support scalable evaluation and training, GE-Sim serves as an action-conditioned neural simulator, producing high-fidelity rollouts for closed-loop policy development. The platform is further equipped with EWMBench, a standardized benchmark suite measuring visual fidelity, physical consistency, and instruction-action alignment. Together, these components establish Genie Envisioner as a scalable and practical foundation for instruction-driven, general-purpose embodied intelligence. All code, models, and benchmarks will be released publicly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05635</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 17:59:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
