<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:11:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>CritiCal: Can Critique Help LLM Uncertainty or Confidence Calibration?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24505</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24505.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qing Zong, Jiayu Liu, Tianshi Zheng, Chunyang Li, Baixuan Xu, Haochen Shi, Weiqi Wang, Zhaowei Wang, Chunkit Chan, Yangqiu Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Accurate confidence calibration in Large Language Models (LLMs) is critical for safe use in high-stakes domains, where clear verbalized confidence enhances user trust. Traditional methods that mimic reference confidence expressions often fail to capture the reasoning needed for accurate confidence assessment. We propose natural language critiques as a solution, ideally suited for confidence calibration, as precise gold confidence labels are hard to obtain and often require multiple generations. This paper studies how natural language critiques can enhance verbalized confidence, addressing: (1) What to critique: uncertainty (question-focused) or confidence (answer-specific)? Analysis shows confidence suits multiple-choice tasks, while uncertainty excels in open-ended scenarios. (2) How to critique: self-critique or critique calibration training? We propose Self-Critique, enabling LLMs to critique and optimize their confidence beyond mere accuracy, and CritiCal, a novel Critique Calibration training method that leverages natural language critiques to improve confidence calibration, moving beyond direct numerical optimization. Experiments show that CritiCal significantly outperforms Self-Critique and other competitive baselines, even surpassing its teacher model, GPT-4o, in complex reasoning tasks. CritiCal also shows robust generalization in out-of-distribution settings, advancing LLM's reliability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24505</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 15:16:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superpositional Gradient Descent: Harnessing Quantum Principles for   Model Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01918</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01918.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ahmet Erdem Pamuk, Emir Kaan Özdemir, Şuayp Talha Kocabay&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly trained with classical optimization techniques like AdamW to improve convergence and generalization. However, the mechanisms by which quantum-inspired methods enhance classical training remain underexplored. We introduce Superpositional Gradient Descent (SGD), a novel optimizer linking gradient updates with quantum superposition by injecting quantum circuit perturbations. We present a mathematical framework and implement hybrid quantum-classical circuits in PyTorch and Qiskit. On synthetic sequence classification and large-scale LLM fine-tuning, SGD converges faster and yields lower final loss than AdamW. Despite promising results, scalability and hardware constraints limit adoption. Overall, this work provides new insights into the intersection of quantum computing and deep learning, suggesting practical pathways for leveraging quantum principles to control and enhance model behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01918</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 16:37:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ariadne: A Controllable Framework for Probing and Extending VLM   Reasoning Boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00710</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00710.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minghe Shen, Zhuo Zhi, Chonghan Liu, Shuo Xing, Zhengzhong Tu, Che Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Vision-Language Models (VLMs) post-trained with Reinforcement Learning (RL) show impressive general reasoning, their evaluation is often confined to language-dominant tasks (e.g., math). This raises a critical question: can RL post-training truly extend the inherent capability boundary of a base VLM, particularly for visual-centric spatial tasks where it initially fails? To investigate this, we introduce Ariadne, a framework utilizing synthetic mazes for multi-step spatial reasoning where task difficulty (e.g., path length, turns) is precisely controlled. We leverage this controllable environment to train VLMs using Reinforcement Learning with Verified Rewards (RLVR) in a difficulty-aware curriculum. Surprisingly, post-RLVR training, the VLM achieves over 50% accuracy on a problem set where the base model scored 0%, demonstrating that our approach expands the model's initial capability boundary. To assess real-world viability, we evaluate out-of-distribution (OOD) generalization on practical benchmarks. Despite training only on synthetic maze samples, Ariadne achieves significant zero-shot improvements, averaging 16% on MapBench (e.g., museum navigation) and 24% on ReasonMap (subway transfer tasks). These results confirm that our method not only broadens the model's fundamental limits but also enhances its generalization to real-world spatial reasoning. We acknowledge our study is limited to the post-training phase, given the opaqueness of pre-training data, and hope our research motivates further work on specialized, capability-extending alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00710</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 21:19:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HAFixAgent: History-Aware Automated Program Repair Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01047</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01047.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Shi, Hao Li, Bram Adams, Ahmed E. Hassan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Automated program repair (APR) has recently shifted toward large language models and agent-based systems, yet most systems rely on local snapshot context, overlooking repository history. Prior work shows that repository history helps repair single-line bugs, since the last commit touching the buggy line is often the bug-introducing one. In this paper, we investigate whether repository history can also improve agentic APR systems at scale, especially for complex multi-hunk bugs. We present HAFixAgent, a History-Aware Bug-Fixing Agent that injects blame-derived repository heuristics into its repair loop. A preliminary study of all 854 real-world bugs from Defects4J motivates our design, showing that bug-relevant history is both widely available and highly concentrated. Empirical comparison of HAFixAgent with two state-of-the-art baselines shows: (1) Effectiveness: HAFixAgent significantly improves over the agent-based baseline (by 212.3%) and the multi-hunk baseline (by 29.9%). (2) Efficiency: history does not significantly increase agent steps and keeps token costs comparable, with notably lower median costs for complex multi-file-multi-hunk bugs. (3) Practicality: combining different historical heuristics repairs more bugs, offering a clear cost-benefit trade-off. HAFixAgent offers a practical recipe for history-aware agentic APR: ground the agent in version control history, prioritize diff-based historical context, and integrate complementary heuristics when needed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01047</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 18:45:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jailbreaking in the Haystack</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04707</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04707.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rishi Rajesh Shah, Chen Henry Wu, Shashwat Saxena, Ziqian Zhong, Alexander Robey, Aditi Raghunathan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in long-context language models (LMs) have enabled million-token inputs, expanding their capabilities across complex tasks like computer-use agents. Yet, the safety implications of these extended contexts remain unclear. To bridge this gap, we introduce NINJA (short for Needle-in-haystack jailbreak attack), a method that jailbreaks aligned LMs by appending benign, model-generated content to harmful user goals. Critical to our method is the observation that the position of harmful goals play an important role in safety. Experiments on standard safety benchmark, HarmBench, show that NINJA significantly increases attack success rates across state-of-the-art open and proprietary models, including LLaMA, Qwen, Mistral, and Gemini. Unlike prior jailbreaking methods, our approach is low-resource, transferable, and less detectable. Moreover, we show that NINJA is compute-optimal -- under a fixed compute budget, increasing context length can outperform increasing the number of trials in best-of-N jailbreak. These findings reveal that even benign long contexts -- when crafted with careful goal positioning -- introduce fundamental vulnerabilities in modern LMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04707</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 01:12:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion-SDPO: Safeguarded Direct Preference Optimization for Diffusion   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minghao Fu, Guo-Hua Wang, Tianyu Cui, Qing-Guo Chen, Zhao Xu, Weihua Luo, Kaifu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-image diffusion models deliver high-quality images, yet aligning them with human preferences remains challenging. We revisit diffusion-based Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) for these models and identify a critical pathology: enlarging the preference margin does not necessarily improve generation quality. In particular, the standard Diffusion-DPO objective can increase the reconstruction error of both winner and loser branches. Consequently, degradation of the less-preferred outputs can become sufficiently severe that the preferred branch is also adversely affected even as the margin grows. To address this, we introduce Diffusion-SDPO, a safeguarded update rule that preserves the winner by adaptively scaling the loser gradient according to its alignment with the winner gradient. A first-order analysis yields a closed-form scaling coefficient that guarantees the error of the preferred output is non-increasing at each optimization step. Our method is simple, model-agnostic, broadly compatible with existing DPO-style alignment frameworks and adds only marginal computational overhead. Across standard text-to-image benchmarks, Diffusion-SDPO delivers consistent gains over preference-learning baselines on automated preference, aesthetic, and prompt alignment metrics. Code is publicly available at https://github.com/AIDC-AI/Diffusion-SDPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03317</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 09:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HaluMem: Evaluating Hallucinations in Memory Systems of Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03506</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03506.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ding Chen, Simin Niu, Kehang Li, Peng Liu, Xiangping Zheng, Bo Tang, Xinchi Li, Feiyu Xiong, Zhiyu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 85&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Memory systems are key components that enable AI systems such as LLMs and AI agents to achieve long-term learning and sustained interaction. However, during memory storage and retrieval, these systems frequently exhibit memory hallucinations, including fabrication, errors, conflicts, and omissions. Existing evaluations of memory hallucinations are primarily end-to-end question answering, which makes it difficult to localize the operational stage within the memory system where hallucinations arise. To address this, we introduce the Hallucination in Memory Benchmark (HaluMem), the first operation level hallucination evaluation benchmark tailored to memory systems. HaluMem defines three evaluation tasks (memory extraction, memory updating, and memory question answering) to comprehensively reveal hallucination behaviors across different operational stages of interaction. To support evaluation, we construct user-centric, multi-turn human-AI interaction datasets, HaluMem-Medium and HaluMem-Long. Both include about 15k memory points and 3.5k multi-type questions. The average dialogue length per user reaches 1.5k and 2.6k turns, with context lengths exceeding 1M tokens, enabling evaluation of hallucinations across different context scales and task complexities. Empirical studies based on HaluMem show that existing memory systems tend to generate and accumulate hallucinations during the extraction and updating stages, which subsequently propagate errors to the question answering stage. Future research should focus on developing interpretable and constrained memory operation mechanisms that systematically suppress hallucinations and improve memory reliability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03506</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:37:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLoop: An Self-Improving Framework for Reinforcement Learning with   Iterative Policy Initialization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04285</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04285.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeng Zhiyuan, Jiashuo Liu, Zhangyue Yin, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Reinforcement Learning for Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) is powerful for training large reasoning models, its training dynamics harbor a critical challenge: RL overfitting, where models gain training rewards but lose generalization. Our analysis reveals this is driven by policy over-specialization and catastrophic forgetting of diverse solutions generated during training. Standard optimization discards this valuable inter-step policy diversity. To address this, we introduce RLoop, a self-improving framework built on iterative policy initialization. RLoop transforms the standard training process into a virtuous cycle: it first uses RL to explore the solution space from a given policy, then filters the successful trajectories to create an expert dataset. This dataset is used via Rejection-sampling Fine-Tuning (RFT) to refine the initial policy, creating a superior starting point for the next iteration. This loop of exploration and exploitation via iterative re-initialization effectively converts transient policy variations into robust performance gains. Our experiments show RLoop mitigates forgetting and substantially improves generalization, boosting average accuracy by 9% and pass@32 by over 15% compared to vanilla RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04285</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 11:27:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VeriCoT: Neuro-symbolic Chain-of-Thought Validation via Logical   Consistency Checks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04662</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04662.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Feng, Nathaniel Weir, Kaj Bostrom, Sam Bayless, Darion Cassel, Sapana Chaudhary, Benjamin Kiesl-Reiter, Huzefa Rangwala&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLMs can perform multi-step reasoning through Chain-of-Thought (CoT), but they cannot reliably verify their own logic. Even when they reach correct answers, the underlying reasoning may be flawed, undermining trust in high-stakes scenarios. To mitigate this issue, we introduce VeriCoT, a neuro-symbolic method that extracts and verifies formal logical arguments from CoT reasoning. VeriCoT formalizes each CoT reasoning step into first-order logic and identifies premises that ground the argument in source context, commonsense knowledge, or prior reasoning steps. The symbolic representation enables automated solvers to verify logical validity while the NL premises allow humans and systems to identify ungrounded or fallacious reasoning steps. Experiments on the ProofWriter, LegalBench, and BioASQ datasets show VeriCoT effectively identifies flawed reasoning, and serves as a strong predictor of final answer correctness. We also leverage VeriCoT's verification signal for (1) inference-time self-reflection, (2) supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on VeriCoT-distilled datasets and (3) preference fine-tuning (PFT) with direct preference optimization (DPO) using verification-based pairwise rewards, further improving reasoning validity and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04662</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:50:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agentic Refactoring: An Empirical Study of AI Coding Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04824</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04824.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kosei Horikawa, Hao Li, Yutaro Kashiwa, Bram Adams, Hajimu Iida, Ahmed E. Hassan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic coding tools, such as OpenAI Codex, Claude Code, and Cursor, are transforming the software engineering landscape. These AI-powered systems function as autonomous teammates capable of planning and executing complex development tasks. Agents have become active participants in refactoring, a cornerstone of sustainable software development aimed at improving internal code quality without altering observable behavior. Despite their increasing adoption, there is a critical lack of empirical understanding regarding how agentic refactoring is utilized in practice, how it compares to human-driven refactoring, and what impact it has on code quality. To address this empirical gap, we present a large-scale study of AI agent-generated refactorings in real-world open-source Java projects, analyzing 15,451 refactoring instances across 12,256 pull requests and 14,988 commits derived from the AIDev dataset. Our empirical analysis shows that refactoring is a common and intentional activity in this development paradigm, with agents explicitly targeting refactoring in 26.1% of commits. Analysis of refactoring types reveals that agentic efforts are dominated by low-level, consistency-oriented edits, such as Change Variable Type (11.8%), Rename Parameter (10.4%), and Rename Variable (8.5%), reflecting a preference for localized improvements over the high-level design changes common in human refactoring. Additionally, the motivations behind agentic refactoring focus overwhelmingly on internal quality concerns, with maintainability (52.5%) and readability (28.1%). Furthermore, quantitative evaluation of code quality metrics shows that agentic refactoring yields small but statistically significant improvements in structural metrics, particularly for medium-level changes, reducing class size and complexity (e.g., Class LOC median Δ = -15.25).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04824</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 21:24:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Reasoning Agents in Evolving Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04898</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04898.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yule Wen, Yixin Ye, Yanzhe Zhang, Diyi Yang, Hao Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agents in the real world must make not only logical but also timely judgments. This requires continuous awareness of the dynamic environment: hazards emerge, opportunities arise, and other agents act, while the agent's reasoning is still unfolding. Despite advances in language model reasoning, existing approaches fail to account for this dynamic nature. We introduce real-time reasoning as a new problem formulation for agents in evolving environments and build Real-Time Reasoning Gym to demonstrate it. We study two paradigms for deploying language models in agents: (1) reactive agents, which employ language models with bounded reasoning computation for rapid responses, and (2) planning agents, which allow extended reasoning computation for complex problems. Our experiments show that even state-of-the-art models struggle with making logical and timely judgments in either paradigm. To address this limitation, we propose AgileThinker, which simultaneously engages both reasoning paradigms. AgileThinker consistently outperforms agents engaging only one reasoning paradigm as the task difficulty and time pressure rise, effectively balancing reasoning depth and response latency. Our work establishes real-time reasoning as a critical testbed for developing practical agents and provides a foundation for research in temporally constrained AI systems, highlighting a path toward real-time capable agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04898</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:51:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Too Good to be Bad: On the Failure of LLMs to Role-Play Villains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04962</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04962.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihao Yi, Qingxuan Jiang, Ruotian Ma, Xingyu Chen, Qu Yang, Mengru Wang, Fanghua Ye, Ying Shen, Zhaopeng Tu, Xiaolong Li, Linus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly tasked with creative generation, including the simulation of fictional characters. However, their ability to portray non-prosocial, antagonistic personas remains largely unexamined. We hypothesize that the safety alignment of modern LLMs creates a fundamental conflict with the task of authentically role-playing morally ambiguous or villainous characters. To investigate this, we introduce the Moral RolePlay benchmark, a new dataset featuring a four-level moral alignment scale and a balanced test set for rigorous evaluation. We task state-of-the-art LLMs with role-playing characters from moral paragons to pure villains. Our large-scale evaluation reveals a consistent, monotonic decline in role-playing fidelity as character morality decreases. We find that models struggle most with traits directly antithetical to safety principles, such as ``Deceitful'' and ``Manipulative'', often substituting nuanced malevolence with superficial aggression. Furthermore, we demonstrate that general chatbot proficiency is a poor predictor of villain role-playing ability, with highly safety-aligned models performing particularly poorly. Our work provides the first systematic evidence of this critical limitation, highlighting a key tension between model safety and creative fidelity. Our benchmark and findings pave the way for developing more nuanced, context-aware alignment methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04962</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 03:50:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Mitigating Hallucinations in Large Vision-Language Models by   Refining Textual Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05017</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05017.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aakriti Agrawal, Gouthaman KV, Rohith Aralikatti, Gauri Jagatap, Jiaxin Yuan, Vijay Kamarshi, Andrea Fanelli, Furong Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we identify an inherent bias in prevailing LVLM architectures toward the language modality, largely resulting from the common practice of simply appending visual embeddings to the input text sequence. To address this, we propose a simple yet effective method that refines textual embeddings by integrating average-pooled visual features. Our approach demonstrably improves visual grounding and significantly reduces hallucinations on established benchmarks. While average pooling offers a straightforward, robust, and efficient means of incorporating visual information, we believe that more sophisticated fusion methods could further enhance visual grounding and cross-modal alignment. Given that the primary focus of this work is to highlight the modality imbalance and its impact on hallucinations -- and to show that refining textual embeddings with visual information mitigates this issue -- we leave exploration of advanced fusion strategies for future work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05017</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 06:39:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motif 2 12.7B technical report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07464</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07464.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junghwan Lim, Sungmin Lee, Dongseok Kim, Taehyun Kim, Eunhwan Park, Jeesoo Lee, Jeongdoo Lee, Junhyeok Lee, Wai Ting Cheung, Dahye Choi, Jaeheui Her, Jaeyeon Huh, Hanbin Jung, Changjin Kang, Beomgyu Kim, Minjae Kim, Taewhan Kim, Youngrok Kim, Hyukjin Kweon, Haesol Lee, Kungyu Lee, Dongpin Oh, Yeongjae Park, Bokki Ryu, Dongjoo Weon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Motif-2-12.7B, a new open-weight foundation model that pushes the efficiency frontier of large language models by combining architectural innovation with system-level optimization. Designed for scalable language understanding and robust instruction generalization under constrained compute budgets, Motif-2-12.7B builds upon Motif-2.6B with the integration of Grouped Differential Attention (GDA), which improves representational efficiency by disentangling signal and noise-control attention pathways. The model is pre-trained on 5.5 trillion tokens spanning diverse linguistic, mathematical, scientific, and programming domains using a curriculum-driven data scheduler that gradually changes the data composition ratio. The training system leverages the MuonClip optimizer alongside custom high-performance kernels, including fused PolyNorm activations and the Parallel Muon algorithm, yielding significant throughput and memory efficiency gains in large-scale distributed environments. Post-training employs a three-stage supervised fine-tuning pipeline that successively enhances general instruction adherence, compositional understanding, and linguistic precision. Motif-2-12.7B demonstrates competitive performance across diverse benchmarks, showing that thoughtful architectural scaling and optimized training design can rival the capabilities of much larger models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07464</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 10:32:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepEyesV2: Toward Agentic Multimodal Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05271</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05271.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jack Hong, Chenxiao Zhao, ChengLin Zhu, Weiheng Lu, Guohai Xu, Xing Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic multimodal models should not only comprehend text and images, but also actively invoke external tools, such as code execution environments and web search, and integrate these operations into reasoning. In this work, we introduce DeepEyesV2 and explore how to build an agentic multimodal model from the perspectives of data construction, training methods, and model evaluation. We observe that direct reinforcement learning alone fails to induce robust tool-use behavior. This phenomenon motivates a two-stage training pipeline: a cold-start stage to establish tool-use patterns, and reinforcement learning stage to further refine tool invocation. We curate a diverse, moderately challenging training dataset, specifically including examples where tool use is beneficial. We further introduce RealX-Bench, a comprehensive benchmark designed to evaluate real-world multimodal reasoning, which inherently requires the integration of multiple capabilities, including perception, search, and reasoning. We evaluate DeepEyesV2 on RealX-Bench and other representative benchmarks, demonstrating its effectiveness across real-world understanding, mathematical reasoning, and search-intensive tasks. Moreover, DeepEyesV2 exhibits task-adaptive tool invocation, tending to use image operations for perception tasks and numerical computations for reasoning tasks. Reinforcement learning further enables complex tool combinations and allows model to selectively invoke tools based on context. We hope our study can provide guidance for community in developing agentic multimodal models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05271</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 14:31:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dense Motion Captioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05369</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05369.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiyao Xu, Benedetta Liberatori, Gül Varol, Paolo Rota&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in 3D human motion and language integration have primarily focused on text-to-motion generation, leaving the task of motion understanding relatively unexplored. We introduce Dense Motion Captioning, a novel task that aims to temporally localize and caption actions within 3D human motion sequences. Current datasets fall short in providing detailed temporal annotations and predominantly consist of short sequences featuring few actions. To overcome these limitations, we present the Complex Motion Dataset (CompMo), the first large-scale dataset featuring richly annotated, complex motion sequences with precise temporal boundaries. Built through a carefully designed data generation pipeline, CompMo includes 60,000 motion sequences, each composed of multiple actions ranging from at least two to ten, accurately annotated with their temporal extents. We further present DEMO, a model that integrates a large language model with a simple motion adapter, trained to generate dense, temporally grounded captions. Our experiments show that DEMO substantially outperforms existing methods on CompMo as well as on adapted benchmarks, establishing a robust baseline for future research in 3D motion understanding and captioning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05369</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 15:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TimeSearch-R: Adaptive Temporal Search for Long-Form Video Understanding via Self-Verification Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05489</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05489.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junwen Pan, Qizhe Zhang, Rui Zhang, Ming Lu, Xin Wan, Yuan Zhang, Chang Liu, Qi She&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Temporal search aims to identify a minimal set of relevant frames from tens of thousands based on a given query, serving as a foundation for accurate long-form video understanding. Existing works attempt to progressively narrow the search space. However, these approaches typically rely on a hand-crafted search process, lacking end-to-end optimization for learning optimal search strategies. In this paper, we propose TimeSearch-R, which reformulates temporal search as interleaved text-video thinking, seamlessly integrating searching video clips into the reasoning process through reinforcement learning (RL). However, applying RL training methods, such as Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), to video reasoning can result in unsupervised intermediate search decisions. This leads to insufficient exploration of the video content and inconsistent logical reasoning. To address these issues, we introduce GRPO with Completeness Self-Verification (GRPO-CSV), which gathers searched video frames from the interleaved reasoning process and utilizes the same policy model to verify the adequacy of searched frames, thereby improving the completeness of video reasoning. Additionally, we construct datasets specifically designed for the SFT cold-start and RL training of GRPO-CSV, filtering out samples with weak temporal dependencies to enhance task difficulty and improve temporal search capabilities. Extensive experiments demonstrate that TimeSearch-R achieves significant improvements on temporal search benchmarks such as Haystack-LVBench and Haystack-Ego4D, as well as long-form video understanding benchmarks like VideoMME and MLVU. Notably, TimeSearch-R establishes a new state-of-the-art on LongVideoBench with 4.1% improvement over the base model Qwen2.5-VL and 2.0% over the advanced video reasoning model Video-R1. Our code is available at https://github.com/Time-Search/TimeSearch-R.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05489</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 18:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Spatial Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05491</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05491.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui Yang, Ziyu Zhu, Yanwei Li, Jingjia Huang, Shen Yan, Siyuan Zhou, Zhe Liu, Xiangtai Li, Shuangye Li, Wenqian Wang, Yi Lin, Hengshuang Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Capturing spatial relationships from visual inputs is a cornerstone of human-like general intelligence. Several previous studies have tried to enhance the spatial awareness of Vision-Language Models (VLMs) by adding extra expert encoders, which brings extra overhead and usually harms general capabilities. To enhance the spatial ability in general architectures, we introduce Visual Spatial Tuning (VST), a comprehensive framework to cultivate VLMs with human-like visuospatial abilities, from spatial perception to reasoning. We first attempt to enhance spatial perception in VLMs by constructing a large-scale dataset termed VST-P, which comprises 4.1 million samples spanning 19 skills across single views, multiple images, and videos. Then, we present VST-R, a curated dataset with 135K samples that instruct models to reason in space. In particular, we adopt a progressive training pipeline: supervised fine-tuning to build foundational spatial knowledge, followed by reinforcement learning to further improve spatial reasoning abilities. Without the side-effect to general capabilities, the proposed VST consistently achieves state-of-the-art results on several spatial benchmarks, including 34.8% on MMSI-Bench and 61.2% on VSIBench. It turns out that the Vision-Language-Action models can be significantly enhanced with the proposed spatial tuning paradigm, paving the way for more physically grounded AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05491</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 18:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Diversity and Quality through Base-Aligned Model Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05650</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05650.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yichen Wang, Chenghao Yang, Tenghao Huang, Muhao Chen, Jonathan May, Mina Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Alignment has greatly improved large language models (LLMs)' output quality at the cost of diversity, yielding highly similar outputs across generations. We propose Base-Aligned Model Collaboration (BACo), an inference-time token-level model collaboration framework that dynamically combines a base LLM with its aligned counterpart to optimize diversity and quality. Inspired by prior work (Fei et al., 2025), BACo employs routing strategies that determine, at each token, from which model to decode based on next-token prediction uncertainty and predicted contents' semantic role. Prior diversity-promoting methods, such as retraining, prompt engineering, and multi-sampling methods, improve diversity but often degrade quality or require costly decoding or post-training. In contrast, BACo achieves both high diversity and quality post hoc within a single pass, while offering strong controllability. We explore a family of routing strategies, across three open-ended generation tasks and 13 metrics covering diversity and quality, BACo consistently surpasses state-of-the-art inference-time baselines. With our best router, BACo achieves a 21.3% joint improvement in diversity and quality. Human evaluations also mirror these improvements. The results suggest that collaboration between base and aligned models can optimize and control diversity and quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05650</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KLASS: KL-Guided Fast Inference in Masked Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05664</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05664.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seo Hyun Kim, Sunwoo Hong, Hojung Jung, Youngrok Park, Se-Young Yun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Masked diffusion models have demonstrated competitive results on various tasks including language generation. However, due to its iterative refinement process, the inference is often bottlenecked by slow and static sampling speed. To overcome this problem, we introduce `KL-Adaptive Stability Sampling' (KLASS), a fast yet effective sampling method that exploits token-level KL divergence to identify stable, high-confidence predictions. By unmasking multiple tokens in each iteration without any additional model training, our approach speeds up generation significantly while maintaining sample quality. On reasoning benchmarks, KLASS achieves up to 2.78times wall-clock speedups while improving performance over standard greedy decoding, attaining state-of-the-art results among diffusion-based samplers. We further validate KLASS across diverse domains, including text, image, and molecular generation, showing its effectiveness as a broadly applicable sampler across different models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05664</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:05:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long Grounded Thoughts: Distilling Compositional Visual Reasoning Chains at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05705</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05705.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; David Acuna, Chao-Han Huck Yang, Yuntian Deng, Jaehun Jung, Ximing Lu, Prithviraj Ammanabrolu, Hyunwoo Kim, Yuan-Hong Liao, Yejin Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in multimodal reasoning has been driven largely by undisclosed datasets and proprietary data synthesis recipes, leaving open questions about how to systematically build large-scale, vision-centric reasoning datasets, particularly for tasks that go beyond visual math. In this work, we introduce a new reasoning data generation framework spanning diverse skills and levels of complexity with over 1M high-quality synthetic vision-centric questions. The dataset also includes preference data and instruction prompts supporting both offline and online RL. Our synthesis framework proceeds in two stages: (1) scale; and (2) complexity. Reasoning traces are then synthesized through a two-stage process that leverages VLMs and reasoning LLMs, producing CoT traces for VLMs that capture the richness and diverse cognitive behaviors found in frontier reasoning models. Remarkably, we show that finetuning Qwen2.5-VL-7B on our data outperforms all open-data baselines across all evaluated vision-centric benchmarks, and even surpasses strong closed-data models such as MiMo-VL-7B-RL on V* Bench, CV-Bench and MMStar-V. Perhaps most surprising, despite being entirely vision-centric, our data transfers positively to text-only reasoning (MMLU-Pro) and audio reasoning (MMAU), demonstrating its effectiveness. Similarly, despite not containing videos or embodied visual data, we observe notable gains when evaluating on a single-evidence embodied QA benchmark (NiEH). Finally, we use our data to analyze the entire VLM post-training pipeline. Our empirical analysis highlights that (i) SFT on high-quality data with non-linear reasoning traces is essential for effective online RL, (ii) staged offline RL matches online RL's performance while reducing compute demands, and (iii) careful SFT on high quality data can substantially improve out-of-domain, cross-modality transfer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05705</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 20:50:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning Improves Traversal of Hierarchical Knowledge in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05933</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05933.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Renfei Zhang, Manasa Kaniselvan, Niloofar Mireshghallah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) is often credited with improving language model reasoning and generalization at the expense of degrading memorized knowledge. We challenge this narrative by observing that RL-enhanced models consistently outperform their base and supervised fine-tuned (SFT) counterparts on pure knowledge recall tasks, particularly those requiring traversal of hierarchical, structured knowledge (e.g., medical codes). We hypothesize these gains stem not from newly acquired data, but from improved procedural skills in navigating and searching existing knowledge hierarchies within the model parameters. To support this hypothesis, we show that structured prompting, which explicitly guides SFTed models through hierarchical traversal, recovers most of the performance gap (reducing 24pp to 7pp on MedConceptsQA for DeepSeek-V3/R1). We further find that while prompting improves final-answer accuracy, RL-enhanced models retain superior ability to recall correct procedural paths on deep-retrieval tasks. Finally our layer-wise internal activation analysis reveals that while factual representations (e.g., activations for the statement "code 57.95 refers to urinary infection") maintain high cosine similarity between SFT and RL models, query representations (e.g., "what is code 57.95") diverge noticeably, indicating that RL primarily transforms how models traverse knowledge rather than the knowledge representation itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05933</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 08:56:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Open Challenges Steering the Future of Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05936</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05936.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Soujanya Poria, Navonil Majumder, Chia-Yu Hung, Amir Ali Bagherzadeh, Chuan Li, Kenneth Kwok, Ziwei Wang, Cheston Tan, Jiajun Wu, David Hsu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Due to their ability of follow natural language instructions, vision-language-action (VLA) models are increasingly prevalent in the embodied AI arena, following the widespread success of their precursors -- LLMs and VLMs. In this paper, we discuss 10 principal milestones in the ongoing development of VLA models -- multimodality, reasoning, data, evaluation, cross-robot action generalization, efficiency, whole-body coordination, safety, agents, and coordination with humans. Furthermore, we discuss the emerging trends of using spatial understanding, modeling world dynamics, post training, and data synthesis -- all aiming to reach these milestones. Through these discussions, we hope to bring attention to the research avenues that may accelerate the development of VLA models into wider acceptability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05936</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 09:02:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stemming Hallucination in Language Models Using a Licensing Oracle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06073</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06073.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Simeon Emanuilov, Richard Ackermann&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language models exhibit remarkable natural language generation capabilities but remain prone to hallucinations, generating factually incorrect information despite producing syntactically coherent responses. This study introduces the Licensing Oracle, an architectural solution designed to stem hallucinations in LMs by enforcing truth constraints through formal validation against structured knowledge graphs. Unlike statistical approaches that rely on data scaling or fine-tuning, the Licensing Oracle embeds a deterministic validation step into the model's generative process, ensuring that only factually accurate claims are made. We evaluated the effectiveness of the Licensing Oracle through experiments comparing it with several state-of-the-art methods, including baseline language model generation, fine-tuning for factual recall, fine-tuning for abstention behavior, and retrieval-augmented generation (RAG). Our results demonstrate that although RAG and fine-tuning improve performance, they fail to eliminate hallucinations. In contrast, the Licensing Oracle achieved perfect abstention precision (AP = 1.0) and zero false answers (FAR-NE = 0.0), ensuring that only valid claims were generated with 89.1% accuracy in factual responses. This work shows that architectural innovations, such as the Licensing Oracle, offer a necessary and sufficient solution for hallucinations in domains with structured knowledge representations, offering guarantees that statistical methods cannot match. Although the Licensing Oracle is specifically designed to address hallucinations in fact-based domains, its framework lays the groundwork for truth-constrained generation in future AI systems, providing a new path toward reliable, epistemically grounded models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06073</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 17:07:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-fficiency: Can Language Models Optimize Real-World Repositories on Real Workloads?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06090</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06090.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jeffrey Jian Ma, Milad Hashemi, Amir Yazdanbakhsh, Kevin Swersky, Ofir Press, Enhui Li, Vijay Janapa Reddi, Parthasarathy Ranganathan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Optimizing the performance of large-scale software repositories demands expertise in code reasoning and software engineering (SWE) to reduce runtime while preserving program correctness. However, most benchmarks emphasize what to fix rather than how to fix code. We introduce SWE-fficiency, a benchmark for evaluating repository-level performance optimization on real workloads. Our suite contains 498 tasks across nine widely used data-science, machine-learning, and HPC repositories (e.g., numpy, pandas, scipy): given a complete codebase and a slow workload, an agent must investigate code semantics, localize bottlenecks and relevant tests, and produce a patch that matches or exceeds expert speedup while passing the same unit tests. To enable this how-to-fix evaluation, our automated pipeline scrapes GitHub pull requests for performance-improving edits, combining keyword filtering, static analysis, coverage tooling, and execution validation to both confirm expert speedup baselines and identify relevant repository unit tests. Empirical evaluation of state-of-the-art agents reveals significant underperformance. On average, agents achieve less than 0.15x the expert speedup: agents struggle in localizing optimization opportunities, reasoning about execution across functions, and maintaining correctness in proposed edits. We release the benchmark and accompanying data pipeline to facilitate research on automated performance engineering and long-horizon software reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06090</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 17:55:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adapting Web Agents with Synthetic Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06101</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06101.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoyang Wang, Yiming Liang, Xuchao Zhang, Qianhui Wu, Siwei Han, Anson Bastos, Rujia Wang, Chetan Bansal, Baolin Peng, Jianfeng Gao, Saravan Rajmohan, Huaxiu Yao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Web agents struggle to adapt to new websites due to the scarcity of environment specific tasks and demonstrations. Recent works have explored synthetic data generation to address this challenge, however, they suffer from data quality issues where synthesized tasks contain hallucinations that cannot be executed, and collected trajectories are noisy with redundant or misaligned actions. In this paper, we propose SynthAgent, a fully synthetic supervision framework that aims at improving synthetic data quality via dual refinement of both tasks and trajectories. Our approach begins by synthesizing diverse tasks through categorized exploration of web elements, ensuring efficient coverage of the target environment. During trajectory collection, we refine tasks when conflicts with actual observations are detected, mitigating hallucinations while maintaining task consistency. After collection, we conduct trajectory refinement with a global context to mitigate potential noise or misalignments. Finally, we fine-tune open-source web agents on the refined synthetic data to adapt them to the target environment. Experimental results demonstrate that SynthAgent outperforms existing synthetic data methods, validating the importance of high-quality synthetic supervision. The code will be publicly available at https://github.com/aiming-lab/SynthAgent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06101</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 18:45:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LUT-LLM: Efficient Large Language Model Inference with Memory-based   Computations on FPGAs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06174</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06174.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zifan He, Shengyu Ye, Rui Ma, Yang Wang, Jason Cong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid progress of large language models (LLMs) has advanced numerous applications, yet efficient single-batch inference remains vital for on-device intelligence. While FPGAs offer fine-grained data control and high energy efficiency, recent GPU optimizations have narrowed their advantage, especially under arithmetic-based computation. To overcome this, we leverage FPGAs' abundant on-chip memory to shift LLM inference from arithmetic- to memory-based computation through table lookups. We present LUT-LLM, the first FPGA accelerator enabling 1B+ LLM inference via vector-quantized memory operations. Our analysis identifies activation-weight co-quantization as the most effective scheme, supported by (1) bandwidth-aware parallel centroid search, (2) efficient 2D table lookups, and (3) a spatial-temporal hybrid design minimizing data caching. Implemented on an AMD V80 FPGA for a customized Qwen 3 1.7B model, LUT-LLM achieves 1.66x lower latency than AMD MI210 and 1.72x higher energy efficiency than NVIDIA A100, scaling to 32B models with 2.16x efficiency gain over A100.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06174</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 01:17:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NURBGen: High-Fidelity Text-to-CAD Generation through LLM-Driven NURBS   Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06194</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06194.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muhammad Usama, Mohammad Sadil Khan, Didier Stricker, Muhammad Zeshan Afzal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating editable 3D CAD models from natural language remains challenging, as existing text-to-CAD systems either produce meshes or rely on scarce design-history data. We present NURBGen, the first framework to generate high-fidelity 3D CAD models directly from text using Non-Uniform Rational B-Splines (NURBS). To achieve this, we fine-tune a large language model (LLM) to translate free-form texts into JSON representations containing NURBS surface parameters (i.e, control points, knot vectors, degrees, and rational weights) which can be directly converted into BRep format using Python. We further propose a hybrid representation that combines untrimmed NURBS with analytic primitives to handle trimmed surfaces and degenerate regions more robustly, while reducing token complexity. Additionally, we introduce partABC, a curated subset of the ABC dataset consisting of individual CAD components, annotated with detailed captions using an automated annotation pipeline. NURBGen demonstrates strong performance on diverse prompts, surpassing prior methods in geometric fidelity and dimensional accuracy, as confirmed by expert evaluations. Code and dataset will be released publicly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06194</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 02:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning with Confidence: Efficient Verification of LLM Reasoning Steps   via Uncertainty Heads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06209</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06209.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingwei Ni, Ekaterina Fadeeva, Tianyi Wu, Mubashara Akhtar, Jiaheng Zhang, Elliott Ash, Markus Leippold, Timothy Baldwin, See-Kiong Ng, Artem Shelmanov, Mrinmaya Sachan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Solving complex tasks usually requires LLMs to generate long multi-step reasoning chains. Previous work has shown that verifying the correctness of individual reasoning steps can further improve the performance and efficiency of LLMs on such tasks and enhance solution interpretability. However, existing verification approaches, such as Process Reward Models (PRMs), are either computationally expensive, limited to specific domains, or require large-scale human or model-generated annotations. Thus, we propose a lightweight alternative for step-level reasoning verification based on data-driven uncertainty scores. We train transformer-based uncertainty quantification heads (UHeads) that use the internal states of a frozen LLM to estimate the uncertainty of its reasoning steps during generation. The approach is fully automatic: target labels are generated either by another larger LLM (e.g., DeepSeek R1) or in a self-supervised manner by the original model itself. UHeads are both effective and lightweight, containing less than 10M parameters. Across multiple domains, including mathematics, planning, and general knowledge question answering, they match or even surpass the performance of PRMs that are up to 810x larger. Our findings suggest that the internal states of LLMs encode their uncertainty and can serve as reliable signals for reasoning verification, offering a promising direction toward scalable and generalizable introspective LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06209</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 03:38:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tiny Model, Big Logic: Diversity-Driven Optimization Elicits Large-Model   Reasoning Ability in VibeThinker-1.5B</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06221</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06221.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sen Xu, Yi Zhou, Wei Wang, Jixin Min, Zhibin Yin, Yingwei Dai, Shixi Liu, Lianyu Pang, Yirong Chen, Junlin Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 94&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Challenging the prevailing consensus that small models inherently lack robust reasoning, this report introduces VibeThinker-1.5B, a 1.5B-parameter dense model developed via our Spectrum-to-Signal Principle (SSP). This challenges the prevailing approach of scaling model parameters to enhance capabilities, as seen in models like DeepSeek R1 (671B) and Kimi k2 (&gt;1T). The SSP framework first employs a Two-Stage Diversity-Exploring Distillation (SFT) to generate a broad spectrum of solutions, followed by MaxEnt-Guided Policy Optimization (RL) to amplify the correct signal. With a total training cost of only $7,800, VibeThinker-1.5B demonstrates superior reasoning capabilities compared to closed-source models like Magistral Medium and Claude Opus 4, and performs on par with open-source models like GPT OSS-20B Medium. Remarkably, it surpasses the 400x larger DeepSeek R1 on three math benchmarks: AIME24 (80.3 vs. 79.8), AIME25 (74.4 vs. 70.0), and HMMT25 (50.4 vs. 41.7). This is a substantial improvement over its base model (6.7, 4.3, and 0.6, respectively). On LiveCodeBench V6, it scores 51.1, outperforming Magistral Medium's 50.3 and its base model's 0.0. These findings demonstrate that small models can achieve reasoning capabilities comparable to large models, drastically reducing training and inference costs and thereby democratizing advanced AI research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06221</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 04:37:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebVIA: A Web-based Vision-Language Agentic Framework for Interactive and Verifiable UI-to-Code Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06251</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06251.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingde Xu, Zhen Yang, Wenyi Hong, Lihang Pan, Xinyue Fan, Yan Wang, Xiaotao Gu, Bin Xu, Jie Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; User interface (UI) development requires translating design mockups into functional code, a process that remains repetitive and labor-intensive. While recent Vision-Language Models (VLMs) automate UI-to-Code generation, they generate only static HTML/CSS/JavaScript layouts lacking interactivity. To address this, we propose WebVIA, the first agentic framework for interactive UI-to-Code generation and validation. The framework comprises three components: 1) an exploration agent to capture multi-state UI screenshots; 2) a UI2Code model that generates executable interactive code; 3) a validation module that verifies the interactivity. Experiments demonstrate that WebVIA-Agent achieves more stable and accurate UI exploration than general-purpose agents (e.g., Gemini-2.5-Pro). In addition, our fine-tuned WebVIA-UI2Code models exhibit substantial improvements in generating executable and interactive HTML/CSS/JavaScript code, outperforming their base counterparts across both interactive and static UI2Code benchmarks. Our code and models are available at https://zheny2751-dotcom.github.io/webvia.github.io/{https://webvia.github.io}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06251</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 06:58:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoSSR: Video Self-Supervised Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06281</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06281.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zefeng He, Xiaoye Qu, Yafu Li, Siyuan Huang, Daizong Liu, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has substantially advanced the video understanding capabilities of Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs). However, the rapid progress of MLLMs is outpacing the complexity of existing video datasets, while the manual annotation of new, high-quality data remains prohibitively expensive. This work investigates a pivotal question: Can the rich, intrinsic information within videos be harnessed to self-generate high-quality, verifiable training data? To investigate this, we introduce three self-supervised pretext tasks: Anomaly Grounding, Object Counting, and Temporal Jigsaw. We construct the Video Intrinsic Understanding Benchmark (VIUBench) to validate their difficulty, revealing that current state-of-the-art MLLMs struggle significantly on these tasks. Building upon these pretext tasks, we develop the VideoSSR-30K dataset and propose VideoSSR, a novel video self-supervised reinforcement learning framework for RLVR. Extensive experiments across 17 benchmarks, spanning four major video domains (General Video QA, Long Video QA, Temporal Grounding, and Complex Reasoning), demonstrate that VideoSSR consistently enhances model performance, yielding an average improvement of over 5\%. These results establish VideoSSR as a potent foundational framework for developing more advanced video understanding in MLLMs. The code is available at https://github.com/lcqysl/VideoSSR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06281</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 08:36:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DRIVE: Data Curation Best Practices for Reinforcement Learning with   Verifiable Reward in Competitive Code Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06307</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06307.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Speed Zhu, Jianwei Cai, Guang Chen, Lulu Wu, Saiyong Yang, Wiggin Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reasoning-first models (e.g., OpenAI o1, DeepSeek R1) have spurred a resurgence of interest in RLVR. Nevertheless, advances are dominated by mathematics (e.g., AIME), with competitive-programming code generation underexplored and data curation receiving less attention than RL algorithm design. We investigate how to construct RLVR datasets (i.e., RL prompts) and present practical training techniques that yield strong performance on competitive-programming code generation. Our pipeline begins with supervised fine-tuning (SFT) distilled from strong open-source models, augmented with general-purpose and reasoning-intensive data. RL then follows a two-stage process with executable, testcase-driven rewards: first, training on a large, uniformly distributed set of competitive-programming problems using Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) with 8 rollouts per prompt and a relatively short response-generation window (e.g., 32k during SFT and 24k in this stage) to expand entropy and mitigate repetition and truncation; second, we perform Pre-GRPO: updating on a small, high-quality set of challenging problems with a large rollout budget (64 rollouts per prompt) under a hard-focus curriculum that continuously retains the most difficult instances throughout training. We implement our method on Qwen2.5-32B and evaluate on LeetCode and Codeforces weekly contests to avoid data leakage. The resulting model achieves state-of-the-art performance among models of similar scale and is comparable to leading systems such as DeepSeek v3.1 and Doubao-1.5-Thinking. We also examine scaling trends and observe strong RL scaling on an internal large-scale MoE model. Our study distills concise best practices for data curation, entropy expansion, and curriculum design in RLVR for competitive-programming code generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06307</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 10:11:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Station: An Open-World Environment for AI-Driven Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06309</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06309.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Stephen Chung, Wenyu Du&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce the STATION, an open-world multi-agent environment that models a miniature scientific ecosystem. Leveraging their extended context windows, agents in the Station can engage in long scientific journeys that include reading papers from peers, formulating hypotheses, submitting code, performing analyses, and publishing results. Importantly, there is no centralized system coordinating their activities - agents are free to choose their own actions and develop their own narratives within the Station. Experiments demonstrate that AI agents in the Station achieve new state-of-the-art performance on a wide range of benchmarks, spanning from mathematics to computational biology to machine learning, notably surpassing AlphaEvolve in circle packing. A rich tapestry of narratives emerges as agents pursue independent research, interact with peers, and build upon a cumulative history. From these emergent narratives, novel methods arise organically, such as a new density-adaptive algorithm for scRNA-seq batch integration. The Station marks a first step towards autonomous scientific discovery driven by emergent behavior in an open-world environment, representing a new paradigm that moves beyond rigid optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06309</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 10:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SofT-GRPO: Surpassing Discrete-Token LLM Reinforcement Learning via   Gumbel-Reparameterized Soft-Thinking Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06411</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06411.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhi Zheng, Wee Sun Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The soft-thinking paradigm for Large Language Model (LLM) reasoning can outperform the conventional discrete-token Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning in some scenarios, underscoring its research and application value. However, while the discrete-token CoT reasoning pattern can be reinforced through policy optimization algorithms such as group relative policy optimization (GRPO), extending the soft-thinking pattern with Reinforcement Learning (RL) remains challenging. This difficulty stems from the complexities of injecting stochasticity into soft-thinking tokens and updating soft-thinking policies accordingly. As a result, previous attempts to combine soft-thinking with GRPO typically underperform their discrete-token GRPO counterparts. To fully unlock the potential of soft-thinking, this paper presents a novel policy optimization algorithm, SofT-GRPO, to reinforce LLMs under the soft-thinking reasoning pattern. SofT-GRPO injects the Gumbel noise into logits, employs the Gumbel-Softmax technique to avoid soft-thinking tokens outside the pre-trained embedding space, and leverages the reparameterization trick in policy gradient. We conduct experiments across base LLMs ranging from 1.5B to 7B parameters, and results demonstrate that SofT-GRPO enables soft-thinking LLMs to slightly outperform discrete-token GRPO on Pass@1 (+0.13% on average accuracy), while exhibiting a substantial uplift on Pass@32 (+2.19% on average accuracy). Codes and weights are available on https://github.com/zz1358m/SofT-GRPO-master&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06411</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 14:55:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Walking the Tightrope of LLMs for Software Development: A Practitioners' Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06428</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06428.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Samuel Ferino, Rashina Hoda, John Grundy, Christoph Treude&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Background: Large Language Models emerged with the potential of provoking a revolution in software development (e.g., automating processes, workforce transformation). Although studies have started to investigate the perceived impact of LLMs for software development, there is a need for empirical studies to comprehend how to balance forward and backward effects of using LLMs. Objective: We investigated how LLMs impact software development and how to manage the impact from a software developer's perspective. Method: We conducted 22 interviews with software practitioners across 3 rounds of data collection and analysis, between October (2024) and September (2025). We employed socio-technical grounded theory (STGT) for data analysis to rigorously analyse interview participants' responses. Results: We identified the benefits (e.g., maintain software development flow, improve developers' mental model, and foster entrepreneurship) and disadvantages (e.g., negative impact on developers' personality and damage to developers' reputation) of using LLMs at individual, team, organisation, and society levels; as well as best practices on how to adopt LLMs. Conclusion: Critically, we present the trade-offs that software practitioners, teams, and organisations face in working with LLMs. Our findings are particularly useful for software team leaders and IT managers to assess the viability of LLMs within their specific context.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06428</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 15:49:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FLEX: Continuous Agent Evolution via Forward Learning from Experience</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06449</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06449.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhicheng Cai, Xinyuan Guo, Yu Pei, JiangTao Feng, Jiangjie Chen, Ya-Qin Zhang, Wei-Ying Ma, Mingxuan Wang, Hao Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autonomous agents driven by Large Language Models (LLMs) have revolutionized reasoning and problem-solving but remain static after training, unable to grow with experience as intelligent beings do during deployment. We introduce Forward Learning with EXperience (FLEX), a gradient-free learning paradigm that enables LLM agents to continuously evolve through accumulated experience. Specifically, FLEX cultivates scalable and inheritable evolution by constructing a structured experience library through continual reflection on successes and failures during interaction with the environment. FLEX delivers substantial improvements on mathematical reasoning, chemical retrosynthesis, and protein fitness prediction (up to 23% on AIME25, 10% on USPTO50k, and 14% on ProteinGym). We further identify a clear scaling law of experiential growth and the phenomenon of experience inheritance across agents, marking a step toward scalable and inheritable continuous agent evolution. Project Page: https://flex-gensi-thuair.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06449</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 16:31:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-to-Move: Training-Free Motion Controlled Video Generation via Dual-Clock Denoising</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08633</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08633.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Assaf Singer, Noam Rotstein, Amir Mann, Ron Kimmel, Or Litany&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion-based video generation can create realistic videos, yet existing image- and text-based conditioning fails to offer precise motion control. Prior methods for motion-conditioned synthesis typically require model-specific fine-tuning, which is computationally expensive and restrictive. We introduce Time-to-Move (TTM), a training-free, plug-and-play framework for motion- and appearance-controlled video generation with image-to-video (I2V) diffusion models. Our key insight is to use crude reference animations obtained through user-friendly manipulations such as cut-and-drag or depth-based reprojection. Motivated by SDEdit's use of coarse layout cues for image editing, we treat the crude animations as coarse motion cues and adapt the mechanism to the video domain. We preserve appearance with image conditioning and introduce dual-clock denoising, a region-dependent strategy that enforces strong alignment in motion-specified regions while allowing flexibility elsewhere, balancing fidelity to user intent with natural dynamics. This lightweight modification of the sampling process incurs no additional training or runtime cost and is compatible with any backbone. Extensive experiments on object and camera motion benchmarks show that TTM matches or exceeds existing training-based baselines in realism and motion control. Beyond this, TTM introduces a unique capability: precise appearance control through pixel-level conditioning, exceeding the limits of text-only prompting. Visit our project page for video examples and code: https://time-to-move.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08633</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 22:47:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MathSE: Improving Multimodal Mathematical Reasoning via Self-Evolving Iterative Reflection and Reward-Guided Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06805</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06805.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinhao Chen, Zhen Yang, Jianxin Shi, Tianyu Wo, Jie Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in vision-language answering tasks. Despite their strengths, these models often encounter challenges in achieving complex reasoning tasks such as mathematical problem-solving. Previous works have focused on fine-tuning on specialized mathematical datasets. However, these datasets are typically distilled directly from teacher models, which capture only static reasoning patterns and leaving substantial gaps compared to student models. This reliance on fixed teacher-derived datasets not only restricts the model's ability to adapt to novel or more intricate questions that extend beyond the confines of the training data, but also lacks the iterative depth needed for robust generalization. To overcome these limitations, we propose \method, a Mathematical Self-Evolving framework for MLLMs. In contrast to traditional one-shot fine-tuning paradigms, \method iteratively refines the model through cycles of inference, reflection, and reward-based feedback. Specifically, we leverage iterative fine-tuning by incorporating correct reasoning paths derived from previous-stage inference and integrating reflections from a specialized Outcome Reward Model (ORM). To verify the effectiveness of \method, we evaluate it on a suite of challenging benchmarks, demonstrating significant performance gains over backbone models. Notably, our experimental results on MathVL-test surpass the leading open-source multimodal mathematical reasoning model QVQ. Our code and models are available at https://zheny2751\allowbreak-dotcom.github.io/\allowbreak MathSE.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06805</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 07:46:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating an Image From 1,000 Words: Enhancing Text-to-Image With   Structured Captions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06876</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06876.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Eyal Gutflaish, Eliran Kachlon, Hezi Zisman, Tal Hacham, Nimrod Sarid, Alexander Visheratin, Saar Huberman, Gal Davidi, Guy Bukchin, Kfir Goldberg, Ron Mokady&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-image models have rapidly evolved from casual creative tools to professional-grade systems, achieving unprecedented levels of image quality and realism. Yet, most models are trained to map short prompts into detailed images, creating a gap between sparse textual input and rich visual outputs. This mismatch reduces controllability, as models often fill in missing details arbitrarily, biasing toward average user preferences and limiting precision for professional use. We address this limitation by training the first open-source text-to-image model on long structured captions, where every training sample is annotated with the same set of fine-grained attributes. This design maximizes expressive coverage and enables disentangled control over visual factors. To process long captions efficiently, we propose DimFusion, a fusion mechanism that integrates intermediate tokens from a lightweight LLM without increasing token length. We also introduce the Text-as-a-Bottleneck Reconstruction (TaBR) evaluation protocol. By assessing how well real images can be reconstructed through a captioning-generation loop, TaBR directly measures controllability and expressiveness, even for very long captions where existing evaluation methods fail. Finally, we demonstrate our contributions by training the large-scale model FIBO, achieving state-of-the-art prompt alignment among open-source models. Model weights are publicly available at https://huggingface.co/briaai/FIBO&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06876</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 09:25:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond English: Toward Inclusive and Scalable Multilingual Machine Translation with LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07003</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07003.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yingfeng Luo, Ziqiang Xu, Yuxuan Ouyang, Murun Yang, Dingyang Lin, Kaiyan Chang, Tong Zheng, Bei Li, Peinan Feng, Quan Du, Tong Xiao, Jingbo Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models have significantly advanced Multilingual Machine Translation (MMT), yet the broad language coverage, consistent translation quality, and English-centric bias remain open challenges. To address these challenges, we introduce LMT, a suite of Large-scale Multilingual Translation models centered on both Chinese and English, covering 60 languages and 234 translation directions. During development, we identify a previously overlooked phenomenon of directional degeneration, where symmetric multi-way fine-tuning data overemphasize reverse directions (X to En/Zh), leading to excessive many-to-one mappings and degraded translation quality. We propose Strategic Downsampling, a simple yet effective method to mitigate this degeneration. In addition, we design Parallel Multilingual Prompting (PMP), which leverages typologically related auxiliary languages to enhance cross-lingual transfer. Through rigorous data curation and refined adaptation strategies, LMT achieves SOTA performance among models of comparable language coverage, with our 4B model (LMT-60-4B) surpassing the much larger Aya-101-13B and NLLB-54B models by a substantial margin. We release LMT in four sizes (0.6B/1.7B/4B/8B) to catalyze future research and provide strong baselines for inclusive, scalable, and high-quality MMT \href{https://github.com/NiuTrans/LMT{https://github.com/NiuTrans/LMT}}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07003</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 11:54:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Llama-Embed-Nemotron-8B: A Universal Text Embedding Model for   Multilingual and Cross-Lingual Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07025</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07025.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yauhen Babakhin, Radek Osmulski, Ronay Ak, Gabriel Moreira, Mengyao Xu, Benedikt Schifferer, Bo Liu, Even Oldridge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce llama-embed-nemotron-8b, an open-weights text embedding model that achieves state-of-the-art performance on the Multilingual Massive Text Embedding Benchmark (MMTEB) leaderboard as of October 21, 2025. While recent models show strong performance, their training data or methodologies are often not fully disclosed. We aim to address this by developing a fully open-source model, publicly releasing its weights and detailed ablation studies, and planning to share the curated training datasets. Our model demonstrates superior performance across all major embedding tasks -- including retrieval, classification and semantic textual similarity (STS) -- and excels in challenging multilingual scenarios, such as low-resource languages and cross-lingual setups. This state-of-the-art performance is driven by a novel data mix of 16.1 million query-document pairs, split between 7.7 million samples from public datasets and 8.4 million synthetically generated examples from various open-weight LLMs. One of our key contributions is a detailed ablation study analyzing core design choices, including a comparison of contrastive loss implementations, an evaluation of synthetic data generation (SDG) strategies, and the impact of model merging. The llama-embed-nemotron-8b is an instruction-aware model, supporting user-defined instructions to enhance performance for specific use-cases. This combination of top-tier performance, broad applicability, and user-driven flexibility enables it to serve as a universal text embedding solution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07025</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:13:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do LLMs Feel? Teaching Emotion Recognition with Prompts, Retrieval, and   Curriculum Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07061</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07061.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinran Li, Xiujuan Xu, Jiaqi Qiao, Yu Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Emotion Recognition in Conversation (ERC) is a crucial task for understanding human emotions and enabling natural human-computer interaction. Although Large Language Models (LLMs) have recently shown great potential in this field, their ability to capture the intrinsic connections between explicit and implicit emotions remains limited. We propose a novel ERC training framework, PRC-Emo, which integrates Prompt engineering, demonstration Retrieval, and Curriculum learning, with the goal of exploring whether LLMs can effectively perceive emotions in conversational contexts. Specifically, we design emotion-sensitive prompt templates based on both explicit and implicit emotional cues to better guide the model in understanding the speaker's psychological states. We construct the first dedicated demonstration retrieval repository for ERC, which includes training samples from widely used datasets, as well as high-quality dialogue examples generated by LLMs and manually verified. Moreover, we introduce a curriculum learning strategy into the LoRA fine-tuning process, incorporating weighted emotional shifts between same-speaker and different-speaker utterances to assign difficulty levels to dialogue samples, which are then organized in an easy-to-hard training sequence. Experimental results on two benchmark datasets-- IEMOCAP and MELD --show that our method achieves new state-of-the-art (SOTA) performance, demonstrating the effectiveness and generalizability of our approach in improving LLM-based emotional understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07061</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 12:52:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RedOne 2.0: Rethinking Domain-specific LLM Post-Training in Social   Networking Services</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07070</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07070.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fei Zhao, Chonggang Lu, Haofu Qian, Fangcheng Shi, Zijie Meng, Jianzhao Huang, Xu Tang, Zheyong Xie, Zheyu Ye, Zhe Xu, Yao Hu, Shaosheng Cao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As a key medium for human interaction and information exchange, social networking services (SNS) pose unique challenges for large language models (LLMs): heterogeneous workloads, fast-shifting norms and slang, and multilingual, culturally diverse corpora that induce sharp distribution shift. Supervised fine-tuning (SFT) can specialize models but often triggers a ``seesaw'' between in-distribution gains and out-of-distribution robustness, especially for smaller models. To address these challenges, we introduce RedOne 2.0, an SNS-oriented LLM trained with a progressive, RL-prioritized post-training paradigm designed for rapid and stable adaptation. The pipeline consist in three stages: (1) Exploratory Learning on curated SNS corpora to establish initial alignment and identify systematic weaknesses; (2) Targeted Fine-Tuning that selectively applies SFT to the diagnosed gaps while mixing a small fraction of general data to mitigate forgetting; and (3) Refinement Learning that re-applies RL with SNS-centric signals to consolidate improvements and harmonize trade-offs across tasks. Across various tasks spanning three categories, our 4B scale model delivers an average improvements about 2.41 over the 7B sub-optimal baseline. Additionally, RedOne 2.0 achieves average performance lift about 8.74 from the base model with less than half the data required by SFT-centric method RedOne, evidencing superior data efficiency and stability at compact scales. Overall, RedOne 2.0 establishes a competitive, cost-effective baseline for domain-specific LLMs in SNS scenario, advancing capability without sacrificing robustness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07070</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:04:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wasm: A Pipeline for Constructing Structured Arabic Interleaved   Multimodal Corpora</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07080</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07080.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Khalil Hennara, Ahmad Bastati, Muhammad Hreden, Mohamed Motasim Hamed, Zeina Aldallal, Sara Chrouf, Safwan AlModhayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The performance of large language models (LLMs) and large multimodal models (LMMs) depends heavily on the quality and scale of their pre-training datasets. Recent research shows that large multimodal models trained on natural documents where images and text are interleaved outperform those trained only on image-text pairs across a wide range of benchmarks, leveraging advanced pre- trained models to enforce semantic alignment, image-sequence consistency, and textual coherence. For Arabic, however, the lack of high-quality multimodal datasets that preserve document structure has limited progress. In this paper, we present our pipeline Wasm for processing the Common Crawl dataset to create a new Arabic multimodal dataset that uniquely provides markdown output. Unlike existing Arabic corpora that focus solely on text extraction, our approach preserves the structural integrity of web content while maintaining flexibility for both text-only and multimodal pre-training scenarios. We provide a comprehensive comparative analysis of our data processing pipeline against those used for major existing datasets, highlighting the convergences in filtering strategies and justifying our specific design choices. To support future research, we publicly release a representative dataset dump along with the multimodal processing pipeline for Arabic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07080</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:10:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MPJudge: Towards Perceptual Assessment of Music-Induced Paintings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07137</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07137.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiqi Jiang, Tianyi Liang, Changbo Wang, Chenhui Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Music induced painting is a unique artistic practice, where visual artworks are created under the influence of music. Evaluating whether a painting faithfully reflects the music that inspired it poses a challenging perceptual assessment task. Existing methods primarily rely on emotion recognition models to assess the similarity between music and painting, but such models introduce considerable noise and overlook broader perceptual cues beyond emotion. To address these limitations, we propose a novel framework for music induced painting assessment that directly models perceptual coherence between music and visual art. We introduce MPD, the first large scale dataset of music painting pairs annotated by domain experts based on perceptual coherence. To better handle ambiguous cases, we further collect pairwise preference annotations. Building on this dataset, we present MPJudge, a model that integrates music features into a visual encoder via a modulation based fusion mechanism. To effectively learn from ambiguous cases, we adopt Direct Preference Optimization for training. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method outperforms existing approaches. Qualitative results further show that our model more accurately identifies music relevant regions in paintings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07137</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 14:18:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward the Frontiers of Reliable Diffusion Sampling via Adversarial Sinkhorn Attention Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07499</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07499.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kwanyoung Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion models have demonstrated strong generative performance when using guidance methods such as classifier-free guidance (CFG), which enhance output quality by modifying the sampling trajectory. These methods typically improve a target output by intentionally degrading another, often the unconditional output, using heuristic perturbation functions such as identity mixing or blurred conditions. However, these approaches lack a principled foundation and rely on manually designed distortions. In this work, we propose Adversarial Sinkhorn Attention Guidance (ASAG), a novel method that reinterprets attention scores in diffusion models through the lens of optimal transport and intentionally disrupt the transport cost via Sinkhorn algorithm. Instead of naively corrupting the attention mechanism, ASAG injects an adversarial cost within self-attention layers to reduce pixel-wise similarity between queries and keys. This deliberate degradation weakens misleading attention alignments and leads to improved conditional and unconditional sample quality. ASAG shows consistent improvements in text-to-image diffusion, and enhances controllability and fidelity in downstream applications such as IP-Adapter and ControlNet. The method is lightweight, plug-and-play, and improves reliability without requiring any model retraining.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07499</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 15:52:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MVU-Eval: Towards Multi-Video Understanding Evaluation for Multimodal   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07250</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07250.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianhao Peng, Haochen Wang, Yuanxing Zhang, Zekun Wang, Zili Wang, Ge Zhang, Jian Yang, Shihao Li, Yanghai Wang, Xintao Wang, Houyi Li, Wei Ji, Pengfei Wan, Wenhao Huang, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Jiaheng Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The advent of Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) has expanded AI capabilities to visual modalities, yet existing evaluation benchmarks remain limited to single-video understanding, overlooking the critical need for multi-video understanding in real-world scenarios (e.g., sports analytics and autonomous driving). To address this significant gap, we introduce MVU-Eval, the first comprehensive benchmark for evaluating Multi-Video Understanding for MLLMs. Specifically, our MVU-Eval mainly assesses eight core competencies through 1,824 meticulously curated question-answer pairs spanning 4,959 videos from diverse domains, addressing both fundamental perception tasks and high-order reasoning tasks. These capabilities are rigorously aligned with real-world applications such as multi-sensor synthesis in autonomous systems and cross-angle sports analytics. Through extensive evaluation of state-of-the-art open-source and closed-source models, we reveal significant performance discrepancies and limitations in current MLLMs' ability to perform understanding across multiple videos. The benchmark will be made publicly available to foster future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07250</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 16:02:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Omni-AVSR: Towards Unified Multimodal Speech Recognition with Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07253</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07253.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Umberto Cappellazzo, Xubo Liu, Pingchuan Ma, Stavros Petridis, Maja Pantic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have recently achieved impressive results in speech recognition across multiple modalities, including Auditory Speech Recognition (ASR), Visual Speech Recognition (VSR), and Audio-Visual Speech Recognition (AVSR). Despite this progress, current LLM-based approaches typically address each task independently, training separate models that raise computational and deployment resource use while missing potential cross-task synergies. They also rely on fixed-rate token compression, which restricts flexibility in balancing accuracy with efficiency. These limitations highlight the need for a unified framework that can support ASR, VSR, and AVSR while enabling elastic inference. To this end, we present Omni-AVSR, a unified audio-visual LLM that combines efficient multi-granularity training with parameter-efficient adaptation. Specifically, we adapt the matryoshka representation learning paradigm to efficiently train across multiple audio and visual granularities, reducing its inherent training resource use. Furthermore, we explore three LoRA-based strategies for adapting the backbone LLM, balancing shared and task-specific specialization. Experiments on LRS2 and LRS3 show that Omni-AVSR achieves comparable or superior accuracy to state-of-the-art baselines while training a single model at substantially lower training and deployment resource use. The model also remains robust under acoustic noise, and we analyze its scaling behavior as LLM size increases, providing insights into the trade-off between performance and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07253</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 16:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VADER: Towards Causal Video Anomaly Understanding with Relation-Aware   Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07299</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07299.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ying Cheng, Yu-Ho Lin, Min-Hung Chen, Fu-En Yang, Shang-Hong Lai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video anomaly understanding (VAU) aims to provide detailed interpretation and semantic comprehension of anomalous events within videos, addressing limitations of traditional methods that focus solely on detecting and localizing anomalies. However, existing approaches often neglect the deeper causal relationships and interactions between objects, which are critical for understanding anomalous behaviors. In this paper, we propose VADER, an LLM-driven framework for Video Anomaly unDErstanding, which integrates keyframe object Relation features with visual cues to enhance anomaly comprehension from video. Specifically, VADER first applies an Anomaly Scorer to assign per-frame anomaly scores, followed by a Context-AwarE Sampling (CAES) strategy to capture the causal context of each anomalous event. A Relation Feature Extractor and a COntrastive Relation Encoder (CORE) jointly model dynamic object interactions, producing compact relational representations for downstream reasoning. These visual and relational cues are integrated with LLMs to generate detailed, causally grounded descriptions and support robust anomaly-related question answering. Experiments on multiple real-world VAU benchmarks demonstrate that VADER achieves strong results across anomaly description, explanation, and causal reasoning tasks, advancing the frontier of explainable video anomaly analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07299</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 16:56:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLVE: Scaling Up Reinforcement Learning for Language Models with   Adaptive Verifiable Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Zeng, Hamish Ivison, Yiping Wang, Lifan Yuan, Shuyue Stella Li, Zhuorui Ye, Siting Li, Jacqueline He, Runlong Zhou, Tong Chen, Chenyang Zhao, Yulia Tsvetkov, Simon Shaolei Du, Natasha Jaques, Hao Peng, Pang Wei Koh, Hannaneh Hajishirzi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Reinforcement Learning (RL) with Adaptive Verifiable Environments (RLVE), an approach using verifiable environments that procedurally generate problems and provide algorithmically verifiable rewards, to scale up RL for language models (LMs). RLVE enables each verifiable environment to dynamically adapt its problem difficulty distribution to the policy model's capabilities as training progresses. In contrast, static data distributions often lead to vanishing learning signals when problems are either too easy or too hard for the policy. To implement RLVE, we create RLVE-Gym, a large-scale suite of 400 verifiable environments carefully developed through manual environment engineering. Using RLVE-Gym, we show that environment scaling, i.e., expanding the collection of training environments, consistently improves generalizable reasoning capabilities. RLVE with joint training across all 400 environments in RLVE-Gym yields a 3.37% absolute average improvement across six reasoning benchmarks, starting from one of the strongest 1.5B reasoning LMs. By comparison, continuing this LM's original RL training yields only a 0.49% average absolute gain despite using over 3x more compute. We release our code publicly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07317</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 17:18:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IterResearch: Rethinking Long-Horizon Agents via Markovian State   Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07327</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07327.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guoxin Chen, Zile Qiao, Xuanzhong Chen, Donglei Yu, Haotian Xu, Wayne Xin Zhao, Ruihua Song, Wenbiao Yin, Huifeng Yin, Liwen Zhang, Kuan Li, Minpeng Liao, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 67&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in deep-research agents have shown promise for autonomous knowledge construction through dynamic reasoning over external sources. However, existing approaches rely on a mono-contextual paradigm that accumulates all information in a single, expanding context window, leading to context suffocation and noise contamination that limit their effectiveness on long-horizon tasks. We introduce IterResearch, a novel iterative deep-research paradigm that reformulates long-horizon research as a Markov Decision Process with strategic workspace reconstruction. By maintaining an evolving report as memory and periodically synthesizing insights, our approach preserves consistent reasoning capacity across arbitrary exploration depths. We further develop Efficiency-Aware Policy Optimization (EAPO), a reinforcement learning framework that incentivizes efficient exploration through geometric reward discounting and enables stable distributed training via adaptive downsampling. Extensive experiments demonstrate that IterResearch achieves substantial improvements over existing open-source agents with average +14.5pp across six benchmarks and narrows the gap with frontier proprietary systems. Remarkably, our paradigm exhibits unprecedented interaction scaling, extending to 2048 interactions with dramatic performance gains (from 3.5\% to 42.5\%), and serves as an effective prompting strategy, improving frontier models by up to 19.2pp over ReAct on long-horizon tasks. These findings position IterResearch as a versatile solution for long-horizon reasoning, effective both as a trained agent and as a prompting paradigm for frontier models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07327</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 17:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grounding Computer Use Agents on Human Demonstrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07332</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07332.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aarash Feizi, Shravan Nayak, Xiangru Jian, Kevin Qinghong Lin, Kaixin Li, Rabiul Awal, Xing Han Lù, Johan Obando-Ceron, Juan A. Rodriguez, Nicolas Chapados, David Vazquez, Adriana Romero-Soriano, Reihaneh Rabbany, Perouz Taslakian, Christopher Pal, Spandana Gella, Sai Rajeswar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 98&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Building reliable computer-use agents requires grounding: accurately connecting natural language instructions to the correct on-screen elements. While large datasets exist for web and mobile interactions, high-quality resources for desktop environments are limited. To address this gap, we introduce GroundCUA, a large-scale desktop grounding dataset built from expert human demonstrations. It covers 87 applications across 12 categories and includes 56K screenshots, with every on-screen element carefully annotated for a total of over 3.56M human-verified annotations. From these demonstrations, we generate diverse instructions that capture a wide range of real-world tasks, providing high-quality data for model training. Using GroundCUA, we develop the GroundNext family of models that map instructions to their target UI elements. At both 3B and 7B scales, GroundNext achieves state-of-the-art results across five benchmarks using supervised fine-tuning, while requiring less than one-tenth the training data of prior work. Reinforcement learning post-training further improves performance, and when evaluated in an agentic setting on the OSWorld benchmark using o3 as planner, GroundNext attains comparable or superior results to models trained with substantially more data,. These results demonstrate the critical role of high-quality, expert-driven datasets in advancing general-purpose computer-use agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07332</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 17:35:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Pretrained Language Models to Think Deeper with Retrofitted   Recurrence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07384</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07384.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sean McLeish, Ang Li, John Kirchenbauer, Dayal Singh Kalra, Brian R. Bartoldson, Bhavya Kailkhura, Avi Schwarzschild, Jonas Geiping, Tom Goldstein, Micah Goldblum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in depth-recurrent language models show that recurrence can decouple train-time compute and parameter count from test-time compute. In this work, we study how to convert existing pretrained non-recurrent language models into depth-recurrent models. We find that using a curriculum of recurrences to increase the effective depth of the model over the course of training preserves performance while reducing total computational cost. In our experiments, on mathematics, we observe that converting pretrained models to recurrent ones results in better performance at a given compute budget than simply post-training the original non-recurrent language model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07384</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 18:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DIMO: Diverse 3D Motion Generation for Arbitrary Objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07409</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07409.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Linzhan Mou, Jiahui Lei, Chen Wang, Lingjie Liu, Kostas Daniilidis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present DIMO, a generative approach capable of generating diverse 3D motions for arbitrary objects from a single image. The core idea of our work is to leverage the rich priors in well-trained video models to extract the common motion patterns and then embed them into a shared low-dimensional latent space. Specifically, we first generate multiple videos of the same object with diverse motions. We then embed each motion into a latent vector and train a shared motion decoder to learn the distribution of motions represented by a structured and compact motion representation, i.e., neural key point trajectories. The canonical 3D Gaussians are then driven by these key points and fused to model the geometry and appearance. During inference time with learned latent space, we can instantly sample diverse 3D motions in a single-forward pass and support several interesting applications including 3D motion interpolation and language-guided motion generation. Our project page is available at https://linzhanm.github.io/dimo.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07409</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 18:56:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DigiData: Training and Evaluating General-Purpose Mobile Control Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07413</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07413.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxuan Sun, Manchen Wang, Shengyi Qian, William R. Wong, Eric Gan, Pierluca D'Oro, Alejandro Castillejo Munoz, Sneha Silwal, Pedro Matias, Nitin Kamra, Satwik Kottur, Nick Raines, Xuanyi Zhao, Joy Chen, Joseph Greer, Andrea Madotto, Allen Bolourchi, James Valori, Kevin Carlberg, Karl Ridgeway, Joseph Tighe&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI agents capable of controlling user interfaces have the potential to transform human interaction with digital devices. To accelerate this transformation, two fundamental building blocks are essential: high-quality datasets that enable agents to achieve complex and human-relevant goals, and robust evaluation methods that allow researchers and practitioners to rapidly enhance agent performance. In this paper, we introduce DigiData, a large-scale, high-quality, diverse, multi-modal dataset designed for training mobile control agents. Unlike existing datasets, which derive goals from unstructured interactions, DigiData is meticulously constructed through comprehensive exploration of app features, resulting in greater diversity and higher goal complexity. Additionally, we present DigiData-Bench, a benchmark for evaluating mobile control agents on real-world complex tasks. We demonstrate that the commonly used step-accuracy metric falls short in reliably assessing mobile control agents and, to address this, we propose dynamic evaluation protocols and AI-powered evaluations as rigorous alternatives for agent assessment. Our contributions aim to significantly advance the development of mobile control agents, paving the way for more intuitive and effective human-device interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07413</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 18:57:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robot Learning from a Physical World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07416</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07416.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiageng Mao, Sicheng He, Hao-Ning Wu, Yang You, Shuyang Sun, Zhicheng Wang, Yanan Bao, Huizhong Chen, Leonidas Guibas, Vitor Guizilini, Howard Zhou, Yue Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce PhysWorld, a framework that enables robot learning from video generation through physical world modeling. Recent video generation models can synthesize photorealistic visual demonstrations from language commands and images, offering a powerful yet underexplored source of training signals for robotics. However, directly retargeting pixel motions from generated videos to robots neglects physics, often resulting in inaccurate manipulations. PhysWorld addresses this limitation by coupling video generation with physical world reconstruction. Given a single image and a task command, our method generates task-conditioned videos and reconstructs the underlying physical world from the videos, and the generated video motions are grounded into physically accurate actions through object-centric residual reinforcement learning with the physical world model. This synergy transforms implicit visual guidance into physically executable robotic trajectories, eliminating the need for real robot data collection and enabling zero-shot generalizable robotic manipulation. Experiments on diverse real-world tasks demonstrate that PhysWorld substantially improves manipulation accuracy compared to previous approaches. Visit https://pointscoder.github.io/PhysWorld_Web/{the project webpage} for details.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07416</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 18:59:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Routing Manifold Alignment Improves Generalization of Mixture-of-Experts   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07419</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07419.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongyang Li, Ziyue Li, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) have been widely adopted in recent large language models since it can efficiently scale up the model capability without increasing the inference cost. However, evaluations on broad downstream tasks reveal a consistent suboptimality of the routers in existing MoE LLMs, which results in a severe performance gap (e.g., 10-20% in accuracy) to the optimal routing. In this paper, we show that aligning the manifold of routing weights with that of task embedding can effectively reduce the gap and improve MoE LLMs' generalization performance. Our method, "Routing Manifold Alignment (RoMA)", introduces an additional manifold regularization term in the post-training objective and only requires lightweight finetuning of routers (with other parameters frozen). Specifically, the regularization encourages the routing weights of each sample to be close to those of its successful neighbors (whose routing weights lead to correct answers) in a task embedding space. Consequently, samples targeting similar tasks will share similar expert choices across layers. Building such bindings between tasks and experts over different samples is essential to achieve better generalization. Moreover, RoMA demonstrates the advantage of unifying the task understanding (by embedding models) with solution generation (by MoE LLMs). In experiments, we finetune routers in OLMoE, DeepSeekMoE, and Qwen3-MoE using RoMA. Evaluations on diverse benchmarks and extensive comparisons with baselines show the substantial improvement brought by RoMA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07419</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 18:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Fact Retrieval: Episodic Memory for RAG with Generative Semantic Workspaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07587</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07587.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shreyas Rajesh, Pavan Holur, Chenda Duan, David Chong, Vwani Roychowdhury&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) face fundamental challenges in long-context reasoning: many documents exceed their finite context windows, while performance on texts that do fit degrades with sequence length, necessitating their augmentation with external memory frameworks. Current solutions, which have evolved from retrieval using semantic embeddings to more sophisticated structured knowledge graphs representations for improved sense-making and associativity, are tailored for fact-based retrieval and fail to build the space-time-anchored narrative representations required for tracking entities through episodic events. To bridge this gap, we propose the Generative Semantic Workspace (GSW), a neuro-inspired generative memory framework that builds structured, interpretable representations of evolving situations, enabling LLMs to reason over evolving roles, actions, and spatiotemporal contexts. Our framework comprises an Operator, which maps incoming observations to intermediate semantic structures, and a Reconciler, which integrates these into a persistent workspace that enforces temporal, spatial, and logical coherence. On the Episodic Memory Benchmark (EpBench) huet_episodic_2025 comprising corpora ranging from 100k to 1M tokens in length, GSW outperforms existing RAG based baselines by up to 20\%. Furthermore, GSW is highly efficient, reducing query-time context tokens by 51\% compared to the next most token-efficient baseline, reducing inference time costs considerably. More broadly, GSW offers a concrete blueprint for endowing LLMs with human-like episodic memory, paving the way for more capable agents that can reason over long horizons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07587</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 19:59:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ResearchRubrics: A Benchmark of Prompts and Rubrics For Evaluating Deep Research Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07685</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07685.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Manasi Sharma, Chen Bo Calvin Zhang, Chaithanya Bandi, Clinton Wang, Ankit Aich, Huy Nghiem, Tahseen Rabbani, Ye Htet, Brian Jang, Sumana Basu, Aishwarya Balwani, Denis Peskoff, Marcos Ayestaran, Sean M. Hendryx, Brad Kenstler, Bing Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep Research (DR) is an emerging agent application that leverages large language models (LLMs) to address open-ended queries. It requires the integration of several capabilities, including multi-step reasoning, cross-document synthesis, and the generation of evidence-backed, long-form answers. Evaluating DR remains challenging because responses are lengthy and diverse, admit many valid solutions, and often depend on dynamic information sources. We introduce ResearchRubrics, a standardized benchmark for DR built with over 2,800+ hours of human labor that pairs realistic, domain-diverse prompts with 2,500+ expert-written, fine-grained rubrics to assess factual grounding, reasoning soundness, and clarity. We also propose a new complexity framework for categorizing DR tasks along three axes: conceptual breadth, logical nesting, and exploration. In addition, we develop human and model-based evaluation protocols that measure rubric adherence for DR agents. We evaluate several state-of-the-art DR systems and find that even leading agents like Gemini's DR and OpenAI's DR achieve under 68% average compliance with our rubrics, primarily due to missed implicit context and inadequate reasoning about retrieved information. Our results highlight the need for robust, scalable assessment of deep research capabilities, to which end we release ResearchRubrics(including all prompts, rubrics, and evaluation code) to facilitate progress toward well-justified research assistants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07685</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 23:07:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CC30k: A Citation Contexts Dataset for Reproducibility-Oriented Sentiment Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07790</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07790.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rochana R. Obadage, Sarah M. Rajtmajer, Jian Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sentiments about the reproducibility of cited papers in downstream literature offer community perspectives and have shown as a promising signal of the actual reproducibility of published findings. To train effective models to effectively predict reproducibility-oriented sentiments and further systematically study their correlation with reproducibility, we introduce the CC30k dataset, comprising a total of 30,734 citation contexts in machine learning papers. Each citation context is labeled with one of three reproducibility-oriented sentiment labels: Positive, Negative, or Neutral, reflecting the cited paper's perceived reproducibility or replicability. Of these, 25,829 are labeled through crowdsourcing, supplemented with negatives generated through a controlled pipeline to counter the scarcity of negative labels. Unlike traditional sentiment analysis datasets, CC30k focuses on reproducibility-oriented sentiments, addressing a research gap in resources for computational reproducibility studies. The dataset was created through a pipeline that includes robust data cleansing, careful crowd selection, and thorough validation. The resulting dataset achieves a labeling accuracy of 94%. We then demonstrated that the performance of three large language models significantly improves on the reproducibility-oriented sentiment classification after fine-tuning using our dataset. The dataset lays the foundation for large-scale assessments of the reproducibility of machine learning papers. The CC30k dataset and the Jupyter notebooks used to produce and analyze the dataset are publicly available at https://github.com/lamps-lab/CC30k .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07790</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 03:13:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligence per Watt: Measuring Intelligence Efficiency of Local AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07885</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07885.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jon Saad-Falcon, Avanika Narayan, Hakki Orhun Akengin, J. Wes Griffin, Herumb Shandilya, Adrian Gamarra Lafuente, Medhya Goel, Rebecca Joseph, Shlok Natarajan, Etash Kumar Guha, Shang Zhu, Ben Athiwaratkun, John Hennessy, Azalia Mirhoseini, Christopher Ré&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM) queries are predominantly processed by frontier models in centralized cloud infrastructure. Rapidly growing demand strains this paradigm, and cloud providers struggle to scale infrastructure at pace. Two advances enable us to rethink this paradigm: small LMs (&lt;=20B active parameters) now achieve competitive performance to frontier models on many tasks, and local accelerators (e.g., Apple M4 Max) run these models at interactive latencies. This raises the question: can local inference viably redistribute demand from centralized infrastructure? Answering this requires measuring whether local LMs can accurately answer real-world queries and whether they can do so efficiently enough to be practical on power-constrained devices (i.e., laptops). We propose intelligence per watt (IPW), task accuracy divided by unit of power, as a metric for assessing capability and efficiency of local inference across model-accelerator pairs. We conduct a large-scale empirical study across 20+ state-of-the-art local LMs, 8 accelerators, and a representative subset of LLM traffic: 1M real-world single-turn chat and reasoning queries. For each query, we measure accuracy, energy, latency, and power. Our analysis reveals 3 findings. First, local LMs can accurately answer 88.7% of single-turn chat and reasoning queries with accuracy varying by domain. Second, from 2023-2025, IPW improved 5.3x and local query coverage rose from 23.2% to 71.3%. Third, local accelerators achieve at least 1.4x lower IPW than cloud accelerators running identical models, revealing significant headroom for optimization. These findings demonstrate that local inference can meaningfully redistribute demand from centralized infrastructure, with IPW serving as the critical metric for tracking this transition. We release our IPW profiling harness for systematic intelligence-per-watt benchmarking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07885</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 06:33:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BiCA: Effective Biomedical Dense Retrieval with Citation-Aware Hard Negatives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08029</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08029.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aarush Sinha, Pavan Kumar S, Roshan Balaji, Nirav Pravinbhai Bhatt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Hard negatives are essential for training effective retrieval models. Hard-negative mining typically relies on ranking documents using cross-encoders or static embedding models based on similarity metrics such as cosine distance. Hard negative mining becomes challenging for biomedical and scientific domains due to the difficulty in distinguishing between source and hard negative documents. However, referenced documents naturally share contextual relevance with the source document but are not duplicates, making them well-suited as hard negatives. In this work, we propose BiCA: Biomedical Dense Retrieval with Citation-Aware Hard Negatives, an approach for hard-negative mining by utilizing citation links in 20,000 PubMed articles for improving a domain-specific small dense retriever. We fine-tune the GTE_small and GTE_Base models using these citation-informed negatives and observe consistent improvements in zero-shot dense retrieval using nDCG@10 for both in-domain and out-of-domain tasks on BEIR and outperform baselines on long-tailed topics in LoTTE using Success@5. Our findings highlight the potential of leveraging document link structure to generate highly informative negatives, enabling state-of-the-art performance with minimal fine-tuning and demonstrating a path towards highly data-efficient domain adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08029</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 09:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DynaAct: Large Language Model Reasoning with Dynamic Action Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08043</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08043.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xueliang Zhao, Wei Wu, Jian Guan, Qintong Li, Lingpeng Kong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In modern sequential decision-making systems, the construction of an optimal candidate action space is critical to efficient inference. However, existing approaches either rely on manually defined action spaces that lack scalability or utilize unstructured spaces that render exhaustive search computationally prohibitive. In this paper, we propose a novel framework named DynaAct for automatically constructing a compact action space to enhance sequential reasoning in complex problem-solving scenarios. Our method first estimates a proxy for the complete action space by extracting general sketches observed in a corpus covering diverse complex reasoning problems using large language models. We then formulate a submodular function that jointly evaluates candidate actions based on their utility to the current state and their diversity, and employ a greedy algorithm to select an optimal candidate set. Extensive experiments on six diverse standard benchmarks demonstrate that our approach significantly improves overall performance, while maintaining efficient inference without introducing substantial latency. The implementation is available at https://github.com/zhaoxlpku/DynaAct.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08043</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 09:47:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MADD: Multi-Agent Drug Discovery Orchestra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08217</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08217.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gleb V. Solovev, Alina B. Zhidkovskaya, Anastasia Orlova, Nina Gubina, Anastasia Vepreva, Rodion Golovinskii, Ilya Tonkii, Ivan Dubrovsky, Ivan Gurev, Dmitry Gilemkhanov, Denis Chistiakov, Timur A. Aliev, Ivan Poddiakov, Galina Zubkova, Ekaterina V. Skorb, Vladimir Vinogradov, Alexander Boukhanovsky, Nikolay Nikitin, Andrei Dmitrenko, Anna Kalyuzhnaya, Andrey Savchenko&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Hit identification is a central challenge in early drug discovery, traditionally requiring substantial experimental resources. Recent advances in artificial intelligence, particularly large language models (LLMs), have enabled virtual screening methods that reduce costs and improve efficiency. However, the growing complexity of these tools has limited their accessibility to wet-lab researchers. Multi-agent systems offer a promising solution by combining the interpretability of LLMs with the precision of specialized models and tools. In this work, we present MADD, a multi-agent system that builds and executes customized hit identification pipelines from natural language queries. MADD employs four coordinated agents to handle key subtasks in de novo compound generation and screening. We evaluate MADD across seven drug discovery cases and demonstrate its superior performance compared to existing LLM-based solutions. Using MADD, we pioneer the application of AI-first drug design to five biological targets and release the identified hit molecules. Finally, we introduce a new benchmark of query-molecule pairs and docking scores for over three million compounds to contribute to the agentic future of drug design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08217</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 13:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Multi-Agent Response Refinement in Conversational Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08319</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08319.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Soyeong Jeong, Aparna Elangovan, Emine Yilmaz, Oleg Rokhlenko&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable success in conversational systems by generating human-like responses. However, they can fall short, especially when required to account for personalization or specific knowledge. In real-life settings, it is impractical to rely on users to detect these errors and request a new response. One way to address this problem is to refine the response before returning it to the user. While existing approaches focus on refining responses within a single LLM, this method struggles to consider diverse aspects needed for effective conversations. In this work, we propose refining responses through a multi-agent framework, where each agent is assigned a specific role for each aspect. We focus on three key aspects crucial to conversational quality: factuality, personalization, and coherence. Each agent is responsible for reviewing and refining one of these aspects, and their feedback is then merged to improve the overall response. To enhance collaboration among them, we introduce a dynamic communication strategy. Instead of following a fixed sequence of agents, our approach adaptively selects and coordinates the most relevant agents based on the specific requirements of each query. We validate our framework on challenging conversational datasets, demonstrating that ours significantly outperforms relevant baselines, particularly in tasks involving knowledge or user's persona, or both.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08319</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 14:48:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniVA: Universal Video Agent towards Open-Source Next-Generation Video Generalist</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08521</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08521.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengyang Liang, Daoan Zhang, Huichi Zhou, Rui Huang, Bobo Li, Yuechen Zhang, Shengqiong Wu, Xiaohan Wang, Jiebo Luo, Lizi Liao, Hao Fei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While specialized AI models excel at isolated video tasks like generation or understanding, real-world applications demand complex, iterative workflows that combine these capabilities. To bridge this gap, we introduce UniVA, an open-source, omni-capable multi-agent framework for next-generation video generalists that unifies video understanding, segmentation, editing, and generation into cohesive workflows. UniVA employs a Plan-and-Act dual-agent architecture that drives a highly automated and proactive workflow: a planner agent interprets user intentions and decomposes them into structured video-processing steps, while executor agents execute these through modular, MCP-based tool servers (for analysis, generation, editing, tracking, etc.). Through a hierarchical multi-level memory (global knowledge, task context, and user-specific preferences), UniVA sustains long-horizon reasoning, contextual continuity, and inter-agent communication, enabling interactive and self-reflective video creation with full traceability. This design enables iterative and any-conditioned video workflows (e.g., text/image/video-conditioned generation rightarrow multi-round editing rightarrow object segmentation rightarrow compositional synthesis) that were previously cumbersome to achieve with single-purpose models or monolithic video-language models. We also introduce UniVA-Bench, a benchmark suite of multi-step video tasks spanning understanding, editing, segmentation, and generation, to rigorously evaluate such agentic video systems. Both UniVA and UniVA-Bench are fully open-sourced, aiming to catalyze research on interactive, agentic, and general-purpose video intelligence for the next generation of multimodal AI systems. (https://univa.online/)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08521</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 17:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AlphaResearch: Accelerating New Algorithm Discovery with Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08522</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08522.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaojian Yu, Kaiyue Feng, Yilun Zhao, Shilin He, Xiao-Ping Zhang, Arman Cohan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models have made significant progress in complex but easy-to-verify problems, yet they still struggle with discovering the unknown. In this paper, we present AlphaResearch, an autonomous research agent designed to discover new algorithms on open-ended problems. To synergize the feasibility and innovation of the discovery process, we construct a novel dual research environment by combining the execution-based verify and simulated real-world peer review environment. AlphaResearch discovers new algorithm by iteratively running the following steps: (1) propose new ideas (2) verify the ideas in the dual research environment (3) optimize the research proposals for better performance. To promote a transparent evaluation process, we construct AlphaResearchComp, a new evaluation benchmark that includes an eight open-ended algorithmic problems competition, with each problem carefully curated and verified through executable pipelines, objective metrics, and reproducibility checks. AlphaResearch gets a 2/8 win rate in head-to-head comparison with human researchers, demonstrate the possibility of accelerating algorithm discovery with LLMs. Notably, the algorithm discovered by AlphaResearch on the ``packing circles'' problem achieves the best-of-known performance, surpassing the results of human researchers and strong baselines from recent work (e.g., AlphaEvolve). Additionally, we conduct a comprehensive analysis of the remaining challenges of the 6/8 failure cases, providing valuable insights for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08522</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 18:03:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Path Not Taken: RLVR Provably Learns Off the Principals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08567</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08567.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hanqing Zhu, Zhenyu Zhang, Hanxian Huang, DiJia Su, Zechun Liu, Jiawei Zhao, Igor Fedorov, Hamed Pirsiavash, Zhizhou Sha, Jinwon Lee, David Z. Pan, Zhangyang Wang, Yuandong Tian, Kai Sheng Tai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) reliably improves the reasoning performance of large language models, yet it appears to modify only a small fraction of parameters. We revisit this paradox and show that sparsity is a surface artifact of a model-conditioned optimization bias: for a fixed pretrained model, updates consistently localize to preferred parameter regions, highly consistent across runs and largely invariant to datasets and RL recipes. We mechanistically explain these dynamics with a Three-Gate Theory: Gate I (KL Anchor) imposes a KL-constrained update; Gate II (Model Geometry) steers the step off principal directions into low-curvature, spectrum-preserving subspaces; and Gate III (Precision) hides micro-updates in non-preferred regions, making the off-principal bias appear as sparsity. We then validate this theory and, for the first time, provide a parameter-level characterization of RLVR's learning dynamics: RLVR learns off principal directions in weight space, achieving gains via minimal spectral drift, reduced principal-subspace rotation, and off-principal update alignment. In contrast, SFT targets principal weights, distorts the spectrum, and even lags RLVR.   Together, these results provide the first parameter-space account of RLVR's training dynamics, revealing clear regularities in how parameters evolve. Crucially, we show that RL operates in a distinct optimization regime from SFT, so directly adapting SFT-era parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) methods can be flawed, as evidenced by our case studies on advanced sparse fine-tuning and LoRA variants. We hope this work charts a path toward a white-box understanding of RLVR and the design of geometry-aware, RLVR-native learning algorithms, rather than repurposed SFT-era heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08567</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 18:49:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lumine: An Open Recipe for Building Generalist Agents in 3D Open Worlds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08892</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08892.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weihao Tan, Xiangyang Li, Yunhao Fang, Heyuan Yao, Shi Yan, Hao Luo, Tenglong Ao, Huihui Li, Hongbin Ren, Bairen Yi, Yujia Qin, Bo An, Libin Liu, Guang Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 145&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Lumine, the first open recipe for developing generalist agents capable of completing hours-long complex missions in real time within challenging 3D open-world environments. Lumine adopts a human-like interaction paradigm that unifies perception, reasoning, and action in an end-to-end manner, powered by a vision-language model. It processes raw pixels at 5 Hz to produce precise 30 Hz keyboard-mouse actions and adaptively invokes reasoning only when necessary. Trained in Genshin Impact, Lumine successfully completes the entire five-hour Mondstadt main storyline on par with human-level efficiency and follows natural language instructions to perform a broad spectrum of tasks in both 3D open-world exploration and 2D GUI manipulation across collection, combat, puzzle-solving, and NPC interaction. In addition to its in-domain performance, Lumine demonstrates strong zero-shot cross-game generalization. Without any fine-tuning, it accomplishes 100-minute missions in Wuthering Waves and the full five-hour first chapter of Honkai: Star Rail. These promising results highlight Lumine's effectiveness across distinct worlds and interaction dynamics, marking a concrete step toward generalist agents in open-ended environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08892</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 02:01:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TiDAR: Think in Diffusion, Talk in Autoregression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08923</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08923.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingyu Liu, Xin Dong, Zhifan Ye, Rishabh Mehta, Yonggan Fu, Vartika Singh, Jan Kautz, Ce Zhang, Pavlo Molchanov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion language models hold the promise of fast parallel generation, while autoregressive (AR) models typically excel in quality due to their causal structure aligning naturally with language modeling. This raises a fundamental question: can we achieve a synergy with high throughput, higher GPU utilization, and AR level quality? Existing methods fail to effectively balance these two aspects, either prioritizing AR using a weaker model for sequential drafting (speculative decoding), leading to lower drafting efficiency, or using some form of left-to-right (AR-like) decoding logic for diffusion, which still suffers from quality degradation and forfeits its potential parallelizability. We introduce TiDAR, a sequence-level hybrid architecture that drafts tokens (Thinking) in Diffusion and samples final outputs (Talking) AutoRegressively - all within a single forward pass using specially designed structured attention masks. This design exploits the free GPU compute density, achieving a strong balance between drafting and verification capacity. Moreover, TiDAR is designed to be serving-friendly (low overhead) as a standalone model. We extensively evaluate TiDAR against AR models, speculative decoding, and diffusion variants across generative and likelihood tasks at 1.5B and 8B scales. Thanks to the parallel drafting and sampling as well as exact KV cache support, TiDAR outperforms speculative decoding in measured throughput and surpasses diffusion models like Dream and Llada in both efficiency and quality. Most notably, TiDAR is the first architecture to close the quality gap with AR models while delivering 4.71x to 5.91x more tokens per second.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08923</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 02:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solving a Million-Step LLM Task with Zero Errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09030</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09030.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Elliot Meyerson, Giuseppe Paolo, Roberto Dailey, Hormoz Shahrzad, Olivier Francon, Conor F. Hayes, Xin Qiu, Babak Hodjat, Risto Miikkulainen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLMs have achieved remarkable breakthroughs in reasoning, insights, and tool use, but chaining these abilities into extended processes at the scale of those routinely executed by humans, organizations, and societies has remained out of reach. The models have a persistent error rate that prevents scale-up: for instance, recent experiments in the Towers of Hanoi benchmark domain showed that the process inevitably becomes derailed after at most a few hundred steps. Thus, although LLM research is often still benchmarked on tasks with relatively few dependent logical steps, there is increasing attention on the ability (or inability) of LLMs to perform long range tasks. This paper describes MAKER, the first system that successfully solves a task with over one million LLM steps with zero errors, and, in principle, scales far beyond this level. The approach relies on an extreme decomposition of a task into subtasks, each of which can be tackled by focused microagents. The high level of modularity resulting from the decomposition allows error correction to be applied at each step through an efficient multi-agent voting scheme. This combination of extreme decomposition and error correction makes scaling possible. Thus, the results suggest that instead of relying on continual improvement of current LLMs, massively decomposed agentic processes (MDAPs) may provide a way to efficiently solve problems at the level of organizations and societies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09030</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 06:27:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PAN: A World Model for General, Interactable, and Long-Horizon World Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09057</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09057.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; PAN Team, Jiannan Xiang, Yi Gu, Zihan Liu, Zeyu Feng, Qiyue Gao, Yiyan Hu, Benhao Huang, Guangyi Liu, Yichi Yang, Kun Zhou, Davit Abrahamyan, Arif Ahmad, Ganesh Bannur, Junrong Chen, Kimi Chen, Mingkai Deng, Ruobing Han, Xinqi Huang, Haoqiang Kang, Zheqi Li, Enze Ma, Hector Ren, Yashowardhan Shinde, Rohan Shingre, Ramsundar Tanikella, Kaiming Tao, Dequan Yang, Xinle Yu, Cong Zeng, Binglin Zhou, Zhengzhong Liu, Zhiting Hu, Eric P. Xing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A world model enables an intelligent agent to imagine, predict, and reason about how the world evolves in response to its actions, and accordingly to plan and strategize. While recent video generation models produce realistic visual sequences, they typically operate in the prompt-to-full-video manner without causal control, interactivity, or long-horizon consistency required for purposeful reasoning. Existing world modeling efforts, on the other hand, often focus on restricted domains (e.g., physical, game, or 3D-scene dynamics) with limited depth and controllability, and struggle to generalize across diverse environments and interaction formats. In this work, we introduce PAN, a general, interactable, and long-horizon world model that predicts future world states through high-quality video simulation conditioned on history and natural language actions. PAN employs the Generative Latent Prediction (GLP) architecture that combines an autoregressive latent dynamics backbone based on a large language model (LLM), which grounds simulation in extensive text-based knowledge and enables conditioning on language-specified actions, with a video diffusion decoder that reconstructs perceptually detailed and temporally coherent visual observations, to achieve a unification between latent space reasoning (imagination) and realizable world dynamics (reality). Trained on large-scale video-action pairs spanning diverse domains, PAN supports open-domain, action-conditioned simulation with coherent, long-term dynamics. Extensive experiments show that PAN achieves strong performance in action-conditioned world simulation, long-horizon forecasting, and simulative reasoning compared to other video generators and world models, taking a step towards general world models that enable predictive simulation of future world states for reasoning and acting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09057</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 07:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MM-CRITIC: A Holistic Evaluation of Large Multimodal Models as Multimodal Critique</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09067</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09067.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gailun Zeng, Ziyang Luo, Hongzhan Lin, Yuchen Tian, Kaixin Li, Ziyang Gong, Jianxiong Guo, Jing Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The ability of critique is vital for models to self-improve and serve as reliable AI assistants. While extensively studied in language-only settings, multimodal critique of Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) remains underexplored despite their growing capabilities in tasks like captioning and visual reasoning. In this work, we introduce MM-CRITIC, a holistic benchmark for evaluating the critique ability of LMMs across multiple dimensions: basic, correction, and comparison. Covering 8 main task types and over 500 tasks, MM-CRITIC collects responses from various LMMs with different model sizes and is composed of 4471 samples. To enhance the evaluation reliability, we integrate expert-informed ground answers into scoring rubrics that guide GPT-4o in annotating responses and generating reference critiques, which serve as anchors for trustworthy judgments. Extensive experiments validate the effectiveness of MM-CRITIC and provide a comprehensive assessment of leading LMMs' critique capabilities under multiple dimensions. Further analysis reveals some key insights, including the correlation between response quality and critique, and varying critique difficulty across evaluation dimensions. Our code is available at https://github.com/MichealZeng0420/MM-Critic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09067</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 07:43:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LoopTool: Closing the Data-Training Loop for Robust LLM Tool Calls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09148</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09148.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kangning Zhang, Wenxiang Jiao, Kounianhua Du, Yuan Lu, Weiwen Liu, Weinan Zhang, Lei Zhang, Yong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Augmenting Large Language Models (LLMs) with external tools enables them to execute complex, multi-step tasks. However, tool learning is hampered by the static synthetic data pipelines where data generation and model training are executed as two separate, non-interactive processes. This approach fails to adaptively focus on a model's specific weaknesses and allows noisy labels to persist, degrading training efficiency. We introduce LoopTool, a fully automated, model-aware data evolution framework that closes this loop by tightly integrating data synthesis and model training. LoopTool iteratively refines both the data and the model through three synergistic modules: (1) Greedy Capability Probing (GCP) diagnoses the model's mastered and failed capabilities; (2) Judgement-Guided Label Verification (JGLV) uses an open-source judge model to find and correct annotation errors, progressively purifying the dataset; and (3) Error-Driven Data Expansion (EDDE) generates new, challenging samples based on identified failures. This closed-loop process operates within a cost-effective, open-source ecosystem, eliminating dependence on expensive closed-source APIs. Experiments show that our 8B model trained with LoopTool significantly surpasses its 32B data generator and achieves new state-of-the-art results on the BFCL-v3 and ACEBench benchmarks for its scale. Our work demonstrates that closed-loop, self-refining data pipelines can dramatically enhance the tool-use capabilities of LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09148</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 09:34:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WMPO: World Model-based Policy Optimization for Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09515</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09515.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fangqi Zhu, Zhengyang Yan, Zicong Hong, Quanxin Shou, Xiao Ma, Song Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models have shown strong potential for general-purpose robotic manipulation, but their reliance on expert demonstrations limits their ability to learn from failures and perform self-corrections. Reinforcement learning (RL) addresses these through self-improving interactions with the physical environment, but suffers from high sample complexity on real robots. We introduce World-Model-based Policy Optimization (WMPO), a principled framework for on-policy VLA RL without interacting with the real environment. In contrast to widely used latent world models, WMPO focuses on pixel-based predictions that align the "imagined" trajectories with the VLA features pretrained with web-scale images. Crucially, WMPO enables the policy to perform on-policy GRPO that provides stronger performance than the often-used off-policy methods. Extensive experiments in both simulation and real-robot settings demonstrate that WMPO (i) substantially improves sample efficiency, (ii) achieves stronger overall performance, (iii) exhibits emergent behaviors such as self-correction, and (iv) demonstrates robust generalization and lifelong learning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09515</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 17:54:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SliderEdit: Continuous Image Editing with Fine-Grained Instruction Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09715</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09715.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Arman Zarei, Samyadeep Basu, Mobina Pournemat, Sayan Nag, Ryan Rossi, Soheil Feizi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-based image editing models have recently achieved impressive performance, enabling complex edits to an input image from a multi-instruction prompt. However, these models apply each instruction in the prompt with a fixed strength, limiting the user's ability to precisely and continuously control the intensity of individual edits. We introduce SliderEdit, a framework for continuous image editing with fine-grained, interpretable instruction control. Given a multi-part edit instruction, SliderEdit disentangles the individual instructions and exposes each as a globally trained slider, allowing smooth adjustment of its strength. Unlike prior works that introduced slider-based attribute controls in text-to-image generation, typically requiring separate training or fine-tuning for each attribute or concept, our method learns a single set of low-rank adaptation matrices that generalize across diverse edits, attributes, and compositional instructions. This enables continuous interpolation along individual edit dimensions while preserving both spatial locality and global semantic consistency. We apply SliderEdit to state-of-the-art image editing models, including FLUX-Kontext and Qwen-Image-Edit, and observe substantial improvements in edit controllability, visual consistency, and user steerability. To the best of our knowledge, we are the first to explore and propose a framework for continuous, fine-grained instruction control in instruction-based image editing models. Our results pave the way for interactive, instruction-driven image manipulation with continuous and compositional control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09715</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 20:21:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hail to the Thief: Exploring Attacks and Defenses in Decentralised GRPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09780</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09780.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nikolay Blagoev, Oğuzhan Ersoy, Lydia Yiyu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) has demonstrated great utilization in post-training of Large Language Models (LLMs). In GRPO, prompts are answered by the model and, through reinforcement learning, preferred completions are learnt. Owing to the small communication volume, GRPO is inherently suitable for decentralised training as the prompts can be concurrently answered by multiple nodes and then exchanged in the forms of strings. In this work, we present the first adversarial attack in decentralised GRPO. We demonstrate that malicious parties can poison such systems by injecting arbitrary malicious tokens in benign models in both out-of-context and in-context attacks. Using empirical examples of math and coding tasks, we show that adversarial attacks can easily poison the benign nodes, polluting their local LLM post-training, achieving attack success rates up to 100% in as few as 50 iterations. We propose two ways to defend against these attacks, depending on whether all users train the same model or different models. We show that these defenses can achieve stop rates of up to 100%, making the attack impossible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09780</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 22:29:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AffordBot: 3D Fine-grained Embodied Reasoning via Multimodal Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10017</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10017.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinyi Wang, Xun Yang, Yanlong Xu, Yuchen Wu, Zhen Li, Na Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Effective human-agent collaboration in physical environments requires understanding not only what to act upon, but also where the actionable elements are and how to interact with them. Existing approaches often operate at the object level or disjointedly handle fine-grained affordance reasoning, lacking coherent, instruction-driven grounding and reasoning. In this work, we introduce a new task: Fine-grained 3D Embodied Reasoning, which requires an agent to predict, for each referenced affordance element in a 3D scene, a structured triplet comprising its spatial location, motion type, and motion axis, based on a task instruction. To solve this task, we propose AffordBot, a novel framework that integrates Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) with a tailored chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning paradigm. To bridge the gap between 3D input and 2D-compatible MLLMs, we render surround-view images of the scene and project 3D element candidates into these views, forming a rich visual representation aligned with the scene geometry. Our CoT pipeline begins with an active perception stage, prompting the MLLM to select the most informative viewpoint based on the instruction, before proceeding with step-by-step reasoning to localize affordance elements and infer plausible interaction motions. Evaluated on the SceneFun3D dataset, AffordBot achieves state-of-the-art performance, demonstrating strong generalization and physically grounded reasoning with only 3D point cloud input and MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10017</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 06:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MuSc-V2: Zero-Shot Multimodal Industrial Anomaly Classification and Segmentation with Mutual Scoring of Unlabeled Samples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10047</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10047.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xurui Li, Feng Xue, Yu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Zero-shot anomaly classification (AC) and segmentation (AS) methods aim to identify and outline defects without using any labeled samples. In this paper, we reveal a key property that is overlooked by existing methods: normal image patches across industrial products typically find many other similar patches, not only in 2D appearance but also in 3D shapes, while anomalies remain diverse and isolated. To explicitly leverage this discriminative property, we propose a Mutual Scoring framework (MuSc-V2) for zero-shot AC/AS, which flexibly supports single 2D/3D or multimodality. Specifically, our method begins by improving 3D representation through Iterative Point Grouping (IPG), which reduces false positives from discontinuous surfaces. Then we use Similarity Neighborhood Aggregation with Multi-Degrees (SNAMD) to fuse 2D/3D neighborhood cues into more discriminative multi-scale patch features for mutual scoring. The core comprises a Mutual Scoring Mechanism (MSM) that lets samples within each modality to assign score to each other, and Cross-modal Anomaly Enhancement (CAE) that fuses 2D and 3D scores to recover modality-specific missing anomalies. Finally, Re-scoring with Constrained Neighborhood (RsCon) suppresses false classification based on similarity to more representative samples. Our framework flexibly works on both the full dataset and smaller subsets with consistently robust performance, ensuring seamless adaptability across diverse product lines. In aid of the novel framework, MuSc-V2 achieves significant performance improvements: a +23.7% AP gain on the MVTec 3D-AD dataset and a +19.3% boost on the Eyecandies dataset, surpassing previous zero-shot benchmarks and even outperforming most few-shot methods. The code will be available at The code will be available at https://github.com/HUST-SLOW/MuSc-V2{https://github.com/HUST-SLOW/MuSc-V2}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10047</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 07:47:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Music Flamingo: Scaling Music Understanding in Audio Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10289</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10289.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sreyan Ghosh, Arushi Goel, Lasha Koroshinadze, Sang-gil Lee, Zhifeng Kong, Joao Felipe Santos, Ramani Duraiswami, Dinesh Manocha, Wei Ping, Mohammad Shoeybi, Bryan Catanzaro&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Music Flamingo, a novel large audio-language model designed to advance music (including song) understanding in foundational audio models. While audio-language research has progressed rapidly, music remains challenging due to its dynamic, layered, and information-dense nature. Progress has been further limited by the difficulty of scaling open audio understanding models, primarily because of the scarcity of high-quality music data and annotations. As a result, prior models are restricted to producing short, high-level captions, answering only surface-level questions, and showing limited generalization across diverse musical cultures. To address these challenges, we curate MF-Skills, a large-scale dataset labeled through a multi-stage pipeline that yields rich captions and question-answer pairs covering harmony, structure, timbre, lyrics, and cultural context. We fine-tune an enhanced Audio Flamingo 3 backbone on MF-Skills and further strengthen multiple skills relevant to music understanding. To improve the model's reasoning abilities, we introduce a post-training recipe: we first cold-start with MF-Think, a novel chain-of-thought dataset grounded in music theory, followed by GRPO-based reinforcement learning with custom rewards. Music Flamingo achieves state-of-the-art results across 10+ benchmarks for music understanding and reasoning, establishing itself as a generalist and musically intelligent audio-language model. Beyond strong empirical results, Music Flamingo sets a new standard for advanced music understanding by demonstrating how models can move from surface-level recognition toward layered, human-like perception of songs. We believe this work provides both a benchmark and a foundation for the community to build the next generation of models that engage with music as meaningfully as humans do.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10289</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 13:21:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rubric-Based Benchmarking and Reinforcement Learning for Advancing LLM Instruction Following</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10507</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10507.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yun He, Wenzhe Li, Hejia Zhang, Songlin Li, Karishma Mandyam, Sopan Khosla, Yuanhao Xiong, Nanshu Wang, Selina Peng, Beibin Li, Shengjie Bi, Shishir G. Patil, Qi Qi, Shengyu Feng, Julian Katz-Samuels, Richard Yuanzhe Pang, Sujan Gonugondla, Hunter Lang, Yue Yu, Yundi Qian, Maryam Fazel-Zarandi, Licheng Yu, Amine Benhalloum, Hany Awadalla, Manaal Faruqui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in large language models (LLMs) has led to impressive performance on a range of tasks, yet advanced instruction following (IF)-especially for complex, multi-turn, and system-prompted instructions-remains a significant challenge. Rigorous evaluation and effective training for such capabilities are hindered by the lack of high-quality, human-annotated benchmarks and reliable, interpretable reward signals. In this work, we introduce AdvancedIF (we will release this benchmark soon), a comprehensive benchmark featuring over 1,600 prompts and expert-curated rubrics that assess LLMs ability to follow complex, multi-turn, and system-level instructions. We further propose RIFL (Rubric-based Instruction-Following Learning), a novel post-training pipeline that leverages rubric generation, a finetuned rubric verifier, and reward shaping to enable effective reinforcement learning for instruction following. Extensive experiments demonstrate that RIFL substantially improves the instruction-following abilities of LLMs, achieving a 6.7% absolute gain on AdvancedIF and strong results on public benchmarks. Our ablation studies confirm the effectiveness of each component in RIFL. This work establishes rubrics as a powerful tool for both training and evaluating advanced IF in LLMs, paving the way for more capable and reliable AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10507</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:14:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Diversity in Image Generation via Attribute-Conditional Human Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10547</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10547.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Isabela Albuquerque, Ira Ktena, Olivia Wiles, Ivana Kajić, Amal Rannen-Triki, Cristina Vasconcelos, Aida Nematzadeh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite advances in generation quality, current text-to-image (T2I) models often lack diversity, generating homogeneous outputs. This work introduces a framework to address the need for robust diversity evaluation in T2I models. Our framework systematically assesses diversity by evaluating individual concepts and their relevant factors of variation. Key contributions include: (1) a novel human evaluation template for nuanced diversity assessment; (2) a curated prompt set covering diverse concepts with their identified factors of variation (e.g. prompt: An image of an apple, factor of variation: color); and (3) a methodology for comparing models in terms of human annotations via binomial tests.   Furthermore, we rigorously compare various image embeddings for diversity measurement. Notably, our principled approach enables ranking of T2I models by diversity, identifying categories where they particularly struggle. This research offers a robust methodology and insights, paving the way for improvements in T2I model diversity and metric development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10547</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:48:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One Small Step in Latent, One Giant Leap for Pixels: Fast Latent Upscale Adapter for Your Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10629</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10629.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aleksandr Razin, Danil Kazantsev, Ilya Makarov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 85&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion models struggle to scale beyond their training resolutions, as direct high-resolution sampling is slow and costly, while post-hoc image super-resolution (ISR) introduces artifacts and additional latency by operating after decoding. We present the Latent Upscaler Adapter (LUA), a lightweight module that performs super-resolution directly on the generator's latent code before the final VAE decoding step. LUA integrates as a drop-in component, requiring no modifications to the base model or additional diffusion stages, and enables high-resolution synthesis through a single feed-forward pass in latent space. A shared Swin-style backbone with scale-specific pixel-shuffle heads supports 2x and 4x factors and remains compatible with image-space SR baselines, achieving comparable perceptual quality with nearly 3x lower decoding and upscaling time (adding only +0.42 s for 1024 px generation from 512 px, compared to 1.87 s for pixel-space SR using the same SwinIR architecture). Furthermore, LUA shows strong generalization across the latent spaces of different VAEs, making it easy to deploy without retraining from scratch for each new decoder. Extensive experiments demonstrate that LUA closely matches the fidelity of native high-resolution generation while offering a practical and efficient path to scalable, high-fidelity image synthesis in modern diffusion pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10629</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:54:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black-Box On-Policy Distillation of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10643</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10643.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianzhu Ye, Li Dong, Zewen Chi, Xun Wu, Shaohan Huang, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Black-box distillation creates student large language models (LLMs) by learning from a proprietary teacher model's text outputs alone, without access to its internal logits or parameters. In this work, we introduce Generative Adversarial Distillation (GAD), which enables on-policy and black-box distillation. GAD frames the student LLM as a generator and trains a discriminator to distinguish its responses from the teacher LLM's, creating a minimax game. The discriminator acts as an on-policy reward model that co-evolves with the student, providing stable, adaptive feedback. Experimental results show that GAD consistently surpasses the commonly used sequence-level knowledge distillation. In particular, Qwen2.5-14B-Instruct (student) trained with GAD becomes comparable to its teacher, GPT-5-Chat, on the LMSYS-Chat automatic evaluation. The results establish GAD as a promising and effective paradigm for black-box LLM distillation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10643</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:58:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depth Anything 3: Recovering the Visual Space from Any Views</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10647</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10647.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haotong Lin, Sili Chen, Junhao Liew, Donny Y. Chen, Zhenyu Li, Guang Shi, Jiashi Feng, Bingyi Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Depth Anything 3 (DA3), a model that predicts spatially consistent geometry from an arbitrary number of visual inputs, with or without known camera poses. In pursuit of minimal modeling, DA3 yields two key insights: a single plain transformer (e.g., vanilla DINO encoder) is sufficient as a backbone without architectural specialization, and a singular depth-ray prediction target obviates the need for complex multi-task learning. Through our teacher-student training paradigm, the model achieves a level of detail and generalization on par with Depth Anything 2 (DA2). We establish a new visual geometry benchmark covering camera pose estimation, any-view geometry and visual rendering. On this benchmark, DA3 sets a new state-of-the-art across all tasks, surpassing prior SOTA VGGT by an average of 44.3% in camera pose accuracy and 25.1% in geometric accuracy. Moreover, it outperforms DA2 in monocular depth estimation. All models are trained exclusively on public academic datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10647</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
