<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:11:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>ModernGBERT: German-only 1B Encoder Model Trained from Scratch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13136</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13136.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anton Ehrmanntraut, Julia Wunderle, Jan Pfister, Fotis Jannidis, Andreas Hotho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the prominence of decoder-only language models, encoders remain crucial for resource-constrained applications. We introduce ModernGBERT (134M, 1B), a fully transparent family of German encoder models trained from scratch, incorporating architectural innovations from ModernBERT. To evaluate the practical trade-offs of training encoders from scratch, we also present LL\"aMmlein2Vec (120M, 1B, 7B), a family of encoders derived from German decoder-only models via LLM2Vec. We benchmark all models on natural language understanding, text embedding, and long-context reasoning tasks, enabling a controlled comparison between dedicated encoders and converted decoders. Our results show that ModernGBERT 1B outperforms prior state-of-the-art German encoders as well as encoders adapted via LLM2Vec, with regard to performance and parameter-efficiency. All models, training data, checkpoints and code are publicly available, advancing the German NLP ecosystem with transparent, high-performance encoder models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13136</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 14:07:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NOVA: A Benchmark for Anomaly Localization and Clinical Reasoning in   Brain MRI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14064</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14064.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cosmin I. Bercea, Jun Li, Philipp Raffler, Evamaria O. Riedel, Lena Schmitzer, Angela Kurz, Felix Bitzer, Paula Roßmüller, Julian Canisius, Mirjam L. Beyrle, Che Liu, Wenjia Bai, Bernhard Kainz, Julia A. Schnabel, Benedikt Wiestler&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In many real-world applications, deployed models encounter inputs that differ from the data seen during training. Out-of-distribution detection identifies whether an input stems from an unseen distribution, while open-world recognition flags such inputs to ensure the system remains robust as ever-emerging, previously unknown categories appear and must be addressed without retraining. Foundation and vision-language models are pre-trained on large and diverse datasets with the expectation of broad generalization across domains, including medical imaging. However, benchmarking these models on test sets with only a few common outlier types silently collapses the evaluation back to a closed-set problem, masking failures on rare or truly novel conditions encountered in clinical use.   We therefore present NOVA, a challenging, real-life evaluation-only benchmark of sim900 brain MRI scans that span 281 rare pathologies and heterogeneous acquisition protocols. Each case includes rich clinical narratives and double-blinded expert bounding-box annotations. Together, these enable joint assessment of anomaly localisation, visual captioning, and diagnostic reasoning. Because NOVA is never used for training, it serves as an extreme stress-test of out-of-distribution generalisation: models must bridge a distribution gap both in sample appearance and in semantic space. Baseline results with leading vision-language models (GPT-4o, Gemini 2.0 Flash, and Qwen2.5-VL-72B) reveal substantial performance drops across all tasks, establishing NOVA as a rigorous testbed for advancing models that can detect, localize, and reason about truly unknown anomalies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14064</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 08:10:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quartet: Native FP4 Training Can Be Optimal for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14669</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14669.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Roberto L. Castro, Andrei Panferov, Soroush Tabesh, Oliver Sieberling, Jiale Chen, Mahdi Nikdan, Saleh Ashkboos, Dan Alistarh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of large language models (LLMs) has been paralleled by unprecedented increases in computational demands, with training costs for state-of-the-art models doubling every few months. Training models directly in low-precision arithmetic offers a solution, by improving both computational throughput and energy efficiency. Specifically, NVIDIA's recent Blackwell architecture facilitates extremely low-precision operations, specifically FP4 variants, promising substantial efficiency gains. Yet, current algorithms for training LLMs in FP4 precision face significant accuracy degradation and often rely on mixed-precision fallbacks. In this paper, we systematically investigate hardware-supported FP4 training and introduce Quartet, a new approach enabling accurate, end-to-end FP4 training with all the major computations (in e.g. linear layers) being performed in low precision. Through extensive evaluations on Llama-type models, we reveal a new low-precision scaling law that quantifies performance trade-offs across varying bit-widths and allows us to identify a "near-optimal" low-precision training technique in terms of accuracy-vs-computation, called Quartet. We implement Quartet using optimized CUDA kernels tailored for NVIDIA Blackwell GPUs, and show that it can achieve state-of-the-art accuracy for FP4 precision, successfully training billion-scale models. Our method demonstrates that fully FP4-based training is a competitive alternative to standard-precision and FP8 training. Our code is available at https://github.com/IST-DASLab/Quartet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14669</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:55:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhyX: Does Your Model Have the "Wits" for Physical Reasoning?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15929</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15929.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hui Shen, Taiqiang Wu, Qi Han, Yunta Hsieh, Jizhou Wang, Yuyue Zhang, Yuxin Cheng, Zijian Hao, Yuansheng Ni, Xin Wang, Zhongwei Wan, Kai Zhang, Wendong Xu, Jing Xiong, Ping Luo, Wenhu Chen, Chaofan Tao, Zhuoqing Mao, Ngai Wong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing benchmarks fail to capture a crucial aspect of intelligence: physical reasoning, the integrated ability to combine domain knowledge, symbolic reasoning, and understanding of real-world constraints. To address this gap, we introduce PhyX: the first large-scale benchmark designed to assess models capacity for physics-grounded reasoning in visual scenarios. PhyX includes 3K meticulously curated multimodal questions spanning 6 reasoning types across 25 sub-domains and 6 core physics domains: thermodynamics, electromagnetism, mechanics, modern physics, optics, and wave\&amp;acoustics. In our comprehensive evaluation, even state-of-the-art models struggle significantly with physical reasoning. GPT-4o, Claude3.7-Sonnet, and GPT-o4-mini achieve only 32.5\%, 42.2\%, and 45.8\% accuracy respectively-performance gaps exceeding 29\% compared to human experts. Our analysis exposes critical limitations in current models: over-reliance on memorized disciplinary knowledge, excessive dependence on mathematical formulations, and surface-level visual pattern matching rather than genuine physical understanding. We provide in-depth analysis through fine-grained statistics, detailed case studies, and multiple evaluation paradigms to thoroughly examine physical reasoning capabilities. To ensure reproducibility, we implement a compatible evaluation protocol based on widely-used toolkits such as VLMEvalKit, enabling one-click evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15929</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 18:33:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Position of Uncertainty: A Cross-Linguistic Study of Positional Bias in   Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16134</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16134.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Menschikov Mikhail, Alexander Kharitonov, Maiia Kotyga, Vadim Porvatov, Anna Zhukovskaya, David Kagramanyan, Egor Shvetsov, Evgeny Burnaev&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models exhibit positional bias -- systematic neglect of information at specific context positions -- yet its interplay with linguistic diversity remains poorly understood. We present a cross-linguistic study across five typologically distinct languages (English, Russian, German, Hindi, Vietnamese), examining how positional bias interacts with model uncertainty, syntax, and prompting. Key findings: (1) Positional bias is model-driven, with language-specific variations -- Qwen2.5-7B favors late positions, challenging assumptions of early-token bias; (2) Explicit positional guidance (e.g., correct context is at position X) reduces accuracy across languages, undermining prompt-engineering practices; (3) Aligning context with positional bias increases entropy, yet minimal entropy does not predict accuracy. (4) We further uncover that LLMs differently impose dominant word order in free-word-order languages like Hindi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16134</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 02:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AudioTrust: Benchmarking the Multifaceted Trustworthiness of Audio Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16211</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16211.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kai Li, Can Shen, Yile Liu, Jirui Han, Kelong Zheng, Xuechao Zou, Zhe Wang, Xingjian Du, Shun Zhang, Hanjun Luo, Yingbin Jin, Xinxin Xing, Ziyang Ma, Yue Liu, Xiaojun Jia, Yifan Zhang, Junfeng Fang, Kun Wang, Yibo Yan, Haoyang Li, Yiming Li, Xiaobin Zhuang, Yang Liu, Haibo Hu, Zhuo Chen, Zhizheng Wu, Xiaolin Hu, Eng-Siong Chng, XiaoFeng Wang, Wenyuan Xu, Wei Dong, Xinfeng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement and expanding applications of Audio Large Language Models (ALLMs) demand a rigorous understanding of their trustworthiness. However, systematic research on evaluating these models, particularly concerning risks unique to the audio modality, remains largely unexplored. Existing evaluation frameworks primarily focus on the text modality or address only a restricted set of safety dimensions, failing to adequately account for the unique characteristics and application scenarios inherent to the audio modality. We introduce AudioTrust-the first multifaceted trustworthiness evaluation framework and benchmark specifically designed for ALLMs. AudioTrust facilitates assessments across six key dimensions: fairness, hallucination, safety, privacy, robustness, and authentication. To comprehensively evaluate these dimensions, AudioTrust is structured around 18 distinct experimental setups. Its core is a meticulously constructed dataset of over 4,420 audio/text samples, drawn from real-world scenarios (e.g., daily conversations, emergency calls, voice assistant interactions), specifically designed to probe the multifaceted trustworthiness of ALLMs. For assessment, the benchmark carefully designs 9 audio-specific evaluation metrics, and we employ a large-scale automated pipeline for objective and scalable scoring of model outputs. Experimental results reveal the trustworthiness boundaries and limitations of current state-of-the-art open-source and closed-source ALLMs when confronted with various high-risk audio scenarios, offering valuable insights for the secure and trustworthy deployment of future audio models. Our platform and benchmark are available at https://github.com/JusperLee/AudioTrust.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16211</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 04:27:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied Agents Meet Personalization: Exploring Memory Utilization for   Personalized Assistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16348</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16348.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taeyoon Kwon, Dongwook Choi, Sunghwan Kim, Hyojun Kim, Seungjun Moon, Beong-woo Kwak, Kuan-Hao Huang, Jinyoung Yeo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Embodied agents empowered by large language models (LLMs) have shown strong performance in household object rearrangement tasks. However, these tasks primarily focus on single-turn interactions with simplified instructions, which do not truly reflect the challenges of providing meaningful assistance to users. To provide personalized assistance, embodied agents must understand the unique semantics that users assign to the physical world (e.g., favorite cup, breakfast routine) by leveraging prior interaction history to interpret dynamic, real-world instructions. Yet, the effectiveness of embodied agents in utilizing memory for personalized assistance remains largely underexplored. To address this gap, we present MEMENTO, a personalized embodied agent evaluation framework designed to comprehensively assess memory utilization capabilities to provide personalized assistance. Our framework consists of a two-stage memory evaluation process design that enables quantifying the impact of memory utilization on task performance. This process enables the evaluation of agents' understanding of personalized knowledge in object rearrangement tasks by focusing on its role in goal interpretation: (1) the ability to identify target objects based on personal meaning (object semantics), and (2) the ability to infer object-location configurations from consistent user patterns, such as routines (user patterns). Our experiments across various LLMs reveal significant limitations in memory utilization, with even frontier models like GPT-4o experiencing a 30.5% performance drop when required to reference multiple memories, particularly in tasks involving user patterns. These findings, along with our detailed analyses and case studies, provide valuable insights for future research in developing more effective personalized embodied agents. Project website: https://connoriginal.github.io/MEMENTO&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16348</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 08:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMMR: Benchmarking Massive Multi-Modal Reasoning Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16459</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16459.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guiyao Tie, Xueyang Zhou, Tianhe Gu, Ruihang Zhang, Chaoran Hu, Sizhe Zhang, Mengqu Sun, Yan Zhang, Pan Zhou, Lichao Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Multi-Modal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have enabled unified processing of language, vision, and structured inputs, opening the door to complex tasks such as logical deduction, spatial reasoning, and scientific analysis. Despite their promise, the reasoning capabilities of MLLMs, particularly those augmented with intermediate thinking traces (MLLMs-T), remain poorly understood and lack standardized evaluation benchmarks. Existing work focuses primarily on perception or final answer correctness, offering limited insight into how models reason or fail across modalities. To address this gap, we introduce the MMMR, a new benchmark designed to rigorously evaluate multi-modal reasoning with explicit thinking. The MMMR comprises 1) a high-difficulty dataset of 1,083 questions spanning six diverse reasoning types with symbolic depth and multi-hop demands and 2) a modular Reasoning Trace Evaluation Pipeline (RTEP) for assessing reasoning quality beyond accuracy through metrics like relevance, consistency, and structured error annotations. Empirical results show that MLLMs-T overall outperform non-thinking counterparts, but even top models like Claude-3.7-Sonnet and Gemini-2.5 Pro suffer from reasoning pathologies such as inconsistency and overthinking. This benchmark reveals persistent gaps between accuracy and reasoning quality and provides an actionable evaluation pipeline for future model development. Overall, the MMMR offers a scalable foundation for evaluating, comparing, and improving the next generation of multi-modal reasoning systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16459</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 09:41:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Graph Model (CGM): A Graph-Integrated Large Language Model for   Repository-Level Software Engineering Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16901</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16901.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongyuan Tao, Ying Zhang, Zhenhao Tang, Hongen Peng, Xukun Zhu, Bingchang Liu, Yingguang Yang, Ziyin Zhang, Zhaogui Xu, Haipeng Zhang, Linchao Zhu, Rui Wang, Hang Yu, Jianguo Li, Peng Di&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown promise in function-level code generation, yet repository-level software engineering tasks remain challenging. Current solutions predominantly rely on proprietary LLM agents, which introduce unpredictability and limit accessibility, raising concerns about data privacy and model customization. This paper investigates whether open-source LLMs can effectively address repository-level tasks without requiring agent-based approaches. We demonstrate this is possible by enabling LLMs to comprehend functions and files within codebases through their semantic information and structural dependencies. To this end, we introduce Code Graph Models (CGMs), which integrate repository code graph structures into the LLM's attention mechanism and map node attributes to the LLM's input space using a specialized adapter. When combined with an agentless graph RAG framework, our approach achieves a 43.00% resolution rate on the SWE-bench Lite benchmark using the open-source Qwen2.5-72B model. This performance ranks first among open weight models, second among methods with open-source systems, and eighth overall, surpassing the previous best open-source model-based method by 12.33%.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16901</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:00:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Model is Stubborn: Diagnosing Instruction Overriding in   Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17225</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17225.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Doohyuk Jang, Yoonjeon Kim, Chanjae Park, Hyun Ryu, Eunho Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models have demonstrated remarkable proficiency in long and complex reasoning tasks. However, they frequently exhibit a problematic reliance on familiar reasoning patterns, a phenomenon we term reasoning rigidity. Despite explicit instructions from users, these models often override clearly stated conditions and default to habitual reasoning trajectories, leading to incorrect conclusions. This behavior presents significant challenges, particularly in domains such as mathematics and logic puzzle, where precise adherence to specified constraints is critical. To systematically investigate reasoning rigidity, a behavior largely unexplored in prior work, we introduce a expert-curated diagnostic set, . Our dataset includes specially modified variants of existing mathematical benchmarks, namely AIME and MATH500, as well as well-known puzzles deliberately redesigned to require deviation from familiar reasoning strategies. Using this dataset, we identify recurring contamination patterns that occur when models default to ingrained reasoning. Specifically, we categorize this contamination into three distinctive modes: (i) Interpretation Overload, (ii) Input Distrust, and (iii) Partial Instruction Attention, each causing models to ignore or distort provided instructions. We publicly release our diagnostic set to facilitate future research on mitigating reasoning rigidity in language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17225</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 19:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FS-DAG: Few Shot Domain Adapting Graph Networks for Visually Rich   Document Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17330</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17330.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amit Agarwal, Srikant Panda, Kulbhushan Pachauri&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we propose Few Shot Domain Adapting Graph (FS-DAG), a scalable and efficient model architecture for visually rich document understanding (VRDU) in few-shot settings. FS-DAG leverages domain-specific and language/vision specific backbones within a modular framework to adapt to diverse document types with minimal data. The model is robust to practical challenges such as handling OCR errors, misspellings, and domain shifts, which are critical in real-world deployments. FS-DAG is highly performant with less than 90M parameters, making it well-suited for complex real-world applications for Information Extraction (IE) tasks where computational resources are limited. We demonstrate FS-DAG's capability through extensive experiments for information extraction task, showing significant improvements in convergence speed and performance compared to state-of-the-art methods. Additionally, this work highlights the ongoing progress in developing smaller, more efficient models that do not compromise on performance. Code : https://github.com/oracle-samples/fs-dag&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17330</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 22:53:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SweEval: Do LLMs Really Swear? A Safety Benchmark for Testing Limits for   Enterprise Use</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17332</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17332.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hitesh Laxmichand Patel, Amit Agarwal, Arion Das, Bhargava Kumar, Srikant Panda, Priyaranjan Pattnayak, Taki Hasan Rafi, Tejaswini Kumar, Dong-Kyu Chae&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Enterprise customers are increasingly adopting Large Language Models (LLMs) for critical communication tasks, such as drafting emails, crafting sales pitches, and composing casual messages. Deploying such models across different regions requires them to understand diverse cultural and linguistic contexts and generate safe and respectful responses. For enterprise applications, it is crucial to mitigate reputational risks, maintain trust, and ensure compliance by effectively identifying and handling unsafe or offensive language. To address this, we introduce SweEval, a benchmark simulating real-world scenarios with variations in tone (positive or negative) and context (formal or informal). The prompts explicitly instruct the model to include specific swear words while completing the task. This benchmark evaluates whether LLMs comply with or resist such inappropriate instructions and assesses their alignment with ethical frameworks, cultural nuances, and language comprehension capabilities. In order to advance research in building ethically aligned AI systems for enterprise use and beyond, we release the dataset and code: https://github.com/amitbcp/multilingual_profanity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17332</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 22:56:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct3D-S2: Gigascale 3D Generation Made Easy with Spatial Sparse   Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17412</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17412.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuang Wu, Youtian Lin, Feihu Zhang, Yifei Zeng, Yikang Yang, Yajie Bao, Jiachen Qian, Siyu Zhu, Philip Torr, Xun Cao, Yao Yao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating high resolution 3D shapes using volumetric representations such as Signed Distance Functions presents substantial computational and memory challenges. We introduce Direct3D S2, a scalable 3D generation framework based on sparse volumes that achieves superior output quality with dramatically reduced training costs. Our key innovation is the Spatial Sparse Attention mechanism, which greatly enhances the efficiency of Diffusion Transformer computations on sparse volumetric data. SSA allows the model to effectively process large token sets within sparse volumes, significantly reducing computational overhead and achieving a 3.9x speedup in the forward pass and a 9.6x speedup in the backward pass. Our framework also includes a variational autoencoder that maintains a consistent sparse volumetric format across input, latent, and output stages. Compared to previous methods with heterogeneous representations in 3D VAE, this unified design significantly improves training efficiency and stability. Our model is trained on public available datasets, and experiments demonstrate that Direct3D S2 not only surpasses state-of-the-art methods in generation quality and efficiency, but also enables training at 1024 resolution using only 8 GPUs, a task typically requiring at least 32 GPUs for volumetric representations at 256 resolution, thus making gigascale 3D generation both practical and accessible. Project page: https://nju3dv.github.io/projects/Direct3D-S2/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17412</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 02:58:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Already Knows the Best Noise: Bayesian Active Noise Selection via   Attention in Video Diffusion Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17561</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17561.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kwanyoung Kim, Sanghyun Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The choice of initial noise significantly affects the quality and prompt alignment of video diffusion models, where different noise seeds for the same prompt can lead to drastically different generations. While recent methods rely on externally designed priors such as frequency filters or inter-frame smoothing, they often overlook internal model signals that indicate which noise seeds are inherently preferable. To address this, we propose ANSE (Active Noise Selection for Generation), a model-aware framework that selects high-quality noise seeds by quantifying attention-based uncertainty. At its core is BANSA (Bayesian Active Noise Selection via Attention), an acquisition function that measures entropy disagreement across multiple stochastic attention samples to estimate model confidence and consistency. For efficient inference-time deployment, we introduce a Bernoulli-masked approximation of BANSA that enables score estimation using a single diffusion step and a subset of attention layers. Experiments on CogVideoX-2B and 5B demonstrate that ANSE improves video quality and temporal coherence with only an 8% and 13% increase in inference time, respectively, providing a principled and generalizable approach to noise selection in video diffusion. See our project page: https://anse-project.github.io/anse-project/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17561</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 07:09:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distilling LLM Agent into Small Models with Retrieval and Code Tools</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17612</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17612.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minki Kang, Jongwon Jeong, Seanie Lee, Jaewoong Cho, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) excel at complex reasoning tasks but remain computationally expensive, limiting their practical deployment. To address this, recent works have focused on distilling reasoning capabilities into smaller language models (sLMs) using chain-of-thought (CoT) traces from teacher LLMs. However, this approach struggles in scenarios requiring rare factual knowledge or precise computation, where sLMs often hallucinate due to limited capability. In this work, we propose Agent Distillation, a framework for transferring not only reasoning capability but full task-solving behavior from LLM-based agents into sLMs with retrieval and code tools. We improve agent distillation along two complementary axes: (1) we introduce a prompting method called first-thought prefix to enhance the quality of teacher-generated trajectories; and (2) we propose a self-consistent action generation for improving test-time robustness of small agents. We evaluate our method on eight reasoning tasks across factual and mathematical domains, covering both in-domain and out-of-domain generalization. Our results show that sLMs as small as 0.5B, 1.5B, 3B parameters can achieve performance competitive with next-tier larger 1.5B, 3B, 7B models fine-tuned using CoT distillation, demonstrating the potential of agent distillation for building practical, tool-using small agents. Our code is available at https://github.com/Nardien/agent-distillation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17612</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 08:20:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Image and Video Generation via Test-Time Evolutionary Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran He, Jiajun Liang, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Kun Gai, Ling Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As the marginal cost of scaling computation (data and parameters) during model pre-training continues to increase substantially, test-time scaling (TTS) has emerged as a promising direction for improving generative model performance by allocating additional computation at inference time. While TTS has demonstrated significant success across multiple language tasks, there remains a notable gap in understanding the test-time scaling behaviors of image and video generative models (diffusion-based or flow-based models). Although recent works have initiated exploration into inference-time strategies for vision tasks, these approaches face critical limitations: being constrained to task-specific domains, exhibiting poor scalability, or falling into reward over-optimization that sacrifices sample diversity. In this paper, we propose Evolutionary Search (EvoSearch), a novel, generalist, and efficient TTS method that effectively enhances the scalability of both image and video generation across diffusion and flow models, without requiring additional training or model expansion. EvoSearch reformulates test-time scaling for diffusion and flow models as an evolutionary search problem, leveraging principles from biological evolution to efficiently explore and refine the denoising trajectory. By incorporating carefully designed selection and mutation mechanisms tailored to the stochastic differential equation denoising process, EvoSearch iteratively generates higher-quality offspring while preserving population diversity. Through extensive evaluation across both diffusion and flow architectures for image and video generation tasks, we demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms existing approaches, achieves higher diversity, and shows strong generalizability to unseen evaluation metrics. Our project is available at the website https://tinnerhrhe.github.io/evosearch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17618</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 08:25:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QwenLong-L1: Towards Long-Context Large Reasoning Models with   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17667</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17667.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fanqi Wan, Weizhou Shen, Shengyi Liao, Yingcheng Shi, Chenliang Li, Ziyi Yang, Ji Zhang, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 81&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent large reasoning models (LRMs) have demonstrated strong reasoning capabilities through reinforcement learning (RL). These improvements have primarily been observed within the short-context reasoning tasks. In contrast, extending LRMs to effectively process and reason on long-context inputs via RL remains a critical unsolved challenge. To bridge this gap, we first formalize the paradigm of long-context reasoning RL, and identify key challenges in suboptimal training efficiency and unstable optimization process. To address these issues, we propose QwenLong-L1, a framework that adapts short-context LRMs to long-context scenarios via progressive context scaling. Specifically, we utilize a warm-up supervised fine-tuning (SFT) stage to establish a robust initial policy, followed by a curriculum-guided phased RL technique to stabilize the policy evolution, and enhanced with a difficulty-aware retrospective sampling strategy to incentivize the policy exploration. Experiments on seven long-context document question-answering benchmarks demonstrate that QwenLong-L1-32B outperforms flagship LRMs like OpenAI-o3-mini and Qwen3-235B-A22B, achieving performance on par with Claude-3.7-Sonnet-Thinking, demonstrating leading performance among state-of-the-art LRMs. This work advances the development of practical long-context LRMs capable of robust reasoning across information-intensive environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17667</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 09:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Overthink it. Preferring Shorter Thinking Chains for Improved LLM   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17813</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17813.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Michael Hassid, Gabriel Synnaeve, Yossi Adi, Roy Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning large language models (LLMs) heavily rely on scaling test-time compute to perform complex reasoning tasks by generating extensive "thinking" chains. While demonstrating impressive results, this approach incurs significant computational costs and inference time. In this work, we challenge the assumption that long thinking chains results in better reasoning capabilities. We first demonstrate that shorter reasoning chains within individual questions are significantly more likely to yield correct answers - up to 34.5% more accurate than the longest chain sampled for the same question. Based on these results, we suggest short-m@k, a novel reasoning LLM inference method. Our method executes k independent generations in parallel and halts computation once the first m thinking processes are done. The final answer is chosen using majority voting among these m chains. Basic short-1@k demonstrates similar or even superior performance over standard majority voting in low-compute settings - using up to 40% fewer thinking tokens. short-3@k, while slightly less efficient than short-1@k, consistently surpasses majority voting across all compute budgets, while still being substantially faster (up to 33% wall time reduction). Inspired by our results, we finetune an LLM using short, long, and randomly selected reasoning chains. We then observe that training on the shorter ones leads to better performance. Our findings suggest rethinking current methods of test-time compute in reasoning LLMs, emphasizing that longer "thinking" does not necessarily translate to improved performance and can, counter-intuitively, lead to degraded results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17813</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 12:29:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOOSE-Chem3: Toward Experiment-Guided Hypothesis Ranking via Simulated   Experimental Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17873</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17873.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wanhao Liu, Zonglin Yang, Jue Wang, Lidong Bing, Di Zhang, Dongzhan Zhou, Yuqiang Li, Houqiang Li, Erik Cambria, Wanli Ouyang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Hypothesis ranking is a crucial component of automated scientific discovery, particularly in natural sciences where wet-lab experiments are costly and throughput-limited. Existing approaches focus on pre-experiment ranking, relying solely on large language model's internal reasoning without incorporating empirical outcomes from experiments. We introduce the task of experiment-guided ranking, which aims to prioritize candidate hypotheses based on the results of previously tested ones. However, developing such strategies is challenging due to the impracticality of repeatedly conducting real experiments in natural science domains. To address this, we propose a simulator grounded in three domain-informed assumptions, modeling hypothesis performance as a function of similarity to a known ground truth hypothesis, perturbed by noise. We curate a dataset of 124 chemistry hypotheses with experimentally reported outcomes to validate the simulator. Building on this simulator, we develop a pseudo experiment-guided ranking method that clusters hypotheses by shared functional characteristics and prioritizes candidates based on insights derived from simulated experimental feedback. Experiments show that our method outperforms pre-experiment baselines and strong ablations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17873</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 13:24:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutarjim: Advancing Bidirectional Arabic-English Translation with a   Small Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17894</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17894.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Khalil Hennara, Muhammad Hreden, Mohamed Motaism Hamed, Zeina Aldallal, Sara Chrouf, Safwan AlModhayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 209&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Mutarjim, a compact yet powerful language model for bidirectional Arabic-English translation. While large-scale LLMs have shown impressive progress in natural language processing tasks, including machine translation, smaller models. Leveraging this insight, we developed Mutarjim based on Kuwain-1.5B , a language model tailored for both Arabic and English. Despite its modest size, Mutarjim outperforms much larger models on several established benchmarks, achieved through an optimized two-phase training approach and a carefully curated, high-quality training corpus.. Experimental results show that Mutarjim rivals models up to 20 times larger while significantly reducing computational costs and training requirements. We also introduce Tarjama-25, a new benchmark designed to overcome limitations in existing Arabic-English benchmarking datasets, such as domain narrowness, short sentence lengths, and English-source bias. Tarjama-25 comprises 5,000 expert-reviewed sentence pairs and spans a wide range of domains, offering a more comprehensive and balanced evaluation framework. Notably, Mutarjim achieves state-of-the-art performance on the English-to-Arabic task in Tarjama-25, surpassing even significantly larger and proprietary models like GPT-4o mini. We publicly release Tarjama-25 to support future research and advance the evaluation of Arabic-English translation systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17894</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 13:42:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VeriThinker: Learning to Verify Makes Reasoning Model Efficient</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17941</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17941.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zigeng Chen, Xinyin Ma, Gongfan Fang, Ruonan Yu, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) excel at complex tasks using Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning. However, their tendency to overthinking leads to unnecessarily lengthy reasoning chains, dramatically increasing inference costs. To mitigate this issue, we introduce VeriThinker, a novel approach for CoT compression. Unlike conventional methods that fine-tune LRMs directly on the original reasoning task using synthetic concise CoT data, we innovatively fine-tune the model solely through an auxiliary verification task. By training LRMs to accurately verify the correctness of CoT solutions, the LRMs inherently become more discerning about the necessity of subsequent self-reflection steps, thereby effectively suppressing overthinking. Extensive experiments validate that VeriThinker substantially reduces reasoning chain lengths while maintaining or even slightly improving accuracy. When applied to DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-7B, our approach reduces reasoning tokens on MATH500 from 3790 to 2125 while improving accuracy by 0.8% (94.0% to 94.8%), and on AIME25, tokens decrease from 14321 to 10287 with a 2.1% accuracy gain (38.7% to 40.8%). Additionally, our experiments demonstrate that VeriThinker can also be zero-shot generalized to speculative reasoning. Code is available at https://github.com/czg1225/VeriThinker&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17941</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 14:17:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Distillation: Pushing the Limits of Medical LLM Reasoning with   Minimalist Rule-Based RL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17952</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17952.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Che Liu, Haozhe Wang, Jiazhen Pan, Zhongwei Wan, Yong Dai, Fangzhen Lin, Wenjia Bai, Daniel Rueckert, Rossella Arcucci&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Improving performance on complex tasks and enabling interpretable decision making in large language models (LLMs), especially for clinical applications, requires effective reasoning. Yet this remains challenging without supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on costly chain-of-thought (CoT) data distilled from closed-source models (e.g., GPT-4o). In this work, we present AlphaMed, the first medical LLM to show that reasoning capability can emerge purely through reinforcement learning (RL), using minimalist rule-based rewards on public multiple-choice QA datasets, without relying on SFT or distilled CoT data. AlphaMed achieves state-of-the-art results on six medical QA benchmarks, outperforming models trained with conventional SFT+RL pipelines. On challenging benchmarks (e.g., MedXpert), AlphaMed even surpasses larger or closed-source models such as DeepSeek-V3-671B and Claude-3.5-Sonnet. To understand the factors behind this success, we conduct a comprehensive data-centric analysis guided by three questions: (i) Can minimalist rule-based RL incentivize reasoning without distilled CoT supervision? (ii) How do dataset quantity and diversity impact reasoning? (iii) How does question difficulty shape the emergence and generalization of reasoning? Our findings show that dataset informativeness is a key driver of reasoning performance, and that minimalist RL on informative, multiple-choice QA data is effective at inducing reasoning without CoT supervision. We also observe divergent trends across benchmarks, underscoring limitations in current evaluation and the need for more challenging, reasoning-oriented medical QA benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17952</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 14:27:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Classifiers Understand Compositionality, but Conditions Apply</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17955</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17955.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yujin Jeong, Arnas Uselis, Seong Joon Oh, Anna Rohrbach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding visual scenes is fundamental to human intelligence. While discriminative models have significantly advanced computer vision, they often struggle with compositional understanding. In contrast, recent generative text-to-image diffusion models excel at synthesizing complex scenes, suggesting inherent compositional capabilities. Building on this, zero-shot diffusion classifiers have been proposed to repurpose diffusion models for discriminative tasks. While prior work offered promising results in discriminative compositional scenarios, these results remain preliminary due to a small number of benchmarks and a relatively shallow analysis of conditions under which the models succeed. To address this, we present a comprehensive study of the discriminative capabilities of diffusion classifiers on a wide range of compositional tasks. Specifically, our study covers three diffusion models (SD 1.5, 2.0, and, for the first time, 3-m) spanning 10 datasets and over 30 tasks. Further, we shed light on the role that target dataset domains play in respective performance; to isolate the domain effects, we introduce a new diagnostic benchmark Self-Bench comprised of images created by diffusion models themselves. Finally, we explore the importance of timestep weighting and uncover a relationship between domain gap and timestep sensitivity, particularly for SD3-m. To sum up, diffusion classifiers understand compositionality, but conditions apply! Code and dataset are available at https://github.com/eugene6923/Diffusion-Classifiers-Compositionality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17955</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 14:29:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QwenLong-CPRS: Towards infty-LLMs with Dynamic Context Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18092</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18092.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weizhou Shen, Chenliang Li, Fanqi Wan, Shengyi Liao, Shaopeng Lai, Bo Zhang, Yingcheng Shi, Yuning Wu, Gang Fu, Zhansheng Li, Bin Yang, Ji Zhang, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This technical report presents QwenLong-CPRS, a context compression framework designed for explicit long-context optimization, addressing prohibitive computation overhead during the prefill stage and the "lost in the middle" performance degradation of large language models (LLMs) during long sequence processing. Implemented through a novel dynamic context optimization mechanism, QwenLong-CPRS enables multi-granularity context compression guided by natural language instructions, achieving both efficiency gains and improved performance.   Evolved from the Qwen architecture series, QwenLong-CPRS introduces four key innovations: (1) Natural language-guided dynamic optimization, (2) Bidirectional reasoning layers for enhanced boundary awareness, (3) Token critic mechanisms with language modeling heads, and (4) Window-parallel inference.   Comprehensive evaluations across five benchmarks (4K-2M word contexts) demonstrate QwenLong-CPRS's threefold effectiveness: (1) Consistent superiority over other context management methods like RAG and sparse attention in both accuracy and efficiency. (2) Architecture-agnostic integration with all flagship LLMs, including GPT-4o, Gemini2.0-pro, Claude3.7-sonnet, DeepSeek-v3, and Qwen2.5-max, achieves 21.59times context compression alongside 19.15-point average performance gains; (3) Deployed with Qwen2.5-32B-Instruct, QwenLong-CPRS surpasses leading proprietary LLMs by 4.85 and 10.88 points on Ruler-128K and InfiniteBench, establishing new SOTA performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18092</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 16:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TabSTAR: A Foundation Tabular Model With Semantically Target-Aware   Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18125</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18125.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alan Arazi, Eilam Shapira, Roi Reichart&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 108&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While deep learning has achieved remarkable success across many domains, it has historically underperformed on tabular learning tasks, which remain dominated by gradient boosting decision trees (GBDTs). However, recent advancements are paving the way for Tabular Foundation Models, which can leverage real-world knowledge and generalize across diverse datasets, particularly when the data contains free-text. Although incorporating language model capabilities into tabular tasks has been explored, most existing methods utilize static, target-agnostic textual representations, limiting their effectiveness. We introduce TabSTAR: a Foundation Tabular Model with Semantically Target-Aware Representations. TabSTAR is designed to enable transfer learning on tabular data with textual features, with an architecture free of dataset-specific parameters. It unfreezes a pretrained text encoder and takes as input target tokens, which provide the model with the context needed to learn task-specific embeddings. TabSTAR achieves state-of-the-art performance for both medium- and large-sized datasets across known benchmarks of classification tasks with text features, and its pretraining phase exhibits scaling laws in the number of datasets, offering a pathway for further performance improvements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18125</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One RL to See Them All: Visual Triple Unified Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18129</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18129.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yan Ma, Linge Du, Xuyang Shen, Shaoxiang Chen, Pengfei Li, Qibing Ren, Lizhuang Ma, Yuchao Dai, Pengfei Liu, Junjie Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) has significantly advanced the reasoning capabilities of vision-language models (VLMs). However, the use of RL beyond reasoning tasks remains largely unexplored, especially for perceptionintensive tasks like object detection and grounding. We propose V-Triune, a Visual Triple Unified Reinforcement Learning system that enables VLMs to jointly learn visual reasoning and perception tasks within a single training pipeline. V-Triune comprises triple complementary components: Sample-Level Data Formatting (to unify diverse task inputs), Verifier-Level Reward Computation (to deliver custom rewards via specialized verifiers) , and Source-Level Metric Monitoring (to diagnose problems at the data-source level). We further introduce a novel Dynamic IoU reward, which provides adaptive, progressive, and definite feedback for perception tasks handled by V-Triune. Our approach is instantiated within off-the-shelf RL training framework using open-source 7B and 32B backbone models. The resulting model, dubbed Orsta (One RL to See Them All), demonstrates consistent improvements across both reasoning and perception tasks. This broad capability is significantly shaped by its training on a diverse dataset, constructed around four representative visual reasoning tasks (Math, Puzzle, Chart, and Science) and four visual perception tasks (Grounding, Detection, Counting, and OCR). Subsequently, Orsta achieves substantial gains on MEGA-Bench Core, with improvements ranging from +2.1 to an impressive +14.1 across its various 7B and 32B model variants, with performance benefits extending to a wide range of downstream tasks. These results highlight the effectiveness and scalability of our unified RL approach for VLMs. The V-Triune system, along with the Orsta models, is publicly available at https://github.com/MiniMax-AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18129</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 17:41:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guided by Gut: Efficient Test-Time Scaling with Reinforced Intrinsic   Confidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20325</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20325.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amirhosein Ghasemabadi, Keith G. Mills, Baochun Li, Di Niu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Test-Time Scaling (TTS) methods for enhancing Large Language Model (LLM) reasoning often incur substantial computational costs, primarily due to extensive reliance on external Process Reward Models (PRMs) or sampling methods like Best-of-N (BoN). This paper introduces Guided by Gut (GG), an efficient self-guided TTS framework that achieves PRM-level performance without costly external verifier models. Our method employs a lightweight tree search guided solely by intrinsic LLM signals, token-level confidence and step novelty. One critical innovation is improving the reliability of internal confidence estimates via a targeted reinforcement learning fine-tuning phase. Empirical evaluations on challenging mathematical reasoning benchmarks demonstrate that GG enables smaller models (e.g., 1.5B parameters) to achieve accuracy matching or surpassing significantly larger models (e.g., 32B-70B parameters), while reducing GPU memory usage by up to 10x. Compared to PRM-based methods, GG achieves comparable accuracy with 8x faster inference speeds and 4-5x lower memory usage. Additionally, GG reduces KV cache memory usage by approximately 50% compared to the BoN strategy, facilitating more efficient and practical deployment of TTS techniques.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20325</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 18:19:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hard Negative Mining for Domain-Specific Retrieval in Enterprise Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18366</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18366.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hansa Meghwani, Amit Agarwal, Priyaranjan Pattnayak, Hitesh Laxmichand Patel, Srikant Panda&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Enterprise search systems often struggle to retrieve accurate, domain-specific information due to semantic mismatches and overlapping terminologies. These issues can degrade the performance of downstream applications such as knowledge management, customer support, and retrieval-augmented generation agents. To address this challenge, we propose a scalable hard-negative mining framework tailored specifically for domain-specific enterprise data. Our approach dynamically selects semantically challenging but contextually irrelevant documents to enhance deployed re-ranking models.   Our method integrates diverse embedding models, performs dimensionality reduction, and uniquely selects hard negatives, ensuring computational efficiency and semantic precision. Evaluation on our proprietary enterprise corpus (cloud services domain) demonstrates substantial improvements of 15\% in MRR@3 and 19\% in MRR@10 compared to state-of-the-art baselines and other negative sampling techniques. Further validation on public domain-specific datasets (FiQA, Climate Fever, TechQA) confirms our method's generalizability and readiness for real-world applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18366</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 20:51:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniConsistency: Learning Style-Agnostic Consistency from Paired   Stylization Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18445</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18445.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiren Song, Cheng Liu, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion models have advanced image stylization significantly, yet two core challenges persist: (1) maintaining consistent stylization in complex scenes, particularly identity, composition, and fine details, and (2) preventing style degradation in image-to-image pipelines with style LoRAs. GPT-4o's exceptional stylization consistency highlights the performance gap between open-source methods and proprietary models. To bridge this gap, we propose OmniConsistency, a universal consistency plugin leveraging large-scale Diffusion Transformers (DiTs). OmniConsistency contributes: (1) an in-context consistency learning framework trained on aligned image pairs for robust generalization; (2) a two-stage progressive learning strategy decoupling style learning from consistency preservation to mitigate style degradation; and (3) a fully plug-and-play design compatible with arbitrary style LoRAs under the Flux framework. Extensive experiments show that OmniConsistency significantly enhances visual coherence and aesthetic quality, achieving performance comparable to commercial state-of-the-art model GPT-4o.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18445</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 01:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Fine-Tuning Powers Reasoning Capability of Multimodal   Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18536</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18536.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoyuan Sun, Jiaqi Wu, Bo Xia, Yifu Luo, Yifei Zhao, Kai Qin, Xufei Lv, Tiantian Zhang, Yongzhe Chang, Xueqian Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Standing in 2025, at a critical juncture in the pursuit of Artificial General Intelligence (AGI), reinforcement fine-tuning (RFT) has demonstrated significant potential in enhancing the reasoning capability of large language models (LLMs) and has led to the development of cutting-edge AI models such as OpenAI-o1 and DeepSeek-R1. Moreover, the efficient application of RFT to enhance the reasoning capability of multimodal large language models (MLLMs) has attracted widespread attention from the community. In this position paper, we argue that reinforcement fine-tuning powers the reasoning capability of multimodal large language models. To begin with, we provide a detailed introduction to the fundamental background knowledge that researchers interested in this field should be familiar with. Furthermore, we meticulously summarize the improvements of RFT in powering reasoning capability of MLLMs into five key points: diverse modalities, diverse tasks and domains, better training algorithms, abundant benchmarks and thriving engineering frameworks. Finally, we propose five promising directions for future research that the community might consider. We hope that this position paper will provide valuable insights to the community at this pivotal stage in the advancement toward AGI. Summary of works done on RFT for MLLMs is available at https://github.com/Sun-Haoyuan23/Awesome-RL-based-Reasoning-MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18536</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 06:01:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>B-score: Detecting biases in large language models using response   history</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18545</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18545.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; An Vo, Mohammad Reza Taesiri, Daeyoung Kim, Anh Totti Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) often exhibit strong biases, e.g, against women or in favor of the number 7. We investigate whether LLMs would be able to output less biased answers when allowed to observe their prior answers to the same question in a multi-turn conversation. To understand which types of questions invite more biased answers, we test LLMs on our proposed set of questions that span 9 topics and belong to three types: (1) Subjective; (2) Random; and (3) Objective. Interestingly, LLMs are able to "de-bias" themselves in a multi-turn conversation in response to questions that seek an Random, unbiased answer. Furthermore, we propose B-score, a novel metric that is effective in detecting biases to Subjective, Random, Easy, and Hard questions. On MMLU, HLE, and CSQA, leveraging B-score substantially improves the verification accuracy of LLM answers (i.e, accepting LLM correct answers and rejecting incorrect ones) compared to using verbalized confidence scores or the frequency of single-turn answers alone. Code and data are available at: https://b-score.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18545</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 06:23:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain-of-Zoom: Extreme Super-Resolution via Scale Autoregression and   Preference Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18600</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18600.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bryan Sangwoo Kim, Jeongsol Kim, Jong Chul Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern single-image super-resolution (SISR) models deliver photo-realistic results at the scale factors on which they are trained, but collapse when asked to magnify far beyond that regime. We address this scalability bottleneck with Chain-of-Zoom (CoZ), a model-agnostic framework that factorizes SISR into an autoregressive chain of intermediate scale-states with multi-scale-aware prompts. CoZ repeatedly re-uses a backbone SR model, decomposing the conditional probability into tractable sub-problems to achieve extreme resolutions without additional training. Because visual cues diminish at high magnifications, we augment each zoom step with multi-scale-aware text prompts generated by a vision-language model (VLM). The prompt extractor itself is fine-tuned using Generalized Reward Policy Optimization (GRPO) with a critic VLM, aligning text guidance towards human preference. Experiments show that a standard 4x diffusion SR model wrapped in CoZ attains beyond 256x enlargement with high perceptual quality and fidelity. Project Page: https://bryanswkim.github.io/chain-of-zoom/ .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18600</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 08:50:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flex-Judge: Think Once, Judge Anywhere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18601</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18601.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jongwoo Ko, Sungnyun Kim, Sungwoo Cho, Se-Young Yun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human-generated reward signals are critical for aligning generative models with human preferences, guiding both training and inference-time evaluations. While large language models (LLMs) employed as proxy evaluators, i.e., LLM-as-a-Judge, significantly reduce the costs associated with manual annotations, they typically require extensive modality-specific training data and fail to generalize well across diverse multimodal tasks. In this paper, we propose Flex-Judge, a reasoning-guided multimodal judge model that leverages minimal textual reasoning data to robustly generalize across multiple modalities and evaluation formats. Our core intuition is that structured textual reasoning explanations inherently encode generalizable decision-making patterns, enabling an effective transfer to multimodal judgments, e.g., with images or videos. Empirical results demonstrate that Flex-Judge, despite being trained on significantly fewer text data, achieves competitive or superior performance compared to state-of-the-art commercial APIs and extensively trained multimodal evaluators. Notably, Flex-Judge presents broad impact in modalities like molecule, where comprehensive evaluation benchmarks are scarce, underscoring its practical value in resource-constrained domains. Our framework highlights reasoning-based text supervision as a powerful, cost-effective alternative to traditional annotation-intensive approaches, substantially advancing scalable multimodal model-as-a-judge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18601</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 08:50:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can MLLMs Guide Me Home? A Benchmark Study on Fine-Grained Visual   Reasoning from Transit Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18675</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18675.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sicheng Feng, Song Wang, Shuyi Ouyang, Lingdong Kong, Zikai Song, Jianke Zhu, Huan Wang, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have recently achieved significant progress in visual tasks, including semantic scene understanding and text-image alignment, with reasoning variants enhancing performance on complex tasks involving mathematics and logic. However, their capacity for reasoning tasks involving fine-grained visual understanding remains insufficiently evaluated. To address this gap, we introduce ReasonMap, a benchmark designed to assess the fine-grained visual understanding and spatial reasoning abilities of MLLMs. ReasonMap encompasses high-resolution transit maps from 30 cities across 13 countries and includes 1,008 question-answer pairs spanning two question types and three templates. Furthermore, we design a two-level evaluation pipeline that properly assesses answer correctness and quality. Comprehensive evaluations of 15 popular MLLMs, including both base and reasoning variants, reveal a counterintuitive pattern: among open-source models, base models outperform reasoning ones, while the opposite trend is observed in closed-source models. Additionally, performance generally degrades when visual inputs are masked, indicating that while MLLMs can leverage prior knowledge to answer some questions, fine-grained visual reasoning tasks still require genuine visual perception for strong performance. Our benchmark study offers new insights into visual reasoning and contributes to investigating the gap between open-source and closed-source models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18675</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 12:33:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse VideoGen2: Accelerate Video Generation with Sparse Attention via   Semantic-Aware Permutation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18875</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18875.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuo Yang, Haocheng Xi, Yilong Zhao, Muyang Li, Jintao Zhang, Han Cai, Yujun Lin, Xiuyu Li, Chenfeng Xu, Kelly Peng, Jianfei Chen, Song Han, Kurt Keutzer, Ion Stoica&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Transformers (DiTs) are essential for video generation but suffer from significant latency due to the quadratic complexity of attention. By computing only critical tokens, sparse attention reduces computational costs and offers a promising acceleration approach. However, we identify that existing methods fail to approach optimal generation quality under the same computation budget for two reasons: (1) Inaccurate critical token identification: current methods cluster tokens based on position rather than semantics, leading to imprecise aggregated representations. (2) Excessive computation waste: critical tokens are scattered among non-critical ones, leading to wasted computation on GPUs, which are optimized for processing contiguous tokens. In this paper, we propose SVG2, a training-free framework that maximizes identification accuracy and minimizes computation waste, achieving a Pareto frontier trade-off between generation quality and efficiency. The core of SVG2 is semantic-aware permutation, which clusters and reorders tokens based on semantic similarity using k-means. This approach ensures both a precise cluster representation, improving identification accuracy, and a densified layout of critical tokens, enabling efficient computation without padding. Additionally, SVG2 integrates top-p dynamic budget control and customized kernel implementations, achieving up to 2.30x and 1.89x speedup while maintaining a PSNR of up to 30 and 26 on HunyuanVideo and Wan 2.1, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18875</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 21:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Neural-MPM for Interactive Fluid Simulations in Real-Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18926</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18926.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingxuan Xu, Hong Huang, Chuhang Zou, Manolis Savva, Yunchao Wei, Wuyang Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a neural physics system for real-time, interactive fluid simulations. Traditional physics-based methods, while accurate, are computationally intensive and suffer from latency issues. Recent machine-learning methods reduce computational costs while preserving fidelity; yet most still fail to satisfy the latency constraints for real-time use and lack support for interactive applications. To bridge this gap, we introduce a novel hybrid method that integrates numerical simulation, neural physics, and generative control. Our neural physics jointly pursues low-latency simulation and high physical fidelity by employing a fallback safeguard to classical numerical solvers. Furthermore, we develop a diffusion-based controller that is trained using a reverse modeling strategy to generate external dynamic force fields for fluid manipulation. Our system demonstrates robust performance across diverse 2D/3D scenarios, material types, and obstacle interactions, achieving real-time simulations at high frame rates (11~29% latency) while enabling fluid control guided by user-friendly freehand sketches. We present a significant step towards practical, controllable, and physically plausible fluid simulations for real-time interactive applications. We promise to release both models and data upon acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18926</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 01:27:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MetaMind: Modeling Human Social Thoughts with Metacognitive Multi-Agent   Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18943</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18943.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuanming Zhang, Yuxuan Chen, Min-Hsuan Yeh, Yixuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human social interactions depend on the ability to infer others' unspoken intentions, emotions, and beliefs-a cognitive skill grounded in the psychological concept of Theory of Mind (ToM). While large language models (LLMs) excel in semantic understanding tasks, they struggle with the ambiguity and contextual nuance inherent in human communication. To bridge this gap, we introduce MetaMind, a multi-agent framework inspired by psychological theories of metacognition, designed to emulate human-like social reasoning. MetaMind decomposes social understanding into three collaborative stages: (1) a Theory-of-Mind Agent generates hypotheses user mental states (e.g., intent, emotion), (2) a Domain Agent refines these hypotheses using cultural norms and ethical constraints, and (3) a Response Agent generates contextually appropriate responses while validating alignment with inferred intent. Our framework achieves state-of-the-art performance across three challenging benchmarks, with 35.7% improvement in real-world social scenarios and 6.2% gain in ToM reasoning. Notably, it enables LLMs to match human-level performance on key ToM tasks for the first time. Ablation studies confirm the necessity of all components, which showcase the framework's ability to balance contextual plausibility, social appropriateness, and user adaptation. This work advances AI systems toward human-like social intelligence, with applications in empathetic dialogue and culturally sensitive interactions. Code is available at https://github.com/XMZhangAI/MetaMind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18943</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 02:32:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VerIPO: Cultivating Long Reasoning in Video-LLMs via Verifier-Gudied   Iterative Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19000</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19000.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunxin Li, Xinyu Chen, Zitao Li, Zhenyu Liu, Longyue Wang, Wenhan Luo, Baotian Hu, Min Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Applying Reinforcement Learning (RL) to Video Large Language Models (Video-LLMs) shows significant promise for complex video reasoning. However, popular Reinforcement Fine-Tuning (RFT) methods, such as outcome-based Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), are limited by data preparation bottlenecks (e.g., noise or high cost) and exhibit unstable improvements in the quality of long chain-of-thoughts (CoTs) and downstream performance.To address these limitations, we propose VerIPO, a Verifier-guided Iterative Policy Optimization method designed to gradually improve video LLMs' capacity for generating deep, long-term reasoning chains. The core component is Rollout-Aware Verifier, positioned between the GRPO and Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) training phases to form the GRPO-Verifier-DPO training loop. This verifier leverages small LLMs as a judge to assess the reasoning logic of rollouts, enabling the construction of high-quality contrastive data, including reflective and contextually consistent CoTs. These curated preference samples drive the efficient DPO stage (7x faster than GRPO), leading to marked improvements in reasoning chain quality, especially in terms of length and contextual consistency. This training loop benefits from GRPO's expansive search and DPO's targeted optimization. Experimental results demonstrate: 1) Significantly faster and more effective optimization compared to standard GRPO variants, yielding superior performance; 2) Our trained models exceed the direct inference of large-scale instruction-tuned Video-LLMs, producing long and contextually consistent CoTs on diverse video reasoning tasks; and 3) Our model with one iteration outperforms powerful LMMs (e.g., Kimi-VL) and long reasoning models (e.g., Video-R1), highlighting its effectiveness and stability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 06:41:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Reasoner: A Single, Composable Plug-and-Play Reasoner for   Frozen LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19075</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19075.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaemin Kim, Hangeol Chang, Hyunmin Hwang, Choonghan Kim, Jong Chul Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable general capabilities, but enhancing skills such as reasoning often demands substantial computational resources and may compromise their generalization. While Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) methods offer a more resource-conscious alternative, they typically requires retraining for each LLM backbone due to architectural dependencies. To address these challenges, here we propose Universal Reasoner (UniR) - a single, lightweight, composable, and plug-and-play reasoning module that can be used with any frozen LLM to endow it with specialized reasoning capabilities. Specifically, UniR decomposes the reward into a standalone reasoning module that is trained independently using predefined rewards, effectively translating trajectory-level signals into token-level guidance. Once trained, UniR can be combined with any frozen LLM at inference time by simply adding its output logits to those of the LLM backbone. This additive structure naturally enables modular composition: multiple UniR modules trained for different tasks can be jointly applied by summing their logits, enabling complex reasoning via composition. Experimental results on mathematical reasoning and machine translation tasks show that UniR significantly outperforms existing baseline fine-tuning methods using the Llama3.2 model. Furthermore, UniR demonstrates strong weak-to-strong generalization: reasoning modules trained on smaller models effectively guide much larger LLMs. This makes UniR a cost-efficient, adaptable, and robust solution for enhancing reasoning in LLMs without compromising their core capabilities. Code is open-sourced at https://github.com/hangeol/UniR&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19075</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 10:19:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jodi: Unification of Visual Generation and Understanding via Joint   Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19084</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19084.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifeng Xu, Zhenliang He, Meina Kan, Shiguang Shan, Xilin Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual generation and understanding are two deeply interconnected aspects of human intelligence, yet they have been traditionally treated as separate tasks in machine learning. In this paper, we propose Jodi, a diffusion framework that unifies visual generation and understanding by jointly modeling the image domain and multiple label domains. Specifically, Jodi is built upon a linear diffusion transformer along with a role switch mechanism, which enables it to perform three particular types of tasks: (1) joint generation, where the model simultaneously generates images and multiple labels; (2) controllable generation, where images are generated conditioned on any combination of labels; and (3) image perception, where multiple labels can be predicted at once from a given image. Furthermore, we present the Joint-1.6M dataset, which contains 200,000 high-quality images collected from public sources, automatic labels for 7 visual domains, and LLM-generated captions. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Jodi excels in both generation and understanding tasks and exhibits strong extensibility to a wider range of visual domains. Code is available at https://github.com/VIPL-GENUN/Jodi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19084</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 10:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shifting AI Efficiency From Model-Centric to Data-Centric Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19147</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19147.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuyang Liu, Zichen Wen, Shaobo Wang, Junjie Chen, Zhishan Tao, Yubo Wang, Xiangqi Jin, Chang Zou, Yiyu Wang, Chenfei Liao, Xu Zheng, Honggang Chen, Weijia Li, Xuming Hu, Conghui He, Linfeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 139&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of large language models (LLMs) and multi-modal LLMs (MLLMs) has historically relied on model-centric scaling through increasing parameter counts from millions to hundreds of billions to drive performance gains. However, as we approach hardware limits on model size, the dominant computational bottleneck has fundamentally shifted to the quadratic cost of self-attention over long token sequences, now driven by ultra-long text contexts, high-resolution images, and extended videos. In this position paper, we argue that the focus of research for efficient AI is shifting from model-centric compression to data-centric compression. We position token compression as the new frontier, which improves AI efficiency via reducing the number of tokens during model training or inference. Through comprehensive analysis, we first examine recent developments in long-context AI across various domains and establish a unified mathematical framework for existing model efficiency strategies, demonstrating why token compression represents a crucial paradigm shift in addressing long-context overhead. Subsequently, we systematically review the research landscape of token compression, analyzing its fundamental benefits and identifying its compelling advantages across diverse scenarios. Furthermore, we provide an in-depth analysis of current challenges in token compression research and outline promising future directions. Ultimately, our work aims to offer a fresh perspective on AI efficiency, synthesize existing research, and catalyze innovative developments to address the challenges that increasing context lengths pose to the AI community's advancement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19147</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 13:51:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOOSE-Chem2: Exploring LLM Limits in Fine-Grained Scientific Hypothesis   Discovery via Hierarchical Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19209</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19209.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zonglin Yang, Wanhao Liu, Ben Gao, Yujie Liu, Wei Li, Tong Xie, Lidong Bing, Wanli Ouyang, Erik Cambria, Dongzhan Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have shown promise in automating scientific hypothesis generation, yet existing approaches primarily yield coarse-grained hypotheses lacking critical methodological and experimental details. We introduce and formally define the novel task of fine-grained scientific hypothesis discovery, which entails generating detailed, experimentally actionable hypotheses from coarse initial research directions. We frame this as a combinatorial optimization problem and investigate the upper limits of LLMs' capacity to solve it when maximally leveraged. Specifically, we explore four foundational questions: (1) how to best harness an LLM's internal heuristics to formulate the fine-grained hypothesis it itself would judge as the most promising among all the possible hypotheses it might generate, based on its own internal scoring-thus defining a latent reward landscape over the hypothesis space; (2) whether such LLM-judged better hypotheses exhibit stronger alignment with ground-truth hypotheses; (3) whether shaping the reward landscape using an ensemble of diverse LLMs of similar capacity yields better outcomes than defining it with repeated instances of the strongest LLM among them; and (4) whether an ensemble of identical LLMs provides a more reliable reward landscape than a single LLM. To address these questions, we propose a hierarchical search method that incrementally proposes and integrates details into the hypothesis, progressing from general concepts to specific experimental configurations. We show that this hierarchical process smooths the reward landscape and enables more effective optimization. Empirical evaluations on a new benchmark of expert-annotated fine-grained hypotheses from recent chemistry literature show that our method consistently outperforms strong baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19209</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 16:13:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PATS: Process-Level Adaptive Thinking Mode Switching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19250</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19250.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Wang, Junxiao Liu, Shimao Zhang, Jiajun Chen, Shujian Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current large-language models (LLMs) typically adopt a fixed reasoning strategy, either simple or complex, for all questions, regardless of their difficulty. This neglect of variation in task and reasoning process complexity leads to an imbalance between performance and efficiency. Existing methods attempt to implement training-free fast-slow thinking system switching to handle problems of varying difficulty, but are limited by coarse-grained solution-level strategy adjustments. To address this issue, we propose a novel reasoning paradigm: Process-Level Adaptive Thinking Mode Switching (PATS), which enables LLMs to dynamically adjust their reasoning strategy based on the difficulty of each step, optimizing the balance between accuracy and computational efficiency. Our approach integrates Process Reward Models (PRMs) with Beam Search, incorporating progressive mode switching and bad-step penalty mechanisms. Experiments on diverse mathematical benchmarks demonstrate that our methodology achieves high accuracy while maintaining moderate token usage. This study emphasizes the significance of process-level, difficulty-aware reasoning strategy adaptation, offering valuable insights into efficient inference for LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19250</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 17:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepResearchGym: A Free, Transparent, and Reproducible Evaluation   Sandbox for Deep Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19253</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19253.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; João Coelho, Jingjie Ning, Jingyuan He, Kangrui Mao, Abhijay Paladugu, Pranav Setlur, Jiahe Jin, Jamie Callan, João Magalhães, Bruno Martins, Chenyan Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep research systems represent an emerging class of agentic information retrieval methods that generate comprehensive and well-supported reports to complex queries. However, most existing frameworks rely on dynamic commercial search APIs, which pose reproducibility and transparency challenges in addition to their cost. To address these limitations, we introduce DeepResearchGym, an open-source sandbox that combines a reproducible search API with a rigorous evaluation protocol for benchmarking deep research systems. The API indexes large-scale public web corpora, namely ClueWeb22 and FineWeb, using a state-of-the-art dense retriever and approximate nearest neighbor search via DiskANN. It achieves lower latency than popular commercial APIs while ensuring stable document rankings across runs, and is freely available for research use. To evaluate deep research systems' outputs, we extend the Researchy Questions benchmark with automatic metrics through LLM-as-a-judge assessments to measure alignment with users' information needs, retrieval faithfulness, and report quality. Experimental results show that systems integrated with DeepResearchGym achieve performance comparable to those using commercial APIs, with performance rankings remaining consistent across evaluation metrics. A human evaluation study further confirms that our automatic protocol aligns with human preferences, validating the framework's ability to help support controlled assessment of deep research systems. Our code and API documentation are available at https://www.deepresearchgym.ai.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19253</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 18:16:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alchemist: Turning Public Text-to-Image Data into Generative Gold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19297</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19297.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Valerii Startsev, Alexander Ustyuzhanin, Alexey Kirillov, Dmitry Baranchuk, Sergey Kastryulin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Pre-training equips text-to-image (T2I) models with broad world knowledge, but this alone is often insufficient to achieve high aesthetic quality and alignment. Consequently, supervised fine-tuning (SFT) is crucial for further refinement. However, its effectiveness highly depends on the quality of the fine-tuning dataset. Existing public SFT datasets frequently target narrow domains (e.g., anime or specific art styles), and the creation of high-quality, general-purpose SFT datasets remains a significant challenge. Current curation methods are often costly and struggle to identify truly impactful samples. This challenge is further complicated by the scarcity of public general-purpose datasets, as leading models often rely on large, proprietary, and poorly documented internal data, hindering broader research progress. This paper introduces a novel methodology for creating general-purpose SFT datasets by leveraging a pre-trained generative model as an estimator of high-impact training samples. We apply this methodology to construct and release Alchemist, a compact (3,350 samples) yet highly effective SFT dataset. Experiments demonstrate that Alchemist substantially improves the generative quality of five public T2I models while preserving diversity and style. Additionally, we release the fine-tuned models' weights to the public.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19297</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 20:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surrogate Signals from Format and Length: Reinforcement Learning for   Solving Mathematical Problems without Ground Truth Answers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19439</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19439.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rihui Xin, Han Liu, Zecheng Wang, Yupeng Zhang, Dianbo Sui, Xiaolin Hu, Bingning Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models have achieved remarkable success in natural language processing tasks, with Reinforcement Learning playing a key role in adapting them to specific applications. However, obtaining ground truth answers for training LLMs in mathematical problem-solving is often challenging, costly, and sometimes unfeasible. This research delves into the utilization of format and length as surrogate signals to train LLMs for mathematical problem-solving, bypassing the need for traditional ground truth answers.Our study shows that a reward function centered on format correctness alone can yield performance improvements comparable to the standard GRPO algorithm in early phases. Recognizing the limitations of format-only rewards in the later phases, we incorporate length-based rewards. The resulting GRPO approach, leveraging format-length surrogate signals, not only matches but surpasses the performance of the standard GRPO algorithm relying on ground truth answers in certain scenarios, achieving 40.0\% accuracy on AIME2024 with a 7B base model. Through systematic exploration and experimentation, this research not only offers a practical solution for training LLMs to solve mathematical problems and reducing the dependence on extensive ground truth data collection, but also reveals the essence of why our label-free approach succeeds: base model is like an excellent student who has already mastered mathematical and logical reasoning skills, but performs poorly on the test paper, it simply needs to develop good answering habits to achieve outstanding results in exams , in other words, to unlock the capabilities it already possesses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19439</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 02:56:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BizFinBench: A Business-Driven Real-World Financial Benchmark for   Evaluating LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19457</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19457.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guilong Lu, Xuntao Guo, Rongjunchen Zhang, Wenqiao Zhu, Ji Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models excel in general tasks, yet assessing their reliability in logic-heavy, precision-critical domains like finance, law, and healthcare remains challenging. To address this, we introduce BizFinBench, the first benchmark specifically designed to evaluate LLMs in real-world financial applications. BizFinBench consists of 6,781 well-annotated queries in Chinese, spanning five dimensions: numerical calculation, reasoning, information extraction, prediction recognition, and knowledge-based question answering, grouped into nine fine-grained categories. The benchmark includes both objective and subjective metrics. We also introduce IteraJudge, a novel LLM evaluation method that reduces bias when LLMs serve as evaluators in objective metrics. We benchmark 25 models, including both proprietary and open-source systems. Extensive experiments show that no model dominates across all tasks. Our evaluation reveals distinct capability patterns: (1) In Numerical Calculation, Claude-3.5-Sonnet (63.18) and DeepSeek-R1 (64.04) lead, while smaller models like Qwen2.5-VL-3B (15.92) lag significantly; (2) In Reasoning, proprietary models dominate (ChatGPT-o3: 83.58, Gemini-2.0-Flash: 81.15), with open-source models trailing by up to 19.49 points; (3) In Information Extraction, the performance spread is the largest, with DeepSeek-R1 scoring 71.46, while Qwen3-1.7B scores 11.23; (4) In Prediction Recognition, performance variance is minimal, with top models scoring between 39.16 and 50.00. We find that while current LLMs handle routine finance queries competently, they struggle with complex scenarios requiring cross-concept reasoning. BizFinBench offers a rigorous, business-aligned benchmark for future research. The code and dataset are available at https://github.com/HiThink-Research/BizFinBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19457</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 03:23:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GraLoRA: Granular Low-Rank Adaptation for Parameter-Efficient   Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20355</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20355.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yeonjoon Jung, Daehyun Ahn, Hyungjun Kim, Taesu Kim, Eunhyeok Park&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) is a popular method for parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) of generative models, valued for its simplicity and effectiveness. Despite recent enhancements, LoRA still suffers from a fundamental limitation: overfitting when the bottleneck is widened. It performs best at ranks 32-64, yet its accuracy stagnates or declines at higher ranks, still falling short of full fine-tuning (FFT) performance. We identify the root cause as LoRA's structural bottleneck, which introduces gradient entanglement to the unrelated input channels and distorts gradient propagation. To address this, we introduce a novel structure, Granular Low-Rank Adaptation (GraLoRA) that partitions weight matrices into sub-blocks, each with its own low-rank adapter. With negligible computational or storage cost, GraLoRA overcomes LoRA's limitations, effectively increases the representational capacity, and more closely approximates FFT behavior. Experiments on code generation and commonsense reasoning benchmarks show that GraLoRA consistently outperforms LoRA and other baselines, achieving up to +8.5% absolute gain in Pass@1 on HumanEval+. These improvements hold across model sizes and rank settings, making GraLoRA a scalable and robust solution for PEFT. Code, data, and scripts are available at https://github.com/SqueezeBits/GraLoRA.git&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20355</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 06:48:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Reason without External Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19590</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19590.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuandong Zhao, Zhewei Kang, Aosong Feng, Sergey Levine, Dawn Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training large language models (LLMs) for complex reasoning via Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) is effective but limited by reliance on costly, domain-specific supervision. We explore Reinforcement Learning from Internal Feedback (RLIF), a framework that enables LLMs to learn from intrinsic signals without external rewards or labeled data. We propose Intuitor, an RLIF method that uses a model's own confidence, termed self-certainty, as its sole reward signal. Intuitor replaces external rewards in Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) with self-certainty scores, enabling fully unsupervised learning. Experiments demonstrate that Intuitor matches GRPO's performance on mathematical benchmarks while achieving superior generalization to out-of-domain tasks like code generation, without requiring gold solutions or test cases. Our findings show that intrinsic model signals can drive effective learning across domains, offering a scalable alternative to RLVR for autonomous AI systems where verifiable rewards are unavailable. Code is available at https://github.com/sunblaze-ucb/Intuitor&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19590</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 07:01:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SynLogic: Synthesizing Verifiable Reasoning Data at Scale for Learning   Logical Reasoning and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19641</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19641.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junteng Liu, Yuanxiang Fan, Zhuo Jiang, Han Ding, Yongyi Hu, Chi Zhang, Yiqi Shi, Shitong Weng, Aili Chen, Shiqi Chen, Yunan Huang, Mozhi Zhang, Pengyu Zhao, Junjie Yan, Junxian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances such as OpenAI-o1 and DeepSeek R1 have demonstrated the potential of Reinforcement Learning (RL) to enhance reasoning abilities in Large Language Models (LLMs). While open-source replication efforts have primarily focused on mathematical and coding domains, methods and resources for developing general reasoning capabilities remain underexplored. This gap is partly due to the challenge of collecting diverse and verifiable reasoning data suitable for RL. We hypothesize that logical reasoning is critical for developing general reasoning capabilities, as logic forms a fundamental building block of reasoning. In this work, we present SynLogic, a data synthesis framework and dataset that generates diverse logical reasoning data at scale, encompassing 35 diverse logical reasoning tasks. The SynLogic approach enables controlled synthesis of data with adjustable difficulty and quantity. Importantly, all examples can be verified by simple rules, making them ideally suited for RL with verifiable rewards. In our experiments, we validate the effectiveness of RL training on the SynLogic dataset based on 7B and 32B models. SynLogic leads to state-of-the-art logical reasoning performance among open-source datasets, surpassing DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-32B by 6 points on BBEH. Furthermore, mixing SynLogic data with mathematical and coding tasks improves the training efficiency of these domains and significantly enhances reasoning generalization. Notably, our mixed training model outperforms DeepSeek-R1-Zero-Qwen-32B across multiple benchmarks. These findings position SynLogic as a valuable resource for advancing the broader reasoning capabilities of LLMs. We open-source both the data synthesis pipeline and the SynLogic dataset at https://github.com/MiniMax-AI/SynLogic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19641</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 07:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Markov Bridge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19752</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19752.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hengli Li, Yuxuan Wang, Song-Chun Zhu, Ying Nian Wu, Zilong Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Discrete diffusion has recently emerged as a promising paradigm in discrete data modeling. However, existing methods typically rely on a fixed rate transition matrix during training, which not only limits the expressiveness of latent representations, a fundamental strength of variational methods, but also constrains the overall design space. To address these limitations, we propose Discrete Markov Bridge, a novel framework specifically designed for discrete representation learning. Our approach is built upon two key components: Matrix Learning and Score Learning. We conduct a rigorous theoretical analysis, establishing formal performance guarantees for Matrix Learning and proving the convergence of the overall framework. Furthermore, we analyze the space complexity of our method, addressing practical constraints identified in prior studies. Extensive empirical evaluations validate the effectiveness of the proposed Discrete Markov Bridge, which achieves an Evidence Lower Bound (ELBO) of 1.38 on the Text8 dataset, outperforming established baselines. Moreover, the proposed model demonstrates competitive performance on the CIFAR-10 dataset, achieving results comparable to those obtained by image-specific generation approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19752</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 09:32:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering Trajectory-Aided LLM Reasoning: An Optimization Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19815</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19815.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junnan Liu, Hongwei Liu, Linchen Xiao, Shudong Liu, Taolin Zhang, Zihan Ma, Songyang Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel framework for comprehending the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs) through the perspective of meta-learning. By conceptualizing reasoning trajectories as pseudo-gradient descent updates to the LLM's parameters, we identify parallels between LLM reasoning and various meta-learning paradigms. We formalize the training process for reasoning tasks as a meta-learning setup, with each question treated as an individual task, and reasoning trajectories serving as the inner loop optimization for adapting model parameters. Once trained on a diverse set of questions, the LLM develops fundamental reasoning capabilities that can generalize to previously unseen questions. Extensive empirical evaluations substantiate the strong connection between LLM reasoning and meta-learning, exploring several issues of significant interest from a meta-learning standpoint. Our work not only enhances the understanding of LLM reasoning but also provides practical insights for improving these models through established meta-learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19815</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 10:52:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ScienceBoard: Evaluating Multimodal Autonomous Agents in Realistic   Scientific Workflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19897</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19897.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qiushi Sun, Zhoumianze Liu, Chang Ma, Zichen Ding, Fangzhi Xu, Zhangyue Yin, Haiteng Zhao, Zhenyu Wu, Kanzhi Cheng, Zhaoyang Liu, Jianing Wang, Qintong Li, Xiangru Tang, Tianbao Xie, Xiachong Feng, Xiang Li, Ben Kao, Wenhai Wang, Biqing Qi, Lingpeng Kong, Zhiyong Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 98&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have extended their impact beyond Natural Language Processing, substantially fostering the development of interdisciplinary research. Recently, various LLM-based agents have been developed to assist scientific discovery progress across multiple aspects and domains. Among these, computer-using agents, capable of interacting with operating systems as humans do, are paving the way to automated scientific problem-solving and addressing routines in researchers' workflows. Recognizing the transformative potential of these agents, we introduce ScienceBoard, which encompasses two complementary contributions: (i) a realistic, multi-domain environment featuring dynamic and visually rich scientific workflows with integrated professional software, where agents can autonomously interact via different interfaces to accelerate complex research tasks and experiments; and (ii) a challenging benchmark of 169 high-quality, rigorously validated real-world tasks curated by humans, spanning scientific-discovery workflows in domains such as biochemistry, astronomy, and geoinformatics. Extensive evaluations of agents with state-of-the-art backbones (e.g., GPT-4o, Claude 3.7, UI-TARS) show that, despite some promising results, they still fall short of reliably assisting scientists in complex workflows, achieving only a 15% overall success rate. In-depth analysis further provides valuable insights for addressing current agent limitations and more effective design principles, paving the way to build more capable agents for scientific discovery. Our code, environment, and benchmark are at https://qiushisun.github.io/ScienceBoard-Home/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19897</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 12:27:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enigmata: Scaling Logical Reasoning in Large Language Models with   Synthetic Verifiable Puzzles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19914</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19914.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiangjie Chen, Qianyu He, Siyu Yuan, Aili Chen, Zhicheng Cai, Weinan Dai, Hongli Yu, Qiying Yu, Xuefeng Li, Jiaze Chen, Hao Zhou, Mingxuan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs), such as OpenAI's o1 and DeepSeek's R1, excel at advanced reasoning tasks like math and coding via Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR), but still struggle with puzzles solvable by humans without domain knowledge. We introduce Enigmata, the first comprehensive suite tailored for improving LLMs with puzzle reasoning skills. It includes 36 tasks across seven categories, each with 1) a generator that produces unlimited examples with controllable difficulty and 2) a rule-based verifier for automatic evaluation. This generator-verifier design supports scalable, multi-task RL training, fine-grained analysis, and seamless RLVR integration. We further propose Enigmata-Eval, a rigorous benchmark, and develop optimized multi-task RLVR strategies. Our trained model, Qwen2.5-32B-Enigmata, consistently surpasses o3-mini-high and o1 on the puzzle reasoning benchmarks like Enigmata-Eval, ARC-AGI (32.8%), and ARC-AGI 2 (0.6%). It also generalizes well to out-of-domain puzzle benchmarks and mathematical reasoning, with little multi-tasking trade-off. When trained on larger models like Seed1.5-Thinking (20B activated parameters and 200B total parameters), puzzle data from Enigmata further boosts SoTA performance on advanced math and STEM reasoning tasks such as AIME (2024-2025), BeyondAIME and GPQA (Diamond), showing nice generalization benefits of Enigmata. This work offers a unified, controllable framework for advancing logical reasoning in LLMs. Resources of this work can be found at https://seed-enigmata.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19914</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 12:40:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REARANK: Reasoning Re-ranking Agent via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20046</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20046.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Le Zhang, Bo Wang, Xipeng Qiu, Siva Reddy, Aishwarya Agrawal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present REARANK, a large language model (LLM)-based listwise reasoning reranking agent. REARANK explicitly reasons before reranking, significantly improving both performance and interpretability. Leveraging reinforcement learning and data augmentation, REARANK achieves substantial improvements over baseline models across popular information retrieval benchmarks, notably requiring only 179 annotated samples. Built on top of Qwen2.5-7B, our REARANK-7B demonstrates performance comparable to GPT-4 on both in-domain and out-of-domain benchmarks and even surpasses GPT-4 on reasoning-intensive BRIGHT benchmarks. These results underscore the effectiveness of our approach and highlight how reinforcement learning can enhance LLM reasoning capabilities in reranking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20046</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 14:31:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Domain Explainability of Preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20088</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20088.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nitay Calderon, Liat Ein-Dor, Roi Reichart&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Preference mechanisms, such as human preference, LLM-as-a-Judge (LaaJ), and reward models, are central to aligning and evaluating large language models (LLMs). Yet, the underlying concepts that drive these preferences remain poorly understood. In this work, we propose a fully automated method for generating local and global concept-based explanations of preferences across multiple domains. Our method utilizes an LLM to identify concepts that distinguish between chosen and rejected responses, and to represent them with concept-based vectors. To model the relationships between concepts and preferences, we propose a white-box Hierarchical Multi-Domain Regression model that captures both domain-general and domain-specific effects. To evaluate our method, we curate a dataset spanning eight challenging and diverse domains and explain twelve mechanisms. Our method achieves strong preference prediction performance, outperforming baselines while also being explainable. Additionally, we assess explanations in two application-driven settings. First, guiding LLM outputs with concepts from LaaJ explanations yields responses that those judges consistently prefer. Second, prompting LaaJs with concepts explaining humans improves their preference predictions. Together, our work establishes a new paradigm for explainability in the era of LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20088</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 15:01:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StructEval: Benchmarking LLMs' Capabilities to Generate Structural   Outputs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20139</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20139.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jialin Yang, Dongfu Jiang, Lipeng He, Sherman Siu, Yuxuan Zhang, Disen Liao, Zhuofeng Li, Huaye Zeng, Yiming Jia, Haozhe Wang, Benjamin Schneider, Chi Ruan, Wentao Ma, Zhiheng Lyu, Yifei Wang, Yi Lu, Quy Duc Do, Ziyan Jiang, Ping Nie, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As Large Language Models (LLMs) become integral to software development workflows, their ability to generate structured outputs has become critically important. We introduce StructEval, a comprehensive benchmark for evaluating LLMs' capabilities in producing both non-renderable (JSON, YAML, CSV) and renderable (HTML, React, SVG) structured formats. Unlike prior benchmarks, StructEval systematically evaluates structural fidelity across diverse formats through two paradigms: 1) generation tasks, producing structured output from natural language prompts, and 2) conversion tasks, translating between structured formats. Our benchmark encompasses 18 formats and 44 types of task, with novel metrics for format adherence and structural correctness. Results reveal significant performance gaps, even state-of-the-art models like o1-mini achieve only 75.58 average score, with open-source alternatives lagging approximately 10 points behind. We find generation tasks more challenging than conversion tasks, and producing correct visual content more difficult than generating text-only structures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20139</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 15:40:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Omni-R1: Reinforcement Learning for Omnimodal Reasoning via Two-System   Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20256</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20256.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Zhong, Muzhi Zhu, Zongze Du, Zheng Huang, Canyu Zhao, Mingyu Liu, Wen Wang, Hao Chen, Chunhua Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-horizon video-audio reasoning and fine-grained pixel understanding impose conflicting requirements on omnimodal models: dense temporal coverage demands many low-resolution frames, whereas precise grounding calls for high-resolution inputs. We tackle this trade-off with a two-system architecture: a Global Reasoning System selects informative keyframes and rewrites the task at low spatial cost, while a Detail Understanding System performs pixel-level grounding on the selected high-resolution snippets. Because ``optimal'' keyframe selection and reformulation are ambiguous and hard to supervise, we formulate them as a reinforcement learning (RL) problem and present Omni-R1, an end-to-end RL framework built on Group Relative Policy Optimization. Omni-R1 trains the Global Reasoning System through hierarchical rewards obtained via online collaboration with the Detail Understanding System, requiring only one epoch of RL on small task splits.   Experiments on two challenging benchmarks, namely Referring Audio-Visual Segmentation (RefAVS) and Reasoning Video Object Segmentation (REVOS), show that Omni-R1 not only surpasses strong supervised baselines but also outperforms specialized state-of-the-art models, while substantially improving out-of-domain generalization and mitigating multimodal hallucination. Our results demonstrate the first successful application of RL to large-scale omnimodal reasoning and highlight a scalable path toward universally foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20256</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:34:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARM: Adaptive Reasoning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20258</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20258.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siye Wu, Jian Xie, Yikai Zhang, Aili Chen, Kai Zhang, Yu Su, Yanghua Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While large reasoning models demonstrate strong performance on complex tasks, they lack the ability to adjust reasoning token usage based on task difficulty. This often leads to the "overthinking" problem -- excessive and unnecessary reasoning -- which, although potentially mitigated by human intervention to control the token budget, still fundamentally contradicts the goal of achieving fully autonomous AI. In this work, we propose Adaptive Reasoning Model (ARM), a reasoning model capable of adaptively selecting appropriate reasoning formats based on the task at hand. These formats include three efficient ones -- Direct Answer, Short CoT, and Code -- as well as a more elaborate format, Long CoT. To train ARM, we introduce Ada-GRPO, an adaptation of Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), which addresses the format collapse issue in traditional GRPO. Ada-GRPO enables ARM to achieve high token efficiency, reducing tokens by an average of 30%, and up to 70%, while maintaining performance comparable to the model that relies solely on Long CoT. Furthermore, not only does it improve inference efficiency through reduced token generation, but it also brings a 2x speedup in training. In addition to the default Adaptive Mode, ARM supports two additional reasoning modes: 1) Instruction-Guided Mode, which allows users to explicitly specify the reasoning format via special tokens -- ideal when the appropriate format is known for a batch of tasks. 2) Consensus-Guided Mode, which aggregates the outputs of the three efficient formats and resorts to Long CoT in case of disagreement, prioritizing performance with higher token usage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20258</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:38:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifelong Safety Alignment for Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20259</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20259.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoyu Wang, Zeyu Qin, Yifei Zhao, Chao Du, Min Lin, Xueqian Wang, Tianyu Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLMs have made impressive progress, but their growing capabilities also expose them to highly flexible jailbreaking attacks designed to bypass safety alignment. While many existing defenses focus on known types of attacks, it is more critical to prepare LLMs for unseen attacks that may arise during deployment. To address this, we propose a lifelong safety alignment framework that enables LLMs to continuously adapt to new and evolving jailbreaking strategies. Our framework introduces a competitive setup between two components: a Meta-Attacker, trained to actively discover novel jailbreaking strategies, and a Defender, trained to resist them. To effectively warm up the Meta-Attacker, we first leverage the GPT-4o API to extract key insights from a large collection of jailbreak-related research papers. Through iterative training, the first iteration Meta-Attacker achieves a 73% attack success rate (ASR) on RR and a 57% transfer ASR on LAT using only single-turn attacks. Meanwhile, the Defender progressively improves its robustness and ultimately reduces the Meta-Attacker's success rate to just 7%, enabling safer and more reliable deployment of LLMs in open-ended environments. The code is available at https://github.com/sail-sg/LifelongSafetyAlignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20259</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:40:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ImgEdit: A Unified Image Editing Dataset and Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20275</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20275.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Ye, Xianyi He, Zongjian Li, Bin Lin, Shenghai Yuan, Zhiyuan Yan, Bohan Hou, Li Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in generative models have enabled high-fidelity text-to-image generation. However, open-source image-editing models still lag behind their proprietary counterparts, primarily due to limited high-quality data and insufficient benchmarks. To overcome these limitations, we introduce ImgEdit, a large-scale, high-quality image-editing dataset comprising 1.2 million carefully curated edit pairs, which contain both novel and complex single-turn edits, as well as challenging multi-turn tasks. To ensure the data quality, we employ a multi-stage pipeline that integrates a cutting-edge vision-language model, a detection model, a segmentation model, alongside task-specific in-painting procedures and strict post-processing. ImgEdit surpasses existing datasets in both task novelty and data quality. Using ImgEdit, we train ImgEdit-E1, an editing model using Vision Language Model to process the reference image and editing prompt, which outperforms existing open-source models on multiple tasks, highlighting the value of ImgEdit and model design. For comprehensive evaluation, we introduce ImgEdit-Bench, a benchmark designed to evaluate image editing performance in terms of instruction adherence, editing quality, and detail preservation. It includes a basic testsuite, a challenging single-turn suite, and a dedicated multi-turn suite. We evaluate both open-source and proprietary models, as well as ImgEdit-E1, providing deep analysis and actionable insights into the current behavior of image-editing models. The source data are publicly available on https://github.com/PKU-YuanGroup/ImgEdit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20275</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:53:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MotionPro: A Precise Motion Controller for Image-to-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20287</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20287.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongwei Zhang, Fuchen Long, Zhaofan Qiu, Yingwei Pan, Wu Liu, Ting Yao, Tao Mei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Animating images with interactive motion control has garnered popularity for image-to-video (I2V) generation. Modern approaches typically rely on large Gaussian kernels to extend motion trajectories as condition without explicitly defining movement region, leading to coarse motion control and failing to disentangle object and camera moving. To alleviate these, we present MotionPro, a precise motion controller that novelly leverages region-wise trajectory and motion mask to regulate fine-grained motion synthesis and identify target motion category (i.e., object or camera moving), respectively. Technically, MotionPro first estimates the flow maps on each training video via a tracking model, and then samples the region-wise trajectories to simulate inference scenario. Instead of extending flow through large Gaussian kernels, our region-wise trajectory approach enables more precise control by directly utilizing trajectories within local regions, thereby effectively characterizing fine-grained movements. A motion mask is simultaneously derived from the predicted flow maps to capture the holistic motion dynamics of the movement regions. To pursue natural motion control, MotionPro further strengthens video denoising by incorporating both region-wise trajectories and motion mask through feature modulation. More remarkably, we meticulously construct a benchmark, i.e., MC-Bench, with 1.1K user-annotated image-trajectory pairs, for the evaluation of both fine-grained and object-level I2V motion control. Extensive experiments conducted on WebVid-10M and MC-Bench demonstrate the effectiveness of MotionPro. Please refer to our project page for more results: https://zhw-zhang.github.io/MotionPro-page/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20287</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenS2V-Nexus: A Detailed Benchmark and Million-Scale Dataset for   Subject-to-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20292</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20292.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shenghai Yuan, Xianyi He, Yufan Deng, Yang Ye, Jinfa Huang, Bin Lin, Chongyang Ma, Jiebo Luo, Li Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Subject-to-Video (S2V) generation aims to create videos that faithfully incorporate reference content, providing enhanced flexibility in the production of videos. To establish the infrastructure for S2V generation, we propose OpenS2V-Nexus, consisting of (i) OpenS2V-Eval, a fine-grained benchmark, and (ii) OpenS2V-5M, a million-scale dataset. In contrast to existing S2V benchmarks inherited from VBench that focus on global and coarse-grained assessment of generated videos, OpenS2V-Eval focuses on the model's ability to generate subject-consistent videos with natural subject appearance and identity fidelity. For these purposes, OpenS2V-Eval introduces 180 prompts from seven major categories of S2V, which incorporate both real and synthetic test data. Furthermore, to accurately align human preferences with S2V benchmarks, we propose three automatic metrics, NexusScore, NaturalScore and GmeScore, to separately quantify subject consistency, naturalness, and text relevance in generated videos. Building on this, we conduct a comprehensive evaluation of 16 representative S2V models, highlighting their strengths and weaknesses across different content. Moreover, we create the first open-source large-scale S2V generation dataset OpenS2V-5M, which consists of five million high-quality 720P subject-text-video triples. Specifically, we ensure subject-information diversity in our dataset by (1) segmenting subjects and building pairing information via cross-video associations and (2) prompting GPT-Image-1 on raw frames to synthesize multi-view representations. Through OpenS2V-Nexus, we deliver a robust infrastructure to accelerate future S2V generation research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20292</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-rebench: An Automated Pipeline for Task Collection and   Decontaminated Evaluation of Software Engineering Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20411</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20411.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ibragim Badertdinov, Alexander Golubev, Maksim Nekrashevich, Anton Shevtsov, Simon Karasik, Andrei Andriushchenko, Maria Trofimova, Daria Litvintseva, Boris Yangel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 78&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM-based agents have shown promising capabilities in a growing range of software engineering (SWE) tasks. However, advancing this field faces two critical challenges. First, high-quality training data is scarce, especially data that reflects real-world SWE scenarios, where agents must interact with development environments, execute code and adapt behavior based on the outcomes of their actions. Existing datasets are either limited to one-shot code generation or comprise small, manually curated collections of interactive tasks, lacking both scale and diversity. Second, the lack of fresh interactive SWE tasks affects evaluation of rapidly improving models, as static benchmarks quickly become outdated due to contamination issues. To address these limitations, we introduce a novel, automated, and scalable pipeline to continuously extract real-world interactive SWE tasks from diverse GitHub repositories. Using this pipeline, we construct SWE-rebench, a public dataset comprising over 21,000 interactive Python-based SWE tasks, suitable for reinforcement learning of SWE agents at scale. Additionally, we use continuous supply of fresh tasks collected using SWE-rebench methodology to build a contamination-free benchmark for agentic software engineering. We compare results of various LLMs on this benchmark to results on SWE-bench Verified and show that performance of some language models might be inflated due to contamination issues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20411</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 18:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SageAttention2++: A More Efficient Implementation of SageAttention2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21136</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21136.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Xiaoming Xu, Jia Wei, Haofeng Huang, Pengle Zhang, Chendong Xiang, Jun Zhu, Jianfei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The efficiency of attention is critical because its time complexity grows quadratically with sequence length. SageAttention2 addresses this by utilizing quantization to accelerate matrix multiplications (Matmul) in attention. To further accelerate SageAttention2, we propose to utilize the faster instruction of FP8 Matmul accumulated in FP16. The instruction is 2x faster than the FP8 Matmul used in SageAttention2. Our experiments show that SageAttention2++ achieves a 3.9x speedup over FlashAttention while maintaining the same attention accuracy as SageAttention2. This means SageAttention2++ effectively accelerates various models, including those for language, image, and video generation, with negligible end-to-end metrics loss. The code will be available at https://github.com/thu-ml/SageAttention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21136</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 12:50:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Latent Capacity of LLMs for One-Step Text Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21189</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21189.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gleb Mezentsev, Ivan Oseledets&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A recent study showed that large language models (LLMs) can reconstruct surprisingly long texts - up to thousands of tokens - via autoregressive generation from just one specially trained input embedding. In this work, we explore whether such reconstruction is possible without autoregression. We show that frozen LLMs can generate hundreds of accurate tokens in just one forward pass, when provided with only two learned embeddings. This reveals a surprising and underexplored capability of LLMs - multi-token generation without iterative decoding. We investigate the behaviour of these embeddings and provide insight into the type of information they encode. We also empirically show that although these representations are not unique for a given text, they form connected and local regions in embedding space - a property that suggests the potential of learning a dedicated encoder into that space.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21189</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 13:39:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>rStar-Coder: Scaling Competitive Code Reasoning with a Large-Scale   Verified Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21297</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21297.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifei Liu, Li Lyna Zhang, Yi Zhu, Bingcheng Dong, Xudong Zhou, Ning Shang, Fan Yang, Mao Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Advancing code reasoning in large language models (LLMs) is fundamentally limited by the scarcity of high-difficulty datasets, especially those with verifiable input-output test cases necessary for rigorous solution validation at scale. We introduce rStar-Coder, which significantly improves LLM code reasoning capabilities by constructing a large-scale, verified dataset of 418K competition-level code problems, 580K long-reasoning solutions along with rich test cases of varying difficulty. This is achieved through three core contributions: (1) we curate competitive programming code problems and oracle solutions to synthesize new, solvable problems; (2) we introduce a reliable input-output test case synthesis pipeline that decouples the generation into a three-step input generation method and a mutual verification mechanism for effective output labeling; (3) we augment problems with high-quality, test-case-verified long-reasoning solutions. Extensive experiments on Qwen models (1.5B-14B) across various code reasoning benchmarks demonstrate the superiority of rStar-Coder dataset, achieving leading performance comparable to frontier reasoning LLMs with much smaller model sizes. On LiveCodeBench, rStar-Coder improves Qwen2.5-7B from 17.4% to an impressive 57.3%, and Qwen2.5-14B from 23.3% to 62.5%, surpassing o3-mini (low) by3.1%. On the more challenging USA Computing Olympiad, our 7B model achieves an average pass@1 accuracy of 16.15%, outperforming the frontier-level QWQ-32B. Code and the dataset will be released at https://github.com/microsoft/rStar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21297</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 15:00:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MME-Reasoning: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Logical Reasoning in MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21327</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21327.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiakang Yuan, Tianshuo Peng, Yilei Jiang, Yiting Lu, Renrui Zhang, Kaituo Feng, Chaoyou Fu, Tao Chen, Lei Bai, Bo Zhang, Xiangyu Yue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Logical reasoning is a fundamental aspect of human intelligence and an essential capability for multimodal large language models (MLLMs). Despite the significant advancement in multimodal reasoning, existing benchmarks fail to comprehensively evaluate their reasoning abilities due to the lack of explicit categorization for logical reasoning types and an unclear understanding of reasoning. To address these issues, we introduce MME-Reasoning, a comprehensive benchmark designed to evaluate the reasoning ability of MLLMs, which covers all three types of reasoning (i.e., inductive, deductive, and abductive) in its questions. We carefully curate the data to ensure that each question effectively evaluates reasoning ability rather than perceptual skills or knowledge breadth, and extend the evaluation protocols to cover the evaluation of diverse questions. Our evaluation reveals substantial limitations of state-of-the-art MLLMs when subjected to holistic assessments of logical reasoning capabilities. Even the most advanced MLLMs show limited performance in comprehensive logical reasoning, with notable performance imbalances across reasoning types. In addition, we conducted an in-depth analysis of approaches such as ``thinking mode'' and Rule-based RL, which are commonly believed to enhance reasoning abilities. These findings highlight the critical limitations and performance imbalances of current MLLMs in diverse logical reasoning scenarios, providing comprehensive and systematic insights into the understanding and evaluation of reasoning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21327</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 15:23:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MME-VideoOCR: Evaluating OCR-Based Capabilities of Multimodal LLMs in   Video Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21333</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21333.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Shi, Huanqian Wang, Wulin Xie, Huanyao Zhang, Lijie Zhao, Yi-Fan Zhang, Xinfeng Li, Chaoyou Fu, Zhuoer Wen, Wenting Liu, Zhuoran Zhang, Xinlong Chen, Bohan Zeng, Sihan Yang, Yuanxing Zhang, Pengfei Wan, Haotian Wang, Wenjing Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have achieved considerable accuracy in Optical Character Recognition (OCR) from static images. However, their efficacy in video OCR is significantly diminished due to factors such as motion blur, temporal variations, and visual effects inherent in video content. To provide clearer guidance for training practical MLLMs, we introduce the MME-VideoOCR benchmark, which encompasses a comprehensive range of video OCR application scenarios. MME-VideoOCR features 10 task categories comprising 25 individual tasks and spans 44 diverse scenarios. These tasks extend beyond text recognition to incorporate deeper comprehension and reasoning of textual content within videos. The benchmark consists of 1,464 videos with varying resolutions, aspect ratios, and durations, along with 2,000 meticulously curated, manually annotated question-answer pairs. We evaluate 18 state-of-the-art MLLMs on MME-VideoOCR, revealing that even the best-performing model (Gemini-2.5 Pro) achieves an accuracy of only 73.7%. Fine-grained analysis indicates that while existing MLLMs demonstrate strong performance on tasks where relevant texts are contained within a single or few frames, they exhibit limited capability in effectively handling tasks that demand holistic video comprehension. These limitations are especially evident in scenarios that require spatio-temporal reasoning, cross-frame information integration, or resistance to language prior bias. Our findings also highlight the importance of high-resolution visual input and sufficient temporal coverage for reliable OCR in dynamic video scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21333</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 15:27:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HoliTom: Holistic Token Merging for Fast Video Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21334</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21334.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kele Shao, Keda Tao, Can Qin, Haoxuan You, Yang Sui, Huan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video large language models (video LLMs) excel at video comprehension but face significant computational inefficiency due to redundant video tokens. Existing token pruning methods offer solutions. However, approaches operating within the LLM (inner-LLM pruning), such as FastV, incur intrinsic computational overhead in shallow layers. In contrast, methods performing token pruning before the LLM (outer-LLM pruning) primarily address spatial redundancy within individual frames or limited temporal windows, neglecting the crucial global temporal dynamics and correlations across longer video sequences. This leads to sub-optimal spatio-temporal reduction and does not leverage video compressibility fully. Crucially, the synergistic potential and mutual influence of combining these strategies remain unexplored. To further reduce redundancy, we introduce HoliTom, a novel training-free holistic token merging framework. HoliTom employs outer-LLM pruning through global redundancy-aware temporal segmentation, followed by spatial-temporal merging to reduce visual tokens by over 90%, significantly alleviating the LLM's computational burden. Complementing this, we introduce a robust inner-LLM token similarity-based merging approach, designed for superior performance and compatibility with outer-LLM pruning. Evaluations demonstrate our method's promising efficiency-performance trade-off on LLaVA-OneVision-7B, reducing computational costs to 6.9% of FLOPs while maintaining 99.1% of the original performance. Furthermore, we achieve a 2.28x reduction in Time-To-First-Token (TTFT) and a 1.32x acceleration in decoding throughput, highlighting the practical benefits of our integrated pruning approach for efficient video LLMs inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21334</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 15:28:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video-Holmes: Can MLLM Think Like Holmes for Complex Video Reasoning?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21374</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21374.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junhao Cheng, Yuying Ge, Teng Wang, Yixiao Ge, Jing Liao, Ying Shan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in CoT reasoning and RL post-training have been reported to enhance video reasoning capabilities of MLLMs. This progress naturally raises a question: can these models perform complex video reasoning in a manner comparable to human experts? However, existing video benchmarks primarily evaluate visual perception and grounding abilities, with questions that can be answered based on explicit prompts or isolated visual cues. Such benchmarks do not fully capture the intricacies of real-world reasoning, where humans must actively search for, integrate, and analyze multiple clues before reaching a conclusion. To address this issue, we present Video-Holmes, a benchmark inspired by the reasoning process of Sherlock Holmes, designed to evaluate the complex video reasoning capabilities of MLLMs. Video-Holmes consists of 1,837 questions derived from 270 manually annotated suspense short films, which spans seven carefully designed tasks. Each task is constructed by first identifying key events and causal relationships within films, and then designing questions that require models to actively locate and connect multiple relevant visual clues scattered across different video segments. Our comprehensive evaluation of state-of-the-art MLLMs reveals that, while these models generally excel at visual perception, they encounter substantial difficulties with integrating information and often miss critical clues. For example, the best-performing model, Gemini-2.5-Pro, achieves an accuracy of only 45%, with most models scoring below 40%. We aim that Video-Holmes can serve as a "Holmes-test" for multimodal reasoning, motivating models to reason more like humans and emphasizing the ongoing challenges in this field. The benchmark is released in https://github.com/TencentARC/Video-Holmes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21374</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 16:05:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R2R: Efficiently Navigating Divergent Reasoning Paths with Small-Large   Model Token Routing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21600</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21600.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Fu, Yi Ge, Yichen You, Enshu Liu, Zhihang Yuan, Guohao Dai, Shengen Yan, Huazhong Yang, Yu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) achieve impressive reasoning capabilities at the cost of substantial inference overhead, posing substantial deployment challenges. Although distilled Small Language Models (SLMs) significantly enhance efficiency, their performance suffers as they fail to follow LLMs' reasoning paths. Luckily, we reveal that only a small fraction of tokens genuinely diverge reasoning paths between LLMs and SLMs. Most generated tokens are either identical or exhibit neutral differences, such as minor variations in abbreviations or expressions. Leveraging this insight, we introduce **Roads to Rome (R2R)**, a neural token routing method that selectively utilizes LLMs only for these critical, path-divergent tokens, while leaving the majority of token generation to the SLM. We also develop an automatic data generation pipeline that identifies divergent tokens and generates token-level routing labels to train the lightweight router. We apply R2R to combine R1-1.5B and R1-32B models from the DeepSeek family, and evaluate on challenging math, coding, and QA benchmarks. With an average activated parameter size of 5.6B, R2R surpasses the average accuracy of R1-7B by 1.6x, outperforming even the R1-14B model. Compared to R1-32B, it delivers a 2.8x wall-clock speedup with comparable performance, advancing the Pareto frontier of test-time scaling efficiency. Our code is available at https://github.com/thu-nics/R2R.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21600</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 16:57:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frame In-N-Out: Unbounded Controllable Image-to-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21491</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21491.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Boyang Wang, Xuweiyi Chen, Matheus Gadelha, Zezhou Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Controllability, temporal coherence, and detail synthesis remain the most critical challenges in video generation. In this paper, we focus on a commonly used yet underexplored cinematic technique known as Frame In and Frame Out. Specifically, starting from image-to-video generation, users can control the objects in the image to naturally leave the scene or provide breaking new identity references to enter the scene, guided by user-specified motion trajectory. To support this task, we introduce a new dataset curated semi-automatically, a comprehensive evaluation protocol targeting this setting, and an efficient identity-preserving motion-controllable video Diffusion Transformer architecture. Our evaluation shows that our proposed approach significantly outperforms existing baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21491</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 17:56:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcing General Reasoning without Verifiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21493</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21493.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangxin Zhou, Zichen Liu, Anya Sims, Haonan Wang, Tianyu Pang, Chongxuan Li, Liang Wang, Min Lin, Chao Du&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The recent paradigm shift towards training large language models (LLMs) using DeepSeek-R1-Zero-style reinforcement learning (RL) on verifiable rewards has led to impressive advancements in code and mathematical reasoning. However, this methodology is limited to tasks where rule-based answer verification is possible and does not naturally extend to real-world domains such as chemistry, healthcare, engineering, law, biology, business, and economics. Current practical workarounds use an additional LLM as a model-based verifier; however, this introduces issues such as reliance on a strong verifier LLM, susceptibility to reward hacking, and the practical burden of maintaining the verifier model in memory during training. To address this and extend DeepSeek-R1-Zero-style training to general reasoning domains, we propose a verifier-free method (VeriFree) that bypasses answer verification and instead uses RL to directly maximize the probability of generating the reference answer. We compare VeriFree with verifier-based methods and demonstrate that, in addition to its significant practical benefits and reduced compute requirements, VeriFree matches and even surpasses verifier-based methods on extensive evaluations across MMLU-Pro, GPQA, SuperGPQA, and math-related benchmarks. Moreover, we provide insights into this method from multiple perspectives: as an elegant integration of training both the policy and implicit verifier in a unified model, and as a variational optimization approach. Code is available at https://github.com/sail-sg/VeriFree.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21493</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 17:56:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI-Genie: A Self-Improving Approach for Iteratively Boosting MLLM-based   Mobile GUI Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21496</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21496.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Han Xiao, Guozhi Wang, Yuxiang Chai, Zimu Lu, Weifeng Lin, Hao He, Lue Fan, Liuyang Bian, Rui Hu, Liang Liu, Shuai Ren, Yafei Wen, Xiaoxin Chen, Aojun Zhou, Hongsheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce UI-Genie, a self-improving framework addressing two key challenges in GUI agents: verification of trajectory outcome is challenging and high-quality training data are not scalable. These challenges are addressed by a reward model and a self-improving pipeline, respectively. The reward model, UI-Genie-RM, features an image-text interleaved architecture that efficiently pro- cesses historical context and unifies action-level and task-level rewards. To sup- port the training of UI-Genie-RM, we develop deliberately-designed data genera- tion strategies including rule-based verification, controlled trajectory corruption, and hard negative mining. To address the second challenge, a self-improvement pipeline progressively expands solvable complex GUI tasks by enhancing both the agent and reward models through reward-guided exploration and outcome verification in dynamic environments. For training the model, we generate UI- Genie-RM-517k and UI-Genie-Agent-16k, establishing the first reward-specific dataset for GUI agents while demonstrating high-quality synthetic trajectory gen- eration without manual annotation. Experimental results show that UI-Genie achieves state-of-the-art performance across multiple GUI agent benchmarks with three generations of data-model self-improvement. We open-source our complete framework implementation and generated datasets to facilitate further research in https://github.com/Euphoria16/UI-Genie.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21496</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 17:58:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paper2Poster: Towards Multimodal Poster Automation from Scientific   Papers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21497</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21497.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei Pang, Kevin Qinghong Lin, Xiangru Jian, Xi He, Philip Torr&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 86&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Academic poster generation is a crucial yet challenging task in scientific communication, requiring the compression of long-context interleaved documents into a single, visually coherent page. To address this challenge, we introduce the first benchmark and metric suite for poster generation, which pairs recent conference papers with author-designed posters and evaluates outputs on (i)Visual Quality-semantic alignment with human posters, (ii)Textual Coherence-language fluency, (iii)Holistic Assessment-six fine-grained aesthetic and informational criteria scored by a VLM-as-judge, and notably (iv)PaperQuiz-the poster's ability to convey core paper content as measured by VLMs answering generated quizzes. Building on this benchmark, we propose PosterAgent, a top-down, visual-in-the-loop multi-agent pipeline: the (a)Parser distills the paper into a structured asset library; the (b)Planner aligns text-visual pairs into a binary-tree layout that preserves reading order and spatial balance; and the (c)Painter-Commenter loop refines each panel by executing rendering code and using VLM feedback to eliminate overflow and ensure alignment. In our comprehensive evaluation, we find that GPT-4o outputs-though visually appealing at first glance-often exhibit noisy text and poor PaperQuiz scores, and we find that reader engagement is the primary aesthetic bottleneck, as human-designed posters rely largely on visual semantics to convey meaning. Our fully open-source variants (e.g. based on the Qwen-2.5 series) outperform existing 4o-driven multi-agent systems across nearly all metrics, while using 87% fewer tokens. It transforms a 22-page paper into a finalized yet editable .pptx poster - all for just $0.005. These findings chart clear directions for the next generation of fully automated poster-generation models. The code and datasets are available at https://github.com/Paper2Poster/Paper2Poster.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21497</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 17:58:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How does Alignment Enhance LLMs' Multilingual Capabilities? A Language   Neurons Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21505</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21505.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shimao Zhang, Zhejian Lai, Xiang Liu, Shuaijie She, Xiao Liu, Yeyun Gong, Shujian Huang, Jiajun Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multilingual Alignment is an effective and representative paradigm to enhance LLMs' multilingual capabilities, which transfers the capabilities from the high-resource languages to the low-resource languages. Meanwhile, some researches on language-specific neurons reveal that there are language-specific neurons that are selectively activated in LLMs when processing different languages. This provides a new perspective to analyze and understand LLMs' mechanisms more specifically in multilingual scenarios. In this work, we propose a new finer-grained neuron identification algorithm, which detects language neurons~(including language-specific neurons and language-related neurons) and language-agnostic neurons. Furthermore, based on the distributional characteristics of different types of neurons, we divide the LLMs' internal process for multilingual inference into four parts: (1) multilingual understanding, (2) shared semantic space reasoning, (3) multilingual output space transformation, and (4) vocabulary space outputting. Additionally, we systematically analyze the models before and after alignment with a focus on different types of neurons. We also analyze the phenomenon of ''Spontaneous Multilingual Alignment''. Overall, our work conducts a comprehensive investigation based on different types of neurons, providing empirical results and valuable insights for better understanding multilingual alignment and multilingual capabilities of LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21505</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 17:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RenderFormer: Transformer-based Neural Rendering of Triangle Meshes with   Global Illumination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21925</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21925.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chong Zeng, Yue Dong, Pieter Peers, Hongzhi Wu, Xin Tong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present RenderFormer, a neural rendering pipeline that directly renders an image from a triangle-based representation of a scene with full global illumination effects and that does not require per-scene training or fine-tuning. Instead of taking a physics-centric approach to rendering, we formulate rendering as a sequence-to-sequence transformation where a sequence of tokens representing triangles with reflectance properties is converted to a sequence of output tokens representing small patches of pixels. RenderFormer follows a two stage pipeline: a view-independent stage that models triangle-to-triangle light transport, and a view-dependent stage that transforms a token representing a bundle of rays to the corresponding pixel values guided by the triangle-sequence from the view-independent stage. Both stages are based on the transformer architecture and are learned with minimal prior constraints. We demonstrate and evaluate RenderFormer on scenes with varying complexity in shape and light transport.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21925</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 03:20:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Let's Predict Sentence by Sentence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22202</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22202.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyeonbin Hwang, Byeongguk Jeon, Seungone Kim, Jiyeon Kim, Hoyeon Chang, Sohee Yang, Seungpil Won, Dohaeng Lee, Youbin Ahn, Minjoon Seo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive language models (LMs) generate one token at a time, yet human reasoning operates over higher-level abstractions - sentences, propositions, and concepts. This contrast raises a central question- Can LMs likewise learn to reason over structured semantic units rather than raw token sequences? In this work, we investigate whether pretrained LMs can be lifted into such abstract reasoning spaces by building on their learned representations. We present a framework that adapts a pretrained token-level LM to operate in sentence space by autoregressively predicting continuous embeddings of next sentences. We explore two embedding paradigms inspired by classical representation learning: 1) semantic embeddings, learned via autoencoding to preserve surface meaning; and 2) contextual embeddings, trained via next-sentence prediction to encode anticipatory structure. We evaluate both under two inference regimes: Discretized, which decodes each predicted embedding into text before re-encoding; and Continuous, which reasons entirely in embedding space for improved efficiency. Across four domains - mathematics, logic, commonsense, and planning - contextual embeddings under continuous inference show competitive performance with Chain-of-Thought (CoT) while reducing inference-time FLOPs on average by half. We also present early signs of scalability and modular adaptation. Finally, to visualize latent trajectories, we introduce SentenceLens, a diagnostic tool that decodes intermediate model states into interpretable sentences. Together, our results indicate that pretrained LMs can effectively transition to abstract, structured reasoning within latent embedding spaces.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22202</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 10:28:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judging Quality Across Languages: A Multilingual Approach to Pretraining   Data Filtering with Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22232</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22232.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mehdi Ali, Manuel Brack, Max Lübbering, Elias Wendt, Abbas Goher Khan, Richard Rutmann, Alex Jude, Maurice Kraus, Alexander Arno Weber, Felix Stollenwerk, David Kaczér, Florian Mai, Lucie Flek, Rafet Sifa, Nicolas Flores-Herr, Joachim Köhler, Patrick Schramowski, Michael Fromm, Kristian Kersting&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; High-quality multilingual training data is essential for effectively pretraining large language models (LLMs). Yet, the availability of suitable open-source multilingual datasets remains limited. Existing state-of-the-art datasets mostly rely on heuristic filtering methods, restricting both their cross-lingual transferability and scalability. Here, we introduce JQL, a systematic approach that efficiently curates diverse and high-quality multilingual data at scale while significantly reducing computational demands. JQL distills LLMs' annotation capabilities into lightweight annotators based on pretrained multilingual embeddings. These models exhibit robust multilingual and cross-lingual performance, even for languages and scripts unseen during training. Evaluated empirically across 35 languages, the resulting annotation pipeline substantially outperforms current heuristic filtering methods like Fineweb2. JQL notably enhances downstream model training quality and increases data retention rates. Our research provides practical insights and valuable resources for multilingual data curation, raising the standards of multilingual dataset development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22232</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 11:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Train Sparse Autoencoders Efficiently by Utilizing Features Correlation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22255</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22255.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vadim Kurochkin, Yaroslav Aksenov, Daniil Laptev, Daniil Gavrilov, Nikita Balagansky&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse Autoencoders (SAEs) have demonstrated significant promise in interpreting the hidden states of language models by decomposing them into interpretable latent directions. However, training SAEs at scale remains challenging, especially when large dictionary sizes are used. While decoders can leverage sparse-aware kernels for efficiency, encoders still require computationally intensive linear operations with large output dimensions. To address this, we propose KronSAE, a novel architecture that factorizes the latent representation via Kronecker product decomposition, drastically reducing memory and computational overhead. Furthermore, we introduce mAND, a differentiable activation function approximating the binary AND operation, which improves interpretability and performance in our factorized framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22255</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 11:41:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork Open Reasoner 1 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22312</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22312.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jujie He, Jiacai Liu, Chris Yuhao Liu, Rui Yan, Chaojie Wang, Peng Cheng, Xiaoyu Zhang, Fuxiang Zhang, Jiacheng Xu, Wei Shen, Siyuan Li, Liang Zeng, Tianwen Wei, Cheng Cheng, Bo An, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The success of DeepSeek-R1 underscores the significant role of reinforcement learning (RL) in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). In this work, we present Skywork-OR1, an effective and scalable RL implementation for long Chain-of-Thought (CoT) models. Building on the DeepSeek-R1-Distill model series, our RL approach achieves notable performance gains, increasing average accuracy across AIME24, AIME25, and LiveCodeBench from 57.8% to 72.8% (+15.0%) for the 32B model and from 43.6% to 57.5% (+13.9%) for the 7B model. Our Skywork-OR1-32B model surpasses both DeepSeek-R1 and Qwen3-32B on the AIME24 and AIME25 benchmarks, while achieving comparable results on LiveCodeBench. The Skywork-OR1-7B and Skywork-OR1-Math-7B models demonstrate competitive reasoning capabilities among models of similar size. We perform comprehensive ablation studies on the core components of our training pipeline to validate their effectiveness. Additionally, we thoroughly investigate the phenomenon of entropy collapse, identify key factors affecting entropy dynamics, and demonstrate that mitigating premature entropy collapse is critical for improved test performance. To support community research, we fully open-source our model weights, training code, and training datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22312</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 12:56:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Multimodal Reasoning via Reinforcement Learning with Cold   Start</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22334</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22334.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lai Wei, Yuting Li, Kaipeng Zheng, Chen Wang, Yue Wang, Linghe Kong, Lichao Sun, Weiran Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive chain-of-thought reasoning capabilities, with reinforcement learning (RL) playing a crucial role in this progress. While "aha moment" patterns--where models exhibit self-correction through reflection--are often attributed to emergent properties from RL, we first demonstrate that these patterns exist in multimodal LLMs (MLLMs) prior to RL training but may not necessarily correlate with improved reasoning performance. Building on these insights, we present a comprehensive study on enhancing multimodal reasoning through a two-stage approach: (1) supervised fine-tuning (SFT) as a cold start with structured chain-of-thought reasoning patterns, followed by (2) reinforcement learning via GRPO to further refine these capabilities. Our extensive experiments show that this combined approach consistently outperforms both SFT-only and RL-only methods across challenging multimodal reasoning benchmarks. The resulting models achieve state-of-the-art performance among open-source MLLMs at both 3B and 7B scales, with our 7B model showing substantial improvements over base models (e.g., 66.3 %rightarrow73.4 % on MathVista, 62.9 %rightarrow70.4 % on We-Math) and our 3B model achieving performance competitive with several 7B models. Overall, this work provides practical guidance for building advanced multimodal reasoning models. Our code is available at https://github.com/waltonfuture/RL-with-Cold-Start.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22334</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 13:21:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised Post-Training for Multi-Modal LLM Reasoning via GRPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22453</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22453.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lai Wei, Yuting Li, Chen Wang, Yue Wang, Linghe Kong, Weiran Huang, Lichao Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Improving Multi-modal Large Language Models (MLLMs) in the post-training stage typically relies on supervised fine-tuning (SFT) or reinforcement learning (RL). However, these supervised methods require expensive and manually annotated multi-modal data--an ultimately unsustainable resource. While recent efforts have explored unsupervised post-training, their methods are complex and difficult to iterate. In this work, we are the first to investigate the use of GRPO, a stable and scalable online RL algorithm, for enabling continual self-improvement without any external supervision. We propose MM-UPT, a simple yet effective framework for unsupervised post-training of MLLMs. MM-UPT builds upon GRPO, replacing traditional reward signals with a self-rewarding mechanism based on majority voting over multiple sampled responses. Our experiments demonstrate that MM-UPT significantly improves the reasoning ability of Qwen2.5-VL-7B (e.g., 66.3 %rightarrow72.9 % on MathVista, 62.9 %rightarrow68.7 % on We-Math), using standard dataset without ground truth labels. MM-UPT also outperforms prior unsupervised baselines and even approaches the results of supervised GRPO. Furthermore, we show that incorporating synthetic questions, generated solely by MLLM itself, can boost performance as well, highlighting a promising approach for scalable self-improvement. Overall, MM-UPT offers a new paradigm for continual, autonomous enhancement of MLLMs in the absence of external supervision. Our code is available at https://github.com/waltonfuture/MM-UPT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22453</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 15:11:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fostering Video Reasoning via Next-Event Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22457</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22457.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haonan Wang, Hongfu Liu, Xiangyan Liu, Chao Du, Kenji Kawaguchi, Ye Wang, Tianyu Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Next-token prediction serves as the foundational learning task enabling reasoning in LLMs. But what should the learning task be when aiming to equip MLLMs with temporal reasoning capabilities over video inputs? Existing tasks such as video question answering often rely on annotations from humans or much stronger MLLMs, while video captioning tends to entangle temporal reasoning with spatial information. To address this gap, we propose next-event prediction (NEP), a learning task that harnesses future video segments as a rich, self-supervised signal to foster temporal reasoning. We segment each video into past and future frames: the MLLM takes the past frames as input and predicts a summary of events derived from the future frames, thereby encouraging the model to reason temporally in order to complete the task. To support this task, we curate V1-33K, a dataset comprising 33,000 automatically extracted video segments spanning diverse real-world scenarios. We further explore a range of video instruction-tuning strategies to study their effects on temporal reasoning. To evaluate progress, we introduce FutureBench to assess coherence in predicting unseen future events. Experiments validate that NEP offers a scalable and effective training paradigm for fostering temporal reasoning in MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22457</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 15:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Entropy Mechanism of Reinforcement Learning for Reasoning Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22617</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22617.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ganqu Cui, Yuchen Zhang, Jiacheng Chen, Lifan Yuan, Zhi Wang, Yuxin Zuo, Haozhan Li, Yuchen Fan, Huayu Chen, Weize Chen, Zhiyuan Liu, Hao Peng, Lei Bai, Wanli Ouyang, Yu Cheng, Bowen Zhou, Ning Ding&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 102&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper aims to overcome a major obstacle in scaling RL for reasoning with LLMs, namely the collapse of policy entropy. Such phenomenon is consistently observed across vast RL runs without entropy intervention, where the policy entropy dropped sharply at the early training stage, this diminished exploratory ability is always accompanied with the saturation of policy performance. In practice, we establish a transformation equation R=-a*e^H+b between entropy H and downstream performance R. This empirical law strongly indicates that, the policy performance is traded from policy entropy, thus bottlenecked by its exhaustion, and the ceiling is fully predictable H=0, R=-a+b. Our finding necessitates entropy management for continuous exploration toward scaling compute for RL. To this end, we investigate entropy dynamics both theoretically and empirically. Our derivation highlights that, the change in policy entropy is driven by the covariance between action probability and the change in logits, which is proportional to its advantage when using Policy Gradient-like algorithms. Empirical study shows that, the values of covariance term and entropy differences matched exactly, supporting the theoretical conclusion. Moreover, the covariance term stays mostly positive throughout training, further explaining why policy entropy would decrease monotonically. Through understanding the mechanism behind entropy dynamics, we motivate to control entropy by restricting the update of high-covariance tokens. Specifically, we propose two simple yet effective techniques, namely Clip-Cov and KL-Cov, which clip and apply KL penalty to tokens with high covariances respectively. Experiments show that these methods encourage exploration, thus helping policy escape entropy collapse and achieve better downstream performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22617</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:38:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast-dLLM: Training-free Acceleration of Diffusion LLM by Enabling KV   Cache and Parallel Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chengyue Wu, Hao Zhang, Shuchen Xue, Zhijian Liu, Shizhe Diao, Ligeng Zhu, Ping Luo, Song Han, Enze Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion-based large language models (Diffusion LLMs) have shown promise for non-autoregressive text generation with parallel decoding capabilities. However, the practical inference speed of open-sourced Diffusion LLMs often lags behind autoregressive models due to the lack of Key-Value (KV) Cache and quality degradation when decoding multiple tokens simultaneously. To bridge this gap, we introduce a novel block-wise approximate KV Cache mechanism tailored for bidirectional diffusion models, enabling cache reuse with negligible performance drop. Additionally, we identify the root cause of generation quality degradation in parallel decoding as the disruption of token dependencies under the conditional independence assumption. To address this, we propose a confidence-aware parallel decoding strategy that selectively decodes tokens exceeding a confidence threshold, mitigating dependency violations and maintaining generation quality. Experimental results on LLaDA and Dream models across multiple LLM benchmarks demonstrate up to 27.6times throughput improvement with minimal accuracy loss, closing the performance gap with autoregressive models and paving the way for practical deployment of Diffusion LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22618</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:39:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebDancer: Towards Autonomous Information Seeking Agency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22648</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22648.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jialong Wu, Baixuan Li, Runnan Fang, Wenbiao Yin, Liwen Zhang, Zhengwei Tao, Dingchu Zhang, Zekun Xi, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Addressing intricate real-world problems necessitates in-depth information seeking and multi-step reasoning. Recent progress in agentic systems, exemplified by Deep Research, underscores the potential for autonomous multi-step research. In this work, we present a cohesive paradigm for building end-to-end agentic information seeking agents from a data-centric and training-stage perspective. Our approach consists of four key stages: (1) browsing data construction, (2) trajectories sampling, (3) supervised fine-tuning for effective cold start, and (4) reinforcement learning for enhanced generalisation. We instantiate this framework in a web agent based on the ReAct, WebDancer. Empirical evaluations on the challenging information seeking benchmarks, GAIA and WebWalkerQA, demonstrate the strong performance of WebDancer, achieving considerable results and highlighting the efficacy of our training paradigm. Further analysis of agent training provides valuable insights and actionable, systematic pathways for developing more capable agentic models. The codes and demo will be released in https://github.com/Alibaba-NLP/WebAgent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22648</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:57:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sherlock: Self-Correcting Reasoning in Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22651</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22651.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Ding, Ruqi Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning Vision-Language Models (VLMs) have shown promising performance on complex multimodal tasks. However, they still face significant challenges: they are highly sensitive to reasoning errors, require large volumes of annotated data or accurate verifiers, and struggle to generalize beyond specific domains. To address these limitations, we explore self-correction as a strategy to enhance reasoning VLMs. We first conduct an in-depth analysis of reasoning VLMs' self-correction abilities and identify key gaps. Based on our findings, we introduce Sherlock, a self-correction and self-improvement training framework. Sherlock introduces a trajectory-level self-correction objective, a preference data construction method based on visual perturbation, and a dynamic beta for preference tuning. Once the model acquires self-correction capabilities using only 20k randomly sampled annotated data, it continues to self-improve without external supervision. Built on the Llama3.2-Vision-11B model, Sherlock achieves remarkable results across eight benchmarks, reaching an average accuracy of 64.1 with direct generation and 65.4 after self-correction. It outperforms LLaVA-CoT (63.2), Mulberry (63.9), and LlamaV-o1 (63.4) while using less than 20% of the annotated data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22651</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:58:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Climb Carves Wisdom Deeper Than the Summit: On the Noisy Rewards in   Learning to Reason</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22653</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22653.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ang Lv, Ruobing Xie, Xingwu Sun, Zhanhui Kang, Rui Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies on post-training large language models (LLMs) for reasoning through reinforcement learning (RL) typically focus on tasks that can be accurately verified and rewarded, such as solving math problems. In contrast, our research investigates the impact of reward noise, a more practical consideration for real-world scenarios involving the post-training of LLMs using reward models. We found that LLMs demonstrate strong robustness to substantial reward noise. For example, manually flipping 40% of the reward function's outputs in math tasks still allows a Qwen-2.5-7B model to achieve rapid convergence, improving its performance on math tasks from 5% to 72%, compared to the 75% accuracy achieved by a model trained with noiseless rewards. Surprisingly, by only rewarding the appearance of key reasoning phrases (namely reasoning pattern reward, RPR), such as ``first, I need to''-without verifying the correctness of answers, the model achieved peak downstream performance (over 70% accuracy for Qwen-2.5-7B) comparable to models trained with strict correctness verification and accurate rewards. Recognizing the importance of the reasoning process over the final results, we combined RPR with noisy reward models. RPR helped calibrate the noisy reward models, mitigating potential false negatives and enhancing the LLM's performance on open-ended tasks. These findings suggest the importance of improving models' foundational abilities during the pre-training phase while providing insights for advancing post-training techniques. Our code and scripts are available at https://github.com/trestad/Noisy-Rewards-in-Learning-to-Reason.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22653</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FAMA: The First Large-Scale Open-Science Speech Foundation Model for   English and Italian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22759</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22759.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sara Papi, Marco Gaido, Luisa Bentivogli, Alessio Brutti, Mauro Cettolo, Roberto Gretter, Marco Matassoni, Mohamed Nabih, Matteo Negri&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The development of speech foundation models (SFMs) like Whisper and SeamlessM4T has significantly advanced the field of speech processing. However, their closed nature--with inaccessible training data and code--poses major reproducibility and fair evaluation challenges. While other domains have made substantial progress toward open science by developing fully transparent models trained on open-source (OS) code and data, similar efforts in speech remain limited. To fill this gap, we introduce FAMA, the first family of open science SFMs for English and Italian, trained on 150k+ hours of OS speech data. Moreover, we present a new dataset containing 16k hours of cleaned and pseudo-labeled speech for both languages. Results show that FAMA achieves competitive performance compared to existing SFMs while being up to 8 times faster. All artifacts, including code, datasets, and models, are released under OS-compliant licenses, promoting openness in speech technology research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22759</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 18:19:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VidText: Towards Comprehensive Evaluation for Video Text Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22810</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22810.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhoufaran Yang, Yan Shu, Zhifei Yang, Yan Zhang, Yu Li, Keyang Lu, Gangyan Zeng, Shaohui Liu, Yu Zhou, Nicu Sebe&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual texts embedded in videos carry rich semantic information, which is crucial for both holistic video understanding and fine-grained reasoning about local human actions. However, existing video understanding benchmarks largely overlook textual information, while OCR-specific benchmarks are constrained to static images, limiting their ability to capture the interaction between text and dynamic visual contexts. To address this gap, we propose VidText, a new benchmark designed for comprehensive and in-depth evaluation of video text understanding. VidText offers the following key features: 1) It covers a wide range of real-world scenarios and supports multilingual content, encompassing diverse settings where video text naturally appears. 2) It introduces a hierarchical evaluation framework with video-level, clip-level, and instance-level tasks, enabling assessment of both global summarization and local retrieval capabilities. 3) The benchmark also introduces a set of paired perception reasoning tasks, ranging from visual text perception to cross-modal reasoning between textual and visual information. Extensive experiments on 18 state-of-the-art Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) reveal that current models struggle across most tasks, with significant room for improvement. Further analysis highlights the impact of both model-intrinsic factors, such as input resolution and OCR capability, and external factors, including the use of auxiliary information and Chain-of-Thought reasoning strategies. We hope VidText will fill the current gap in video understanding benchmarks and serve as a foundation for future research on multimodal reasoning with video text in dynamic environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22810</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 19:39:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>cadrille: Multi-modal CAD Reconstruction with Online Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22914</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22914.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Maksim Kolodiazhnyi, Denis Tarasov, Dmitrii Zhemchuzhnikov, Alexander Nikulin, Ilya Zisman, Anna Vorontsova, Anton Konushin, Vladislav Kurenkov, Danila Rukhovich&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Computer-Aided Design (CAD) plays a central role in engineering and manufacturing, making it possible to create precise and editable 3D models. Using a variety of sensor or user-provided data as inputs for CAD reconstruction can democratize access to design applications. However, existing methods typically focus on a single input modality, such as point clouds, images, or text, which limits their generalizability and robustness. Leveraging recent advances in vision-language models (VLM), we propose a multi-modal CAD reconstruction model that simultaneously processes all three input modalities. Inspired by large language model (LLM) training paradigms, we adopt a two-stage pipeline: supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on large-scale procedurally generated data, followed by reinforcement learning (RL) fine-tuning using online feedback, obtained programatically. Furthermore, we are the first to explore RL fine-tuning of LLMs for CAD tasks demonstrating that online RL algorithms such as Group Relative Preference Optimization (GRPO) outperform offline alternatives. In the DeepCAD benchmark, our SFT model outperforms existing single-modal approaches in all three input modalities simultaneously. More importantly, after RL fine-tuning, cadrille sets new state-of-the-art on three challenging datasets, including a real-world one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22914</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 22:32:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoReasonBench: Can MLLMs Perform Vision-Centric Complex Video   Reasoning?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23359</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23359.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuanxin Liu, Kun Ouyang, Haoning Wu, Yi Liu, Lin Sui, Xinhao Li, Yan Zhong, Y. Charles, Xinyu Zhou, Xu Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have shown that long chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning can significantly enhance the performance of large language models (LLMs) on complex tasks. However, this benefit is yet to be demonstrated in the domain of video understanding, since most existing benchmarks lack the reasoning depth required to demonstrate the advantages of extended CoT chains. While recent efforts have proposed benchmarks aimed at video reasoning, the tasks are often knowledge-driven and do not rely heavily on visual content. To bridge this gap, we introduce VideoReasonBench, a benchmark designed to evaluate vision-centric, complex video reasoning. To ensure visual richness and high reasoning complexity, each video in VideoReasonBench depicts a sequence of fine-grained operations on a latent state that is only visible in part of the video. The questions evaluate three escalating levels of video reasoning skills: recalling observed visual information, inferring the content of latent states, and predicting information beyond the video. Under such task setting, models have to precisely recall multiple operations in the video, and perform step-by-step reasoning to get correct final answers for these questions. Using VideoReasonBench, we comprehensively evaluate 18 state-of-the-art multimodal LLMs (MLLMs), finding that most perform poorly on complex video reasoning, e.g., GPT-4o achieves only 6.9% accuracy, while the thinking-enhanced Gemini-2.5-Pro significantly outperforms others with 56.0% accuracy. Our investigations on "test-time scaling" further reveal that extended thinking budget, while offering none or minimal benefits on existing video benchmarks, is essential for improving the performance on VideoReasonBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23359</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 11:33:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-bench Goes Live!</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23419</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23419.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Linghao Zhang, Shilin He, Chaoyun Zhang, Yu Kang, Bowen Li, Chengxing Xie, Junhao Wang, Maoquan Wang, Yufan Huang, Shengyu Fu, Elsie Nallipogu, Qingwei Lin, Yingnong Dang, Saravan Rajmohan, Dongmei Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The issue-resolving task, where a model generates patches to fix real-world bugs, has emerged as a critical benchmark for evaluating the capabilities of large language models (LLMs). While SWE-bench and its variants have become standard in this domain, they suffer from key limitations: they have not been updated since their initial releases, cover a narrow set of repositories, and depend heavily on manual effort for instance construction and environment setup. These factors hinder scalability and introduce risks of overfitting and data contamination. In this work, we present SWE-bench-Live, a live-updatable benchmark designed to overcome these challenges. Our initial release consists of 1,319 tasks derived from real GitHub issues created since 2024, spanning 93 repositories. Each task is accompanied by a dedicated Docker image to ensure reproducible execution. Central to our benchmark is \method, an automated curation pipeline that streamlines the entire process from instance creation to environment setup, removing manual bottlenecks and enabling scalability and continuous updates. We evaluate a range of state-of-the-art agent frameworks and LLMs on SWE-bench-Live, revealing a substantial performance gap compared to static benchmarks like SWE-bench, even under controlled evaluation conditions. To better understand this discrepancy, we perform detailed analyses across repository origin, issue recency, and task difficulty. By providing a fresh, diverse, and executable benchmark grounded in live repository activity, SWE-bench-Live facilitates rigorous, contamination-resistant evaluation of LLMs and agents in dynamic, real-world software development settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23419</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 13:09:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Satori-SWE: Evolutionary Test-Time Scaling for Sample-Efficient Software   Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23604</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23604.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guangtao Zeng, Maohao Shen, Delin Chen, Zhenting Qi, Subhro Das, Dan Gutfreund, David Cox, Gregory Wornell, Wei Lu, Zhang-Wei Hong, Chuang Gan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language models (LMs) perform well on standardized coding benchmarks but struggle with real-world software engineering tasks such as resolving GitHub issues in SWE-Bench, especially when model parameters are less than 100B. While smaller models are preferable in practice due to their lower computational cost, improving their performance remains challenging. Existing approaches primarily rely on supervised fine-tuning (SFT) with high-quality data, which is expensive to curate at scale. An alternative is test-time scaling: generating multiple outputs, scoring them using a verifier, and selecting the best one. Although effective, this strategy often requires excessive sampling and costly scoring, limiting its practical application. We propose Evolutionary Test-Time Scaling (EvoScale), a sample-efficient method that treats generation as an evolutionary process. By iteratively refining outputs via selection and mutation, EvoScale shifts the output distribution toward higher-scoring regions, reducing the number of samples needed to find correct solutions. To reduce the overhead from repeatedly sampling and selection, we train the model to self-evolve using reinforcement learning (RL). Rather than relying on external verifiers at inference time, the model learns to self-improve the scores of its own generations across iterations. Evaluated on SWE-Bench-Verified, EvoScale enables our 32B model, Satori-SWE-32B, to match or exceed the performance of models with over 100B parameters while using a few samples. Code, data, and models will be fully open-sourced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23604</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 16:15:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Table-R1: Inference-Time Scaling for Table Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23621</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23621.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zheyuan Yang, Lyuhao Chen, Arman Cohan, Yilun Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 78&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we present the first study to explore inference-time scaling on table reasoning tasks. We develop and evaluate two post-training strategies to enable inference-time scaling: distillation from frontier model reasoning traces and reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR). For distillation, we introduce a large-scale dataset of reasoning traces generated by DeepSeek-R1, which we use to fine-tune LLMs into the Table-R1-SFT model. For RLVR, we propose task-specific verifiable reward functions and apply the GRPO algorithm to obtain the Table-R1-Zero model. We evaluate our Table-R1-series models across diverse table reasoning tasks, including short-form QA, fact verification, and free-form QA. Notably, the Table-R1-Zero model matches or exceeds the performance of GPT-4.1 and DeepSeek-R1, while using only a 7B-parameter LLM. It also demonstrates strong generalization to out-of-domain datasets. Extensive ablation and qualitative analyses reveal the benefits of instruction tuning, model architecture choices, and cross-task generalization, as well as emergence of essential table reasoning skills during RL training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23621</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 16:28:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Reasoning Models More Prone to Hallucination?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23646</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23646.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijun Yao, Yantao Liu, Yanxu Chen, Jianhui Chen, Junfeng Fang, Lei Hou, Juanzi Li, Tat-Seng Chua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently evolved large reasoning models (LRMs) show powerful performance in solving complex tasks with long chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning capability. As these LRMs are mostly developed by post-training on formal reasoning tasks, whether they generalize the reasoning capability to help reduce hallucination in fact-seeking tasks remains unclear and debated. For instance, DeepSeek-R1 reports increased performance on SimpleQA, a fact-seeking benchmark, while OpenAI-o3 observes even severer hallucination. This discrepancy naturally raises the following research question: Are reasoning models more prone to hallucination? This paper addresses the question from three perspectives. (1) We first conduct a holistic evaluation for the hallucination in LRMs. Our analysis reveals that LRMs undergo a full post-training pipeline with cold start supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and verifiable reward RL generally alleviate their hallucination. In contrast, both distillation alone and RL training without cold start fine-tuning introduce more nuanced hallucinations. (2) To explore why different post-training pipelines alters the impact on hallucination in LRMs, we conduct behavior analysis. We characterize two critical cognitive behaviors that directly affect the factuality of a LRM: Flaw Repetition, where the surface-level reasoning attempts repeatedly follow the same underlying flawed logic, and Think-Answer Mismatch, where the final answer fails to faithfully match the previous CoT process. (3) Further, we investigate the mechanism behind the hallucination of LRMs from the perspective of model uncertainty. We find that increased hallucination of LRMs is usually associated with the misalignment between model uncertainty and factual accuracy. Our work provides an initial understanding of the hallucination in LRMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23646</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 16:53:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D-AR: Diffusion via Autoregressive Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23660</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23660.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziteng Gao, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents Diffusion via Autoregressive models (D-AR), a new paradigm recasting the image diffusion process as a vanilla autoregressive procedure in the standard next-token-prediction fashion. We start by designing the tokenizer that converts images into sequences of discrete tokens, where tokens in different positions can be decoded into different diffusion denoising steps in the pixel space. Thanks to the diffusion properties, these tokens naturally follow a coarse-to-fine order, which directly lends itself to autoregressive modeling. Therefore, we apply standard next-token prediction on these tokens, without modifying any underlying designs (either causal masks or training/inference strategies), and such sequential autoregressive token generation directly mirrors the diffusion procedure in image space. That is, once the autoregressive model generates an increment of tokens, we can directly decode these tokens into the corresponding diffusion denoising step in the streaming manner. Our pipeline naturally reveals several intriguing properties, for example, it supports consistent previews when generating only a subset of tokens and enables zero-shot layout-controlled synthesis. On the standard ImageNet benchmark, our method achieves 2.09 FID using a 775M Llama backbone with 256 discrete tokens. We hope our work can inspire future research on unified autoregressive architectures of visual synthesis, especially with large language models. Code and models will be available at https://github.com/showlab/D-AR&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23660</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:09:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VF-Eval: Evaluating Multimodal LLMs for Generating Feedback on AIGC   Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23693</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23693.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tingyu Song, Tongyan Hu, Guo Gan, Yilun Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; MLLMs have been widely studied for video question answering recently. However, most existing assessments focus on natural videos, overlooking synthetic videos, such as AI-generated content (AIGC). Meanwhile, some works in video generation rely on MLLMs to evaluate the quality of generated videos, but the capabilities of MLLMs on interpreting AIGC videos remain largely underexplored. To address this, we propose a new benchmark, VF-Eval, which introduces four tasks-coherence validation, error awareness, error type detection, and reasoning evaluation-to comprehensively evaluate the abilities of MLLMs on AIGC videos. We evaluate 13 frontier MLLMs on VF-Eval and find that even the best-performing model, GPT-4.1, struggles to achieve consistently good performance across all tasks. This highlights the challenging nature of our benchmark. Additionally, to investigate the practical applications of VF-Eval in improving video generation, we conduct an experiment, RePrompt, demonstrating that aligning MLLMs more closely with human feedback can benefit video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23693</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:31:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AnySplat: Feed-forward 3D Gaussian Splatting from Unconstrained Views</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23716</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23716.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lihan Jiang, Yucheng Mao, Linning Xu, Tao Lu, Kerui Ren, Yichen Jin, Xudong Xu, Mulin Yu, Jiangmiao Pang, Feng Zhao, Dahua Lin, Bo Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce AnySplat, a feed forward network for novel view synthesis from uncalibrated image collections. In contrast to traditional neural rendering pipelines that demand known camera poses and per scene optimization, or recent feed forward methods that buckle under the computational weight of dense views, our model predicts everything in one shot. A single forward pass yields a set of 3D Gaussian primitives encoding both scene geometry and appearance, and the corresponding camera intrinsics and extrinsics for each input image. This unified design scales effortlessly to casually captured, multi view datasets without any pose annotations. In extensive zero shot evaluations, AnySplat matches the quality of pose aware baselines in both sparse and dense view scenarios while surpassing existing pose free approaches. Moreover, it greatly reduce rendering latency compared to optimization based neural fields, bringing real time novel view synthesis within reach for unconstrained capture settings.Project page: https://city-super.github.io/anysplat/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23716</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:49:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ATLAS: Learning to Optimally Memorize the Context at Test Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23735</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23735.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ali Behrouz, Zeman Li, Praneeth Kacham, Majid Daliri, Yuan Deng, Peilin Zhong, Meisam Razaviyayn, Vahab Mirrokni&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Transformers have been established as the most popular backbones in sequence modeling, mainly due to their effectiveness in in-context retrieval tasks and the ability to learn at scale. Their quadratic memory and time complexity, however, bound their applicability in longer sequences and so has motivated researchers to explore effective alternative architectures such as modern recurrent neural networks (a.k.a long-term recurrent memory module). Despite their recent success in diverse downstream tasks, they struggle in tasks that requires long context understanding and extrapolation to longer sequences. We observe that these shortcomings come from three disjoint aspects in their design: (1) limited memory capacity that is bounded by the architecture of memory and feature mapping of the input; (2) online nature of update, i.e., optimizing the memory only with respect to the last input; and (3) less expressive management of their fixed-size memory. To enhance all these three aspects, we present ATLAS, a long-term memory module with high capacity that learns to memorize the context by optimizing the memory based on the current and past tokens, overcoming the online nature of long-term memory models. Building on this insight, we present a new family of Transformer-like architectures, called DeepTransformers, that are strict generalizations of the original Transformer architecture. Our experimental results on language modeling, common-sense reasoning, recall-intensive, and long-context understanding tasks show that ATLAS surpasses the performance of Transformers and recent linear recurrent models. ATLAS further improves the long context performance of Titans, achieving +80\% accuracy in 10M context length of BABILong benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23735</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:57:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial-MLLM: Boosting MLLM Capabilities in Visual-based Spatial   Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23747</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23747.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Diankun Wu, Fangfu Liu, Yi-Hsin Hung, Yueqi Duan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have significantly enhanced performance on 2D visual tasks. However, improving their spatial intelligence remains a challenge. Existing 3D MLLMs always rely on additional 3D or 2.5D data to incorporate spatial awareness, restricting their utility in scenarios with only 2D inputs, such as images or videos. In this paper, we present Spatial-MLLM, a novel framework for visual-based spatial reasoning from purely 2D observations. Unlike conventional video MLLMs which rely on CLIP-based visual encoders optimized for semantic understanding, our key insight is to unleash the strong structure prior from the feed-forward visual geometry foundation model. Specifically, we propose a dual-encoder architecture: a pretrained 2D visual encoder to extract semantic features, and a spatial encoder-initialized from the backbone of the visual geometry model-to extract 3D structure features. A connector then integrates both features into unified visual tokens for enhanced spatial understanding. Furthermore, we propose a space-aware frame sampling strategy at inference time, which selects the spatially informative frames of a video sequence, ensuring that even under limited token length, the model focuses on frames critical for spatial reasoning. Beyond architecture improvements, we construct the Spatial-MLLM-120k dataset and train the model on it using supervised fine-tuning and GRPO. Extensive experiments on various real-world datasets demonstrate that our spatial-MLLM achieves state-of-the-art performance in a wide range of visual-based spatial understanding and reasoning tasks. Project page: https://diankun-wu.github.io/Spatial-MLLM/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23747</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:59:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LoRAShop: Training-Free Multi-Concept Image Generation and Editing with   Rectified Flow Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23758</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23758.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yusuf Dalva, Hidir Yesiltepe, Pinar Yanardag&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce LoRAShop, the first framework for multi-concept image editing with LoRA models. LoRAShop builds on a key observation about the feature interaction patterns inside Flux-style diffusion transformers: concept-specific transformer features activate spatially coherent regions early in the denoising process. We harness this observation to derive a disentangled latent mask for each concept in a prior forward pass and blend the corresponding LoRA weights only within regions bounding the concepts to be personalized. The resulting edits seamlessly integrate multiple subjects or styles into the original scene while preserving global context, lighting, and fine details. Our experiments demonstrate that LoRAShop delivers better identity preservation compared to baselines. By eliminating retraining and external constraints, LoRAShop turns personalized diffusion models into a practical `photoshop-with-LoRAs' tool and opens new avenues for compositional visual storytelling and rapid creative iteration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23758</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZeroGUI: Automating Online GUI Learning at Zero Human Cost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23762</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23762.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenyu Yang, Shiqian Su, Shi Liu, Xuan Dong, Yue Yu, Weijie Su, Xuehui Wang, Zhaoyang Liu, Jinguo Zhu, Hao Li, Wenhai Wang, Yu Qiao, Xizhou Zhu, Jifeng Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of large Vision-Language Models (VLMs) has propelled the development of pure-vision-based GUI Agents, capable of perceiving and operating Graphical User Interfaces (GUI) to autonomously fulfill user instructions. However, existing approaches usually adopt an offline learning framework, which faces two core limitations: (1) heavy reliance on high-quality manual annotations for element grounding and action supervision, and (2) limited adaptability to dynamic and interactive environments. To address these limitations, we propose ZeroGUI, a scalable, online learning framework for automating GUI Agent training at Zero human cost. Specifically, ZeroGUI integrates (i) VLM-based automatic task generation to produce diverse training goals from the current environment state, (ii) VLM-based automatic reward estimation to assess task success without hand-crafted evaluation functions, and (iii) two-stage online reinforcement learning to continuously interact with and learn from GUI environments. Experiments on two advanced GUI Agents (UI-TARS and Aguvis) demonstrate that ZeroGUI significantly boosts performance across OSWorld and AndroidLab environments. The code is available at https://github.com/OpenGVLab/ZeroGUI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23762</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
