<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:15:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>From Code Foundation Models to Agents and Applications: A Practical Guide to Code Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18538</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.18538.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jian Yang, Xianglong Liu, Weifeng Lv, Ken Deng, Shawn Guo, Lin Jing, Yizhi Li, Shark Liu, Xianzhen Luo, Yuyu Luo, Changzai Pan, Ensheng Shi, Yingshui Tan, Renshuai Tao, Jiajun Wu, Xianjie Wu, Zhenhe Wu, Daoguang Zan, Chenchen Zhang, Wei Zhang, He Zhu, Terry Yue Zhuo, Kerui Cao, Xianfu Cheng, Jun Dong, Shengjie Fang, Zhiwei Fei, Xiangyuan Guan, Qipeng Guo, Zhiguang Han, Joseph James, Tianqi Luo, Renyuan Li, Yuhang Li, Yiming Liang, Congnan Liu, Jiaheng Liu, Qian Liu, Ruitong Liu, Tyler Loakman, Xiangxin Meng, Chuang Peng, Tianhao Peng, Jiajun Shi, Mingjie Tang, Boyang Wang, Haowen Wang, Yunli Wang, Fanglin Xu, Zihan Xu, Fei Yuan, Ge Zhang, Jiayi Zhang, Xinhao Zhang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Hualei Zhu, King Zhu, Brown Dai, Aishan Liu, Zhoujun Li, Chenghua Lin, Tianyu Liu, Chao Peng, Kai Shen, Libo Qin, Shuangyong Song, Zizheng Zhan, Jiajun Zhang, Jie Zhang, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Bo Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 278&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have fundamentally transformed automated software development by enabling direct translation of natural language descriptions into functional code, driving commercial adoption through tools like Github Copilot (Microsoft), Cursor (Anysphere), Trae (ByteDance), and Claude Code (Anthropic). While the field has evolved dramatically from rule-based systems to Transformer-based architectures, achieving performance improvements from single-digit to over 95\% success rates on benchmarks like HumanEval. In this work, we provide a comprehensive synthesis and practical guide (a series of analytic and probing experiments) about code LLMs, systematically examining the complete model life cycle from data curation to post-training through advanced prompting paradigms, code pre-training, supervised fine-tuning, reinforcement learning, and autonomous coding agents. We analyze the code capability of the general LLMs (GPT-4, Claude, LLaMA) and code-specialized LLMs (StarCoder, Code LLaMA, DeepSeek-Coder, and QwenCoder), critically examining the techniques, design decisions, and trade-offs. Further, we articulate the research-practice gap between academic research (e.g., benchmarks and tasks) and real-world deployment (e.g., software-related code tasks), including code correctness, security, contextual awareness of large codebases, and integration with development workflows, and map promising research directions to practical needs. Last, we conduct a series of experiments to provide a comprehensive analysis of code pre-training, supervised fine-tuning, and reinforcement learning, covering scaling law, framework selection, hyperparameter sensitivity, model architectures, and dataset comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18538</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 17:09:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Research: A Systematic Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02038</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02038.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengliang Shi, Yiqun Chen, Haitao Li, Weiwei Sun, Shiyu Ni, Yougang Lyu, Run-Ze Fan, Bowen Jin, Yixuan Weng, Minjun Zhu, Qiujie Xie, Xinyu Guo, Qu Yang, Jiayi Wu, Jujia Zhao, Xiaqiang Tang, Xinbei Ma, Cunxiang Wang, Jiaxin Mao, Qingyao Ai, Jen-Tse Huang, Wenxuan Wang, Yue Zhang, Yiming Yang, Zhaopeng Tu, Zhaochun Ren&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 65&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have rapidly evolved from text generators into powerful problem solvers. Yet, many open tasks demand critical thinking, multi-source, and verifiable outputs, which are beyond single-shot prompting or standard retrieval-augmented generation. Recently, numerous studies have explored Deep Research (DR), which aims to combine the reasoning capabilities of LLMs with external tools, such as search engines, thereby empowering LLMs to act as research agents capable of completing complex, open-ended tasks. This survey presents a comprehensive and systematic overview of deep research systems, including a clear roadmap, foundational components, practical implementation techniques, important challenges, and future directions. Specifically, our main contributions are as follows: (i) we formalize a three-stage roadmap and distinguish deep research from related paradigms; (ii) we introduce four key components: query planning, information acquisition, memory management, and answer generation, each paired with fine-grained sub-taxonomies; (iii) we summarize optimization techniques, including prompting, supervised fine-tuning, and agentic reinforcement learning; and (iv) we consolidate evaluation criteria and open challenges, aiming to guide and facilitate future development. As the field of deep research continues to evolve rapidly, we are committed to continuously updating this survey to reflect the latest progress in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02038</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 15:28:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Consistency Critic: Correcting Inconsistencies in Generated Images via Reference-Guided Attentive Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20614</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20614.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziheng Ouyang, Yiren Song, Yaoli Liu, Shihao Zhu, Qibin Hou, Ming-Ming Cheng, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Previous works have explored various customized generation tasks given a reference image, but they still face limitations in generating consistent fine-grained details. In this paper, our aim is to solve the inconsistency problem of generated images by applying a reference-guided post-editing approach and present our ImageCritic. We first construct a dataset of reference-degraded-target triplets obtained via VLM-based selection and explicit degradation, which effectively simulates the common inaccuracies or inconsistencies observed in existing generation models. Furthermore, building on a thorough examination of the model's attention mechanisms and intrinsic representations, we accordingly devise an attention alignment loss and a detail encoder to precisely rectify inconsistencies. ImageCritic can be integrated into an agent framework to automatically detect inconsistencies and correct them with multi-round and local editing in complex scenarios. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ImageCritic can effectively resolve detail-related issues in various customized generation scenarios, providing significant improvements over existing methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20614</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:40:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinity-RoPE: Action-Controllable Infinite Video Generation Emerges From Autoregressive Self-Rollout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20649</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20649.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hidir Yesiltepe, Tuna Han Salih Meral, Adil Kaan Akan, Kaan Oktay, Pinar Yanardag&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current autoregressive video diffusion models are constrained by three core bottlenecks: (i) the finite temporal horizon imposed by the base model's 3D Rotary Positional Embedding (3D-RoPE), (ii) slow prompt responsiveness in maintaining fine-grained action control during long-form rollouts, and (iii) the inability to realize discontinuous cinematic transitions within a single generation stream. We introduce infty-RoPE, a unified inference-time framework that addresses all three limitations through three interconnected components: Block-Relativistic RoPE, KV Flush, and RoPE Cut. Block-Relativistic RoPE reformulates temporal encoding as a moving local reference frame, where each newly generated latent block is rotated relative to the base model's maximum frame horizon while earlier blocks are rotated backward to preserve relative temporal geometry. This relativistic formulation eliminates fixed temporal positions, enabling continuous video generation far beyond the base positional limits. To obtain fine-grained action control without re-encoding, KV Flush renews the KV cache by retaining only two latent frames, the global sink and the last generated latent frame, thereby ensuring immediate prompt responsiveness. Finally, RoPE Cut introduces controlled discontinuities in temporal RoPE coordinates, enabling multi-cut scene transitions within a single continuous rollout. Together, these components establish infty-RoPE as a training-free foundation for infinite-horizon, controllable, and cinematic video diffusion. Comprehensive experiments show that infty-RoPE consistently surpasses previous autoregressive models in overall VBench scores.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20649</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongVT: Incentivizing "Thinking with Long Videos" via Native Tool Calling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20785</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20785.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zuhao Yang, Sudong Wang, Kaichen Zhang, Keming Wu, Sicong Leng, Yifan Zhang, Chengwei Qin, Shijian Lu, Xingxuan Li, Lidong Bing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 181&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large multimodal models (LMMs) have shown great potential for video reasoning with textual Chain-of-Thought. However, they remain vulnerable to hallucinations, especially when processing long-form videos where evidence is sparse and temporally dispersed. Inspired by how humans comprehend long videos - by first skimming globally and then examining relevant clips for details - we introduce LongVT, an end-to-end agentic framework that enables "Thinking with Long Videos" via interleaved Multimodal Chain-of-Tool-Thought. Specifically, we exploit LMMs' inherent temporal grounding ability as a native video cropping tool to zoom in on a specific video clip and resample finer-grained video frames. This global-to-local reasoning loop continues until answers are grounded in retrieved visual evidence. Given the scarcity of fine-grained question-answering (QA) data for the long video reasoning task, we curate and will release a data suite named VideoSIAH to facilitate both training and evaluation. Specifically, our training dataset consists of 247.9K samples for tool-integrated cold-start supervised fine-tuning, 1.6K samples for agentic reinforcement learning, and 15.4K samples for agentic reinforcement fine-tuning, respectively. Our evaluation benchmark consists of 1,280 QA pairs that are carefully curated through a semi-automatic data pipeline with human-in-the-loop validation. With a meticulously designed three-stage training strategy and extensive empirical validation, LongVT consistently outperforms existing strong baselines across four challenging long-video understanding and reasoning benchmarks. Our codes, data, and model checkpoints are publicly available at https://github.com/EvolvingLMMs-Lab/LongVT .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20785</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 19:22:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qwen3-VL Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21631</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.21631.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuai Bai, Yuxuan Cai, Ruizhe Chen, Keqin Chen, Xionghui Chen, Zesen Cheng, Lianghao Deng, Wei Ding, Chang Gao, Chunjiang Ge, Wenbin Ge, Zhifang Guo, Qidong Huang, Jie Huang, Fei Huang, Binyuan Hui, Shutong Jiang, Zhaohai Li, Mingsheng Li, Mei Li, Kaixin Li, Zicheng Lin, Junyang Lin, Xuejing Liu, Jiawei Liu, Chenglong Liu, Yang Liu, Dayiheng Liu, Shixuan Liu, Dunjie Lu, Ruilin Luo, Chenxu Lv, Rui Men, Lingchen Meng, Xuancheng Ren, Xingzhang Ren, Sibo Song, Yuchong Sun, Jun Tang, Jianhong Tu, Jianqiang Wan, Peng Wang, Pengfei Wang, Qiuyue Wang, Yuxuan Wang, Tianbao Xie, Yiheng Xu, Haiyang Xu, Jin Xu, Zhibo Yang, Mingkun Yang, Jianxin Yang, An Yang, Bowen Yu, Fei Zhang, Hang Zhang, Xi Zhang, Bo Zheng, Humen Zhong, Jingren Zhou, Fan Zhou, Jing Zhou, Yuanzhi Zhu, Ke Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 146&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Qwen3-VL, the most capable vision-language model in the Qwen series to date, achieving superior performance across a broad range of multimodal benchmarks. It natively supports interleaved contexts of up to 256K tokens, seamlessly integrating text, images, and video. The model family includes both dense (2B/4B/8B/32B) and mixture-of-experts (30B-A3B/235B-A22B) variants to accommodate diverse latency-quality trade-offs. Qwen3-VL delivers three core pillars: (i) markedly stronger pure-text understanding, surpassing comparable text-only backbones in several cases; (ii) robust long-context comprehension with a native 256K-token window for both text and interleaved multimodal inputs, enabling faithful retention, retrieval, and cross-referencing across long documents and videos; and (iii) advanced multimodal reasoning across single-image, multi-image, and video tasks, demonstrating leading performance on comprehensive evaluations such as MMMU and visual-math benchmarks (e.g., MathVista and MathVision). Architecturally, we introduce three key upgrades: (i) an enhanced interleaved-MRoPE for stronger spatial-temporal modeling across images and video; (ii) DeepStack integration, which effectively leverages multi-level ViT features to tighten vision-language alignment; and (iii) text-based time alignment for video, evolving from T-RoPE to explicit textual timestamp alignment for more precise temporal grounding. Under comparable token budgets and latency constraints, Qwen3-VL achieves superior performance in both dense and Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architectures. We envision Qwen3-VL serving as a foundational engine for image-grounded reasoning, agentic decision-making, and multimodal code intelligence in real-world workflows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21631</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 17:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ToolOrchestra: Elevating Intelligence via Efficient Model and Tool Orchestration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21689</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.21689.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongjin Su, Shizhe Diao, Ximing Lu, Mingjie Liu, Jiacheng Xu, Xin Dong, Yonggan Fu, Peter Belcak, Hanrong Ye, Hongxu Yin, Yi Dong, Evelina Bakhturina, Tao Yu, Yejin Choi, Jan Kautz, Pavlo Molchanov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 111&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models are powerful generalists, yet solving deep and complex problems such as those of the Humanity's Last Exam (HLE) remains both conceptually challenging and computationally expensive. We show that small orchestrators managing other models and a variety of tools can both push the upper bound of intelligence and improve efficiency in solving difficult agentic tasks. We introduce ToolOrchestra, a method for training small orchestrators that coordinate intelligent tools. ToolOrchestra explicitly uses reinforcement learning with outcome-, efficiency-, and user-preference-aware rewards. Using ToolOrchestra, we produce Orchestrator, an 8B model that achieves higher accuracy at lower cost than previous tool-use agents while aligning with user preferences on which tools are to be used for a given query. On HLE, Orchestrator achieves a score of 37.1%, outperforming GPT-5 (35.1%) while being 2.5x more efficient. On tau2-Bench and FRAMES, Orchestrator surpasses GPT-5 by a wide margin while using only about 30% of the cost. Extensive analysis shows that Orchestrator achieves the best trade-off between performance and cost under multiple metrics, and generalizes robustly to unseen tools. These results demonstrate that composing diverse tools with a lightweight orchestration model is both more efficient and more effective than existing methods, paving the way for practical and scalable tool-augmented reasoning systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21689</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 18:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSeekMath-V2: Towards Self-Verifiable Mathematical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22570</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.22570.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhihong Shao, Yuxiang Luo, Chengda Lu, Z. Z. Ren, Jiewen Hu, Tian Ye, Zhibin Gou, Shirong Ma, Xiaokang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 84&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models have made significant progress in mathematical reasoning, which serves as an important testbed for AI and could impact scientific research if further advanced. By scaling reasoning with reinforcement learning that rewards correct final answers, LLMs have improved from poor performance to saturating quantitative reasoning competitions like AIME and HMMT in one year. However, this approach faces fundamental limitations. Pursuing higher final answer accuracy doesn't address a key issue: correct answers don't guarantee correct reasoning. Moreover, many mathematical tasks like theorem proving require rigorous step-by-step derivation rather than numerical answers, making final answer rewards inapplicable. To push the limits of deep reasoning, we believe it is necessary to verify the comprehensiveness and rigor of mathematical reasoning. Self-verification is particularly important for scaling test-time compute, especially for open problems without known solutions. Towards self-verifiable mathematical reasoning, we investigate how to train an accurate and faithful LLM-based verifier for theorem proving. We then train a proof generator using the verifier as the reward model, and incentivize the generator to identify and resolve as many issues as possible in their own proofs before finalizing them. To maintain the generation-verification gap as the generator becomes stronger, we propose to scale verification compute to automatically label new hard-to-verify proofs, creating training data to further improve the verifier. Our resulting model, DeepSeekMath-V2, demonstrates strong theorem-proving capabilities, achieving gold-level scores on IMO 2025 and CMO 2024 and a near-perfect 118/120 on Putnam 2024 with scaled test-time compute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22570</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 16:01:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MG-Nav: Dual-Scale Visual Navigation via Sparse Spatial Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22609</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.22609.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bo Wang, Jiehong Lin, Chenzhi Liu, Xinting Hu, Yifei Yu, Tianjia Liu, Zhongrui Wang, Xiaojuan Qi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present MG-Nav (Memory-Guided Navigation), a dual-scale framework for zero-shot visual navigation that unifies global memory-guided planning with local geometry-enhanced control. At its core is the Sparse Spatial Memory Graph (SMG), a compact, region-centric memory where each node aggregates multi-view keyframe and object semantics, capturing both appearance and spatial structure while preserving viewpoint diversity. At the global level, the agent is localized on SMG and a goal-conditioned node path is planned via an image-to-instance hybrid retrieval, producing a sequence of reachable waypoints for long-horizon guidance. At the local level, a navigation foundation policy executes these waypoints in point-goal mode with obstacle-aware control, and switches to image-goal mode when navigating from the final node towards the visual target. To further enhance viewpoint alignment and goal recognition, we introduce VGGT-adapter, a lightweight geometric module built on the pre-trained VGGT model, which aligns observation and goal features in a shared 3D-aware space. MG-Nav operates global planning and local control at different frequencies, using periodic re-localization to correct errors. Experiments on HM3D Instance-Image-Goal and MP3D Image-Goal benchmarks demonstrate that MG-Nav achieves state-of-the-art zero-shot performance and remains robust under dynamic rearrangements and unseen scene conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22609</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 16:43:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REASONEDIT: Towards Reasoning-Enhanced Image Editing Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22625</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.22625.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fukun Yin, Shiyu Liu, Yucheng Han, Zhibo Wang, Peng Xing, Rui Wang, Wei Cheng, Yingming Wang, Aojie Li, Zixin Yin, Pengtao Chen, Xiangyu Zhang, Daxin Jiang, Xianfang Zeng, Gang Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in image editing models have shown remarkable progress. A common architectural design couples a multimodal large language model (MLLM) encoder with a diffusion decoder, as seen in systems such as Step1X-Edit and Qwen-Image-Edit, where the MLLM encodes both the reference image and the instruction but remains frozen during training. In this work, we demonstrate that unlocking the reasoning capabilities of MLLM can further push the boundaries of editing models. Specifically, we explore two reasoning mechanisms, thinking and reflection, which enhance instruction understanding and editing accuracy. Based on that, our proposed framework enables image editing in a thinking-editing-reflection loop: the thinking mechanism leverages the world knowledge of MLLM to interpret abstract instructions, while the reflection reviews editing results, automatically corrects unintended manipulations, and identifies the stopping round. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our reasoning approach achieves significant performance gains, with improvements of ImgEdit (+4.3%), GEdit (+4.7%), and Kris (+8.2%) when initializing our DiT from the Step1X-Edit (ReasonEdit-S), and also outperforms previous open-source methods on both GEdit and Kris when integrated with Qwen-Image-Edit (ReasonEdit-Q).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22625</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 17:02:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometrically-Constrained Agent for Spatial Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22659</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.22659.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeren Chen, Xiaoya Lu, Zhijie Zheng, Pengrui Li, Lehan He, Yijin Zhou, Jing Shao, Bohan Zhuang, Lu Sheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision Language Models (VLMs) exhibit a fundamental semantic-to-geometric gap in spatial reasoning: they excel at qualitative semantic inference but their reasoning operates within a lossy semantic space, misaligned with high-fidelity geometry. Current paradigms fail to bridge this gap. Training-based methods suffer from an ``oracle paradox,'' learning flawed spatial logic from imperfect oracles. Tool-integrated methods constrain the final computation but critically leave the VLM's planning process unconstrained, resulting in geometrically flawed plans. In this work, we propose Geometrically-Constrained Agent (GCA), a training-free agentic paradigm that resolves this gap by introducing a formal task constraint. Specifically, we strategically decouples the VLM's role into two stages. First, acting as a semantic analyst, the VLM translates the user's ambiguous query into the formal, verifiable task constraint, which defines the reference frame and objective. Second, acting as a task solver, the VLM generates and executes tool calls strictly within the deterministic bounds defined by the constraint. This geometrically-constrained reasoning strategy successfully resolve the semantic-to-geometric gap, yielding a robust and verifiable reasoning pathway for spatial reasoning. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that GCA achieves SOTA performance on multiple spatial reasoning benchmarks, surpassing existing training-based and tool-integrated methods by ~27%. Please see our homepage at https://gca-spatial-reasoning.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22659</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 17:50:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Z-Image: An Efficient Image Generation Foundation Model with Single-Stream Diffusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22699</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.22699.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Z-Image Team, Huanqia Cai, Sihan Cao, Ruoyi Du, Peng Gao, Steven Hoi, Shijie Huang, Zhaohui Hou, Dengyang Jiang, Xin Jin, Liangchen Li, Zhen Li, Zhong-Yu Li, David Liu, Dongyang Liu, Junhan Shi, Qilong Wu, Feng Yu, Chi Zhang, Shifeng Zhang, Shilin Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 217&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The landscape of high-performance image generation models is currently dominated by proprietary systems, such as Nano Banana Pro and Seedream 4.0. Leading open-source alternatives, including Qwen-Image, Hunyuan-Image-3.0 and FLUX.2, are characterized by massive parameter counts (20B to 80B), making them impractical for inference, and fine-tuning on consumer-grade hardware. To address this gap, we propose Z-Image, an efficient 6B-parameter foundation generative model built upon a Scalable Single-Stream Diffusion Transformer (S3-DiT) architecture that challenges the "scale-at-all-costs" paradigm. By systematically optimizing the entire model lifecycle -- from a curated data infrastructure to a streamlined training curriculum -- we complete the full training workflow in just 314K H800 GPU hours (approx. $630K). Our few-step distillation scheme with reward post-training further yields Z-Image-Turbo, offering both sub-second inference latency on an enterprise-grade H800 GPU and compatibility with consumer-grade hardware (&lt;16GB VRAM). Additionally, our omni-pre-training paradigm also enables efficient training of Z-Image-Edit, an editing model with impressive instruction-following capabilities. Both qualitative and quantitative experiments demonstrate that our model achieves performance comparable to or surpassing that of leading competitors across various dimensions. Most notably, Z-Image exhibits exceptional capabilities in photorealistic image generation and bilingual text rendering, delivering results that rival top-tier commercial models, thereby demonstrating that state-of-the-art results are achievable with significantly reduced computational overhead. We publicly release our code, weights, and online demo to foster the development of accessible, budget-friendly, yet state-of-the-art generative models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22699</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 18:52:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DualCamCtrl: Dual-Branch Diffusion Model for Geometry-Aware Camera-Controlled Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23127</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.23127.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongfei Zhang, Kanghao Chen, Zixin Zhang, Harold Haodong Chen, Yuanhuiyi Lyu, Yuqi Zhang, Shuai Yang, Kun Zhou, Yingcong Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents DualCamCtrl, a novel end-to-end diffusion model for camera-controlled video generation. Recent works have advanced this field by representing camera poses as ray-based conditions, yet they often lack sufficient scene understanding and geometric awareness. DualCamCtrl specifically targets this limitation by introducing a dual-branch framework that mutually generates camera-consistent RGB and depth sequences. To harmonize these two modalities, we further propose the Semantic Guided Mutual Alignment (SIGMA) mechanism, which performs RGB-depth fusion in a semantics-guided and mutually reinforced manner. These designs collectively enable DualCamCtrl to better disentangle appearance and geometry modeling, generating videos that more faithfully adhere to the specified camera trajectories. Additionally, we analyze and reveal the distinct influence of depth and camera poses across denoising stages and further demonstrate that early and late stages play complementary roles in forming global structure and refining local details. Extensive experiments demonstrate that DualCamCtrl achieves more consistent camera-controlled video generation, with over 40\% reduction in camera motion errors compared with prior methods. Our project page: https://soyouthinkyoucantell.github.io/dualcamctrl-page/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23127</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 12:19:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision Bridge Transformer at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23199</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.23199.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenxiong Tan, Zeqing Wang, Xingyi Yang, Songhua Liu, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Vision Bridge Transformer (ViBT), a large-scale instantiation of Brownian Bridge Models designed for conditional generation. Unlike traditional diffusion models that transform noise into data, Bridge Models directly model the trajectory between inputs and outputs, creating an efficient data-to-data translation paradigm. By scaling these models to 20B and 1.3B parameters, we demonstrate their effectiveness for image and video translation tasks. To support this scale, we adopt a Transformer architecture and propose a variance-stabilized velocity-matching objective for robust training. Together, these advances highlight the power of scaling Bridge Models for instruction-based image editing and complex video translation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23199</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 14:03:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SimScale: Learning to Drive via Real-World Simulation at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23369</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.23369.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haochen Tian, Tianyu Li, Haochen Liu, Jiazhi Yang, Yihang Qiu, Guang Li, Junli Wang, Yinfeng Gao, Zhang Zhang, Liang Wang, Hangjun Ye, Tieniu Tan, Long Chen, Hongyang Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Achieving fully autonomous driving systems requires learning rational decisions in a wide span of scenarios, including safety-critical and out-of-distribution ones. However, such cases are underrepresented in real-world corpus collected by human experts. To complement for the lack of data diversity, we introduce a novel and scalable simulation framework capable of synthesizing massive unseen states upon existing driving logs. Our pipeline utilizes advanced neural rendering with a reactive environment to generate high-fidelity multi-view observations controlled by the perturbed ego trajectory. Furthermore, we develop a pseudo-expert trajectory generation mechanism for these newly simulated states to provide action supervision. Upon the synthesized data, we find that a simple co-training strategy on both real-world and simulated samples can lead to significant improvements in both robustness and generalization for various planning methods on challenging real-world benchmarks, up to +6.8 EPDMS on navhard and +2.9 on navtest. More importantly, such policy improvement scales smoothly by increasing simulation data only, even without extra real-world data streaming in. We further reveal several crucial findings of such a sim-real learning system, which we term SimScale, including the design of pseudo-experts and the scaling properties for different policy architectures. Our simulation data and code would be released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23369</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 17:17:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LFM2 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23404</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.23404.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Amini, Anna Banaszak, Harold Benoit, Arthur Böök, Tarek Dakhran, Song Duong, Alfred Eng, Fernando Fernandes, Marc Härkönen, Anne Harrington, Ramin Hasani, Saniya Karwa, Yuri Khrustalev, Maxime Labonne, Mathias Lechner, Valentine Lechner, Simon Lee, Zetian Li, Noel Loo, Jacob Marks, Edoardo Mosca, Samuel J. Paech, Paul Pak, Rom N. Parnichkun, Alex Quach, Ryan Rogers, Daniela Rus, Nayan Saxena, Bettina Schlager, Tim Seyde, Jimmy T. H. Smith, Aditya Tadimeti, Neehal Tumma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present LFM2, a family of Liquid Foundation Models designed for efficient on-device deployment and strong task capabilities. Using hardware-in-the-loop architecture search under edge latency and memory constraints, we obtain a compact hybrid backbone that combines gated short convolutions with a small number of grouped query attention blocks, delivering up to 2x faster prefill and decode on CPUs compared to similarly sized models. The LFM2 family covers 350M-8.3B parameters, including dense models (350M, 700M, 1.2B, 2.6B) and a mixture-of-experts variant (8.3B total, 1.5B active), all with 32K context length. LFM2's training pipeline includes a tempered, decoupled Top-K knowledge distillation objective that avoids support mismatch; curriculum learning with difficulty-ordered data; and a three-stage post-training recipe of supervised fine-tuning, length-normalized preference optimization, and model merging. Pre-trained on 10-12T tokens, LFM2 models achieve strong results across diverse benchmarks; for example, LFM2-2.6B reaches 79.56% on IFEval and 82.41% on GSM8K. We further build multimodal and retrieval variants: LFM2-VL for vision-language tasks, LFM2-Audio for speech, and LFM2-ColBERT for retrieval. LFM2-VL supports tunable accuracy-latency tradeoffs via token-efficient visual processing, while LFM2-Audio separates audio input and output pathways to enable real-time speech-to-speech interaction competitive with models 3x larger. LFM2-ColBERT provides a low-latency encoder for queries and documents, enabling high-performance retrieval across multiple languages. All models are released with open weights and deployment packages for ExecuTorch, llama.cpp, and vLLM, making LFM2 a practical base for edge applications that need fast, memory-efficient inference and strong task capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23404</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 17:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AnyTalker: Scaling Multi-Person Talking Video Generation with Interactivity Refinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23475</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.23475.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhizhou Zhong, Yicheng Ji, Zhe Kong, Yiying Liu, Jiarui Wang, Jiasun Feng, Lupeng Liu, Xiangyi Wang, Yanjia Li, Yuqing She, Ying Qin, Huan Li, Shuiyang Mao, Wei Liu, Wenhan Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, multi-person video generation has started to gain prominence. While a few preliminary works have explored audio-driven multi-person talking video generation, they often face challenges due to the high costs of diverse multi-person data collection and the difficulty of driving multiple identities with coherent interactivity. To address these challenges, we propose AnyTalker, a multi-person generation framework that features an extensible multi-stream processing architecture. Specifically, we extend Diffusion Transformer's attention block with a novel identity-aware attention mechanism that iteratively processes identity-audio pairs, allowing arbitrary scaling of drivable identities. Besides, training multi-person generative models demands massive multi-person data. Our proposed training pipeline depends solely on single-person videos to learn multi-person speaking patterns and refines interactivity with only a few real multi-person clips. Furthermore, we contribute a targeted metric and dataset designed to evaluate the naturalness and interactivity of the generated multi-person videos. Extensive experiments demonstrate that AnyTalker achieves remarkable lip synchronization, visual quality, and natural interactivity, striking a favorable balance between data costs and identity scalability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.23475</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 18:59:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What about gravity in video generation? Post-Training Newton's Laws with Verifiable Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00425</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.00425.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minh-Quan Le, Yuanzhi Zhu, Vicky Kalogeiton, Dimitris Samaras&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent video diffusion models can synthesize visually compelling clips, yet often violate basic physical laws-objects float, accelerations drift, and collisions behave inconsistently-revealing a persistent gap between visual realism and physical realism. We propose NewtonRewards, the first physics-grounded post-training framework for video generation based on verifiable rewards. Instead of relying on human or VLM feedback, NewtonRewards extracts measurable proxies from generated videos using frozen utility models: optical flow serves as a proxy for velocity, while high-level appearance features serve as a proxy for mass. These proxies enable explicit enforcement of Newtonian structure through two complementary rewards: a Newtonian kinematic constraint enforcing constant-acceleration dynamics, and a mass conservation reward preventing trivial, degenerate solutions. We evaluate NewtonRewards on five Newtonian Motion Primitives (free fall, horizontal/parabolic throw, and ramp sliding down/up) using our newly constructed large-scale benchmark, NewtonBench-60K. Across all primitives in visual and physics metrics, NewtonRewards consistently improves physical plausibility, motion smoothness, and temporal coherence over prior post-training methods. It further maintains strong performance under out-of-distribution shifts in height, speed, and friction. Our results show that physics-grounded verifiable rewards offer a scalable path toward physics-aware video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00425</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 10:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wikontic: Constructing Wikidata-Aligned, Ontology-Aware Knowledge Graphs with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00590</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.00590.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alla Chepurova, Aydar Bulatov, Yuri Kuratov, Mikhail Burtsev&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Knowledge graphs (KGs) provide structured, verifiable grounding for large language models (LLMs), but current LLM-based systems commonly use KGs as auxiliary structures for text retrieval, leaving their intrinsic quality underexplored. In this work, we propose Wikontic, a multi-stage pipeline that constructs KGs from open-domain text by extracting candidate triplets with qualifiers, enforcing Wikidata-based type and relation constraints, and normalizing entities to reduce duplication. The resulting KGs are compact, ontology-consistent, and well-connected; on MuSiQue, the correct answer entity appears in 96% of generated triplets. On HotpotQA, our triplets-only setup achieves 76.0 F1, and on MuSiQue 59.8 F1, matching or surpassing several retrieval-augmented generation baselines that still require textual context. In addition, Wikontic attains state-of-the-art information-retention performance on the MINE-1 benchmark (86%), outperforming prior KG construction methods. Wikontic is also efficient at build time: KG construction uses less than 1,000 output tokens, about 3times fewer than AriGraph and &lt;1/20 of GraphRAG. The proposed pipeline enhances the quality of the generated KG and offers a scalable solution for leveraging structured knowledge in LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.00590</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 18:44:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing Reinforcement Learning with LLMs: Formulation and Practices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01374</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.01374.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chujie Zheng, Kai Dang, Bowen Yu, Mingze Li, Huiqiang Jiang, Junrong Lin, Yuqiong Liu, An Yang, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 93&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper proposes a novel formulation for reinforcement learning (RL) with large language models, explaining why and under what conditions the true sequence-level reward can be optimized via a surrogate token-level objective in policy gradient methods such as REINFORCE. Specifically, through a first-order approximation, we show that this surrogate becomes increasingly valid only when both the training-inference discrepancy and policy staleness are minimized. This insight provides a principled explanation for the crucial role of several widely adopted techniques in stabilizing RL training, including importance sampling correction, clipping, and particularly Routing Replay for Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) models. Through extensive experiments with a 30B MoE model totaling hundreds of thousands of GPU hours, we show that for on-policy training, the basic policy gradient algorithm with importance sampling correction achieves the highest training stability. When off-policy updates are introduced to accelerate convergence, combining clipping and Routing Replay becomes essential to mitigate the instability caused by policy staleness. Notably, once training is stabilized, prolonged optimization consistently yields comparable final performance regardless of cold-start initialization. We hope that the shared insights and the developed recipes for stable RL training will facilitate future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01374</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 07:45:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Envision: Benchmarking Unified Understanding &amp; Generation for Causal World Process Insights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01816</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.01816.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Juanxi Tian, Siyuan Li, Conghui He, Lijun Wu, Cheng Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current multimodal models aim to transcend the limitations of single-modality representations by unifying understanding and generation, often using text-to-image (T2I) tasks to calibrate semantic consistency. However, their reliance on static, single-image generation in training and evaluation leads to overfitting to static pattern matching and semantic fusion, while fundamentally hindering their ability to model dynamic processes that unfold over time. To address these constraints, we propose Envision-a causal event progression benchmark for chained text-to-multi-image generation. Grounded in world knowledge and structured by spatiotemporal causality, it reorganizes existing evaluation dimensions and includes 1,000 four-stage prompts spanning six scientific and humanities domains. To transition evaluation from single images to sequential frames and assess whether models truly internalize world knowledge while adhering to causal-temporal constraints, we introduce Envision-Score, a holistic metric integrating multi-dimensional consistency, physicality, and aesthetics. Comprehensive evaluation of 15 models (10 specialized T2I models, 5 unified models) uncovers: specialized T2I models demonstrate proficiency in aesthetic rendering yet lack intrinsic world knowledge. Unified multimodal models bridge this gap, consistently outperforming specialized counterparts in causal narrative coherence. However, even these unified architectures remain subordinate to closed-source models and struggle to overcome the core challenge of spatiotemporal consistency. This demonstrates that a focus on causally-isolated single images impedes multi-frame reasoning and generation, promoting static pattern matching over dynamic world modeling-ultimately limiting world knowledge internalization, generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01816</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 15:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Far Are We from Genuinely Useful Deep Research Agents?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01948</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.01948.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dingling Zhang, He Zhu, Jincheng Ren, Kangqi Song, Xinran Zhou, Boyu Feng, Shudong Liu, Jiabin Luo, Weihao Xie, Zhaohui Wang, Tianrui Qin, King Zhu, Yuqing Wang, Qianben Chen, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Wei Wang, Jiaheng Liu, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep Research Agents (DRAs) aim to automatically produce analyst-level reports through iterative information retrieval and synthesis. However, most existing DRAs were validated on question-answering benchmarks, while research on generating comprehensive reports remains overlooked. Worse, current benchmarks for report synthesis suffer from task complexity and subjective metrics -- this fails to reflect user demands and limits the practical utility of generated reports. To address these gaps, we present Fine-grained DEepResearch bench (FINDER), an enhanced benchmark consisting of 100 human-curated research tasks with 419 structured checklist items that standardize report structure, analytical depth, and factual grounding. Based on approximately 1,000 reports produced by mainstream DRAs, we further propose Deep rEsearch Failure Taxonomy (DEFT), the first failure taxonomy for deep research agents. DEFT contains 14 fine-grained failure modes across reasoning, retrieval, and generation, and is built upon grounded theory with human-LLM co-annotating and inter-annotator reliability validation. Our experimental findings reveal that current DRAs struggle not with task comprehension but with evidence integration, verification, and reasoning-resilient planning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01948</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 17:58:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TUNA: Taming Unified Visual Representations for Native Unified Multimodal Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02014</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02014.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiheng Liu, Weiming Ren, Haozhe Liu, Zijian Zhou, Shoufa Chen, Haonan Qiu, Xiaoke Huang, Zhaochong An, Fanny Yang, Aditya Patel, Viktar Atliha, Tony Ng, Xiao Han, Chuyan Zhu, Chenyang Zhang, Ding Liu, Juan-Manuel Perez-Rua, Sen He, Jürgen Schmidhuber, Wenhu Chen, Ping Luo, Wei Liu, Tao Xiang, Jonas Schult, Yuren Cong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 69&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified multimodal models (UMMs) aim to jointly perform multimodal understanding and generation within a single framework. We present TUNA, a native UMM that builds a unified continuous visual representation by cascading a VAE encoder with a representation encoder. This unified representation space allows end-to-end processing of images and videos for both understanding and generation tasks. Compared to prior UMMs with decoupled representations, TUNA's unified visual space avoids representation format mismatches introduced by separate encoders, outperforming decoupled alternatives in both understanding and generation. Moreover, we observe that stronger pretrained representation encoders consistently yield better performance across all multimodal tasks, highlighting the importance of the representation encoder. Finally, in this unified setting, jointly training on both understanding and generation data allows the two tasks to benefit from each other rather than interfere. Our extensive experiments on multimodal understanding and generation benchmarks show that TUNA achieves state-of-the-art results in image and video understanding, image and video generation, and image editing, demonstrating the effectiveness and scalability of its unified representation design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02014</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 18:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork-R1V4: Toward Agentic Multimodal Intelligence through Interleaved Thinking with Images and DeepResearch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02395</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02395.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Zhang, Liang Hu, Haofeng Sun, Peiyu Wang, Yichen Wei, Shukang Yin, Jiangbo Pei, Wei Shen, Peng Xia, Yi Peng, Tianyidan Xie, Eric Li, Yang Liu, Xuchen Song, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite recent progress in multimodal agentic systems, existing approaches often treat image manipulation and web search as disjoint capabilities, rely heavily on costly reinforcement learning, and lack planning grounded in real tool-execution traces. To address these limitations, we present Skywork-R1V4, a 30B (A3B) parameter multimodal agentic model that unifies multimodal planning, active image manipulation ("thinking with images"), deep multimodal search, and, most critically, interleaved reasoning that dynamically alternates between visual operations and external knowledge retrieval. Trained solely via supervised fine-tuning on fewer than 30,000 high-quality, planning-execution-consistent trajectories and validated through stepwise consistency filtering, Skywork-R1V4 achieves state-of-the-art results across perception and multimodal search benchmarks: it scores 66.1 on MMSearch and 67.2 on FVQA, surpassing Gemini 2.5 Flash on all 11 metrics. Skywork-R1V4 exhibits emergent long-horizon reasoning at inference time, successfully orchestrating more than 10 tool calls to solve complex, multi-step tasks. Our results demonstrate that sophisticated agentic multimodal intelligence can be achieved through carefully curated supervised learning alone, without any reliance on reinforcement learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02395</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 04:12:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guided Self-Evolving LLMs with Minimal Human Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02472</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02472.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenhao Yu, Zhenwen Liang, Chengsong Huang, Kishan Panaganti, Tianqing Fang, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI self-evolution has long been envisioned as a path toward superintelligence, where models autonomously acquire, refine, and internalize knowledge from their own learning experiences. Yet in practice, unguided self-evolving systems often plateau quickly or even degrade as training progresses. These failures arise from issues such as concept drift, diversity collapse, and mis-evolution, as models reinforce their own biases and converge toward low-entropy behaviors. To enable models to self-evolve in a stable and controllable manner while minimizing reliance on human supervision, we introduce R-Few, a guided Self-Play Challenger-Solver framework that incorporates lightweight human oversight through in-context grounding and mixed training. At each iteration, the Challenger samples a small set of human-labeled examples to guide synthetic question generation, while the Solver jointly trains on human and synthetic examples under an online, difficulty-based curriculum. Across math and general reasoning benchmarks, R-Few achieves consistent and iterative improvements. For example, Qwen3-8B-Base improves by +3.0 points over R-Zero on math tasks and achieves performance on par with General-Reasoner, despite the latter being trained on 20 times more human data. Ablation studies confirm the complementary contributions of grounded challenger training and curriculum-based solver training, and further analysis shows that R-Few mitigates drift, yielding more stable and controllable co-evolutionary dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02472</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 07:06:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSeek-V3.2: Pushing the Frontier of Open Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02556</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02556.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; DeepSeek-AI, Aixin Liu, Aoxue Mei, Bangcai Lin, Bing Xue, Bingxuan Wang, Bingzheng Xu, Bochao Wu, Bowei Zhang, Chaofan Lin, Chen Dong, Chengda Lu, Chenggang Zhao, Chengqi Deng, Chenhao Xu, Chong Ruan, Damai Dai, Daya Guo, Dejian Yang, Deli Chen, Erhang Li, Fangqi Zhou, Fangyun Lin, Fucong Dai, Guangbo Hao, Guanting Chen, Guowei Li, H. Zhang, Hanwei Xu, Hao Li, Haofen Liang, Haoran Wei, Haowei Zhang, Haowen Luo, Haozhe Ji, Honghui Ding, Hongxuan Tang, Huanqi Cao, Huazuo Gao, Hui Qu, Hui Zeng, Jialiang Huang, Jiashi Li, Jiaxin Xu, Jiewen Hu, Jingchang Chen, Jingting Xiang, Jingyang Yuan, Jingyuan Cheng, Jinhua Zhu, Jun Ran, Junguang Jiang, Junjie Qiu, Junlong Li, Junxiao Song, Kai Dong, Kaige Gao, Kang Guan, Kexin Huang, Kexing Zhou, Kezhao Huang, Kuai Yu, Lean Wang, Lecong Zhang, Lei Wang, Liang Zhao, Liangsheng Yin, Lihua Guo, Lingxiao Luo, Linwang Ma, Litong Wang, Liyue Zhang, M. S. Di, M. Y Xu, Mingchuan Zhang, Minghua Zhang, Minghui Tang, Mingxu Zhou, Panpan Huang, Peixin Cong, Peiyi Wang, Qiancheng Wang, Qihao Zhu, Qingyang Li, Qinyu Chen, Qiushi Du, Ruiling Xu, Ruiqi Ge, Ruisong Zhang, Ruizhe Pan, Runji Wang, Runqiu Yin, Runxin Xu, Ruomeng Shen, Ruoyu Zhang, S. H. Liu, Shanghao Lu, Shangyan Zhou, Shanhuang Chen, Shaofei Cai, Shaoyuan Chen, Shengding Hu, Shengyu Liu, Shiqiang Hu, Shirong Ma, Shiyu Wang, Shuiping Yu, Shunfeng Zhou, Shuting Pan, Songyang Zhou, Tao Ni, Tao Yun, Tian Pei, Tian Ye, Tianyuan Yue, Wangding Zeng, Wen Liu, Wenfeng Liang, Wenjie Pang, Wenjing Luo, Wenjun Gao, Wentao Zhang, Xi Gao, Xiangwen Wang, Xiao Bi, Xiaodong Liu, Xiaohan Wang, Xiaokang Chen, Xiaokang Zhang, Xiaotao Nie, Xin Cheng, Xin Liu, Xin Xie, Xingchao Liu, Xingkai Yu, Xingyou Li, Xinyu Yang, Xinyuan Li, Xu Chen, Xuecheng Su, Xuehai Pan, Xuheng Lin, Xuwei Fu, Y. Q. Wang, Yang Zhang, Yanhong Xu, Yanru Ma, Yao Li, Yao Li, Yao Zhao, Yaofeng Sun, Yaohui Wang, Yi Qian, Yi Yu, Yichao Zhang, Yifan Ding, Yifan Shi, Yiliang Xiong, Ying He, Ying Zhou, Yinmin Zhong, Yishi Piao, Yisong Wang, Yixiao Chen, Yixuan Tan, Yixuan Wei, Yiyang Ma, Yiyuan Liu, Yonglun Yang, Yongqiang Guo, Yongtong Wu, Yu Wu, Yuan Cheng, Yuan Ou, Yuanfan Xu, Yuduan Wang, Yue Gong, Yuhan Wu, Yuheng Zou, Yukun Li, Yunfan Xiong, Yuxiang Luo, Yuxiang You, Yuxuan Liu, Yuyang Zhou, Z. F. Wu, Z. Z. Ren, Zehua Zhao, Zehui Ren, Zhangli Sha, Zhe Fu, Zhean Xu, Zhenda Xie, Zhengyan Zhang, Zhewen Hao, Zhibin Gou, Zhicheng Ma, Zhigang Yan, Zhihong Shao, Zhixian Huang, Zhiyu Wu, Zhuoshu Li, Zhuping Zhang, Zian Xu, Zihao Wang, Zihui Gu, Zijia Zhu, Zilin Li, Zipeng Zhang, Ziwei Xie, Ziyi Gao, Zizheng Pan, Zongqing Yao, Bei Feng, Hui Li, J. L. Cai, Jiaqi Ni, Lei Xu, Meng Li, Ning Tian, R. J. Chen, R. L. Jin, S. S. Li, Shuang Zhou, Tianyu Sun, X. Q. Li, Xiangyue Jin, Xiaojin Shen, Xiaosha Chen, Xinnan Song, Xinyi Zhou, Y. X. Zhu, Yanping Huang, Yaohui Li, Yi Zheng, Yuchen Zhu, Yunxian Ma, Zhen Huang, Zhipeng Xu, Zhongyu Zhang, Dongjie Ji, Jian Liang, Jianzhong Guo, Jin Chen, Leyi Xia, Miaojun Wang, Mingming Li, Peng Zhang, Ruyi Chen, Shangmian Sun, Shaoqing Wu, Shengfeng Ye, T. Wang, W. L. Xiao, Wei An, Xianzu Wang, Xiaowen Sun, Xiaoxiang Wang, Ying Tang, Yukun Zha, Zekai Zhang, Zhe Ju, Zhen Zhang, Zihua Qu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 242&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce DeepSeek-V3.2, a model that harmonizes high computational efficiency with superior reasoning and agent performance. The key technical breakthroughs of DeepSeek-V3.2 are as follows: (1) DeepSeek Sparse Attention (DSA): We introduce DSA, an efficient attention mechanism that substantially reduces computational complexity while preserving model performance in long-context scenarios. (2) Scalable Reinforcement Learning Framework: By implementing a robust reinforcement learning protocol and scaling post-training compute, DeepSeek-V3.2 performs comparably to GPT-5. Notably, our high-compute variant, DeepSeek-V3.2-Speciale, surpasses GPT-5 and exhibits reasoning proficiency on par with Gemini-3.0-Pro, achieving gold-medal performance in both the 2025 International Mathematical Olympiad (IMO) and the International Olympiad in Informatics (IOI). (3) Large-Scale Agentic Task Synthesis Pipeline: To integrate reasoning into tool-use scenarios, we developed a novel synthesis pipeline that systematically generates training data at scale. This methodology facilitates scalable agentic post-training, yielding substantial improvements in generalization and instruction-following robustness within complex, interactive environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02556</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 09:25:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PaperDebugger: A Plugin-Based Multi-Agent System for In-Editor Academic Writing, Review, and Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02589</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.02589.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyi Hou, Andre Lin Huikai, Nuo Chen, Yiwei Gong, Bingsheng He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models are increasingly embedded into academic writing workflows, yet existing assistants remain external to the editor, preventing deep interaction with document state, structure, and revision history. This separation makes it impossible to support agentic, context-aware operations directly within LaTeX editors such as Overleaf. We present PaperDebugger, an in-editor, multi-agent, and plugin-based academic writing assistant that brings LLM-driven reasoning directly into the writing environment. Enabling such in-editor interaction is technically non-trivial: it requires reliable bidirectional synchronization with the editor, fine-grained version control and patching, secure state management, multi-agent scheduling, and extensible communication with external tools. PaperDebugger addresses these challenges through a Chrome-approved extension, a Kubernetes-native orchestration layer, and a Model Context Protocol (MCP) toolchain that integrates literature search, reference lookup, document scoring, and revision pipelines. Our demo showcases a fully integrated workflow, including localized edits, structured reviews, parallel agent execution, and diff-based updates, encapsulated within a minimal-intrusion user interface (UI). Early aggregated analytics demonstrate active user engagement and validate the practicality of an editor-native, agentic writing assistant. More details about this demo and video could be found at https://github.com/PaperDebugger/PaperDebugger.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.02589</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 10:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MultiShotMaster: A Controllable Multi-Shot Video Generation Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03041</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.03041.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qinghe Wang, Xiaoyu Shi, Baolu Li, Weikang Bian, Quande Liu, Huchuan Lu, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Kun Gai, Xu Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current video generation techniques excel at single-shot clips but struggle to produce narrative multi-shot videos, which require flexible shot arrangement, coherent narrative, and controllability beyond text prompts. To tackle these challenges, we propose MultiShotMaster, a framework for highly controllable multi-shot video generation. We extend a pretrained single-shot model by integrating two novel variants of RoPE. First, we introduce Multi-Shot Narrative RoPE, which applies explicit phase shift at shot transitions, enabling flexible shot arrangement while preserving the temporal narrative order. Second, we design Spatiotemporal Position-Aware RoPE to incorporate reference tokens and grounding signals, enabling spatiotemporal-grounded reference injection. In addition, to overcome data scarcity, we establish an automated data annotation pipeline to extract multi-shot videos, captions, cross-shot grounding signals and reference images. Our framework leverages the intrinsic architectural properties to support multi-shot video generation, featuring text-driven inter-shot consistency, customized subject with motion control, and background-driven customized scene. Both shot count and duration are flexibly configurable. Extensive experiments demonstrate the superior performance and outstanding controllability of our framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03041</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 18:59:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PretrainZero: Reinforcement Active Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03442</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.03442.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xingrun Xing, Zhiyuan Fan, Jie Lou, Guoqi Li, Jiajun Zhang, Debing Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Mimicking human behavior to actively learning from general experience and achieve artificial general intelligence has always been a human dream. Recent reinforcement learning (RL) based large-thinking models demonstrate impressive expert-level abilities, i.e., software and math, but still rely heavily on verifiable rewards in specific domains, placing a significant bottleneck to extend the performance boundary of general reasoning capabilities. In this work, we propose PretrainZero, a reinforcement active learning framework built on the pretraining corpus to extend RL from domain-specific post-training to general pretraining. PretrainZero features the following characteristics: 1) Active pretraining: inspired by the active learning ability of humans, PretrainZero learns a unified reasoning policy to actively identify reasonable and informative contents from pretraining corpus, and reason to predict these contents by RL. 2) Self-supervised learning: without any verifiable labels, pretrained reward models, or supervised fine-tuning, we directly pretrain reasoners from 3 to 30B base models on the general Wikipedia corpus using RL, significantly breaking the verification data-wall for general reasoning. 3) Verification scaling: by tackling increasingly challenging masked spans, PretrainZero substantially enhances the general reasoning abilities of pretrained base models. In reinforcement pretraining, PretrainZero improves Qwen3-4B-Base for 8.43, 5.96 and 10.60 on MMLU-Pro, SuperGPQA and math average benchmarks. In post-training, the pretrained models can also serve as reasoning foundation models for downstream RLVR tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03442</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 04:51:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TwinFlow: Realizing One-step Generation on Large Models with Self-adversarial Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05150</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05150.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenglin Cheng, Peng Sun, Jianguo Li, Tao Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large multi-modal generative models have demonstrated impressive capabilities in multi-modal generation, including image and video generation. These models are typically built upon multi-step frameworks like diffusion and flow matching, which inherently limits their inference efficiency (requiring 40-100 Number of Function Evaluations (NFEs)). While various few-step methods aim to accelerate the inference, existing solutions have clear limitations. Prominent distillation-based methods, such as progressive and consistency distillation, either require an iterative distillation procedure or show significant degradation at very few steps (&lt; 4-NFE). Meanwhile, integrating adversarial training into distillation (e.g., DMD/DMD2 and SANA-Sprint) to enhance performance introduces training instability, added complexity, and high GPU memory overhead due to the auxiliary trained models. To this end, we propose TwinFlow, a simple yet effective framework for training 1-step generative models that bypasses the need of fixed pretrained teacher models and avoids standard adversarial networks during training, making it ideal for building large-scale, efficient models. On text-to-image tasks, our method achieves a GenEval score of 0.83 in 1-NFE, outperforming strong baselines like SANA-Sprint (a GAN loss-based framework) and RCGM (a consistency-based framework). Notably, we demonstrate the scalability of TwinFlow by full-parameter training on Qwen-Image-20B and transform it into an efficient few-step generator. With just 1-NFE, our approach matches the performance of the original 100-NFE model on both the GenEval and DPG-Bench benchmarks, reducing computational cost by 100times with minor quality degradation. Project page is available at https://zhenglin-cheng.com/twinflow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05150</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 07:45:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DAComp: Benchmarking Data Agents across the Full Data Intelligence Lifecycle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04324</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04324.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fangyu Lei, Jinxiang Meng, Yiming Huang, Junjie Zhao, Yitong Zhang, Jianwen Luo, Xin Zou, Ruiyi Yang, Wenbo Shi, Yan Gao, Shizhu He, Zuo Wang, Qian Liu, Yang Wang, Ke Wang, Jun Zhao, Kang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 149&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Real-world enterprise data intelligence workflows encompass data engineering that turns raw sources into analytical-ready tables and data analysis that convert those tables into decision-oriented insights. We introduce DAComp, a benchmark of 210 tasks that mirrors these complex workflows. Data engineering (DE) tasks require repository-level engineering on industrial schemas, including designing and building multi-stage SQL pipelines from scratch and evolving existing systems under evolving requirements. Data analysis (DA) tasks pose open-ended business problems that demand strategic planning, exploratory analysis through iterative coding, interpretation of intermediate results, and the synthesis of actionable recommendations. Engineering tasks are scored through execution-based, multi-metric evaluation. Open-ended tasks are assessed by a reliable, experimentally validated LLM-judge, which is guided by hierarchical, meticulously crafted rubrics. Our experiments reveal that even state-of-the-art agents falter on DAComp. Performance on DE tasks is particularly low, with success rates under 20%, exposing a critical bottleneck in holistic pipeline orchestration, not merely code generation. Scores on DA tasks also average below 40%, highlighting profound deficiencies in open-ended reasoning and demonstrating that engineering and analysis are distinct capabilities. By clearly diagnosing these limitations, DAComp provides a rigorous and realistic testbed to drive the development of truly capable autonomous data agents for enterprise settings. Our data and code are available at https://da-comp.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04324</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 23:21:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Live Avatar: Streaming Real-time Audio-Driven Avatar Generation with Infinite Length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04677</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04677.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yubo Huang, Hailong Guo, Fangtai Wu, Shifeng Zhang, Shijie Huang, Qijun Gan, Lin Liu, Sirui Zhao, Enhong Chen, Jiaming Liu, Steven Hoi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 167&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing diffusion-based video generation methods are fundamentally constrained by sequential computation and long-horizon inconsistency, limiting their practical adoption in real-time, streaming audio-driven avatar synthesis. We present Live Avatar, an algorithm-system co-designed framework that enables efficient, high-fidelity, and infinite-length avatar generation using a 14-billion-parameter diffusion model. Our approach introduces Timestep-forcing Pipeline Parallelism (TPP), a distributed inference paradigm that pipelines denoising steps across multiple GPUs, effectively breaking the autoregressive bottleneck and ensuring stable, low-latency real-time streaming. To further enhance temporal consistency and mitigate identity drift and color artifacts, we propose the Rolling Sink Frame Mechanism (RSFM), which maintains sequence fidelity by dynamically recalibrating appearance using a cached reference image. Additionally, we leverage Self-Forcing Distribution Matching Distillation to facilitate causal, streamable adaptation of large-scale models without sacrificing visual quality. Live Avatar demonstrates state-of-the-art performance, reaching 20 FPS end-to-end generation on 5 H800 GPUs, and, to the best of our knowledge, is the first to achieve practical, real-time, high-fidelity avatar generation at this scale. Our work establishes a new paradigm for deploying advanced diffusion models in industrial long-form video synthesis applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04677</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 11:11:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reward Forcing: Efficient Streaming Video Generation with Rewarded Distribution Matching Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04678</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04678.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunhong Lu, Yanhong Zeng, Haobo Li, Hao Ouyang, Qiuyu Wang, Ka Leong Cheng, Jiapeng Zhu, Hengyuan Cao, Zhipeng Zhang, Xing Zhu, Yujun Shen, Min Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Efficient streaming video generation is critical for simulating interactive and dynamic worlds. Existing methods distill few-step video diffusion models with sliding window attention, using initial frames as sink tokens to maintain attention performance and reduce error accumulation. However, video frames become overly dependent on these static tokens, resulting in copied initial frames and diminished motion dynamics. To address this, we introduce Reward Forcing, a novel framework with two key designs. First, we propose EMA-Sink, which maintains fixed-size tokens initialized from initial frames and continuously updated by fusing evicted tokens via exponential moving average as they exit the sliding window. Without additional computation cost, EMA-Sink tokens capture both long-term context and recent dynamics, preventing initial frame copying while maintaining long-horizon consistency. Second, to better distill motion dynamics from teacher models, we propose a novel Rewarded Distribution Matching Distillation (Re-DMD). Vanilla distribution matching treats every training sample equally, limiting the model's ability to prioritize dynamic content. Instead, Re-DMD biases the model's output distribution toward high-reward regions by prioritizing samples with greater dynamics rated by a vision-language model. Re-DMD significantly enhances motion quality while preserving data fidelity. We include both quantitative and qualitative experiments to show that Reward Forcing achieves state-of-the-art performance on standard benchmarks while enabling high-quality streaming video generation at 23.1 FPS on a single H100 GPU.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04678</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 11:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantics Lead the Way: Harmonizing Semantic and Texture Modeling with Asynchronous Latent Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04926</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04926.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yueming Pan, Ruoyu Feng, Qi Dai, Yuqi Wang, Wenfeng Lin, Mingyu Guo, Chong Luo, Nanning Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Latent Diffusion Models (LDMs) inherently follow a coarse-to-fine generation process, where high-level semantic structure is generated slightly earlier than fine-grained texture. This indicates the preceding semantics potentially benefit texture generation by providing a semantic anchor. Recent advances have integrated semantic priors from pretrained visual encoders to further enhance LDMs, yet they still denoise semantic and VAE-encoded texture synchronously, neglecting such ordering. Observing these, we propose Semantic-First Diffusion (SFD), a latent diffusion paradigm that explicitly prioritizes semantic formation. SFD first constructs composite latents by combining a compact semantic latent, which is extracted from a pretrained visual encoder via a dedicated Semantic VAE, with the texture latent. The core of SFD is to denoise the semantic and texture latents asynchronously using separate noise schedules: semantics precede textures by a temporal offset, providing clearer high-level guidance for texture refinement and enabling natural coarse-to-fine generation. On ImageNet 256x256 with guidance, SFD achieves FID 1.06 (LightningDiT-XL) and FID 1.04 (1.0B LightningDiT-XXL), while achieving up to 100x faster convergence than the original DiT. SFD also improves existing methods like ReDi and VA-VAE, demonstrating the effectiveness of asynchronous, semantics-led modeling. Project page and code: https://yuemingpan.github.io/SFD.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04926</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 15:57:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nex-N1: Agentic Models Trained via a Unified Ecosystem for Large-Scale Environment Construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04987</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.04987.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nex-AGI Team, Yuxuan Cai, Lu Chen, Qiaoling Chen, Yuyang Ding, Liwen Fan, Wenjie Fu, Yufei Gao, Honglin Guo, Pinxue Guo, Zhenhua Han, Zhengfu He, Hanglei Hu, Kai Hu, Shengjia Hua, Tianyu Huai, Baodai Huang, Li Ji, Zhen Jiang, Zhikai Lei, Bufan Li, Jiahang Lin, Lizhi Lin, Jinxiu Liu, Shichun Liu, Ziming Liu, Yuchen Ni, Pengfang Qian, Yujiong Shen, Qingyun Shi, Wentao Shu, Peng Sun, Yiran Suo, Tian Tang, Boyu Tian, Guoteng Wang, Junzhe Wang, Peixin Wang, Zhiheng Xi, Hang Yan, Jie Yang, Zhixiong Yang, Tianchu Yao, Guangze Ye, Qianxi Yu, Shuo Zhang, Xinyue Zhang, Yiqi Zhang, Jiarong Zhao, Miao Zheng, Rui Zheng, Enyu Zhou, Jiazheng Zhou, Maosen Zhou, Yuhao Zhou, Tao Gui, Yining Zheng, Xinchi Chen, Jie Zhou, Siyuan Feng, Qin Chen, Liang He, Qi Zhang, Xuanjing Huang, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The evolution of Large Language Models (LLMs) from passive responders to autonomous agents necessitates a fundamental shift in learning paradigms -- from static imitation to incentive-driven decision making. However, this transition is significantly impeded by the lack of scalable infrastructure capable of constructing high-quality interaction signals for effective policy learning. To address this, we introduce a comprehensive method designed to systematically scale the diversity and complexity of interactive environments. Our method realizes this scaling by addressing three orthogonal dimensions: (1) Complexity: NexAU, a flexible agent framework that supports building complex agent hierarchies via simple configurations; (2) Diversity: NexA4A automatically generates diverse agent hierarchies from natural language to cover infinite domains; and (3) Fidelity: NexGAP bridges the simulation-reality gap by integrating dynamic real-world environment for grounded trajectories synthesis. We train Nex-N1 upon the diverse and complex interactive environments established by our infrastructure. Empirical results on benchmarks such as SWE-bench and tau2 demonstrate that Nex-N1 consistently outperforms SOTA open-source models and achieves competitive performance against frontier proprietary models on complex agentic tasks. We open-source the Nex ecosystem and model weights to facilitate further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04987</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 16:57:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARM-Thinker: Reinforcing Multimodal Generative Reward Models with Agentic Tool Use and Visual Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05111</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05111.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengyuan Ding, Xinyu Fang, Ziyu Liu, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Xiangyu Zhao, Haodong Duan, Xiaoyi Dong, Jianze Liang, Bin Wang, Conghui He, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward models are critical for aligning vision-language systems with human preferences, yet current approaches suffer from hallucination, weak visual grounding, and an inability to use tools for verification, limiting their reliability on complex multimodal reasoning tasks. We present ARM-Thinker, an A}gentic multimodal Reward Model that autonomously invokes external tools (e.g., image cropping, doc page retrieval) to ground judgments in verifiable evidence, replacing static, non-interactive reward scoring. This enables the model to verify fine-grained visual details, cross-reference multi-page evidence, and validate reasoning claims, which are capabilities absent in existing reward models. We train ARM-Thinker with multi-stage reinforcement learning, jointly optimizing tool-calling decisions and judgment accuracy. To evaluate agentic reward modeling, we introduce ARMBench-VL, comprising three benchmarks that assess fine-grained visual grounding (image-level tools), multi-page document understanding (retrieval tools), and instruction following (text-level verification). ARM-Thinker achieves +16.2% average improvement on reward modeling benchmarks, +9.6% on tool-use tasks, and outperforms baselines on multimodal math and logical reasoning benchmarks. Our results demonstrate that agentic capabilities significantly enhance both accuracy and interpretability of reward models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05111</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 18:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EditThinker: Unlocking Iterative Reasoning for Any Image Editor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05965</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.05965.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongyu Li, Manyuan Zhang, Dian Zheng, Ziyu Guo, Yimeng Jia, Kaituo Feng, Hao Yu, Yexin Liu, Yan Feng, Peng Pei, Xunliang Cai, Linjiang Huang, Hongsheng Li, Si Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-based image editing has emerged as a prominent research area, which, benefiting from image generation foundation models, have achieved high aesthetic quality, making instruction-following capability the primary challenge. Existing approaches improve instruction adherence via supervised or reinforcement learning, yet single-turn success rates remain limited due to inherent stochasticity and a lack of deliberation. In this work, we propose a deliberative editing framework to 'think' while they edit, which simulates the human cognitive loop by iteratively executing a Think-while-Edit cycle: Critiquing results and Refining instructions , followed by Repeating the generation until satisfactory. Specifically, we train a single MLLM, EditThinker, to act as the reasoning engine of this framework, which jointly produce the critique score, reasoning process, and refined instructions. We employ reinforcement learning to align the EditThinker's thinking with its editing, thereby generating more targeted instruction improvements. Extensive experiments on four benchmarks demonstrate that our approach significantly improves the instruction-following capability of any image editing model by a large margin. We will release our data construction framework, datasets, and models to benefit the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05965</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 18:58:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Native Parallel Reasoner: Reasoning in Parallelism via Self-Distilled Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07461</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07461.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tong Wu, Yang Liu, Jun Bai, Zixia Jia, Shuyi Zhang, Ziyong Lin, Yanting Wang, Song-Chun Zhu, Zilong Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Native Parallel Reasoner (NPR), a teacher-free framework that enables Large Language Models (LLMs) to self-evolve genuine parallel reasoning capabilities. NPR transforms the model from sequential emulation to native parallel cognition through three key innovations: 1) a self-distilled progressive training paradigm that transitions from ``cold-start'' format discovery to strict topological constraints without external supervision; 2) a novel Parallel-Aware Policy Optimization (PAPO) algorithm that optimizes branching policies directly within the execution graph, allowing the model to learn adaptive decomposition via trial and error; and 3) a robust NPR Engine that refactors memory management and flow control of SGLang to enable stable, large-scale parallel RL training. Across eight reasoning benchmarks, NPR trained on Qwen3-4B achieves performance gains of up to 24.5% and inference speedups up to 4.6x. Unlike prior baselines that often fall back to autoregressive decoding, NPR demonstrates 100% genuine parallel execution, establishing a new standard for self-evolving, efficient, and scalable agentic reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07461</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:39:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Video Editing with Temporal Reasoner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07469</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07469.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangpeng Yang, Ji Xie, Yiyuan Yang, Yan Huang, Min Xu, Qiang Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing video editing methods face a critical trade-off: expert models offer precision but rely on task-specific priors like masks, hindering unification; conversely, unified temporal in-context learning models are mask-free but lack explicit spatial cues, leading to weak instruction-to-region mapping and imprecise localization. To resolve this conflict, we propose VideoCoF, a novel Chain-of-Frames approach inspired by Chain-of-Thought reasoning. VideoCoF enforces a ``see, reason, then edit" procedure by compelling the video diffusion model to first predict reasoning tokens (edit-region latents) before generating the target video tokens. This explicit reasoning step removes the need for user-provided masks while achieving precise instruction-to-region alignment and fine-grained video editing. Furthermore, we introduce a RoPE alignment strategy that leverages these reasoning tokens to ensure motion alignment and enable length extrapolation beyond the training duration. We demonstrate that with a minimal data cost of only 50k video pairs, VideoCoF achieves state-of-the-art performance on VideoCoF-Bench, validating the efficiency and effectiveness of our approach. Our code, weight, data are available at https://github.com/knightyxp/VideoCoF.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07469</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:50:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Real: Imaginary Extension of Rotary Position Embeddings for Long-Context LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07525</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07525.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoran Liu, Yuerong Song, Zhigeng Liu, Zengfeng Huang, Qipeng Guo, Zhaoxiang Liu, Shiguo Lian, Ziwei He, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Rotary Position Embeddings (RoPE) have become a standard for encoding sequence order in Large Language Models (LLMs) by applying rotations to query and key vectors in the complex plane. Standard implementations, however, utilize only the real component of the complex-valued dot product for attention score calculation. This simplification discards the imaginary component, which contains valuable phase information, leading to a potential loss of relational details crucial for modeling long-context dependencies. In this paper, we propose an extension that re-incorporates this discarded imaginary component. Our method leverages the full complex-valued representation to create a dual-component attention score. We theoretically and empirically demonstrate that this approach enhances the modeling of long-context dependencies by preserving more positional information. Furthermore, evaluations on a suite of long-context language modeling benchmarks show that our method consistently improves performance over the standard RoPE, with the benefits becoming more significant as context length increases. The code is available at https://github.com/OpenMOSS/rope_pp.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07525</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 12:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Interplay of Pre-Training, Mid-Training, and RL on Reasoning Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07783</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07783.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Charlie Zhang, Graham Neubig, Xiang Yue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reinforcement learning (RL) techniques have yielded impressive reasoning improvements in language models, yet it remains unclear whether post-training truly extends a model's reasoning ability beyond what it acquires during pre-training. A central challenge is the lack of control in modern training pipelines: large-scale pre-training corpora are opaque, mid-training is often underexamined, and RL objectives interact with unknown prior knowledge in complex ways. To resolve this ambiguity, we develop a fully controlled experimental framework that isolates the causal contributions of pre-training, mid-training, and RL-based post-training. Our approach employs synthetic reasoning tasks with explicit atomic operations, parseable step-by-step reasoning traces, and systematic manipulation of training distributions. We evaluate models along two axes: extrapolative generalization to more complex compositions and contextual generalization across surface contexts. Using this framework, we reconcile competing views on RL's effectiveness. We show that: 1) RL produces true capability gains (pass@128) only when pre-training leaves sufficient headroom and when RL data target the model's edge of competence, tasks at the boundary that are difficult but not yet out of reach. 2) Contextual generalization requires minimal yet sufficient pre-training exposure, after which RL can reliably transfer. 3) Mid-training significantly enhances performance under fixed compute compared with RL only, demonstrating its central but underexplored role in training pipelines. 4) Process-level rewards reduce reward hacking and improve reasoning fidelity. Together, these results clarify the interplay between pre-training, mid-training, and RL, offering a foundation for understanding and improving reasoning LM training strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07783</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OneStory: Coherent Multi-Shot Video Generation with Adaptive Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07802</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07802.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaochong An, Menglin Jia, Haonan Qiu, Zijian Zhou, Xiaoke Huang, Zhiheng Liu, Weiming Ren, Kumara Kahatapitiya, Ding Liu, Sen He, Chenyang Zhang, Tao Xiang, Fanny Yang, Serge Belongie, Tian Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Storytelling in real-world videos often unfolds through multiple shots -- discontinuous yet semantically connected clips that together convey a coherent narrative. However, existing multi-shot video generation (MSV) methods struggle to effectively model long-range cross-shot context, as they rely on limited temporal windows or single keyframe conditioning, leading to degraded performance under complex narratives. In this work, we propose OneStory, enabling global yet compact cross-shot context modeling for consistent and scalable narrative generation. OneStory reformulates MSV as a next-shot generation task, enabling autoregressive shot synthesis while leveraging pretrained image-to-video (I2V) models for strong visual conditioning. We introduce two key modules: a Frame Selection module that constructs a semantically-relevant global memory based on informative frames from prior shots, and an Adaptive Conditioner that performs importance-guided patchification to generate compact context for direct conditioning. We further curate a high-quality multi-shot dataset with referential captions to mirror real-world storytelling patterns, and design effective training strategies under the next-shot paradigm. Finetuned from a pretrained I2V model on our curated 60K dataset, OneStory achieves state-of-the-art narrative coherence across diverse and complex scenes in both text- and image-conditioned settings, enabling controllable and immersive long-form video storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07802</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:32:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voxify3D: Pixel Art Meets Volumetric Rendering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07834</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07834.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi-Chuan Huang, Jiewen Chan, Hao-Jen Chien, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Voxel art is a distinctive stylization widely used in games and digital media, yet automated generation from 3D meshes remains challenging due to conflicting requirements of geometric abstraction, semantic preservation, and discrete color coherence. Existing methods either over-simplify geometry or fail to achieve the pixel-precise, palette-constrained aesthetics of voxel art. We introduce Voxify3D, a differentiable two-stage framework bridging 3D mesh optimization with 2D pixel art supervision. Our core innovation lies in the synergistic integration of three components: (1) orthographic pixel art supervision that eliminates perspective distortion for precise voxel-pixel alignment; (2) patch-based CLIP alignment that preserves semantics across discretization levels; (3) palette-constrained Gumbel-Softmax quantization enabling differentiable optimization over discrete color spaces with controllable palette strategies. This integration addresses fundamental challenges: semantic preservation under extreme discretization, pixel-art aesthetics through volumetric rendering, and end-to-end discrete optimization. Experiments show superior performance (37.12 CLIP-IQA, 77.90\% user preference) across diverse characters and controllable abstraction (2-8 colors, 20x-50x resolutions). Project page: https://yichuanh.github.io/Voxify-3D/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07834</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 18:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving Source Video Realism: High-Fidelity Face Swapping for Cinematic Quality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07951</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.07951.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zekai Luo, Zongze Du, Zhouhang Zhu, Hao Zhong, Muzhi Zhu, Wen Wang, Yuling Xi, Chenchen Jing, Hao Chen, Chunhua Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video face swapping is crucial in film and entertainment production, where achieving high fidelity and temporal consistency over long and complex video sequences remains a significant challenge. Inspired by recent advances in reference-guided image editing, we explore whether rich visual attributes from source videos can be similarly leveraged to enhance both fidelity and temporal coherence in video face swapping. Building on this insight, this work presents LivingSwap, the first video reference guided face swapping model. Our approach employs keyframes as conditioning signals to inject the target identity, enabling flexible and controllable editing. By combining keyframe conditioning with video reference guidance, the model performs temporal stitching to ensure stable identity preservation and high-fidelity reconstruction across long video sequences. To address the scarcity of data for reference-guided training, we construct a paired face-swapping dataset, Face2Face, and further reverse the data pairs to ensure reliable ground-truth supervision. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method achieves state-of-the-art results, seamlessly integrating the target identity with the source video's expressions, lighting, and motion, while significantly reducing manual effort in production workflows. Project webpage: https://aim-uofa.github.io/LivingSwap&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07951</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 19:00:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EgoX: Egocentric Video Generation from a Single Exocentric Video</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08269</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08269.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taewoong Kang, Kinam Kim, Dohyeon Kim, Minho Park, Junha Hyung, Jaegul Choo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 115&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Egocentric perception enables humans to experience and understand the world directly from their own point of view. Translating exocentric (third-person) videos into egocentric (first-person) videos opens up new possibilities for immersive understanding but remains highly challenging due to extreme camera pose variations and minimal view overlap. This task requires faithfully preserving visible content while synthesizing unseen regions in a geometrically consistent manner. To achieve this, we present EgoX, a novel framework for generating egocentric videos from a single exocentric input. EgoX leverages the pretrained spatio temporal knowledge of large-scale video diffusion models through lightweight LoRA adaptation and introduces a unified conditioning strategy that combines exocentric and egocentric priors via width and channel wise concatenation. Additionally, a geometry-guided self-attention mechanism selectively attends to spatially relevant regions, ensuring geometric coherence and high visual fidelity. Our approach achieves coherent and realistic egocentric video generation while demonstrating strong scalability and robustness across unseen and in-the-wild videos.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08269</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 05:53:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BrainExplore: Large-Scale Discovery of Interpretable Visual Representations in the Human Brain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08560</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08560.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Navve Wasserman, Matias Cosarinsky, Yuval Golbari, Aude Oliva, Antonio Torralba, Tamar Rott Shaham, Michal Irani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding how the human brain represents visual concepts, and in which brain regions these representations are encoded, remains a long-standing challenge. Decades of work have advanced our understanding of visual representations, yet brain signals remain large and complex, and the space of possible visual concepts is vast. As a result, most studies remain small-scale, rely on manual inspection, focus on specific regions and properties, and rarely include systematic validation. We present a large-scale, automated framework for discovering and explaining visual representations across the human cortex. Our method comprises two main stages. First, we discover candidate interpretable patterns in fMRI activity through unsupervised, data-driven decomposition methods. Next, we explain each pattern by identifying the set of natural images that most strongly elicit it and generating a natural-language description of their shared visual meaning. To scale this process, we introduce an automated pipeline that tests multiple candidate explanations, assigns quantitative reliability scores, and selects the most consistent description for each voxel pattern. Our framework reveals thousands of interpretable patterns spanning many distinct visual concepts, including fine-grained representations previously unreported.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08560</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 13:01:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wan-Move: Motion-controllable Video Generation via Latent Trajectory Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08765</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08765.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruihang Chu, Yefei He, Zhekai Chen, Shiwei Zhang, Xiaogang Xu, Bin Xia, Dingdong Wang, Hongwei Yi, Xihui Liu, Hengshuang Zhao, Yu Liu, Yingya Zhang, Yujiu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 128&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Wan-Move, a simple and scalable framework that brings motion control to video generative models. Existing motion-controllable methods typically suffer from coarse control granularity and limited scalability, leaving their outputs insufficient for practical use. We narrow this gap by achieving precise and high-quality motion control. Our core idea is to directly make the original condition features motion-aware for guiding video synthesis. To this end, we first represent object motions with dense point trajectories, allowing fine-grained control over the scene. We then project these trajectories into latent space and propagate the first frame's features along each trajectory, producing an aligned spatiotemporal feature map that tells how each scene element should move. This feature map serves as the updated latent condition, which is naturally integrated into the off-the-shelf image-to-video model, e.g., Wan-I2V-14B, as motion guidance without any architecture change. It removes the need for auxiliary motion encoders and makes fine-tuning base models easily scalable. Through scaled training, Wan-Move generates 5-second, 480p videos whose motion controllability rivals Kling 1.5 Pro's commercial Motion Brush, as indicated by user studies. To support comprehensive evaluation, we further design MoveBench, a rigorously curated benchmark featuring diverse content categories and hybrid-verified annotations. It is distinguished by larger data volume, longer video durations, and high-quality motion annotations. Extensive experiments on MoveBench and the public dataset consistently show Wan-Move's superior motion quality. Code, models, and benchmark data are made publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08765</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 16:13:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniPSD: Layered PSD Generation with Diffusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09247</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09247.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng Liu, Yiren Song, Haofan Wang, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in diffusion models have greatly improved image generation and editing, yet generating or reconstructing layered PSD files with transparent alpha channels remains highly challenging. We propose OmniPSD, a unified diffusion framework built upon the Flux ecosystem that enables both text-to-PSD generation and image-to-PSD decomposition through in-context learning. For text-to-PSD generation, OmniPSD arranges multiple target layers spatially into a single canvas and learns their compositional relationships through spatial attention, producing semantically coherent and hierarchically structured layers. For image-to-PSD decomposition, it performs iterative in-context editing, progressively extracting and erasing textual and foreground components to reconstruct editable PSD layers from a single flattened image. An RGBA-VAE is employed as an auxiliary representation module to preserve transparency without affecting structure learning. Extensive experiments on our new RGBA-layered dataset demonstrate that OmniPSD achieves high-fidelity generation, structural consistency, and transparency awareness, offering a new paradigm for layered design generation and decomposition with diffusion transformers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09247</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 02:09:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StereoWorld: Geometry-Aware Monocular-to-Stereo Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09363</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09363.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ke Xing, Longfei Li, Yuyang Yin, Hanwen Liang, Guixun Luo, Chen Fang, Jue Wang, Konstantinos N. Plataniotis, Xiaojie Jin, Yao Zhao, Yunchao Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 71&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The growing adoption of XR devices has fueled strong demand for high-quality stereo video, yet its production remains costly and artifact-prone. To address this challenge, we present StereoWorld, an end-to-end framework that repurposes a pretrained video generator for high-fidelity monocular-to-stereo video generation. Our framework jointly conditions the model on the monocular video input while explicitly supervising the generation with a geometry-aware regularization to ensure 3D structural fidelity. A spatio-temporal tiling scheme is further integrated to enable efficient, high-resolution synthesis. To enable large-scale training and evaluation, we curate a high-definition stereo video dataset containing over 11M frames aligned to natural human interpupillary distance (IPD). Extensive experiments demonstrate that StereoWorld substantially outperforms prior methods, generating stereo videos with superior visual fidelity and geometric consistency. The project webpage is available at https://ke-xing.github.io/StereoWorld/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09363</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 06:50:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLaDA2.0: Scaling Up Diffusion Language Models to 100B</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15745</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15745.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tiwei Bie, Maosong Cao, Kun Chen, Lun Du, Mingliang Gong, Zhuochen Gong, Yanmei Gu, Jiaqi Hu, Zenan Huang, Zhenzhong Lan, Chengxi Li, Chongxuan Li, Jianguo Li, Zehuan Li, Huabin Liu, Ling Liu, Guoshan Lu, Xiaocheng Lu, Yuxin Ma, Jianfeng Tan, Lanning Wei, Ji-Rong Wen, Yipeng Xing, Xiaolu Zhang, Junbo Zhao, Da Zheng, Jun Zhou, Junlin Zhou, Zhanchao Zhou, Liwang Zhu, Yihong Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 77&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents LLaDA2.0 -- a tuple of discrete diffusion large language models (dLLM) scaling up to 100B total parameters through systematic conversion from auto-regressive (AR) models -- establishing a new paradigm for frontier-scale deployment. Instead of costly training from scratch, LLaDA2.0 upholds knowledge inheritance, progressive adaption and efficiency-aware design principle, and seamless converts a pre-trained AR model into dLLM with a novel 3-phase block-level WSD based training scheme: progressive increasing block-size in block diffusion (warm-up), large-scale full-sequence diffusion (stable) and reverting back to compact-size block diffusion (decay). Along with post-training alignment with SFT and DPO, we obtain LLaDA2.0-mini (16B) and LLaDA2.0-flash (100B), two instruction-tuned Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) variants optimized for practical deployment. By preserving the advantages of parallel decoding, these models deliver superior performance and efficiency at the frontier scale. Both models were open-sourced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15745</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 09:26:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-pro 2.0: An Efficient Russian Hybrid-Reasoning Model and Playground</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10430</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10430.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dmitrii Stoianov, Danil Taranets, Olga Tsymboi, Ramil Latypov, Almaz Dautov, Vladislav Kruglikov, Nikita Surkov, German Abramov, Pavel Gein, Dmitry Abulkhanov, Mikhail Gashkov, Viktor Zelenkovskiy, Artem Batalov, Aleksandr Medvedev, Anatolii Potapov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 113&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce T-pro 2.0, an open-weight Russian LLM for hybrid reasoning and efficient inference. The model supports direct answering and reasoning-trace generation, using a Cyrillic-dense tokenizer and an adapted EAGLE speculative-decoding pipeline to reduce latency. To enable reproducible and extensible research, we release the model weights, the T-Wix 500k instruction corpus, the T-Math reasoning benchmark, and the EAGLE weights on Hugging Face. These resources allow users to study Russian-language reasoning and to extend or adapt both the model and the inference pipeline. A public web demo exposes reasoning and non-reasoning modes and illustrates the speedups achieved by our inference stack across domains. T-pro 2.0 thus serves as an accessible open system for building and evaluating efficient, practical Russian LLM applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10430</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 08:40:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-horizon Reasoning Agent for Olympiad-Level Mathematical Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10739</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10739.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Songyang Gao, Yuzhe Gu, Zijian Wu, Lingkai Kong, Wenwei Zhang, Zhongrui Cai, Fan Zheng, Tianyou Ma, Junhao Shen, Haiteng Zhao, Duanyang Zhang, Huilun Zhang, Kuikun Liu, Chengqi Lyu, Yanhui Duan, Chiyu Chen, Ningsheng Ma, Jianfei Gao, Han Lyu, Dahua Lin, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have achieved significant progress in solving complex reasoning tasks by Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR). This advancement is also inseparable from the oversight automated by reliable verifiers. However, current outcome-based verifiers (OVs) are unable to inspect the unreliable intermediate steps in the long reasoning chains of thought (CoTs). Meanwhile, current process-based verifiers (PVs) have difficulties in reliably detecting errors in the complex long CoTs, limited by the scarcity of high-quality annotations due to the prohibitive costs of human annotations. Therefore, we propose the Outcome-based Process Verifier (OPV), which verifies the rationale process of summarized outcomes from long CoTs to achieve both accurate and efficient verification and enable large-scale annotation. To empower the proposed verifier, we adopt an iterative active learning framework with expert annotations to progressively improve the verification capability of OPV with fewer annotation costs. Specifically, in each iteration, the most uncertain cases of the current best OPV are annotated and then subsequently used to train a new OPV through Rejection Fine-Tuning (RFT) and RLVR for the next round. Extensive experiments demonstrate OPV's superior performance and broad applicability. It achieves new state-of-the-art results on our held-out \thisbench, outperforming much larger open-source models such as Qwen3-Max-Preview with an F1 score of 83.1 compared to 76.3. Furthermore, OPV effectively detects false positives within synthetic dataset, closely align with expert assessment. When collaborating with policy models, OPV consistently yields performance gains, e.g., raising the accuracy of DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-32B from 55.2\% to 73.3\% on AIME2025 as the compute budget scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10739</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 15:26:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are We Ready for RL in Text-to-3D Generation? A Progressive Investigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10949</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10949.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiwen Tang, Zoey Guo, Kaixin Zhu, Ray Zhang, Qizhi Chen, Dongzhi Jiang, Junli Liu, Bohan Zeng, Haoming Song, Delin Qu, Tianyi Bai, Dan Xu, Wentao Zhang, Bin Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL), earlier proven to be effective in large language and multi-modal models, has been successfully extended to enhance 2D image generation recently. However, applying RL to 3D generation remains largely unexplored due to the higher spatial complexity of 3D objects, which require globally consistent geometry and fine-grained local textures. This makes 3D generation significantly sensitive to reward designs and RL algorithms. To address these challenges, we conduct the first systematic study of RL for text-to-3D autoregressive generation across several dimensions. (1) Reward designs: We evaluate reward dimensions and model choices, showing that alignment with human preference is crucial, and that general multi-modal models provide robust signal for 3D attributes. (2) RL algorithms: We study GRPO variants, highlighting the effectiveness of token-level optimization, and further investigate the scaling of training data and iterations. (3) Text-to-3D Benchmarks: Since existing benchmarks fail to measure implicit reasoning abilities in 3D generation models, we introduce MME-3DR. (4) Advanced RL paradigms: Motivated by the natural hierarchy of 3D generation, we propose Hi-GRPO, which optimizes the global-to-local hierarchical 3D generation through dedicated reward ensembles. Based on these insights, we develop AR3D-R1, the first RL-enhanced text-to-3D model, expert from coarse shape to texture refinement. We hope this study provides insights into RL-driven reasoning for 3D generation. Code is released at https://github.com/Ivan-Tang-3D/3DGen-R1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10949</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DentalGPT: Incentivizing Multimodal Complex Reasoning in Dentistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11558</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11558.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenyang Cai, Jiaming Zhang, Junjie Zhao, Ziyi Zeng, Yanchao Li, Jingyi Liang, Junying Chen, Yunjin Yang, Jiajun You, Shuzhi Deng, Tongfei Wang, Wanting Chen, Chunxiu Hao, Ruiqi Xie, Zhenwei Wen, Xiangyi Feng, Zou Ting, Jin Zou Lin, Jianquan Li, Guangjun Yu, Liangyi Chen, Junwen Wang, Shan Jiang, Benyou Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reliable interpretation of multimodal data in dentistry is essential for automated oral healthcare, yet current multimodal large language models (MLLMs) struggle to capture fine-grained dental visual details and lack sufficient reasoning ability for precise diagnosis. To address these limitations, we present DentalGPT, a specialized dental MLLM developed through high-quality domain knowledge injection and reinforcement learning. Specifically, the largest annotated multimodal dataset for dentistry to date was constructed by aggregating over 120k dental images paired with detailed descriptions that highlight diagnostically relevant visual features, making it the multimodal dataset with the most extensive collection of dental images to date. Training on this dataset significantly enhances the MLLM's visual understanding of dental conditions, while the subsequent reinforcement learning stage further strengthens its capability for multimodal complex reasoning. Comprehensive evaluations on intraoral and panoramic benchmarks, along with dental subsets of medical VQA benchmarks, show that DentalGPT achieves superior performance in disease classification and dental VQA tasks, outperforming many state-of-the-art MLLMs despite having only 7B parameters. These results demonstrate that high-quality dental data combined with staged adaptation provides an effective pathway for building capable and domain-specialized dental MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11558</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 13:42:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SVG-T2I: Scaling Up Text-to-Image Latent Diffusion Model Without Variational Autoencoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11749</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11749.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minglei Shi, Haolin Wang, Borui Zhang, Wenzhao Zheng, Bohan Zeng, Ziyang Yuan, Xiaoshi Wu, Yuanxing Zhang, Huan Yang, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Kun Gai, Jie Zhou, Jiwen Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual generation grounded in Visual Foundation Model (VFM) representations offers a highly promising unified pathway for integrating visual understanding, perception, and generation. Despite this potential, training large-scale text-to-image diffusion models entirely within the VFM representation space remains largely unexplored. To bridge this gap, we scale the SVG (Self-supervised representations for Visual Generation) framework, proposing SVG-T2I to support high-quality text-to-image synthesis directly in the VFM feature domain. By leveraging a standard text-to-image diffusion pipeline, SVG-T2I achieves competitive performance, reaching 0.75 on GenEval and 85.78 on DPG-Bench. This performance validates the intrinsic representational power of VFMs for generative tasks. We fully open-source the project, including the autoencoder and generation model, together with their training, inference, evaluation pipelines, and pre-trained weights, to facilitate further research in representation-driven visual generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11749</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 17:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-Free Linear Attention is a Free Lunch: Exact Solution from Continuous-Time Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12602</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12602.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingdi Lei, Di Zhang, Soujanya Poria&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Linear-time attention and State Space Models (SSMs) promise to solve the quadratic cost bottleneck in long-context language models employing softmax attention. We introduce Error-Free Linear Attention (EFLA), a numerically stable, fully parallelism and generalized formulation of the delta rule. Specifically, we formulate the online learning update as a continuous-time dynamical system and prove that its exact solution is not only attainable but also computable in linear time with full parallelism. By leveraging the rank-1 structure of the dynamics matrix, we directly derive the exact closed-form solution effectively corresponding to the infinite-order Runge-Kutta method. This attention mechanism is theoretically free from error accumulation, perfectly capturing the continuous dynamics while preserving the linear-time complexity. Through an extensive suite of experiments, we show that EFLA enables robust performance in noisy environments, achieving lower language modeling perplexity and superior downstream benchmark performance than DeltaNet without introducing additional parameters. Our work provides a new theoretical foundation for building high-fidelity, scalable linear-time attention models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12602</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 08:51:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scone: Bridging Composition and Distinction in Subject-Driven Image Generation via Unified Understanding-Generation Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12675</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12675.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuran Wang, Bohan Zeng, Chengzhuo Tong, Wenxuan Liu, Yang Shi, Xiaochen Ma, Hao Liang, Yuanxing Zhang, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Subject-driven image generation has advanced from single- to multi-subject composition, while neglecting distinction, the ability to identify and generate the correct subject when inputs contain multiple candidates. This limitation restricts effectiveness in complex, realistic visual settings. We propose Scone, a unified understanding-generation method that integrates composition and distinction. Scone enables the understanding expert to act as a semantic bridge, conveying semantic information and guiding the generation expert to preserve subject identity while minimizing interference. A two-stage training scheme first learns composition, then enhances distinction through semantic alignment and attention-based masking. We also introduce SconeEval, a benchmark for evaluating both composition and distinction across diverse scenarios. Experiments demonstrate that Scone outperforms existing open-source models in composition and distinction tasks on two benchmarks. Our model, benchmark, and training data are available at: https://github.com/Ryann-Ran/Scone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12675</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 12:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NL2Repo-Bench: Towards Long-Horizon Repository Generation Evaluation of Coding Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12730</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12730.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingzhe Ding, Shengda Long, Changxin Pu, Huan Zhou, Hongwan Gao, Xiang Gao, Chao He, Yue Hou, Fei Hu, Zhaojian Li, Weiran Shi, Zaiyuan Wang, Daoguang Zan, Chenchen Zhang, Xiaoxu Zhang, Qizhi Chen, Xianfu Cheng, Bo Deng, Qingshui Gu, Kai Hua, Juntao Lin, Pai Liu, Mingchen Li, Xuanguang Pan, Zifan Peng, Yujia Qin, Yong Shan, Zhewen Tan, Weihao Xie, Zihan Wang, Yishuo Yuan, Jiayu Zhang, Enduo Zhao, Yunfei Zhao, He Zhu, Chenyang Zou, Ming Ding, Jianpeng Jiao, Jiaheng Liu, Minghao Liu, Qian Liu, Chongyao Tao, Jian Yang, Tong Yang, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Xinjie Chen, Wenhao Huang, Ge Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in coding agents suggest rapid progress toward autonomous software development, yet existing benchmarks fail to rigorously evaluate the long-horizon capabilities required to build complete software systems. Most prior evaluations focus on localized code generation, scaffolded completion, or short-term repair tasks, leaving open the question of whether agents can sustain coherent reasoning, planning, and execution over the extended horizons demanded by real-world repository construction. To address this gap, we present NL2Repo Bench, a benchmark explicitly designed to evaluate the long-horizon repository generation ability of coding agents. Given only a single natural-language requirements document and an empty workspace, agents must autonomously design the architecture, manage dependencies, implement multi-module logic, and produce a fully installable Python library. Our experiments across state-of-the-art open- and closed-source models reveal that long-horizon repository generation remains largely unsolved: even the strongest agents achieve below 40% average test pass rates and rarely complete an entire repository correctly. Detailed analysis uncovers fundamental long-horizon failure modes, including premature termination, loss of global coherence, fragile cross-file dependencies, and inadequate planning over hundreds of interaction steps. NL2Repo Bench establishes a rigorous, verifiable testbed for measuring sustained agentic competence and highlights long-horizon reasoning as a central bottleneck for the next generation of autonomous coding agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12730</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 15:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QwenLong-L1.5: Post-Training Recipe for Long-Context Reasoning and Memory Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12967</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12967.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weizhou Shen, Ziyi Yang, Chenliang Li, Zhiyuan Lu, Miao Peng, Huashan Sun, Yingcheng Shi, Shengyi Liao, Shaopeng Lai, Bo Zhang, Dayiheng Liu, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 103&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce QwenLong-L1.5, a model that achieves superior long-context reasoning capabilities through systematic post-training innovations. The key technical breakthroughs of QwenLong-L1.5 are as follows: (1) Long-Context Data Synthesis Pipeline: We develop a systematic synthesis framework that generates challenging reasoning tasks requiring multi-hop grounding over globally distributed evidence. By deconstructing documents into atomic facts and their underlying relationships, and then programmatically composing verifiable reasoning questions, our approach creates high-quality training data at scale, moving substantially beyond simple retrieval tasks to enable genuine long-range reasoning capabilities. (2) Stabilized Reinforcement Learning for Long-Context Training: To overcome the critical instability in long-context RL, we introduce task-balanced sampling with task-specific advantage estimation to mitigate reward bias, and propose Adaptive Entropy-Controlled Policy Optimization (AEPO) that dynamically regulates exploration-exploitation trade-offs. (3) Memory-Augmented Architecture for Ultra-Long Contexts: Recognizing that even extended context windows cannot accommodate arbitrarily long sequences, we develop a memory management framework with multi-stage fusion RL training that seamlessly integrates single-pass reasoning with iterative memory-based processing for tasks exceeding 4M tokens. Based on Qwen3-30B-A3B-Thinking, QwenLong-L1.5 achieves performance comparable to GPT-5 and Gemini-2.5-Pro on long-context reasoning benchmarks, surpassing its baseline by 9.90 points on average. On ultra-long tasks (1M~4M tokens), QwenLong-L1.5's memory-agent framework yields a 9.48-point gain over the agent baseline. Additionally, the acquired long-context reasoning ability translates to enhanced performance in general domains like scientific reasoning, memory tool using, and extended dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12967</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 04:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video Reality Test: Can AI-Generated ASMR Videos fool VLMs and Humans?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13281</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13281.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Wang, Weijia Wu, Yi Zhan, Rui Zhao, Ming Hu, James Cheng, Wei Liu, Philip Torr, Kevin Qinghong Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in video generation have produced vivid content that are often indistinguishable from real videos, making AI-generated video detection an emerging societal challenge. Prior AIGC detection benchmarks mostly evaluate video without audio, target broad narrative domains, and focus on classification solely. Yet it remains unclear whether state-of-the-art video generation models can produce immersive, audio-paired videos that reliably deceive humans and VLMs. To this end, we introduce Video Reality Test, an ASMR-sourced video benchmark suite for testing perceptual realism under tight audio-visual coupling, featuring the following dimensions: (i) Immersive ASMR video-audio sources. Built on carefully curated real ASMR videos, the benchmark targets fine-grained action-object interactions with diversity across objects, actions, and backgrounds. (ii) Peer-Review evaluation. An adversarial creator-reviewer protocol where video generation models act as creators aiming to fool reviewers, while VLMs serve as reviewers seeking to identify fakeness. Our experimental findings show: The best creator Veo3.1-Fast even fools most VLMs: the strongest reviewer (Gemini 2.5-Pro) achieves only 56\% accuracy (random 50\%), far below that of human experts (81.25\%). Adding audio improves real-fake discrimination, yet superficial cues such as watermarks can still significantly mislead models. These findings delineate the current boundary of video generation realism and expose limitations of VLMs in perceptual fidelity and audio-visual consistency. Our code is available at https://github.com/video-reality-test/video-reality-test.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13281</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KlingAvatar 2.0 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13313</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13313.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kling Team, Jialu Chen, Yikang Ding, Zhixue Fang, Kun Gai, Yuan Gao, Kang He, Jingyun Hua, Boyuan Jiang, Mingming Lao, Xiaohan Li, Hui Liu, Jiwen Liu, Xiaoqiang Liu, Yuan Liu, Shun Lu, Yongsen Mao, Yingchao Shao, Huafeng Shi, Xiaoyu Shi, Peiqin Sun, Songlin Tang, Pengfei Wan, Chao Wang, Xuebo Wang, Haoxian Zhang, Yuanxing Zhang, Yan Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Avatar video generation models have achieved remarkable progress in recent years. However, prior work exhibits limited efficiency in generating long-duration high-resolution videos, suffering from temporal drifting, quality degradation, and weak prompt following as video length increases. To address these challenges, we propose KlingAvatar 2.0, a spatio-temporal cascade framework that performs upscaling in both spatial resolution and temporal dimension. The framework first generates low-resolution blueprint video keyframes that capture global semantics and motion, and then refines them into high-resolution, temporally coherent sub-clips using a first-last frame strategy, while retaining smooth temporal transitions in long-form videos. To enhance cross-modal instruction fusion and alignment in extended videos, we introduce a Co-Reasoning Director composed of three modality-specific large language model (LLM) experts. These experts reason about modality priorities and infer underlying user intent, converting inputs into detailed storylines through multi-turn dialogue. A Negative Director further refines negative prompts to improve instruction alignment. Building on these components, we extend the framework to support ID-specific multi-character control. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our model effectively addresses the challenges of efficient, multimodally aligned long-form high-resolution video generation, delivering enhanced visual clarity, realistic lip-teeth rendering with accurate lip synchronization, strong identity preservation, and coherent multimodal instruction following.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13313</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 13:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seedance 1.5 pro: A Native Audio-Visual Joint Generation Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13507</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13507.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Heyi Chen, Siyan Chen, Xin Chen, Yanfei Chen, Ying Chen, Zhuo Chen, Feng Cheng, Tianheng Cheng, Xinqi Cheng, Xuyan Chi, Jian Cong, Jing Cui, Qinpeng Cui, Qide Dong, Junliang Fan, Jing Fang, Zetao Fang, Chengjian Feng, Han Feng, Mingyuan Gao, Yu Gao, Dong Guo, Qiushan Guo, Boyang Hao, Qingkai Hao, Bibo He, Qian He, Tuyen Hoang, Ruoqing Hu, Xi Hu, Weilin Huang, Zhaoyang Huang, Zhongyi Huang, Donglei Ji, Siqi Jiang, Wei Jiang, Yunpu Jiang, Zhuo Jiang, Ashley Kim, Jianan Kong, Zhichao Lai, Shanshan Lao, Yichong Leng, Ai Li, Feiya Li, Gen Li, Huixia Li, JiaShi Li, Liang Li, Ming Li, Shanshan Li, Tao Li, Xian Li, Xiaojie Li, Xiaoyang Li, Xingxing Li, Yameng Li, Yifu Li, Yiying Li, Chao Liang, Han Liang, Jianzhong Liang, Ying Liang, Zhiqiang Liang, Wang Liao, Yalin Liao, Heng Lin, Kengyu Lin, Shanchuan Lin, Xi Lin, Zhijie Lin, Feng Ling, Fangfang Liu, Gaohong Liu, Jiawei Liu, Jie Liu, Jihao Liu, Shouda Liu, Shu Liu, Sichao Liu, Songwei Liu, Xin Liu, Xue Liu, Yibo Liu, Zikun Liu, Zuxi Liu, Junlin Lyu, Lecheng Lyu, Qian Lyu, Han Mu, Xiaonan Nie, Jingzhe Ning, Xitong Pan, Yanghua Peng, Lianke Qin, Xueqiong Qu, Yuxi Ren, Kai Shen, Guang Shi, Lei Shi, Yan Song, Yinglong Song, Fan Sun, Li Sun, Renfei Sun, Yan Sun, Zeyu Sun, Wenjing Tang, Yaxue Tang, Zirui Tao, Feng Wang, Furui Wang, Jinran Wang, Junkai Wang, Ke Wang, Kexin Wang, Qingyi Wang, Rui Wang, Sen Wang, Shuai Wang, Tingru Wang, Weichen Wang, Xin Wang, Yanhui Wang, Yue Wang, Yuping Wang, Yuxuan Wang, Ziyu Wang, Guoqiang Wei, Wanru Wei, Di Wu, Guohong Wu, Hanjie Wu, Jian Wu, Jie Wu, Ruolan Wu, Xinglong Wu, Yonghui Wu, Ruiqi Xia, Liang Xiang, Fei Xiao, XueFeng Xiao, Pan Xie, Shuangyi Xie, Shuang Xu, Jinlan Xue, Shen Yan, Bangbang Yang, Ceyuan Yang, Jiaqi Yang, Runkai Yang, Tao Yang, Yang Yang, Yihang Yang, ZhiXian Yang, Ziyan Yang, Songting Yao, Yifan Yao, Zilyu Ye, Bowen Yu, Jian Yu, Chujie Yuan, Linxiao Yuan, Sichun Zeng, Weihong Zeng, Xuejiao Zeng, Yan Zeng, Chuntao Zhang, Heng Zhang, Jingjie Zhang, Kuo Zhang, Liang Zhang, Liying Zhang, Manlin Zhang, Ting Zhang, Weida Zhang, Xiaohe Zhang, Xinyan Zhang, Yan Zhang, Yuan Zhang, Zixiang Zhang, Fengxuan Zhao, Huating Zhao, Yang Zhao, Hao Zheng, Jianbin Zheng, Xiaozheng Zheng, Yangyang Zheng, Yijie Zheng, Jiexin Zhou, Jiahui Zhu, Kuan Zhu, Shenhan Zhu, Wenjia Zhu, Benhui Zou, Feilong Zuo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent strides in video generation have paved the way for unified audio-visual generation. In this work, we present Seedance 1.5 pro, a foundational model engineered specifically for native, joint audio-video generation. Leveraging a dual-branch Diffusion Transformer architecture, the model integrates a cross-modal joint module with a specialized multi-stage data pipeline, achieving exceptional audio-visual synchronization and superior generation quality. To ensure practical utility, we implement meticulous post-training optimizations, including Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) on high-quality datasets and Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback (RLHF) with multi-dimensional reward models. Furthermore, we introduce an acceleration framework that boosts inference speed by over 10X. Seedance 1.5 pro distinguishes itself through precise multilingual and dialect lip-syncing, dynamic cinematic camera control, and enhanced narrative coherence, positioning it as a robust engine for professional-grade content creation. Seedance 1.5 pro is now accessible on Volcano Engine at https://console.volcengine.com/ark/region:ark+cn-beijing/experience/vision?type=GenVideo.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13507</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 16:36:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memory in the Age of AI Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13564</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13564.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuyang Hu, Shichun Liu, Yanwei Yue, Guibin Zhang, Boyang Liu, Fangyi Zhu, Jiahang Lin, Honglin Guo, Shihan Dou, Zhiheng Xi, Senjie Jin, Jiejun Tan, Yanbin Yin, Jiongnan Liu, Zeyu Zhang, Zhongxiang Sun, Yutao Zhu, Hao Sun, Boci Peng, Zhenrong Cheng, Xuanbo Fan, Jiaxin Guo, Xinlei Yu, Zhenhong Zhou, Zewen Hu, Jiahao Huo, Junhao Wang, Yuwei Niu, Yu Wang, Zhenfei Yin, Xiaobin Hu, Yue Liao, Qiankun Li, Kun Wang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Yixin Liu, Dawei Cheng, Qi Zhang, Tao Gui, Shirui Pan, Yan Zhang, Philip Torr, Zhicheng Dou, Ji-Rong Wen, Xuanjing Huang, Yu-Gang Jiang, Shuicheng Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 120&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Memory has emerged, and will continue to remain, a core capability of foundation model-based agents. As research on agent memory rapidly expands and attracts unprecedented attention, the field has also become increasingly fragmented. Existing works that fall under the umbrella of agent memory often differ substantially in their motivations, implementations, and evaluation protocols, while the proliferation of loosely defined memory terminologies has further obscured conceptual clarity. Traditional taxonomies such as long/short-term memory have proven insufficient to capture the diversity of contemporary agent memory systems. This work aims to provide an up-to-date landscape of current agent memory research. We begin by clearly delineating the scope of agent memory and distinguishing it from related concepts such as LLM memory, retrieval augmented generation (RAG), and context engineering. We then examine agent memory through the unified lenses of forms, functions, and dynamics. From the perspective of forms, we identify three dominant realizations of agent memory, namely token-level, parametric, and latent memory. From the perspective of functions, we propose a finer-grained taxonomy that distinguishes factual, experiential, and working memory. From the perspective of dynamics, we analyze how memory is formed, evolved, and retrieved over time. To support practical development, we compile a comprehensive summary of memory benchmarks and open-source frameworks. Beyond consolidation, we articulate a forward-looking perspective on emerging research frontiers, including memory automation, reinforcement learning integration, multimodal memory, multi-agent memory, and trustworthiness issues. We hope this survey serves not only as a reference for existing work, but also as a conceptual foundation for rethinking memory as a first-class primitive in the design of future agentic intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13564</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 17:22:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReFusion: A Diffusion Large Language Model with Parallel Autoregressive Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13586</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13586.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jia-Nan Li, Jian Guan, Wei Wu, Chongxuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 87&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive models (ARMs) are hindered by slow sequential inference. While masked diffusion models (MDMs) offer a parallel alternative, they suffer from critical drawbacks: high computational overhead from precluding Key-Value (KV) caching, and incoherent generation arising from learning dependencies over an intractable space of token combinations. To address these limitations, we introduce ReFusion, a novel masked diffusion model that achieves superior performance and efficiency by elevating parallel decoding from the token level to a higher slot level, where each slot is a fixed-length, contiguous sub-sequence. This is achieved through an iterative ``plan-and-infill'' decoding process: a diffusion-based planning step first identifies a set of weakly dependent slots, and an autoregressive infilling step then decodes these selected slots in parallel. The slot-based design simultaneously unlocks full KV cache reuse with a unified causal framework and reduces the learning complexity from the token combination space to a manageable slot-level permutation space. Extensive experiments on seven diverse benchmarks show that ReFusion not only overwhelmingly surpasses prior MDMs with 34% performance gains and an over 18times speedup on average, but also bridges the performance gap to strong ARMs while maintaining a 2.33times average speedup.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13586</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 17:41:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongVie 2: Multimodal Controllable Ultra-Long Video World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13604</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13604.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianxiong Gao, Zhaoxi Chen, Xian Liu, Junhao Zhuang, Chengming Xu, Jianfeng Feng, Yu Qiao, Yanwei Fu, Chenyang Si, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Building video world models upon pretrained video generation systems represents an important yet challenging step toward general spatiotemporal intelligence. A world model should possess three essential properties: controllability, long-term visual quality, and temporal consistency. To this end, we take a progressive approach-first enhancing controllability and then extending toward long-term, high-quality generation. We present LongVie 2, an end-to-end autoregressive framework trained in three stages: (1) Multi-modal guidance, which integrates dense and sparse control signals to provide implicit world-level supervision and improve controllability; (2) Degradation-aware training on the input frame, bridging the gap between training and long-term inference to maintain high visual quality; and (3) History-context guidance, which aligns contextual information across adjacent clips to ensure temporal consistency. We further introduce LongVGenBench, a comprehensive benchmark comprising 100 high-resolution one-minute videos covering diverse real-world and synthetic environments. Extensive experiments demonstrate that LongVie 2 achieves state-of-the-art performance in long-range controllability, temporal coherence, and visual fidelity, and supports continuous video generation lasting up to five minutes, marking a significant step toward unified video world modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13604</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboTracer: Mastering Spatial Trace with Reasoning in Vision-Language Models for Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13660</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13660.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Enshen Zhou, Cheng Chi, Yibo Li, Jingkun An, Jiayuan Zhang, Shanyu Rong, Yi Han, Yuheng Ji, Mengzhen Liu, Pengwei Wang, Zhongyuan Wang, Lu Sheng, Shanghang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatial tracing, as a fundamental embodied interaction ability for robots, is inherently challenging as it requires multi-step metric-grounded reasoning compounded with complex spatial referring and real-world metric measurement. However, existing methods struggle with this compositional task. To this end, we propose RoboTracer, a 3D-aware VLM that first achieves both 3D spatial referring and measuring via a universal spatial encoder and a regression-supervised decoder to enhance scale awareness during supervised fine-tuning (SFT). Moreover, RoboTracer advances multi-step metric-grounded reasoning via reinforcement fine-tuning (RFT) with metric-sensitive process rewards, supervising key intermediate perceptual cues to accurately generate spatial traces. To support SFT and RFT training, we introduce TraceSpatial, a large-scale dataset of 30M QA pairs, spanning outdoor/indoor/tabletop scenes and supporting complex reasoning processes (up to 9 steps). We further present TraceSpatial-Bench, a challenging benchmark filling the gap to evaluate spatial tracing. Experimental results show that RoboTracer surpasses baselines in spatial understanding, measuring, and referring, with an average success rate of 79.1%, and also achieves SOTA performance on TraceSpatial-Bench by a large margin, exceeding Gemini-2.5-Pro by 36% accuracy. Notably, RoboTracer can be integrated with various control policies to execute long-horizon, dynamic tasks across diverse robots (UR5, G1 humanoid) in cluttered real-world scenes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13660</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:52:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Scalable Pre-training of Visual Tokenizers for Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13687</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13687.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingfeng Yao, Yuda Song, Yucong Zhou, Xinggang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 98&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The quality of the latent space in visual tokenizers (e.g., VAEs) is crucial for modern generative models. However, the standard reconstruction-based training paradigm produces a latent space that is biased towards low-level information, leading to a foundation flaw: better pixel-level accuracy does not lead to higher-quality generation. This implies that pouring extensive compute into visual tokenizer pre-training translates poorly to improved performance in generation. We identify this as the ``pre-training scaling problem`` and suggest a necessary shift: to be effective for generation, a latent space must concisely represent high-level semantics. We present VTP, a unified visual tokenizer pre-training framework, pioneering the joint optimization of image-text contrastive, self-supervised, and reconstruction losses. Our large-scale study reveals two principal findings: (1) understanding is a key driver of generation, and (2) much better scaling properties, where generative performance scales effectively with compute, parameters, and data allocated to the pretraining of the visual tokenizer. After large-scale pre-training, our tokenizer delivers a competitive profile (78.2 zero-shot accuracy and 0.36 rFID on ImageNet) and 4.1 times faster convergence on generation compared to advanced distillation methods. More importantly, it scales effectively: without modifying standard DiT training specs, solely investing more FLOPS in pretraining VTP achieves 65.8\% FID improvement in downstream generation, while conventional autoencoder stagnates very early at 1/10 FLOPS. Our pre-trained models are available at https://github.com/MiniMax-AI/VTP.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13687</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenDataArena: A Fair and Open Arena for Benchmarking Post-Training Dataset Value</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14051</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14051.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengzhang Cai, Xin Gao, Yu Li, Honglin Lin, Zheng Liu, Zhuoshi Pan, Qizhi Pei, Xiaoran Shang, Mengyuan Sun, Zinan Tang, Xiaoyang Wang, Zhanping Zhong, Yun Zhu, Dahua Lin, Conghui He, Lijun Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid evolution of Large Language Models (LLMs) is predicated on the quality and diversity of post-training datasets. However, a critical dichotomy persists: while models are rigorously benchmarked, the data fueling them remains a black box--characterized by opaque composition, uncertain provenance, and a lack of systematic evaluation. This opacity hinders reproducibility and obscures the causal link between data characteristics and model behaviors. To bridge this gap, we introduce OpenDataArena (ODA), a holistic and open platform designed to benchmark the intrinsic value of post-training data. ODA establishes a comprehensive ecosystem comprising four key pillars: (i) a unified training-evaluation pipeline that ensures fair, open comparisons across diverse models (e.g., Llama, Qwen) and domains; (ii) a multi-dimensional scoring framework that profiles data quality along tens of distinct axes; (iii) an interactive data lineage explorer to visualize dataset genealogy and dissect component sources; and (iv) a fully open-source toolkit for training, evaluation, and scoring to foster data research. Extensive experiments on ODA--covering over 120 training datasets across multiple domains on 22 benchmarks, validated by more than 600 training runs and 40 million processed data points--reveal non-trivial insights. Our analysis uncovers the inherent trade-offs between data complexity and task performance, identifies redundancy in popular benchmarks through lineage tracing, and maps the genealogical relationships across datasets. We release all results, tools, and configurations to democratize access to high-quality data evaluation. Rather than merely expanding a leaderboard, ODA envisions a shift from trial-and-error data curation to a principled science of Data-Centric AI, paving the way for rigorous studies on data mixing laws and the strategic composition of foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14051</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 03:33:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HyperVL: An Efficient and Dynamic Multimodal Large Language Model for Edge Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14052</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14052.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; HyperAI Team, Yuchen Liu, Kaiyang Han, Zhiqiang Xia, Yuhang Dong, Chen Song, Kangyu Tang, Jiaming Xu, Xiushi Feng, WenXuan Yu, Li Peng, Mingyang Wang, Kai Wang, Changpeng Yang, Yang Li, Haoyu Lu, Hao Wang, Bingna Xu, Guangyao Liu, Long Huang, Kaibin Guo, Jinyang Wu, Dan Wu, Hongzhen Wang, Peng Zhou, Shuai Nie, Shande Wang, Runyu Shi, Ying Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current multimodal large lanauge models possess strong perceptual and reasoning capabilities, however high computational and memory requirements make them difficult to deploy directly on on-device environments. While small-parameter models are progressively endowed with strong general capabilities, standard Vision Transformer (ViT) encoders remain a critical bottleneck, suffering from excessive latency and memory consumption when processing high-resolution inputs.To address these challenges, we introduce HyperVL, an efficient multimodal large language model tailored for on-device inference. HyperVL adopts an image-tiling strategy to cap peak memory usage and incorporates two novel techniques: (1) a Visual Resolution Compressor (VRC) that adaptively predicts optimal encoding resolutions to eliminate redundant computation, and (2) Dual Consistency Learning (DCL), which aligns multi-scale ViT encoders within a unified framework, enabling dynamic switching between visual branches under a shared LLM. Extensive experiments demonstrate that HyperVL achieves state-of-the-art performance among models of comparable size across multiple benchmarks. Furthermore, it significantly significantly reduces latency and power consumption on real mobile devices, demonstrating its practicality for on-device multimodal inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14052</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 03:36:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WorldPlay: Towards Long-Term Geometric Consistency for Real-Time Interactive World Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14614</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14614.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenqiang Sun, Haiyu Zhang, Haoyuan Wang, Junta Wu, Zehan Wang, Zhenwei Wang, Yunhong Wang, Jun Zhang, Tengfei Wang, Chunchao Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 66&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents WorldPlay, a streaming video diffusion model that enables real-time, interactive world modeling with long-term geometric consistency, resolving the trade-off between speed and memory that limits current methods. WorldPlay draws power from three key innovations. 1) We use a Dual Action Representation to enable robust action control in response to the user's keyboard and mouse inputs. 2) To enforce long-term consistency, our Reconstituted Context Memory dynamically rebuilds context from past frames and uses temporal reframing to keep geometrically important but long-past frames accessible, effectively alleviating memory attenuation. 3) We also propose Context Forcing, a novel distillation method designed for memory-aware model. Aligning memory context between the teacher and student preserves the student's capacity to use long-range information, enabling real-time speeds while preventing error drift. Taken together, WorldPlay generates long-horizon streaming 720p video at 24 FPS with superior consistency, comparing favorably with existing techniques and showing strong generalization across diverse scenes. Project page and online demo can be found: https://3d-models.hunyuan.tencent.com/world/ and https://3d.hunyuan.tencent.com/sceneTo3D.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14614</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 17:22:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast and Accurate Causal Parallel Decoding using Jacobi Forcing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14681</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14681.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lanxiang Hu, Siqi Kou, Yichao Fu, Samyam Rajbhandari, Tajana Rosing, Yuxiong He, Zhijie Deng, Hao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-token generation has emerged as a promising paradigm for accelerating transformer-based large model inference. Recent efforts primarily explore diffusion Large Language Models (dLLMs) for parallel decoding to reduce inference latency. To achieve AR-level generation quality, many techniques adapt AR models into dLLMs to enable parallel decoding. However, they suffer from limited speedup compared to AR models due to a pretrain-to-posttrain mismatch. Specifically, the masked data distribution in post-training deviates significantly from the real-world data distribution seen during pretraining, and dLLMs rely on bidirectional attention, which conflicts with the causal prior learned during pretraining and hinders the integration of exact KV cache reuse. To address this, we introduce Jacobi Forcing, a progressive distillation paradigm where models are trained on their own generated parallel decoding trajectories, smoothly shifting AR models into efficient parallel decoders while preserving their pretrained causal inference property. The models trained under this paradigm, Jacobi Forcing Model, achieves 3.8x wall-clock speedup on coding and math benchmarks with minimal loss in performance. Based on Jacobi Forcing Models' trajectory characteristics, we introduce multi-block decoding with rejection recycling, which enables up to 4.5x higher token acceptance count per iteration and nearly 4.0x wall-clock speedup, effectively trading additional compute for lower inference latency. Our code is available at https://github.com/hao-ai-lab/JacobiForcing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14681</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:45:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMGR: Multi-Modal Generative Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14691</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14691.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zefan Cai, Haoyi Qiu, Tianyi Ma, Haozhe Zhao, Gengze Zhou, Kung-Hsiang Huang, Parisa Kordjamshidi, Minjia Zhang, Xiao Wen, Jiuxiang Gu, Nanyun Peng, Junjie Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 114&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video foundation models generate visually realistic and temporally coherent content, but their reliability as world simulators depends on whether they capture physical, logical, and spatial constraints. Existing metrics such as Frechet Video Distance (FVD) emphasize perceptual quality and overlook reasoning failures, including violations of causality, physics, and global consistency. We introduce MMGR (Multi-Modal Generative Reasoning Evaluation and Benchmark), a principled evaluation framework based on five reasoning abilities: Physical, Logical, 3D Spatial, 2D Spatial, and Temporal. MMGR evaluates generative reasoning across three domains: Abstract Reasoning (ARC-AGI, Sudoku), Embodied Navigation (real-world 3D navigation and localization), and Physical Commonsense (sports and compositional interactions). MMGR applies fine-grained metrics that require holistic correctness across both video and image generation. We benchmark leading video models (Veo-3, Sora-2, Wan-2.2) and image models (Nano-banana, Nano-banana Pro, GPT-4o-image, Qwen-image), revealing strong performance gaps across domains. Models show moderate success on Physical Commonsense tasks but perform poorly on Abstract Reasoning (below 10 percent accuracy on ARC-AGI) and struggle with long-horizon spatial planning in embodied settings. Our analysis highlights key limitations in current models, including overreliance on perceptual data, weak global state consistency, and objectives that reward visual plausibility over causal correctness. MMGR offers a unified diagnostic benchmark and a path toward reasoning-aware generative world models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14691</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Reasoning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14693</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14693.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zitian Gao, Lynx Chen, Yihao Xiao, He Xing, Ran Tao, Haoming Luo, Joey Zhou, Bryan Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal transformers (UTs) have been widely used for complex reasoning tasks such as ARC-AGI and Sudoku, yet the specific sources of their performance gains remain underexplored. In this work, we systematically analyze UTs variants and show that improvements on ARC-AGI primarily arise from the recurrent inductive bias and strong nonlinear components of Transformer, rather than from elaborate architectural designs. Motivated by this finding, we propose the Universal Reasoning Model (URM), which enhances the UT with short convolution and truncated backpropagation. Our approach substantially improves reasoning performance, achieving state-of-the-art 53.8% pass@1 on ARC-AGI 1 and 16.0% pass@1 on ARC-AGI 2. Our code is avaliable at https://github.com/zitian-gao/URM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14693</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DEER: Draft with Diffusion, Verify with Autoregressive Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15176</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15176.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zicong Cheng, Guo-Wei Yang, Jia Li, Zhijie Deng, Meng-Hao Guo, Shi-Min Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Efficiency, as a critical practical challenge for LLM-driven agentic and reasoning systems, is increasingly constrained by the inherent latency of autoregressive (AR) decoding. Speculative decoding mitigates this cost through a draft-verify scheme, yet existing approaches rely on AR draft models (a.k.a., drafters), which introduce two fundamental issues: (1) step-wise uncertainty accumulation leads to a progressive collapse of trust between the target model and the drafter, and (2) inherently sequential decoding of AR drafters. Together, these factors cause limited speedups. In this paper, we show that a diffusion large language model (dLLM) drafters can naturally overcome these issues through its fundamentally different probabilistic modeling and efficient parallel decoding strategy. Building on this insight, we introduce DEER, an efficient speculative decoding framework that drafts with diffusion and verifies with AR models. To enable high-quality drafting, DEER employs a two-stage training pipeline to align the dLLM-based drafters with the target AR model, and further adopts single-step decoding to generate long draft segments. Experiments show DEER reaches draft acceptance lengths of up to 32 tokens, far surpassing the 10 tokens achieved by EAGLE-3. Moreover, on HumanEval with Qwen3-30B-A3B, DEER attains a 5.54x speedup, while EAGLE-3 achieves only 2.41x. Code, model, demo, etc, will be available at https://czc726.github.io/DEER/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15176</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 08:19:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step-GUI Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15431</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15431.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haolong Yan, Jia Wang, Xin Huang, Yeqing Shen, Ziyang Meng, Zhimin Fan, Kaijun Tan, Jin Gao, Lieyu Shi, Mi Yang, Shiliang Yang, Zhirui Wang, Brian Li, Kang An, Chenyang Li, Lei Lei, Mengmeng Duan, Danxun Liang, Guodong Liu, Hang Cheng, Hao Wu, Jie Dong, Junhao Huang, Mei Chen, Renjie Yu, Shunshan Li, Xu Zhou, Yiting Dai, Yineng Deng, Yingdan Liang, Zelin Chen, Wen Sun, Chengxu Yan, Chunqin Xu, Dong Li, Fengqiong Xiao, Guanghao Fan, Guopeng Li, Guozhen Peng, Hongbing Li, Hang Li, Hongming Chen, Jingjing Xie, Jianyong Li, Jingyang Zhang, Jiaju Ren, Jiayu Yuan, Jianpeng Yin, Kai Cao, Liang Zhao, Liguo Tan, Liying Shi, Mengqiang Ren, Min Xu, Manjiao Liu, Mao Luo, Mingxin Wan, Na Wang, Nan Wu, Ning Wang, Peiyao Ma, Qingzhou Zhang, Qiao Wang, Qinlin Zeng, Qiong Gao, Qiongyao Li, Shangwu Zhong, Shuli Gao, Shaofan Liu, Shisi Gao, Shuang Luo, Xingbin Liu, Xiaojia Liu, Xiaojie Hou, Xin Liu, Xuanti Feng, Xuedan Cai, Xuan Wen, Xianwei Zhu, Xin Liang, Xin Liu, Xin Zhou, Yingxiu Zhao, Yukang Shi, Yunfang Xu, Yuqing Zeng, Yixun Zhang, Zejia Weng, Zhonghao Yan, Zhiguo Huang, Zhuoyu Wang, Zheng Ge, Jing Li, Yibo Zhu, Binxing Jiao, Xiangyu Zhang, Daxin Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 124&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal large language models unlock unprecedented opportunities for GUI automation. However, a fundamental challenge remains: how to efficiently acquire high-quality training data while maintaining annotation reliability? We introduce a self-evolving training pipeline powered by the Calibrated Step Reward System, which converts model-generated trajectories into reliable training signals through trajectory-level calibration, achieving &gt;90% annotation accuracy with 10-100x lower cost. Leveraging this pipeline, we introduce Step-GUI, a family of models (4B/8B) that achieves state-of-the-art GUI performance (8B: 80.2% AndroidWorld, 48.5% OSWorld, 62.6% ScreenShot-Pro) while maintaining robust general capabilities. As GUI agent capabilities improve, practical deployment demands standardized interfaces across heterogeneous devices while protecting user privacy. To this end, we propose GUI-MCP, the first Model Context Protocol for GUI automation with hierarchical architecture that combines low-level atomic operations and high-level task delegation to local specialist models, enabling high-privacy execution where sensitive data stays on-device. Finally, to assess whether agents can handle authentic everyday usage, we introduce AndroidDaily, a benchmark grounded in real-world mobile usage patterns with 3146 static actions and 235 end-to-end tasks across high-frequency daily scenarios (8B: static 89.91%, end-to-end 52.50%). Our work advances the development of practical GUI agents and demonstrates strong potential for real-world deployment in everyday digital interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15431</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 13:26:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qwen-Image-Layered: Towards Inherent Editability via Layer Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15603</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15603.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengming Yin, Zekai Zhang, Zecheng Tang, Kaiyuan Gao, Xiao Xu, Kun Yan, Jiahao Li, Yilei Chen, Yuxiang Chen, Heung-Yeung Shum, Lionel M. Ni, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin, Chenfei Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent visual generative models often struggle with consistency during image editing due to the entangled nature of raster images, where all visual content is fused into a single canvas. In contrast, professional design tools employ layered representations, allowing isolated edits while preserving consistency. Motivated by this, we propose Qwen-Image-Layered, an end-to-end diffusion model that decomposes a single RGB image into multiple semantically disentangled RGBA layers, enabling inherent editability, where each RGBA layer can be independently manipulated without affecting other content. To support variable-length decomposition, we introduce three key components: (1) an RGBA-VAE to unify the latent representations of RGB and RGBA images; (2) a VLD-MMDiT (Variable Layers Decomposition MMDiT) architecture capable of decomposing a variable number of image layers; and (3) a Multi-stage Training strategy to adapt a pretrained image generation model into a multilayer image decomposer. Furthermore, to address the scarcity of high-quality multilayer training images, we build a pipeline to extract and annotate multilayer images from Photoshop documents (PSD). Experiments demonstrate that our method significantly surpasses existing approaches in decomposition quality and establishes a new paradigm for consistent image editing. Our code and models are released on https://github.com/QwenLM/Qwen-Image-Layered{https://github.com/QwenLM/Qwen-Image-Layered}&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15603</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 17:12:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TurboDiffusion: Accelerating Video Diffusion Models by 100-200 Times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16093</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16093.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Kaiwen Zheng, Kai Jiang, Haoxu Wang, Ion Stoica, Joseph E. Gonzalez, Jianfei Chen, Jun Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce TurboDiffusion, a video generation acceleration framework that can speed up end-to-end diffusion generation by 100-200x while maintaining video quality. TurboDiffusion mainly relies on several components for acceleration: (1) Attention acceleration: TurboDiffusion uses low-bit SageAttention and trainable Sparse-Linear Attention (SLA) to speed up attention computation. (2) Step distillation: TurboDiffusion adopts rCM for efficient step distillation. (3) W8A8 quantization: TurboDiffusion quantizes model parameters and activations to 8 bits to accelerate linear layers and compress the model. In addition, TurboDiffusion incorporates several other engineering optimizations.   We conduct experiments on the Wan2.2-I2V-14B-720P, Wan2.1-T2V-1.3B-480P, Wan2.1-T2V-14B-720P, and Wan2.1-T2V-14B-480P models. Experimental results show that TurboDiffusion achieves 100-200x speedup for video generation even on a single RTX 5090 GPU, while maintaining comparable video quality. The GitHub repository, which includes model checkpoints and easy-to-use code, is available at https://github.com/thu-ml/TurboDiffusion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16093</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 02:21:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptation of Agentic AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16301</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16301.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengcheng Jiang, Jiacheng Lin, Zhiyi Shi, Zifeng Wang, Luxi He, Yichen Wu, Ming Zhong, Peiyang Song, Qizheng Zhang, Heng Wang, Xueqiang Xu, Hanwen Xu, Pengrui Han, Dylan Zhang, Jiashuo Sun, Chaoqi Yang, Kun Qian, Tian Wang, Changran Hu, Manling Li, Quanzheng Li, Hao Peng, Sheng Wang, Jingbo Shang, Chao Zhang, Jiaxuan You, Liyuan Liu, Pan Lu, Yu Zhang, Heng Ji, Yejin Choi, Dawn Song, Jimeng Sun, Jiawei Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 96&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Cutting-edge agentic AI systems are built on foundation models that can be adapted to plan, reason, and interact with external tools to perform increasingly complex and specialized tasks. As these systems grow in capability and scope, adaptation becomes a central mechanism for improving performance, reliability, and generalization. In this paper, we unify the rapidly expanding research landscape into a systematic framework that spans both agent adaptations and tool adaptations. We further decompose these into tool-execution-signaled and agent-output-signaled forms of agent adaptation, as well as agent-agnostic and agent-supervised forms of tool adaptation. We demonstrate that this framework helps clarify the design space of adaptation strategies in agentic AI, makes their trade-offs explicit, and provides practical guidance for selecting or switching among strategies during system design. We then review the representative approaches in each category, analyze their strengths and limitations, and highlight key open challenges and future opportunities. Overall, this paper aims to offer a conceptual foundation and practical roadmap for researchers and practitioners seeking to build more capable, efficient, and reliable agentic AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16301</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 08:38:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Scientific General Intelligence of LLMs with Scientist-Aligned Workflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16969</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16969.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wanghan Xu, Yuhao Zhou, Yifan Zhou, Qinglong Cao, Shuo Li, Jia Bu, Bo Liu, Yixin Chen, Xuming He, Xiangyu Zhao, Xiang Zhuang, Fengxiang Wang, Zhiwang Zhou, Qiantai Feng, Wenxuan Huang, Jiaqi Wei, Hao Wu, Yuejin Yang, Guangshuai Wang, Sheng Xu, Ziyan Huang, Xinyao Liu, Jiyao Liu, Cheng Tang, Wei Li, Ying Chen, Junzhi Ning, Pengfei Jiang, Chenglong Ma, Ye Du, Changkai Ji, Huihui Xu, Ming Hu, Jiangbin Zheng, Xin Chen, Yucheng Wu, Feifei Jiang, Xi Chen, Xiangru Tang, Yuchen Fu, Yingzhou Lu, Yuanyuan Zhang, Lihao Sun, Chengbo Li, Jinzhe Ma, Wanhao Liu, Yating Liu, Kuo-Cheng Wu, Shengdu Chai, Yizhou Wang, Ouwen Zhangjin, Chen Tang, Shufei Zhang, Wenbo Cao, Junjie Ren, Taoyong Cui, Zhouheng Yao, Juntao Deng, Yijie Sun, Feng Liu, Wangxu Wei, Jingyi Xu, Zhangrui Li, Junchao Gong, Zijie Guo, Zhiyu Yao, Zaoyu Chen, Tianhao Peng, Fangchen Yu, Bo Zhang, Dongzhan Zhou, Shixiang Tang, Jiaheng Liu, Fenghua Ling, Yan Lu, Yuchen Ren, Ben Fei, Zhen Zhao, Xinyu Gu, Rui Su, Xiao-Ming Wu, Weikang Si, Yang Liu, Hao Chen, Xiangchao Yan, Xue Yang, Junchi Yan, Jiamin Wu, Qihao Zheng, Chenhui Li, Zhiqiang Gao, Hao Kong, Junjun He, Mao Su, Tianfan Fu, Peng Ye, Chunfeng Song, Nanqing Dong, Yuqiang Li, Huazhu Fu, Siqi Sun, Lijing Cheng, Jintai Lin, Wanli Ouyang, Bowen Zhou, Wenlong Zhang, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 107&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite advances in scientific AI, a coherent framework for Scientific General Intelligence (SGI)-the ability to autonomously conceive, investigate, and reason across scientific domains-remains lacking. We present an operational SGI definition grounded in the Practical Inquiry Model (PIM: Deliberation, Conception, Action, Perception) and operationalize it via four scientist-aligned tasks: deep research, idea generation, dry/wet experiments, and experimental reasoning. SGI-Bench comprises over 1,000 expert-curated, cross-disciplinary samples inspired by Science's 125 Big Questions, enabling systematic evaluation of state-of-the-art LLMs. Results reveal gaps: low exact match (10--20%) in deep research despite step-level alignment; ideas lacking feasibility and detail; high code executability but low execution result accuracy in dry experiments; low sequence fidelity in wet protocols; and persistent multimodal comparative-reasoning challenges. We further introduce Test-Time Reinforcement Learning (TTRL), which optimizes retrieval-augmented novelty rewards at inference, enhancing hypothesis novelty without reference answer. Together, our PIM-grounded definition, workflow-centric benchmark, and empirical insights establish a foundation for AI systems that genuinely participate in scientific discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16969</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 12:44:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DataFlow: An LLM-Driven Framework for Unified Data Preparation and Workflow Automation in the Era of Data-Centric AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16676</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16676.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Liang, Xiaochen Ma, Zhou Liu, Zhen Hao Wong, Zhengyang Zhao, Zimo Meng, Runming He, Chengyu Shen, Qifeng Cai, Zhaoyang Han, Meiyi Qiang, Yalin Feng, Tianyi Bai, Zewei Pan, Ziyi Guo, Yizhen Jiang, Jingwen Deng, Qijie You, Peichao Lai, Tianyu Guo, Chi Hsu Tsai, Hengyi Feng, Rui Hu, Wenkai Yu, Junbo Niu, Bohan Zeng, Ruichuan An, Lu Ma, Jihao Huang, Yaowei Zheng, Conghui He, Linpeng Tang, Bin Cui, Weinan E, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 194&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapidly growing demand for high-quality data in Large Language Models (LLMs) has intensified the need for scalable, reliable, and semantically rich data preparation pipelines. However, current practices remain dominated by ad-hoc scripts and loosely specified workflows, which lack principled abstractions, hinder reproducibility, and offer limited support for model-in-the-loop data generation. To address these challenges, we present DataFlow, a unified and extensible LLM-driven data preparation framework. DataFlow is designed with system-level abstractions that enable modular, reusable, and composable data transformations, and provides a PyTorch-style pipeline construction API for building debuggable and optimizable dataflows. The framework consists of nearly 200 reusable operators and six domain-general pipelines spanning text, mathematical reasoning, code, Text-to-SQL, agentic RAG, and large-scale knowledge extraction. To further improve usability, we introduce DataFlow-Agent, which automatically translates natural-language specifications into executable pipelines via operator synthesis, pipeline planning, and iterative verification. Across six representative use cases, DataFlow consistently improves downstream LLM performance. Our math, code, and text pipelines outperform curated human datasets and specialized synthetic baselines, achieving up to +3\% execution accuracy in Text-to-SQL over SynSQL, +7\% average improvements on code benchmarks, and 1--3 point gains on MATH, GSM8K, and AIME. Moreover, a unified 10K-sample dataset produced by DataFlow enables base models to surpass counterparts trained on 1M Infinity-Instruct data. These results demonstrate that DataFlow provides a practical and high-performance substrate for reliable, reproducible, and scalable LLM data preparation, and establishes a system-level foundation for future data-centric AI development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16676</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 15:46:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kling-Omni Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16776</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16776.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kling Team, Jialu Chen, Yuanzheng Ci, Xiangyu Du, Zipeng Feng, Kun Gai, Sainan Guo, Feng Han, Jingbin He, Kang He, Xiao Hu, Xiaohua Hu, Boyuan Jiang, Fangyuan Kong, Hang Li, Jie Li, Qingyu Li, Shen Li, Xiaohan Li, Yan Li, Jiajun Liang, Borui Liao, Yiqiao Liao, Weihong Lin, Quande Liu, Xiaokun Liu, Yilun Liu, Yuliang Liu, Shun Lu, Hangyu Mao, Yunyao Mao, Haodong Ouyang, Wenyu Qin, Wanqi Shi, Xiaoyu Shi, Lianghao Su, Haozhi Sun, Peiqin Sun, Pengfei Wan, Chao Wang, Chenyu Wang, Meng Wang, Qiulin Wang, Runqi Wang, Xintao Wang, Xuebo Wang, Zekun Wang, Min Wei, Tiancheng Wen, Guohao Wu, Xiaoshi Wu, Zhenhua Wu, Da Xie, Yingtong Xiong, Yulong Xu, Sile Yang, Zikang Yang, Weicai Ye, Ziyang Yuan, Shenglong Zhang, Shuaiyu Zhang, Yuanxing Zhang, Yufan Zhang, Wenzheng Zhao, Ruiliang Zhou, Yan Zhou, Guosheng Zhu, Yongjie Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 163&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Kling-Omni, a generalist generative framework designed to synthesize high-fidelity videos directly from multimodal visual language inputs. Adopting an end-to-end perspective, Kling-Omni bridges the functional separation among diverse video generation, editing, and intelligent reasoning tasks, integrating them into a holistic system. Unlike disjointed pipeline approaches, Kling-Omni supports a diverse range of user inputs, including text instructions, reference images, and video contexts, processing them into a unified multimodal representation to deliver cinematic-quality and highly-intelligent video content creation. To support these capabilities, we constructed a comprehensive data system that serves as the foundation for multimodal video creation. The framework is further empowered by efficient large-scale pre-training strategies and infrastructure optimizations for inference. Comprehensive evaluations reveal that Kling-Omni demonstrates exceptional capabilities in in-context generation, reasoning-based editing, and multimodal instruction following. Moving beyond a content creation tool, we believe Kling-Omni is a pivotal advancement toward multimodal world simulators capable of perceiving, reasoning, generating and interacting with the dynamic and complex worlds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16776</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 17:08:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhysBrain: Human Egocentric Data as a Bridge from Vision Language Models to Physical Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16793</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16793.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaopeng Lin, Shijie Lian, Bin Yu, Ruoqi Yang, Changti Wu, Yuzhuo Miao, Yurun Jin, Yukun Shi, Cong Huang, Bojun Cheng, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Robotic generalization relies on physical intelligence: the ability to reason about state changes, contact-rich interactions, and long-horizon planning under egocentric perception and action. However, most VLMs are trained primarily on third-person data, creating a fundamental viewpoint mismatch for humanoid robots. Scaling robot egocentric data collection remains impractical due to high cost and limited diversity, whereas large-scale human egocentric videos offer a scalable alternative that naturally capture rich interaction context and causal structure. The key challenge is to convert raw egocentric videos into structured and reliable embodiment training supervision. Accordingly, we propose an Egocentric2Embodiment translation pipeline that transforms first-person videos into multi-level, schema-driven VQA supervision with enforced evidence grounding and temporal consistency, enabling the construction of the Egocentric2Embodiment dataset (E2E-3M) at scale. An egocentric-aware embodied brain, termed PhysBrain, is obtained by training on the E2E-3M dataset. PhysBrain exhibits substantially improved egocentric understanding, particularly for planning on EgoThink. It provides an egocentric-aware initialization that enables more sample-efficient VLA fine-tuning and higher SimplerEnv success rates (53.9\%), demonstrating effective transfer from human egocentric supervision to downstream robot control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16793</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 17:27:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StereoPilot: Learning Unified and Efficient Stereo Conversion via Generative Priors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16915</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16915.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guibao Shen, Yihua Du, Wenhang Ge, Jing He, Chirui Chang, Donghao Zhou, Zhen Yang, Luozhou Wang, Xin Tao, Ying-Cong Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid growth of stereoscopic displays, including VR headsets and 3D cinemas, has led to increasing demand for high-quality stereo video content. However, producing 3D videos remains costly and complex, while automatic Monocular-to-Stereo conversion is hindered by the limitations of the multi-stage ``Depth-Warp-Inpaint'' (DWI) pipeline. This paradigm suffers from error propagation, depth ambiguity, and format inconsistency between parallel and converged stereo configurations. To address these challenges, we introduce UniStereo, the first large-scale unified dataset for stereo video conversion, covering both stereo formats to enable fair benchmarking and robust model training. Building upon this dataset, we propose StereoPilot, an efficient feed-forward model that directly synthesizes the target view without relying on explicit depth maps or iterative diffusion sampling. Equipped with a learnable domain switcher and a cycle consistency loss, StereoPilot adapts seamlessly to different stereo formats and achieves improved consistency. Extensive experiments demonstrate that StereoPilot significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods in both visual fidelity and computational efficiency. Project page: https://hit-perfect.github.io/StereoPilot/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16915</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next-Embedding Prediction Makes Strong Vision Learners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16922</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16922.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sihan Xu, Ziqiao Ma, Wenhao Chai, Xuweiyi Chen, Weiyang Jin, Joyce Chai, Saining Xie, Stella X. Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 82&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Inspired by the success of generative pretraining in natural language, we ask whether the same principles can yield strong self-supervised visual learners. Instead of training models to output features for downstream use, we train them to generate embeddings to perform predictive tasks directly. This work explores such a shift from learning representations to learning models. Specifically, models learn to predict future patch embeddings conditioned on past ones, using causal masking and stop gradient, which we refer to as Next-Embedding Predictive Autoregression (NEPA). We demonstrate that a simple Transformer pretrained on ImageNet-1k with next embedding prediction as its sole learning objective is effective - no pixel reconstruction, discrete tokens, contrastive loss, or task-specific heads. This formulation retains architectural simplicity and scalability, without requiring additional design complexity. NEPA achieves strong results across tasks, attaining 83.8% and 85.3% top-1 accuracy on ImageNet-1K with ViT-B and ViT-L backbones after fine-tuning, and transferring effectively to semantic segmentation on ADE20K. We believe generative pretraining from embeddings provides a simple, scalable, and potentially modality-agnostic alternative to visual self-supervised learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16922</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Refocusing: Flexible Defocus Control from a Single Image</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16923</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16923.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chun-Wei Tuan Mu, Jia-Bin Huang, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Depth-of-field control is essential in photography, but getting the perfect focus often takes several tries or special equipment. Single-image refocusing is still difficult. It involves recovering sharp content and creating realistic bokeh. Current methods have significant drawbacks. They need all-in-focus inputs, depend on synthetic data from simulators, and have limited control over aperture. We introduce Generative Refocusing, a two-step process that uses DeblurNet to recover all-in-focus images from various inputs and BokehNet for creating controllable bokeh. Our main innovation is semi-supervised training. This method combines synthetic paired data with unpaired real bokeh images, using EXIF metadata to capture real optical characteristics beyond what simulators can provide. Our experiments show we achieve top performance in defocus deblurring, bokeh synthesis, and refocusing benchmarks. Additionally, our Generative Refocusing allows text-guided adjustments and custom aperture shapes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16923</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4D-RGPT: Toward Region-level 4D Understanding via Perceptual Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17012</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.17012.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chiao-An Yang, Ryo Hachiuma, Sifei Liu, Subhashree Radhakrishnan, Raymond A. Yeh, Yu-Chiang Frank Wang, Min-Hung Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite advances in Multimodal LLMs (MLLMs), their ability to reason over 3D structures and temporal dynamics remains limited, constrained by weak 4D perception and temporal understanding. Existing 3D and 4D Video Question Answering (VQA) benchmarks also emphasize static scenes and lack region-level prompting. We tackle these issues by introducing: (a) 4D-RGPT, a specialized MLLM designed to capture 4D representations from video inputs with enhanced temporal perception; (b) Perceptual 4D Distillation (P4D), a training framework that transfers 4D representations from a frozen expert model into 4D-RGPT for comprehensive 4D perception; and (c) R4D-Bench, a benchmark for depth-aware dynamic scenes with region-level prompting, built via a hybrid automated and human-verified pipeline. Our 4D-RGPT achieves notable improvements on both existing 4D VQA benchmarks and the proposed R4D-Bench benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17012</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 19:13:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mindscape-Aware Retrieval Augmented Generation for Improved Long Context Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17220</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.17220.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqing Li, Jiangnan Li, Zheng Lin, Ziyan Zhou, Junjie Wu, Weiping Wang, Jie Zhou, Mo Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 87&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humans understand long and complex texts by relying on a holistic semantic representation of the content. This global view helps organize prior knowledge, interpret new information, and integrate evidence dispersed across a document, as revealed by the Mindscape-Aware Capability of humans in psychology. Current Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) systems lack such guidance and therefore struggle with long-context tasks. In this paper, we propose Mindscape-Aware RAG (MiA-RAG), the first approach that equips LLM-based RAG systems with explicit global context awareness. MiA-RAG builds a mindscape through hierarchical summarization and conditions both retrieval and generation on this global semantic representation. This enables the retriever to form enriched query embeddings and the generator to reason over retrieved evidence within a coherent global context. We evaluate MiA-RAG across diverse long-context and bilingual benchmarks for evidence-based understanding and global sense-making. It consistently surpasses baselines, and further analysis shows that it aligns local details with a coherent global representation, enabling more human-like long-context retrieval and reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17220</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 04:08:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seed-Prover 1.5: Mastering Undergraduate-Level Theorem Proving via Learning from Experience</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17260</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.17260.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiangjie Chen, Wenxiang Chen, Jiacheng Du, Jinyi Hu, Zhicheng Jiang, Allan Jie, Xiaoran Jin, Xing Jin, Chenggang Li, Wenlei Shi, Zhihong Wang, Mingxuan Wang, Chenrui Wei, Shufa Wei, Huajian Xin, Fan Yang, Weihao Gao, Zheng Yuan, Tianyang Zhan, Zeyu Zheng, Tianxi Zhou, Thomas Hanwen Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models have recently made significant progress to generate rigorous mathematical proofs. In contrast, utilizing LLMs for theorem proving in formal languages (such as Lean) remains challenging and computationally expensive, particularly when addressing problems at the undergraduate level and beyond. In this work, we present Seed-Prover 1.5, a formal theorem-proving model trained via large-scale agentic reinforcement learning, alongside an efficient test-time scaling (TTS) workflow. Through extensive interactions with Lean and other tools, the model continuously accumulates experience during the RL process, substantially enhancing the capability and efficiency of formal theorem proving. Furthermore, leveraging recent advancements in natural language proving, our TTS workflow efficiently bridges the gap between natural and formal languages. Compared to state-of-the-art methods, Seed-Prover 1.5 achieves superior performance with a smaller compute budget. It solves 88\% of PutnamBench (undergraduate-level), 80\% of Fate-H (graduate-level), and 33\% of Fate-X (PhD-level) problems. Notably, using our system, we solved 11 out of 12 problems from Putnam 2025 within 9 hours. Our findings suggest that scaling learning from experience, driven by high-quality formal feedback, holds immense potential for the future of formal mathematical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17260</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 06:19:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InsertAnywhere: Bridging 4D Scene Geometry and Diffusion Models for Realistic Video Object Insertion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17504</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.17504.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hoiyeong Jin, Hyojin Jang, Jeongho Kim, Junha Hyung, Kinam Kim, Dongjin Kim, Huijin Choi, Hyeonji Kim, Jaegul Choo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 92&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in diffusion-based video generation have opened new possibilities for controllable video editing, yet realistic video object insertion (VOI) remains challenging due to limited 4D scene understanding and inadequate handling of occlusion and lighting effects. We present InsertAnywhere, a new VOI framework that achieves geometrically consistent object placement and appearance-faithful video synthesis. Our method begins with a 4D aware mask generation module that reconstructs the scene geometry and propagates user specified object placement across frames while maintaining temporal coherence and occlusion consistency. Building upon this spatial foundation, we extend a diffusion based video generation model to jointly synthesize the inserted object and its surrounding local variations such as illumination and shading. To enable supervised training, we introduce ROSE++, an illumination aware synthetic dataset constructed by transforming the ROSE object removal dataset into triplets of object removed video, object present video, and a VLM generated reference image. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate that our framework produces geometrically plausible and visually coherent object insertions across diverse real world scenarios, significantly outperforming existing research and commercial models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17504</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 12:14:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust-R1: Degradation-Aware Reasoning for Robust Visual Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17532</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.17532.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Tang, Jianmin Chen, Wei Wei, Xiaogang Xu, Runtao Liu, Xiangyu Wu, Qipeng Xie, Jiafei Wu, Lei Zhang, Qifeng Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models struggle to maintain reliable performance under extreme real-world visual degradations, which impede their practical robustness. Existing robust MLLMs predominantly rely on implicit training/adaptation that focuses solely on visual encoder generalization, suffering from limited interpretability and isolated optimization. To overcome these limitations, we propose Robust-R1, a novel framework that explicitly models visual degradations through structured reasoning chains. Our approach integrates: (i) supervised fine-tuning for degradation-aware reasoning foundations, (ii) reward-driven alignment for accurately perceiving degradation parameters, and (iii) dynamic reasoning depth scaling adapted to degradation intensity. To facilitate this approach, we introduce a specialized 11K dataset featuring realistic degradations synthesized across four critical real-world visual processing stages, each annotated with structured chains connecting degradation parameters, perceptual influence, pristine semantic reasoning chain, and conclusion. Comprehensive evaluations demonstrate state-of-the-art robustness: Robust-R1 outperforms all general and robust baselines on the real-world degradation benchmark R-Bench, while maintaining superior anti-degradation performance under multi-intensity adversarial degradations on MMMB, MMStar, and RealWorldQA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17532</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 12:56:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Region-Constraint In-Context Generation for Instructional Video Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17650</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.17650.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongwei Zhang, Fuchen Long, Wei Li, Zhaofan Qiu, Wu Liu, Ting Yao, Tao Mei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The In-context generation paradigm recently has demonstrated strong power in instructional image editing with both data efficiency and synthesis quality. Nevertheless, shaping such in-context learning for instruction-based video editing is not trivial. Without specifying editing regions, the results can suffer from the problem of inaccurate editing regions and the token interference between editing and non-editing areas during denoising. To address these, we present ReCo, a new instructional video editing paradigm that novelly delves into constraint modeling between editing and non-editing regions during in-context generation. Technically, ReCo width-wise concatenates source and target video for joint denoising. To calibrate video diffusion learning, ReCo capitalizes on two regularization terms, i.e., latent and attention regularization, conducting on one-step backward denoised latents and attention maps, respectively. The former increases the latent discrepancy of the editing region between source and target videos while reducing that of non-editing areas, emphasizing the modification on editing area and alleviating outside unexpected content generation. The latter suppresses the attention of tokens in the editing region to the tokens in counterpart of the source video, thereby mitigating their interference during novel object generation in target video. Furthermore, we propose a large-scale, high-quality video editing dataset, i.e., ReCo-Data, comprising 500K instruction-video pairs to benefit model training. Extensive experiments conducted on four major instruction-based video editing tasks demonstrate the superiority of our proposal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17650</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 14:49:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Reasoning Meets Its Laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17901</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.17901.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyu Zhang, Yifan Sun, Tianang Leng, Jingyan Shen, Liu Ziyin, Paul Pu Liang, Huan Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the superior performance of Large Reasoning Models (LRMs), their reasoning behaviors are often counterintuitive, leading to suboptimal reasoning capabilities. To theoretically formalize the desired reasoning behaviors, this paper presents the Laws of Reasoning (LoRe), a unified framework that characterizes intrinsic reasoning patterns in LRMs. We first propose compute law with the hypothesis that the reasoning compute should scale linearly with question complexity. Beyond compute, we extend LoRe with a supplementary accuracy law. Since the question complexity is difficult to quantify in practice, we examine these hypotheses by two properties of the laws, monotonicity and compositionality. We therefore introduce LoRe-Bench, a benchmark that systematically measures these two tractable properties for large reasoning models. Evaluation shows that most reasoning models exhibit reasonable monotonicity but lack compositionality. In response, we develop an effective finetuning approach that enforces compute-law compositionality. Extensive empirical studies demonstrate that better compliance with compute laws yields consistently improved reasoning performance on multiple benchmarks, and uncovers synergistic effects across properties and laws. Project page: https://lore-project.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17901</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 18:59:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Both Semantics and Reconstruction Matter: Making Representation Encoders Ready for Text-to-Image Generation and Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17909</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.17909.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shilong Zhang, He Zhang, Zhifei Zhang, Chongjian Ge, Shuchen Xue, Shaoteng Liu, Mengwei Ren, Soo Ye Kim, Yuqian Zhou, Qing Liu, Daniil Pakhomov, Kai Zhang, Zhe Lin, Ping Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern Latent Diffusion Models (LDMs) typically operate in low-level Variational Autoencoder (VAE) latent spaces that are primarily optimized for pixel-level reconstruction. To unify vision generation and understanding, a burgeoning trend is to adopt high-dimensional features from representation encoders as generative latents. However, we empirically identify two fundamental obstacles in this paradigm: (1) the discriminative feature space lacks compact regularization, making diffusion models prone to off-manifold latents that lead to inaccurate object structures; and (2) the encoder's inherently weak pixel-level reconstruction hinders the generator from learning accurate fine-grained geometry and texture. In this paper, we propose a systematic framework to adapt understanding-oriented encoder features for generative tasks. We introduce a semantic-pixel reconstruction objective to regularize the latent space, enabling the compression of both semantic information and fine-grained details into a highly compact representation (96 channels with 16x16 spatial downsampling). This design ensures that the latent space remains semantically rich and achieves state-of-the-art image reconstruction, while remaining compact enough for accurate generation. Leveraging this representation, we design a unified Text-to-Image (T2I) and image editing model. Benchmarking against various feature spaces, we demonstrate that our approach achieves state-of-the-art reconstruction, faster convergence, and substantial performance gains in both T2I and editing tasks, validating that representation encoders can be effectively adapted into robust generative components.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17909</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bottom-up Policy Optimization: Your Language Model Policy Secretly Contains Internal Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19673</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.19673.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqiao Tan, Minzheng Wang, Shizhu He, Huanxuan Liao, Chengfeng Zhao, Qiunan Lu, Tian Liang, Jun Zhao, Kang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing reinforcement learning (RL) approaches treat large language models (LLMs) as a single unified policy, overlooking their internal mechanisms. Understanding how policy evolves across layers and modules is therefore crucial for enabling more targeted optimization and raveling out complex reasoning mechanisms. In this paper, we decompose the language model policy by leveraging the intrinsic split of the Transformer residual stream and the equivalence between the composition of hidden states with the unembedding matrix and the resulting samplable policy. This decomposition reveals Internal Layer Policies, corresponding to contributions from individual layers, and Internal Modular Policies, which align with the self-attention and feed-forward network (FFN) components within each layer. By analyzing the entropy of internal policy, we find that: (a) Early layers keep high entropy for exploration, top layers converge to near-zero entropy for refinement, with convergence patterns varying across model series. (b) LLama's prediction space rapidly converges in the final layer, whereas Qwen-series models, especially Qwen3, exhibit a more human-like, progressively structured reasoning pattern. Motivated by these findings, we propose Bottom-up Policy Optimization (BuPO), a novel RL paradigm that directly optimizes the internal layer policy during early training. By aligning training objective at lower layer, BuPO reconstructs foundational reasoning capabilities and achieves superior performance. Extensive experiments on complex reasoning benchmarks demonstrates the effectiveness of our method. Our code is available at https://github.com/Trae1ounG/BuPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19673</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 18:51:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Prism Hypothesis: Harmonizing Semantic and Pixel Representations via Unified Autoencoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19693</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.19693.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weichen Fan, Haiwen Diao, Quan Wang, Dahua Lin, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep representations across modalities are inherently intertwined. In this paper, we systematically analyze the spectral characteristics of various semantic and pixel encoders. Interestingly, our study uncovers a highly inspiring and rarely explored correspondence between an encoder's feature spectrum and its functional role: semantic encoders primarily capture low-frequency components that encode abstract meaning, whereas pixel encoders additionally retain high-frequency information that conveys fine-grained detail. This heuristic finding offers a unifying perspective that ties encoder behavior to its underlying spectral structure. We define it as the Prism Hypothesis, where each data modality can be viewed as a projection of the natural world onto a shared feature spectrum, just like the prism. Building on this insight, we propose Unified Autoencoding (UAE), a model that harmonizes semantic structure and pixel details via an innovative frequency-band modulator, enabling their seamless coexistence. Extensive experiments on ImageNet and MS-COCO benchmarks validate that our UAE effectively unifies semantic abstraction and pixel-level fidelity into a single latent space with state-of-the-art performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19693</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step-DeepResearch Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20491</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20491.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chen Hu, Haikuo Du, Heng Wang, Lin Lin, Mingrui Chen, Peng Liu, Ruihang Miao, Tianchi Yue, Wang You, Wei Ji, Wei Yuan, Wenjin Deng, Xiaojian Yuan, Xiaoyun Zhang, Xiangyu Liu, Xikai Liu, Yanming Xu, Yicheng Cao, Yifei Zhang, Yongyao Wang, Yubo Shu, Yurong Zhang, Yuxiang Zhang, Zheng Gong, Zhichao Chang, Binyan Li, Dan Ma, Furong Jia, Hongyuan Wang, Jiayu Liu, Jing Bai, Junlan Liu, Manjiao Liu, Na Wang, Qiuping Wu, Qinxin Du, Shiwei Li, Wen Sun, Yifeng Gong, Yonglin Chen, Yuling Zhao, Yuxuan Lin, Ziqi Ren, Zixuan Wang, Aihu Zhang, Brian Li, Buyun Ma, Kang An, Li Xie, Mingliang Li, Pan Li, Shidong Yang, Xi Chen, Xiaojia Liu, Yuchu Luo, Yuan Song, YuanHao Ding, Yuanwei Liang, Zexi Li, Zhaoning Zhang, Zixin Zhang, Binxing Jiao, Daxin Jiang, Jiansheng Chen, Jing Li, Xiangyu Zhang, Yibo Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 76&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As LLMs shift toward autonomous agents, Deep Research has emerged as a pivotal metric. However, existing academic benchmarks like BrowseComp often fail to meet real-world demands for open-ended research, which requires robust skills in intent recognition, long-horizon decision-making, and cross-source verification. To address this, we introduce Step-DeepResearch, a cost-effective, end-to-end agent. We propose a Data Synthesis Strategy Based on Atomic Capabilities to reinforce planning and report writing, combined with a progressive training path from agentic mid-training to SFT and RL. Enhanced by a Checklist-style Judger, this approach significantly improves robustness. Furthermore, to bridge the evaluation gap in the Chinese domain, we establish ADR-Bench for realistic deep research scenarios. Experimental results show that Step-DeepResearch (32B) scores 61.4% on Scale AI Research Rubrics. On ADR-Bench, it significantly outperforms comparable models and rivals SOTA closed-source models like OpenAI and Gemini DeepResearch. These findings prove that refined training enables medium-sized models to achieve expert-level capabilities at industry-leading cost-efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20491</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 16:32:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Reason in 4D: Dynamic Spatial Understanding for Vision Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20557</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20557.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengchao Zhou, Yuxin Chen, Yuying Ge, Wei Huang, Jiehong Lin, Ying Shan, Xiaojuan Qi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language models (VLM) excel at general understanding yet remain weak at dynamic spatial reasoning (DSR), i.e., reasoning about the evolvement of object geometry and relationship in 3D space over time, largely due to the scarcity of scalable 4D-aware training resources. To bridge this gap across aspects of dataset, benchmark and model, we introduce DSR Suite. First, we propose an automated pipeline that generates multiple-choice question-answer pairs from in-the-wild videos for DSR. By leveraging modern vision foundation models, the pipeline extracts rich geometric and motion information, including camera poses, local point clouds, object masks, orientations, and 3D trajectories. These geometric cues enable the construction of DSR-Train for learning and further human-refined DSR-Bench for evaluation. Compared with previous works, our data emphasize (i) in-the-wild video sources, (ii) object- and scene-level 3D requirements, (iii) viewpoint transformations, (iv) multi-object interactions, and (v) fine-grained, procedural answers. Beyond data, we propose a lightweight Geometry Selection Module (GSM) to seamlessly integrate geometric priors into VLMs, which condenses question semantics and extracts question-relevant knowledge from pretrained 4D reconstruction priors into a compact set of geometry tokens. This targeted extraction avoids overwhelming the model with irrelevant knowledge. Experiments show that integrating DSR-Train and GSM into Qwen2.5-VL-7B significantly enhances its dynamic spatial reasoning capability, while maintaining accuracy on general video understanding benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20557</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 17:56:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent temporal abstractions in autoregressive models enable hierarchical reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20605</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20605.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seijin Kobayashi, Yanick Schimpf, Maximilian Schlegel, Angelika Steger, Maciej Wolczyk, Johannes von Oswald, Nino Scherrer, Kaitlin Maile, Guillaume Lajoie, Blake A. Richards, Rif A. Saurous, James Manyika, Blaise Agüera y Arcas, Alexander Meulemans, João Sacramento&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large-scale autoregressive models pretrained on next-token prediction and finetuned with reinforcement learning (RL) have achieved unprecedented success on many problem domains. During RL, these models explore by generating new outputs, one token at a time. However, sampling actions token-by-token can result in highly inefficient learning, particularly when rewards are sparse. Here, we show that it is possible to overcome this problem by acting and exploring within the internal representations of an autoregressive model. Specifically, to discover temporally-abstract actions, we introduce a higher-order, non-causal sequence model whose outputs control the residual stream activations of a base autoregressive model. On grid world and MuJoCo-based tasks with hierarchical structure, we find that the higher-order model learns to compress long activation sequence chunks onto internal controllers. Critically, each controller executes a sequence of behaviorally meaningful actions that unfold over long timescales and are accompanied with a learned termination condition, such that composing multiple controllers over time leads to efficient exploration on novel tasks. We show that direct internal controller reinforcement, a process we term "internal RL", enables learning from sparse rewards in cases where standard RL finetuning fails. Our results demonstrate the benefits of latent action generation and reinforcement in autoregressive models, suggesting internal RL as a promising avenue for realizing hierarchical RL within foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20605</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 18:51:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpatialTree: How Spatial Abilities Branch Out in MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20617</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20617.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxi Xiao, Longfei Li, Shen Yan, Xinhang Liu, Sida Peng, Yunchao Wei, Xiaowei Zhou, Bingyi Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Cognitive science suggests that spatial ability develops progressively-from perception to reasoning and interaction. Yet in multimodal LLMs (MLLMs), this hierarchy remains poorly understood, as most studies focus on a narrow set of tasks. We introduce SpatialTree, a cognitive-science-inspired hierarchy that organizes spatial abilities into four levels: low-level perception (L1), mental mapping (L2), simulation (L3), and agentic competence (L4). Based on this taxonomy, we construct the first capability-centric hierarchical benchmark, thoroughly evaluating mainstream MLLMs across 27 sub-abilities. The evaluation results reveal a clear structure: L1 skills are largely orthogonal, whereas higher-level skills are strongly correlated, indicating increasing interdependency. Through targeted supervised fine-tuning, we uncover a surprising transfer dynamic-negative transfer within L1, but strong cross-level transfer from low- to high-level abilities with notable synergy. Finally, we explore how to improve the entire hierarchy. We find that naive RL that encourages extensive "thinking" is unreliable: it helps complex reasoning but hurts intuitive perception. We propose a simple auto-think strategy that suppresses unnecessary deliberation, enabling RL to consistently improve performance across all levels. By building SpatialTree, we provide a proof-of-concept framework for understanding and systematically scaling spatial abilities in MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20617</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 18:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongVideoAgent: Multi-Agent Reasoning with Long Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runtao Liu, Ziyi Liu, Jiaqi Tang, Yue Ma, Renjie Pi, Jipeng Zhang, Qifeng Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal LLMs and systems that use tools for long-video QA point to the promise of reasoning over hour-long episodes. However, many methods still compress content into lossy summaries or rely on limited toolsets, weakening temporal grounding and missing fine-grained cues. We propose a multi-agent framework in which a master LLM coordinates a grounding agent to localize question-relevant segments and a vision agent to extract targeted textual observations. The master agent plans with a step limit, and is trained with reinforcement learning to encourage concise, correct, and efficient multi-agent cooperation. This design helps the master agent focus on relevant clips via grounding, complements subtitles with visual detail, and yields interpretable trajectories. On our proposed LongTVQA and LongTVQA+ which are episode-level datasets aggregated from TVQA/TVQA+, our multi-agent system significantly outperforms strong non-agent baselines. Experiments also show reinforcement learning further strengthens reasoning and planning for the trained agent. Code and data will be shared at https://longvideoagent.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20618</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 18:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SemanticGen: Video Generation in Semantic Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20619</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20619.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianhong Bai, Xiaoshi Wu, Xintao Wang, Fu Xiao, Yuanxing Zhang, Qinghe Wang, Xiaoyu Shi, Menghan Xia, Zuozhu Liu, Haoji Hu, Pengfei Wan, Kun Gai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; State-of-the-art video generative models typically learn the distribution of video latents in the VAE space and map them to pixels using a VAE decoder. While this approach can generate high-quality videos, it suffers from slow convergence and is computationally expensive when generating long videos. In this paper, we introduce SemanticGen, a novel solution to address these limitations by generating videos in the semantic space. Our main insight is that, due to the inherent redundancy in videos, the generation process should begin in a compact, high-level semantic space for global planning, followed by the addition of high-frequency details, rather than directly modeling a vast set of low-level video tokens using bi-directional attention. SemanticGen adopts a two-stage generation process. In the first stage, a diffusion model generates compact semantic video features, which define the global layout of the video. In the second stage, another diffusion model generates VAE latents conditioned on these semantic features to produce the final output. We observe that generation in the semantic space leads to faster convergence compared to the VAE latent space. Our method is also effective and computationally efficient when extended to long video generation. Extensive experiments demonstrate that SemanticGen produces high-quality videos and outperforms state-of-the-art approaches and strong baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20619</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 18:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Implicit Visual Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21218</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21218.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kelvin Li, Chuyi Shang, Leonid Karlinsky, Rogerio Feris, Trevor Darrell, Roei Herzig&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) have made significant progress, they remain largely text-centric, relying on language as their core reasoning modality. As a result, they are limited in their ability to handle reasoning tasks that are predominantly visual. Recent approaches have sought to address this by supervising intermediate visual steps with helper images, depth maps, or image crops. However, these strategies impose restrictive priors on what "useful" visual abstractions look like, add heavy annotation costs, and struggle to generalize across tasks. To address this critical limitation, we propose a task-agnostic mechanism that trains LMMs to discover and use visual reasoning tokens without explicit supervision. These tokens attend globally and re-encode the image in a task-adaptive way, enabling the model to extract relevant visual information without hand-crafted supervision. Our approach outperforms direct fine-tuning and achieves state-of-the-art results on a diverse range of vision-centric tasks -- including those where intermediate abstractions are hard to specify -- while also generalizing to multi-task instruction tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21218</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 14:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yume-1.5: A Text-Controlled Interactive World Generation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22096</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.22096.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaofeng Mao, Zhen Li, Chuanhao Li, Xiaojie Xu, Kaining Ying, Tong He, Jiangmiao Pang, Yu Qiao, Kaipeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent approaches have demonstrated the promise of using diffusion models to generate interactive and explorable worlds. However, most of these methods face critical challenges such as excessively large parameter sizes, reliance on lengthy inference steps, and rapidly growing historical context, which severely limit real-time performance and lack text-controlled generation capabilities. To address these challenges, we propose \method, a novel framework designed to generate realistic, interactive, and continuous worlds from a single image or text prompt. \method achieves this through a carefully designed framework that supports keyboard-based exploration of the generated worlds. The framework comprises three core components: (1) a long-video generation framework integrating unified context compression with linear attention; (2) a real-time streaming acceleration strategy powered by bidirectional attention distillation and an enhanced text embedding scheme; (3) a text-controlled method for generating world events. We have provided the codebase in the supplementary material.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22096</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 17:52:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupling Experts and Routers in Mixture-of-Experts via an Auxiliary Loss</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23447</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.23447.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ang Lv, Jin Ma, Yiyuan Ma, Siyuan Qiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 81&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) models lack explicit constraints to ensure the router's decisions align well with the experts' capabilities, which ultimately limits model performance. To address this, we propose expert-router coupling (ERC) loss, a lightweight auxiliary loss that tightly couples the router's decisions with expert capabilities. Our approach treats each expert's router embedding as a proxy token for the tokens assigned to that expert, and feeds perturbed router embeddings through the experts to obtain internal activations. The ERC loss enforces two constraints on these activations: (1) Each expert must exhibit higher activation for its own proxy token than for the proxy tokens of any other expert. (2) Each proxy token must elicit stronger activation from its corresponding expert than from any other expert. These constraints jointly ensure that each router embedding faithfully represents its corresponding expert's capability, while each expert specializes in processing the tokens actually routed to it. The ERC loss is computationally efficient, operating only on n^2 activations, where n is the number of experts. This represents a fixed cost independent of batch size, unlike prior coupling methods that scale with the number of tokens (often millions per batch). Through pre-training MoE-LLMs ranging from 3B to 15B parameters and extensive analysis on trillions of tokens, we demonstrate the effectiveness of the ERC loss. Moreover, the ERC loss offers flexible control and quantitative tracking of expert specialization levels during training, providing valuable insights into MoEs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23447</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 13:03:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiveTalk: Real-Time Multimodal Interactive Video Diffusion via Improved On-Policy Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23576</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.23576.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ethan Chern, Zhulin Hu, Bohao Tang, Jiadi Su, Steffi Chern, Zhijie Deng, Pengfei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Real-time video generation via diffusion is essential for building general-purpose multimodal interactive AI systems. However, the simultaneous denoising of all video frames with bidirectional attention via an iterative process in diffusion models prevents real-time interaction. While existing distillation methods can make the model autoregressive and reduce sampling steps to mitigate this, they focus primarily on text-to-video generation, leaving the human-AI interaction unnatural and less efficient. This paper targets real-time interactive video diffusion conditioned on a multimodal context, including text, image, and audio, to bridge the gap. Given the observation that the leading on-policy distillation approach Self Forcing encounters challenges (visual artifacts like flickering, black frames, and quality degradation) with multimodal conditioning, we investigate an improved distillation recipe with emphasis on the quality of condition inputs as well as the initialization and schedule for the on-policy optimization. On benchmarks for multimodal-conditioned (audio, image, and text) avatar video generation including HDTF, AVSpeech, and CelebV-HQ, our distilled model matches the visual quality of the full-step, bidirectional baselines of similar or larger size with 20x less inference cost and latency. Further, we integrate our model with audio language models and long-form video inference technique Anchor-Heavy Identity Sinks to build LiveTalk, a real-time multimodal interactive avatar system. System-level evaluation on our curated multi-turn interaction benchmark shows LiveTalk outperforms state-of-the-art models (Sora2, Veo3) in multi-turn video coherence and content quality, while reducing response latency from 1 to 2 minutes to real-time generation, enabling seamless human-AI multimodal interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23576</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 16:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
