<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:11:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>INTIMA: A Benchmark for Human-AI Companionship Behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09998</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09998.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lucie-Aimée Kaffee, Giada Pistilli, Yacine Jernite&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI companionship, where users develop emotional bonds with AI systems, has emerged as a significant pattern with positive but also concerning implications. We introduce Interactions and Machine Attachment Benchmark (INTIMA), a benchmark for evaluating companionship behaviors in language models. Drawing from psychological theories and user data, we develop a taxonomy of 31 behaviors across four categories and 368 targeted prompts. Responses to these prompts are evaluated as companionship-reinforcing, boundary-maintaining, or neutral. Applying INTIMA to Gemma-3, Phi-4, o3-mini, and Claude-4 reveals that companionship-reinforcing behaviors remain much more common across all models, though we observe marked differences between models. Different commercial providers prioritize different categories within the more sensitive parts of the benchmark, which is concerning since both appropriate boundary-setting and emotional support matter for user well-being. These findings highlight the need for more consistent approaches to handling emotionally charged interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09998</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 08:25:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZARA: Zero-shot Motion Time-Series Analysis via Knowledge and Retrieval   Driven LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04038</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04038.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zechen Li, Baiyu Chen, Hao Xue, Flora D. Salim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Motion sensor time-series are central to human activity recognition (HAR), with applications in health, sports, and smart devices. However, existing methods are trained for fixed activity sets and require costly retraining when new behaviours or sensor setups appear. Recent attempts to use large language models (LLMs) for HAR, typically by converting signals into text or images, suffer from limited accuracy and lack verifiable interpretability. We propose ZARA, the first agent-based framework for zero-shot, explainable HAR directly from raw motion time-series. ZARA integrates an automatically derived pair-wise feature knowledge base that captures discriminative statistics for every activity pair, a multi-sensor retrieval module that surfaces relevant evidence, and a hierarchical agent pipeline that guides the LLM to iteratively select features, draw on this evidence, and produce both activity predictions and natural-language explanations. ZARA enables flexible and interpretable HAR without any fine-tuning or task-specific classifiers. Extensive experiments on 8 HAR benchmarks show that ZARA achieves SOTA zero-shot performance, delivering clear reasoning while exceeding the strongest baselines by 2.53x in macro F1. Ablation studies further confirm the necessity of each module, marking ZARA as a promising step toward trustworthy, plug-and-play motion time-series analysis. Our codes are available at https://github.com/zechenli03/ZARA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04038</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 02:57:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TempFlow-GRPO: When Timing Matters for GRPO in Flow Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04324</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04324.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoxuan He, Siming Fu, Yuke Zhao, Wanli Li, Jian Yang, Dacheng Yin, Fengyun Rao, Bo Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent flow matching models for text-to-image generation have achieved remarkable quality, yet their integration with reinforcement learning for human preference alignment remains suboptimal, hindering fine-grained reward-based optimization. We observe that the key impediment to effective GRPO training of flow models is the temporal uniformity assumption in existing approaches: sparse terminal rewards with uniform credit assignment fail to capture the varying criticality of decisions across generation timesteps, resulting in inefficient exploration and suboptimal convergence. To remedy this shortcoming, we introduce TempFlow-GRPO (Temporal Flow GRPO), a principled GRPO framework that captures and exploits the temporal structure inherent in flow-based generation. TempFlow-GRPO introduces two key innovations: (i) a trajectory branching mechanism that provides process rewards by concentrating stochasticity at designated branching points, enabling precise credit assignment without requiring specialized intermediate reward models; and (ii) a noise-aware weighting scheme that modulates policy optimization according to the intrinsic exploration potential of each timestep, prioritizing learning during high-impact early stages while ensuring stable refinement in later phases. These innovations endow the model with temporally-aware optimization that respects the underlying generative dynamics, leading to state-of-the-art performance in human preference alignment and standard text-to-image benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04324</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 11:10:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiance Fields in XR: A Survey on How Radiance Fields are Envisioned   and Addressed for XR Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04326</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04326.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ke Li, Mana Masuda, Susanne Schmidt, Shohei Mori&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The development of radiance fields (RF), such as 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) and Neural Radiance Fields (NeRF), has revolutionized interactive photorealistic view synthesis and presents enormous opportunities for XR research and applications. However, despite the exponential growth of RF research, RF-related contributions to the XR community remain sparse. To better understand this research gap, we performed a systematic survey of current RF literature to analyze (i) how RF is envisioned for XR applications, (ii) how they have already been implemented, and (iii) the remaining research gaps. We collected 365 RF contributions related to XR from computer vision, computer graphics, robotics, multimedia, human-computer interaction, and XR communities, seeking to answer the above research questions. Among the 365 papers, we performed an analysis of 66 papers that already addressed a detailed aspect of RF research for XR. With this survey, we extended and positioned XR-specific RF research topics in the broader RF research field and provide a helpful resource for the XR community to navigate within the rapid development of RF research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04326</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 11:14:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain-of-Agents: End-to-End Agent Foundation Models via Multi-Agent   Distillation and Agentic RL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13167</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13167.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weizhen Li, Jianbo Lin, Zhuosong Jiang, Jingyi Cao, Xinpeng Liu, Jiayu Zhang, Zhenqiang Huang, Qianben Chen, Weichen Sun, Qiexiang Wang, Hongxuan Lu, Tianrui Qin, Chenghao Zhu, Yi Yao, Shuying Fan, Xiaowan Li, Tiannan Wang, Pai Liu, King Zhu, He Zhu, Dingfeng Shi, Piaohong Wang, Yeyi Guan, Xiangru Tang, Minghao Liu, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Jian Yang, Jiaheng Liu, Ge Zhang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 104&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) and multi-agent systems have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in complex problem-solving tasks such as deep research, vibe coding, and mathematical reasoning. However, most existing multi-agent systems are built upon manual prompt/workflow engineering with sophisticated agent frameworks, making them computationally inefficient, less capable, and can not benefit from data-centric learning. In this work, we introduce Chain-of-Agents (CoA), a novel paradigm of LLM reasoning that enables native end-to-end complex problem-solving in the same way as a multi-agent system (i.e., multi-turn problem solving with multiple tools and multiple agents) within one model. In chain-of-agents problem-solving, the model dynamically activates different tool agents and role-playing agents to simulate multi-agent collaboration in an end-to-end fashion. To elicit end-to-end chain-of-agents problem-solving abilities in LLMs, we introduce a multi-agent distillation framework to distill state-of-the-art multi-agent systems into chain-of-agents trajectories for agentic supervised fine-tuning. We then use agentic reinforcement learning on verifiable agentic tasks to further improve the models' capabilities on chain-of-agents problem solving. We call the resulting models Agent Foundation Models (AFMs). Our empirical studies demonstrate that AFM establishes new state-of-the-art performance across diverse benchmarks in both web agent and code agent settings. We make the entire research, including the model weights, code for training and evaluation, and the training data, fully open-sourced, which offers a solid starting point for future research on agent models and agentic RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13167</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 17:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPARSE Data, Rich Results: Few-Shot Semi-Supervised Learning via   Class-Conditioned Image Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06429</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.06429.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guido Manni, Clemente Lauretti, Loredana Zollo, Paolo Soda&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep learning has revolutionized medical imaging, but its effectiveness is severely limited by insufficient labeled training data. This paper introduces a novel GAN-based semi-supervised learning framework specifically designed for low labeled-data regimes, evaluated across settings with 5 to 50 labeled samples per class. Our approach integrates three specialized neural networks -- a generator for class-conditioned image translation, a discriminator for authenticity assessment and classification, and a dedicated classifier -- within a three-phase training framework. The method alternates between supervised training on limited labeled data and unsupervised learning that leverages abundant unlabeled images through image-to-image translation rather than generation from noise. We employ ensemble-based pseudo-labeling that combines confidence-weighted predictions from the discriminator and classifier with temporal consistency through exponential moving averaging, enabling reliable label estimation for unlabeled data. Comprehensive evaluation across eleven MedMNIST datasets demonstrates that our approach achieves statistically significant improvements over six state-of-the-art GAN-based semi-supervised methods, with particularly strong performance in the extreme 5-shot setting where the scarcity of labeled data is most challenging. The framework maintains its superiority across all evaluated settings (5, 10, 20, and 50 shots per class). Our approach offers a practical solution for medical imaging applications where annotation costs are prohibitive, enabling robust classification performance even with minimal labeled data. Code is available at https://github.com/GuidoManni/SPARSE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06429</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 16:16:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MultiRef: Controllable Image Generation with Multiple Visual References</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06905</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.06905.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruoxi Chen, Dongping Chen, Siyuan Wu, Sinan Wang, Shiyun Lang, Petr Sushko, Gaoyang Jiang, Yao Wan, Ranjay Krishna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual designers naturally draw inspiration from multiple visual references, combining diverse elements and aesthetic principles to create artwork. However, current image generative frameworks predominantly rely on single-source inputs -- either text prompts or individual reference images. In this paper, we focus on the task of controllable image generation using multiple visual references. We introduce MultiRef-bench, a rigorous evaluation framework comprising 990 synthetic and 1,000 real-world samples that require incorporating visual content from multiple reference images. The synthetic samples are synthetically generated through our data engine RefBlend, with 10 reference types and 33 reference combinations. Based on RefBlend, we further construct a dataset MultiRef containing 38k high-quality images to facilitate further research. Our experiments across three interleaved image-text models (i.e., OmniGen, ACE, and Show-o) and six agentic frameworks (e.g., ChatDiT and LLM + SD) reveal that even state-of-the-art systems struggle with multi-reference conditioning, with the best model OmniGen achieving only 66.6% in synthetic samples and 79.0% in real-world cases on average compared to the golden answer. These findings provide valuable directions for developing more flexible and human-like creative tools that can effectively integrate multiple sources of visual inspiration. The dataset is publicly available at: https://multiref.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06905</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 09:36:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Podcast Recommendations with Profile-Aware LLM-as-a-Judge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08777</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.08777.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Francesco Fabbri, Gustavo Penha, Edoardo D'Amico, Alice Wang, Marco De Nadai, Jackie Doremus, Paul Gigioli, Andreas Damianou, Oskar Stal, Mounia Lalmas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating personalized recommendations remains a central challenge, especially in long-form audio domains like podcasts, where traditional offline metrics suffer from exposure bias and online methods such as A/B testing are costly and operationally constrained. In this paper, we propose a novel framework that leverages Large Language Models (LLMs) as offline judges to assess the quality of podcast recommendations in a scalable and interpretable manner. Our two-stage profile-aware approach first constructs natural-language user profiles distilled from 90 days of listening history. These profiles summarize both topical interests and behavioral patterns, serving as compact, interpretable representations of user preferences. Rather than prompting the LLM with raw data, we use these profiles to provide high-level, semantically rich context-enabling the LLM to reason more effectively about alignment between a user's interests and recommended episodes. This reduces input complexity and improves interpretability. The LLM is then prompted to deliver fine-grained pointwise and pairwise judgments based on the profile-episode match. In a controlled study with 47 participants, our profile-aware judge matched human judgments with high fidelity and outperformed or matched a variant using raw listening histories. The framework enables efficient, profile-aware evaluation for iterative testing and model selection in recommender systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08777</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 09:23:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training-Free Text-Guided Color Editing with Multi-Modal Diffusion   Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09131</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09131.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zixin Yin, Xili Dai, Ling-Hao Chen, Deyu Zhou, Jianan Wang, Duomin Wang, Gang Yu, Lionel M. Ni, Lei Zhang, Heung-Yeung Shum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-guided color editing in images and videos is a fundamental yet unsolved problem, requiring fine-grained manipulation of color attributes, including albedo, light source color, and ambient lighting, while preserving physical consistency in geometry, material properties, and light-matter interactions. Existing training-free methods offer broad applicability across editing tasks but struggle with precise color control and often introduce visual inconsistency in both edited and non-edited regions. In this work, we present ColorCtrl, a training-free color editing method that leverages the attention mechanisms of modern Multi-Modal Diffusion Transformers (MM-DiT). By disentangling structure and color through targeted manipulation of attention maps and value tokens, our method enables accurate and consistent color editing, along with word-level control of attribute intensity. Our method modifies only the intended regions specified by the prompt, leaving unrelated areas untouched. Extensive experiments on both SD3 and FLUX.1-dev demonstrate that ColorCtrl outperforms existing training-free approaches and achieves state-of-the-art performances in both edit quality and consistency. Furthermore, our method surpasses strong commercial models such as FLUX.1 Kontext Max and GPT-4o Image Generation in terms of consistency. When extended to video models like CogVideoX, our approach exhibits greater advantages, particularly in maintaining temporal coherence and editing stability. Finally, our method also generalizes to instruction-based editing diffusion models such as Step1X-Edit and FLUX.1 Kontext dev, further demonstrating its versatility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09131</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 17:57:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Describe What You See with Multimodal Large Language Models to Enhance   Video Recommendations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09789</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09789.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marco De Nadai, Andreas Damianou, Mounia Lalmas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing video recommender systems rely primarily on user-defined metadata or on low-level visual and acoustic signals extracted by specialised encoders. These low-level features describe what appears on the screen but miss deeper semantics such as intent, humour, and world knowledge that make clips resonate with viewers. For example, is a 30-second clip simply a singer on a rooftop, or an ironic parody filmed amid the fairy chimneys of Cappadocia, Turkey? Such distinctions are critical to personalised recommendations yet remain invisible to traditional encoding pipelines. In this paper, we introduce a simple, recommendation system-agnostic zero-finetuning framework that injects high-level semantics into the recommendation pipeline by prompting an off-the-shelf Multimodal Large Language Model (MLLM) to summarise each clip into a rich natural-language description (e.g. "a superhero parody with slapstick fights and orchestral stabs"), bridging the gap between raw content and user intent. We use MLLM output with a state-of-the-art text encoder and feed it into standard collaborative, content-based, and generative recommenders. On the MicroLens-100K dataset, which emulates user interactions with TikTok-style videos, our framework consistently surpasses conventional video, audio, and metadata features in five representative models. Our findings highlight the promise of leveraging MLLMs as on-the-fly knowledge extractors to build more intent-aware video recommenders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09789</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 13:19:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speed Always Wins: A Survey on Efficient Architectures for Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09834</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09834.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weigao Sun, Jiaxi Hu, Yucheng Zhou, Jusen Du, Disen Lan, Kexin Wang, Tong Zhu, Xiaoye Qu, Yu Zhang, Xiaoyu Mo, Daizong Liu, Yuxuan Liang, Wenliang Chen, Guoqi Li, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have delivered impressive results in language understanding, generation, reasoning, and pushes the ability boundary of multimodal models. Transformer models, as the foundation of modern LLMs, offer a strong baseline with excellent scaling properties. However, the traditional transformer architecture requires substantial computations and poses significant obstacles for large-scale training and practical deployment. In this survey, we offer a systematic examination of innovative LLM architectures that address the inherent limitations of transformers and boost the efficiency. Starting from language modeling, this survey covers the background and technical details of linear and sparse sequence modeling methods, efficient full attention variants, sparse mixture-of-experts, hybrid model architectures incorporating the above techniques, and emerging diffusion LLMs. Additionally, we discuss applications of these techniques to other modalities and consider their wider implications for developing scalable, resource-aware foundation models. By grouping recent studies into the above category, this survey presents a blueprint of modern efficient LLM architectures, and we hope this could help motivate future research toward more efficient, versatile AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09834</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 14:13:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DINOv3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10104</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10104.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Oriane Siméoni, Huy V. Vo, Maximilian Seitzer, Federico Baldassarre, Maxime Oquab, Cijo Jose, Vasil Khalidov, Marc Szafraniec, Seungeun Yi, Michaël Ramamonjisoa, Francisco Massa, Daniel Haziza, Luca Wehrstedt, Jianyuan Wang, Timothée Darcet, Théo Moutakanni, Leonel Sentana, Claire Roberts, Andrea Vedaldi, Jamie Tolan, John Brandt, Camille Couprie, Julien Mairal, Hervé Jégou, Patrick Labatut, Piotr Bojanowski&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 186&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-supervised learning holds the promise of eliminating the need for manual data annotation, enabling models to scale effortlessly to massive datasets and larger architectures. By not being tailored to specific tasks or domains, this training paradigm has the potential to learn visual representations from diverse sources, ranging from natural to aerial images -- using a single algorithm. This technical report introduces DINOv3, a major milestone toward realizing this vision by leveraging simple yet effective strategies. First, we leverage the benefit of scaling both dataset and model size by careful data preparation, design, and optimization. Second, we introduce a new method called Gram anchoring, which effectively addresses the known yet unsolved issue of dense feature maps degrading during long training schedules. Finally, we apply post-hoc strategies that further enhance our models' flexibility with respect to resolution, model size, and alignment with text. As a result, we present a versatile vision foundation model that outperforms the specialized state of the art across a broad range of settings, without fine-tuning. DINOv3 produces high-quality dense features that achieve outstanding performance on various vision tasks, significantly surpassing previous self- and weakly-supervised foundation models. We also share the DINOv3 suite of vision models, designed to advance the state of the art on a wide spectrum of tasks and data by providing scalable solutions for diverse resource constraints and deployment scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10104</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 18:00:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mSCoRe: a Multilingual and Scalable Benchmark for Skill-based   Commonsense Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10137</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10137.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nghia Trung Ngo, Franck Dernoncourt, Thien Huu Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in reasoning-reinforced Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown remarkable capabilities in complex reasoning tasks. However, the mechanism underlying their utilization of different human reasoning skills remains poorly investigated, especially for multilingual commonsense reasoning that involves everyday knowledge across different languages and cultures. To address this gap, we propose a Multilingual and Scalable Benchmark for Skill-based Commonsense Reasoning (mSCoRe). Our benchmark incorporates three key components that are designed to systematically evaluate LLM's reasoning capabilities, including: (1) a novel taxonomy of reasoning skills that enables fine-grained analysis of models' reasoning processes, (2) a robust data synthesis pipeline tailored specifically for commonsense reasoning evaluation, and (3) a complexity scaling framework allowing task difficulty to scale dynamically alongside future improvements in LLM abilities. Extensive experiments on eights state-of-the-art LLMs of varying sizes and training approaches demonstrate that mSCoRe remains significantly challenging for current models, particularly at higher complexity levels. Our results reveal the limitations of such reasoning-reinforced models when confronted with nuanced multilingual general and cultural commonsense. We further provide detailed analysis on the models' reasoning processes, suggesting future directions for improving multilingual commonsense reasoning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10137</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 18:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XQuant: Breaking the Memory Wall for LLM Inference with KV Cache   Rematerialization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10395</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10395.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aditya Tomar, Coleman Hooper, Minjae Lee, Haocheng Xi, Rishabh Tiwari, Wonjun Kang, Luca Manolache, Michael W. Mahoney, Kurt Keutzer, Amir Gholami&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although LLM inference has emerged as a critical workload for many downstream applications, efficiently inferring LLMs is challenging due to the substantial memory footprint and bandwidth requirements. In parallel, compute capabilities have steadily outpaced both memory capacity and bandwidth over the last few decades, a trend that remains evident in modern GPU hardware and exacerbates the challenge of LLM inference. As such, new algorithms are emerging that trade increased computation for reduced memory operations. To that end, we present XQuant, which takes advantage of this trend, enabling an order-of-magnitude reduction in memory consumption through low-bit quantization with substantial accuracy benefits relative to state-of-the-art KV cache quantization methods. We accomplish this by quantizing and caching the layer input activations X, instead of using standard KV caching, and then rematerializing the Keys and Values on-the-fly during inference. This results in an immediate 2times memory savings compared to KV caching. By applying XQuant, we achieve up to sim 7.7times memory savings with &lt;0.1 perplexity degradation compared to the FP16 baseline. Furthermore, our approach leverages the fact that X values are similar across layers. Building on this observation, we introduce XQuant-CL, which exploits the cross-layer similarity in the X embeddings for extreme compression. Across different models, XQuant-CL attains up to 10times memory savings relative to the FP16 baseline with only 0.01 perplexity degradation, and 12.5times memory savings with only 0.1 perplexity degradation. XQuant exploits the rapidly increasing compute capabilities of hardware platforms to eliminate the memory bottleneck, while surpassing state-of-the-art KV cache quantization methods and achieving near-FP16 accuracy across a wide range of models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10395</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 06:52:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ComoRAG: A Cognitive-Inspired Memory-Organized RAG for Stateful Long   Narrative Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10419</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10419.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Juyuan Wang, Rongchen Zhao, Wei Wei, Yufeng Wang, Mo Yu, Jie Zhou, Jin Xu, Liyan Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 69&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Narrative comprehension on long stories and novels has been a challenging domain attributed to their intricate plotlines and entangled, often evolving relations among characters and entities. Given the LLM's diminished reasoning over extended context and high computational cost, retrieval-based approaches remain a pivotal role in practice. However, traditional RAG methods can fall short due to their stateless, single-step retrieval process, which often overlooks the dynamic nature of capturing interconnected relations within long-range context. In this work, we propose ComoRAG, holding the principle that narrative reasoning is not a one-shot process, but a dynamic, evolving interplay between new evidence acquisition and past knowledge consolidation, analogous to human cognition when reasoning with memory-related signals in the brain. Specifically, when encountering a reasoning impasse, ComoRAG undergoes iterative reasoning cycles while interacting with a dynamic memory workspace. In each cycle, it generates probing queries to devise new exploratory paths, then integrates the retrieved evidence of new aspects into a global memory pool, thereby supporting the emergence of a coherent context for the query resolution. Across four challenging long-context narrative benchmarks (200K+ tokens), ComoRAG outperforms strong RAG baselines with consistent relative gains up to 11% compared to the strongest baseline. Further analysis reveals that ComoRAG is particularly advantageous for complex queries requiring global comprehension, offering a principled, cognitively motivated paradigm for retrieval-based long context comprehension towards stateful reasoning. Our code is publicly released at https://github.com/EternityJune25/ComoRAG&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10419</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 07:52:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-Node: Self-Explanation is All We Need</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10461</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10461.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Prajit Sengupta, Islem Rekik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graph neural networks (GNNs) have achieved state-of-the-art results in computer vision and medical image classification tasks by capturing structural dependencies across data instances. However, their decision-making remains largely opaque, limiting their trustworthiness in high-stakes clinical applications where interpretability is essential. Existing explainability techniques for GNNs are typically post-hoc and global, offering limited insight into individual node decisions or local reasoning. We introduce X-Node, a self-explaining GNN framework in which each node generates its own explanation as part of the prediction process. For every node, we construct a structured context vector encoding interpretable cues such as degree, centrality, clustering, feature saliency, and label agreement within its local topology. A lightweight Reasoner module maps this context into a compact explanation vector, which serves three purposes: (1) reconstructing the node's latent embedding via a decoder to enforce faithfulness, (2) generating a natural language explanation using a pre-trained LLM (e.g., Grok or Gemini), and (3) guiding the GNN itself via a "text-injection" mechanism that feeds explanations back into the message-passing pipeline. We evaluate X-Node on two graph datasets derived from MedMNIST and MorphoMNIST, integrating it with GCN, GAT, and GIN backbones. Our results show that X-Node maintains competitive classification accuracy while producing faithful, per-node explanations. Repository: https://github.com/basiralab/X-Node.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10461</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 09:00:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantic IDs for Joint Generative Search and Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10478</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10478.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gustavo Penha, Edoardo D'Amico, Marco De Nadai, Enrico Palumbo, Alexandre Tamborrino, Ali Vardasbi, Max Lefarov, Shawn Lin, Timothy Heath, Francesco Fabbri, Hugues Bouchard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative models powered by Large Language Models (LLMs) are emerging as a unified solution for powering both recommendation and search tasks. A key design choice in these models is how to represent items, traditionally through unique identifiers (IDs) and more recently with Semantic IDs composed of discrete codes, obtained from embeddings. While task-specific embedding models can improve performance for individual tasks, they may not generalize well in a joint setting. In this paper, we explore how to construct Semantic IDs that perform well both in search and recommendation when using a unified model. We compare a range of strategies to construct Semantic IDs, looking into task-specific and cross-tasks approaches, and also whether each task should have its own semantic ID tokens in a joint search and recommendation generative model. Our results show that using a bi-encoder model fine-tuned on both search and recommendation tasks to obtain item embeddings, followed by the construction of a unified Semantic ID space provides an effective trade-off, enabling strong performance in both tasks. We hope these findings spark follow-up work on generalisable, semantically grounded ID schemes and inform the next wave of unified generative recommender architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10478</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 09:28:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MM-BrowseComp: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Multimodal Browsing Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13186</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13186.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shilong Li, Xingyuan Bu, Wenjie Wang, Jiaheng Liu, Jun Dong, Haoyang He, Hao Lu, Haozhe Zhang, Chenchen Jing, Zhen Li, Chuanhao Li, Jiayi Tian, Chenchen Zhang, Tianhao Peng, Yancheng He, Jihao Gu, Yuanxing Zhang, Jian Yang, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Ruizhe Ding, Shilei Wen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI agents with advanced reasoning and tool use capabilities have demonstrated impressive performance in web browsing for deep search. While existing benchmarks such as BrowseComp evaluate these browsing abilities, they primarily focus on textual information, overlooking the prevalence of multimodal content. To bridge this gap, we introduce MM-BrowseComp, a novel benchmark comprising 224 challenging, hand-crafted questions specifically designed to assess agents' multimodal retrieval and reasoning capabilities. These questions often incorporate images in prompts, and crucial information encountered during the search and reasoning process may also be embedded within images or videos on webpages. Consequently, methods relying solely on text prove insufficient for our benchmark. Additionally, we provide a verified checklist for each question, enabling fine-grained analysis of multimodal dependencies and reasoning paths. Our comprehensive evaluation of state-of-the-art models on MM-BrowseComp reveals that even top models like OpenAI o3 with tools achieve only 29.02\% accuracy, highlighting the suboptimal multimodal capabilities and lack of native multimodal reasoning in current models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13186</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 13:46:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advances in Speech Separation: Techniques, Challenges, and Future Trends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10830</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10830.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kai Li, Guo Chen, Wendi Sang, Yi Luo, Zhuo Chen, Shuai Wang, Shulin He, Zhong-Qiu Wang, Andong Li, Zhiyong Wu, Xiaolin Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The field of speech separation, addressing the "cocktail party problem", has seen revolutionary advances with DNNs. Speech separation enhances clarity in complex acoustic environments and serves as crucial pre-processing for speech recognition and speaker recognition. However, current literature focuses narrowly on specific architectures or isolated approaches, creating fragmented understanding. This survey addresses this gap by providing systematic examination of DNN-based speech separation techniques. Our work differentiates itself through: (I) Comprehensive perspective: We systematically investigate learning paradigms, separation scenarios with known/unknown speakers, comparative analysis of supervised/self-supervised/unsupervised frameworks, and architectural components from encoders to estimation strategies. (II) Timeliness: Coverage of cutting-edge developments ensures access to current innovations and benchmarks. (III) Unique insights: Beyond summarization, we evaluate technological trajectories, identify emerging patterns, and highlight promising directions including domain-robust frameworks, efficient architectures, multimodal integration, and novel self-supervised paradigms. (IV) Fair evaluation: We provide quantitative evaluations on standard datasets, revealing true capabilities and limitations of different methods. This comprehensive survey serves as an accessible reference for experienced researchers and newcomers navigating speech separation's complex landscape.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10830</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 16:54:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TexVerse: A Universe of 3D Objects with High-Resolution Textures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10868</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10868.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yibo Zhang, Li Zhang, Rui Ma, Nan Cao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce TexVerse, a large-scale 3D dataset featuring high-resolution textures. While recent advances in large-scale 3D datasets have enhanced high-resolution geometry generation, creating high-resolution textures end-to-end remains underexplored due to the lack of suitable datasets. TexVerse fills this gap with a curated collection of over 858K unique high-resolution 3D models sourced from Sketchfab, including more than 158K models with physically based rendering (PBR) materials. Each model encompasses all of its high-resolution variants, bringing the total to 1.6M 3D instances. TexVerse also includes specialized subsets: TexVerse-Skeleton, with 69K rigged models, and TexVerse-Animation, with 54K animated models, both preserving original skeleton and animation data uploaded by the user. We also provide detailed model annotations describing overall characteristics, structural components, and intricate features. TexVerse offers a high-quality data resource with wide-ranging potential applications in texture synthesis, PBR material development, animation, and various 3D vision and graphics tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10868</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:43:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRL: Self-Search Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10874</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10874.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuchen Fan, Kaiyan Zhang, Heng Zhou, Yuxin Zuo, Yanxu Chen, Yu Fu, Xinwei Long, Xuekai Zhu, Che Jiang, Yuchen Zhang, Li Kang, Gang Chen, Cheng Huang, Zhizhou He, Bingning Wang, Lei Bai, Ning Ding, Bowen Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We investigate the potential of large language models (LLMs) to serve as efficient simulators for agentic search tasks in reinforcement learning (RL), thereby reducing dependence on costly interactions with external search engines. To this end, we first quantify the intrinsic search capability of LLMs via structured prompting and repeated sampling, which we term Self-Search. Our results reveal that LLMs exhibit strong scaling behavior with respect to the inference budget, achieving high pass@k on question-answering benchmarks, including the challenging BrowseComp task. Building on these observations, we introduce Self-Search RL (SSRL), which enhances LLMs' Self-Search capability through format-based and rule-based rewards. SSRL enables models to iteratively refine their knowledge utilization internally, without requiring access to external tools. Empirical evaluations demonstrate that SSRL-trained policy models provide a cost-effective and stable environment for search-driven RL training, reducing reliance on external search engines and facilitating robust sim-to-real transfer. We draw the following conclusions: 1) LLMs possess world knowledge that can be effectively elicited to achieve high performance; 2) SSRL demonstrates the potential of leveraging internal knowledge to reduce hallucination; 3) SSRL-trained models integrate seamlessly with external search engines without additional effort. Our findings highlight the potential of LLMs to support more scalable RL agent training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10874</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:46:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BeyondWeb: Lessons from Scaling Synthetic Data for Trillion-scale   Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10975</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10975.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pratyush Maini, Vineeth Dorna, Parth Doshi, Aldo Carranza, Fan Pan, Jack Urbanek, Paul Burstein, Alex Fang, Alvin Deng, Amro Abbas, Brett Larsen, Cody Blakeney, Charvi Bannur, Christina Baek, Darren Teh, David Schwab, Haakon Mongstad, Haoli Yin, Josh Wills, Kaleigh Mentzer, Luke Merrick, Ricardo Monti, Rishabh Adiga, Siddharth Joshi, Spandan Das, Zhengping Wang, Bogdan Gaza, Ari Morcos, Matthew Leavitt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language model (LLM) pretraining have shown that simply scaling data quantity eventually leads to diminishing returns, hitting a data wall. In response, the use of synthetic data for pretraining has emerged as a promising paradigm for pushing the frontier of performance. Despite this, the factors affecting synthetic data quality remain poorly understood. In this work, we introduce BeyondWeb, a synthetic data generation framework that produces high-quality synthetic data for pretraining. BeyondWeb significantly extends the capabilities of traditional web-scale datasets, outperforming state-of-the-art synthetic pretraining datasets such as Cosmopedia and Nemotron-CC's high-quality synthetic subset (Nemotron-Synth) by up to 5.1 percentage points (pp) and 2.6pp, respectively, when averaged across a suite of 14 benchmark evaluations. It delivers up to 7.7x faster training than open web data and 2.7x faster than Nemotron-Synth. Remarkably, a 3B model trained for 180B tokens on BeyondWeb outperforms an 8B model trained for the same token budget on Cosmopedia. We also present several insights from BeyondWeb on synthetic data for pretraining: what drives its benefits, which data to rephrase and how, and the impact of model size and family on data quality. Overall, our work shows that there's no silver bullet for generating high-quality synthetic pretraining data. The best outcomes require jointly optimizing many factors, a challenging task that requires rigorous science and practical expertise. Naive approaches can yield modest improvements, potentially at great cost, while well-executed methods can yield transformative improvements, as exemplified by BeyondWeb.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10975</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAESTRO: Masked AutoEncoders for Multimodal, Multitemporal, and   Multispectral Earth Observation Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10894</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10894.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Antoine Labatie, Michael Vaccaro, Nina Lardiere, Anatol Garioud, Nicolas Gonthier&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-supervised learning holds great promise for remote sensing, but standard self-supervised methods must be adapted to the unique characteristics of Earth observation data. We take a step in this direction by conducting a comprehensive benchmark of fusion strategies and reconstruction target normalization schemes for multimodal, multitemporal, and multispectral Earth observation data. Based on our findings, we propose MAESTRO, a novel adaptation of the Masked Autoencoder, featuring optimized fusion strategies and a tailored target normalization scheme that introduces a spectral prior as a self-supervisory signal. Evaluated on four Earth observation datasets, MAESTRO sets a new state-of-the-art on tasks that strongly rely on multitemporal dynamics, while remaining highly competitive on tasks dominated by a single mono-temporal modality. Code to reproduce all our experiments is available at https://github.com/ignf/maestro.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10894</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedSAMix: A Training-Free Model Merging Approach for Medical Image   Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11032</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11032.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanwu Yang, Guinan Su, Jiesi Hu, Francesco Sammarco, Jonas Geiping, Thomas Wolfers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal medical image segmentation models have emerged as a promising paradigm due to their strong generalizability across diverse tasks, showing great potential for a wide range of clinical applications. This potential has been partly driven by the success of general-purpose vision models such as the Segment Anything Model (SAM), which has inspired the development of various fine-tuned variants for medical segmentation tasks. However, fine-tuned variants like MedSAM are trained on comparatively limited medical imaging data that often suffers from heterogeneity, scarce annotations, and distributional shifts. These challenges limit their ability to generalize across a wide range of medical segmentation tasks. In this regard, we propose MedSAMix, a training-free model merging method that integrates the strengths of both generalist models (e.g., SAM) and specialist models (e.g., MedSAM) for medical image segmentation. In contrast to traditional model merging approaches that rely on manual configuration and often result in suboptimal outcomes, we propose a zero-order optimization method to automatically discover optimal layer-wise merging solutions. Furthermore, for clinical applications, we develop two regimes to meet the demand of domain-specificity and generalizability in different scenarios by single-task optimization and multi-objective optimization respectively. Extensive evaluations on 25 medical segmentation tasks demonstrate that MedSAMix effectively mitigates model bias and consistently improves performance in both domain-specific accuracy and generalization, achieving improvements of 6.67% on specialized tasks and 4.37% on multi-task evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11032</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 19:35:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PaperRegister: Boosting Flexible-grained Paper Search via Hierarchical   Register Indexing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11116</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11116.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuoqun Li, Xuanang Chen, Hongyu Lin, Yaojie Lu, Xianpei Han, Le Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Paper search is an important activity for researchers, typically involving using a query with description of a topic to find relevant papers. As research deepens, paper search requirements may become more flexible, sometimes involving specific details such as module configuration rather than being limited to coarse-grained topics. However, previous paper search systems are unable to meet these flexible-grained requirements, as these systems mainly collect paper abstracts to construct index of corpus, which lack detailed information to support retrieval by finer-grained queries. In this work, we propose PaperRegister, consisted of offline hierarchical indexing and online adaptive retrieval, transforming traditional abstract-based index into hierarchical index tree for paper search, thereby supporting queries at flexible granularity. Experiments on paper search tasks across a range of granularity demonstrate that PaperRegister achieves the state-of-the-art performance, and particularly excels in fine-grained scenarios, highlighting the good potential as an effective solution for flexible-grained paper search in real-world applications. Code for this work is in https://github.com/Li-Z-Q/PaperRegister.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11116</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 23:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StyleMM: Stylized 3D Morphable Face Model via Text-Driven Aligned Image   Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11203</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11203.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seungmi Lee, Kwan Yun, Junyong Noh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce StyleMM, a novel framework that can construct a stylized 3D Morphable Model (3DMM) based on user-defined text descriptions specifying a target style. Building upon a pre-trained mesh deformation network and a texture generator for original 3DMM-based realistic human faces, our approach fine-tunes these models using stylized facial images generated via text-guided image-to-image (i2i) translation with a diffusion model, which serve as stylization targets for the rendered mesh. To prevent undesired changes in identity, facial alignment, or expressions during i2i translation, we introduce a stylization method that explicitly preserves the facial attributes of the source image. By maintaining these critical attributes during image stylization, the proposed approach ensures consistent 3D style transfer across the 3DMM parameter space through image-based training. Once trained, StyleMM enables feed-forward generation of stylized face meshes with explicit control over shape, expression, and texture parameters, producing meshes with consistent vertex connectivity and animatability. Quantitative and qualitative evaluations demonstrate that our approach outperforms state-of-the-art methods in terms of identity-level facial diversity and stylization capability. The code and videos are available at [kwanyun.github.io/stylemm_page](kwanyun.github.io/stylemm_page).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11203</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 04:29:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Solving Math Quiz: Evaluating the Ability of Large Reasoning   Models to Ask for Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11252</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11252.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Youcheng Huang, Bowen Qin, Chen Huang, Duanyu Feng, Xi Yang, Wenqiang Lei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have demonstrated remarkable problem-solving abilities in mathematics, as evaluated by existing benchmarks exclusively on well-defined problems. However, such evaluation setup constitutes a critical gap, since a genuine intelligent agent should not only solve problems (as a math quiz solver), but also be able~to ask for information when the problems lack sufficient information, enabling proactivity in responding users' requests. To bridge such gap, we proposes a new dataset consisting of two types of incomplete problems with diverse contexts. Based on the dataset, our systematical evaluation of LRMs reveals their inability in proactively asking for information. In addition, we uncover the behaviors related to overthinking and hallucination of LRMs, and highlight the potential and challenges of supervised fine-tuning in learning such ability. We hope to provide new insights in developing LRMs with genuine intelligence, rather than just solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11252</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 06:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FantasyTalking2: Timestep-Layer Adaptive Preference Optimization for   Audio-Driven Portrait Animation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11255</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11255.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; MengChao Wang, Qiang Wang, Fan Jiang, Mu Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in audio-driven portrait animation have demonstrated impressive capabilities. However, existing methods struggle to align with fine-grained human preferences across multiple dimensions, such as motion naturalness, lip-sync accuracy, and visual quality. This is due to the difficulty of optimizing among competing preference objectives, which often conflict with one another, and the scarcity of large-scale, high-quality datasets with multidimensional preference annotations. To address these, we first introduce Talking-Critic, a multimodal reward model that learns human-aligned reward functions to quantify how well generated videos satisfy multidimensional expectations. Leveraging this model, we curate Talking-NSQ, a large-scale multidimensional human preference dataset containing 410K preference pairs. Finally, we propose Timestep-Layer adaptive multi-expert Preference Optimization (TLPO), a novel framework for aligning diffusion-based portrait animation models with fine-grained, multidimensional preferences. TLPO decouples preferences into specialized expert modules, which are then fused across timesteps and network layers, enabling comprehensive, fine-grained enhancement across all dimensions without mutual interference. Experiments demonstrate that Talking-Critic significantly outperforms existing methods in aligning with human preference ratings. Meanwhile, TLPO achieves substantial improvements over baseline models in lip-sync accuracy, motion naturalness, and visual quality, exhibiting superior performance in both qualitative and quantitative evaluations. Ours project page: https://fantasy-amap.github.io/fantasy-talking2/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11255</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 06:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>G-CUT3R: Guided 3D Reconstruction with Camera and Depth Prior   Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11379</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11379.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ramil Khafizov, Artem Komarichev, Ruslan Rakhimov, Peter Wonka, Evgeny Burnaev&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce G-CUT3R, a novel feed-forward approach for guided 3D scene reconstruction that enhances the CUT3R model by integrating prior information. Unlike existing feed-forward methods that rely solely on input images, our method leverages auxiliary data, such as depth, camera calibrations, or camera positions, commonly available in real-world scenarios. We propose a lightweight modification to CUT3R, incorporating a dedicated encoder for each modality to extract features, which are fused with RGB image tokens via zero convolution. This flexible design enables seamless integration of any combination of prior information during inference. Evaluated across multiple benchmarks, including 3D reconstruction and other multi-view tasks, our approach demonstrates significant performance improvements, showing its ability to effectively utilize available priors while maintaining compatibility with varying input modalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11379</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 10:25:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Punctuation Matters: A Large-Scale Comparison of Prompt Robustness   Methods for LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11383</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11383.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mikhail Seleznyov, Mikhail Chaichuk, Gleb Ershov, Alexander Panchenko, Elena Tutubalina, Oleg Somov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are highly sensitive to subtle, non-semantic variations in prompt phrasing and formatting. In this work, we present the first systematic evaluation of 5 methods for improving prompt robustness within a unified experimental framework. We benchmark these techniques on 8 models from Llama, Qwen and Gemma families across 52 tasks from Natural Instructions dataset. Our evaluation covers robustness methods from both fine-tuned and in-context learning paradigms, and tests their generalization against multiple types of distribution shifts. Finally, we extend our analysis to GPT-4.1 and DeepSeek V3 to assess frontier models' current robustness to format perturbations. Our findings offer actionable insights into the relative effectiveness of these robustness methods, enabling practitioners to make informed decisions when aiming for stable and reliable LLM performance in real-world applications. Code: https://github.com/AIRI-Institute/when-punctuation-matters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11383</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 10:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrieval-augmented reasoning with lean language models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11386</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11386.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ryan Sze-Yin Chan, Federico Nanni, Tomas Lazauskas, Rosie Wood, Penelope Yong, Lionel Tarassenko, Mark Girolami, James Geddes, Andrew Duncan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This technical report details a novel approach to combining reasoning and retrieval augmented generation (RAG) within a single, lean language model architecture. While existing RAG systems typically rely on large-scale models and external APIs, our work addresses the increasing demand for performant and privacy-preserving solutions deployable in resource-constrained or secure environments. Building on recent developments in test-time scaling and small-scale reasoning models, we develop a retrieval augmented conversational agent capable of interpreting complex, domain-specific queries using a lightweight backbone model. Our system integrates a dense retriever with fine-tuned Qwen2.5-Instruct models, using synthetic query generation and reasoning traces derived from frontier models (e.g., DeepSeek-R1) over a curated corpus, in this case, the NHS A-to-Z condition pages. We explore the impact of summarisation-based document compression, synthetic data design, and reasoning-aware fine-tuning on model performance. Evaluation against both non-reasoning and general-purpose lean models demonstrates that our domain-specific fine-tuning approach yields substantial gains in answer accuracy and consistency, approaching frontier-level performance while remaining feasible for local deployment. All implementation details and code are publicly released to support reproducibility and adaptation across domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11386</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 10:38:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-Policy RL Meets Off-Policy Experts: Harmonizing Supervised   Fine-Tuning and Reinforcement Learning via Dynamic Weighting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11408</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11408.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenhao Zhang, Yuexiang Xie, Yuchang Sun, Yanxi Chen, Guoyin Wang, Yaliang Li, Bolin Ding, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) and Reinforcement Learning (RL) are two prominent post-training paradigms for refining the capabilities and aligning the behavior of Large Language Models (LLMs). Existing approaches that integrate SFT and RL often face the risk of disrupting established model patterns and inducing overfitting to expert data. To address this, we present a novel investigation into the unified view of SFT and RL through an off-policy versus on-policy lens. We propose CHORD, a framework for the Controllable Harmonization of On- and Off-Policy Reinforcement Learning via Dynamic Weighting, which reframes SFT not as a separate stage but as a dynamically weighted auxiliary objective within the on-policy RL process. Based on an analysis of off-policy expert data's influence at both holistic and granular levels, we incorporate a dual-control mechanism in CHORD. Specifically, the framework first employs a global coefficient to holistically guide the transition from off-policy imitation to on-policy exploration, and then applies a token-wise weighting function that enables granular learning from expert tokens, which preserves on-policy exploration and mitigates disruption from off-policy data. We conduct extensive experiments on widely used benchmarks, providing empirical evidence that CHORD achieves a stable and efficient learning process. By effectively harmonizing off-policy expert data with on-policy exploration, CHORD demonstrates significant improvements over baselines. We release the implementation at https://github.com/modelscope/Trinity-RFT/tree/main/examples/mix_chord to inspire further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11408</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 11:20:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Copyright Protection for Large Language Models: A Survey of Methods,   Challenges, and Trends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11548</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11548.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenhua Xu, Xubin Yue, Zhebo Wang, Qichen Liu, Xixiang Zhao, Jingxuan Zhang, Wenjun Zeng, Wengpeng Xing, Dezhang Kong, Changting Lin, Meng Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Copyright protection for large language models is of critical importance, given their substantial development costs, proprietary value, and potential for misuse. Existing surveys have predominantly focused on techniques for tracing LLM-generated content-namely, text watermarking-while a systematic exploration of methods for protecting the models themselves (i.e., model watermarking and model fingerprinting) remains absent. Moreover, the relationships and distinctions among text watermarking, model watermarking, and model fingerprinting have not been comprehensively clarified. This work presents a comprehensive survey of the current state of LLM copyright protection technologies, with a focus on model fingerprinting, covering the following aspects: (1) clarifying the conceptual connection from text watermarking to model watermarking and fingerprinting, and adopting a unified terminology that incorporates model watermarking into the broader fingerprinting framework; (2) providing an overview and comparison of diverse text watermarking techniques, highlighting cases where such methods can function as model fingerprinting; (3) systematically categorizing and comparing existing model fingerprinting approaches for LLM copyright protection; (4) presenting, for the first time, techniques for fingerprint transfer and fingerprint removal; (5) summarizing evaluation metrics for model fingerprints, including effectiveness, harmlessness, robustness, stealthiness, and reliability; and (6) discussing open challenges and future research directions. This survey aims to offer researchers a thorough understanding of both text watermarking and model fingerprinting technologies in the era of LLMs, thereby fostering further advances in protecting their intellectual property.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11548</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 15:50:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ovis2.5 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11737</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11737.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiyin Lu, Yang Li, Yu Xia, Yuwei Hu, Shanshan Zhao, Yanqing Ma, Zhichao Wei, Yinglun Li, Lunhao Duan, Jianshan Zhao, Yuxuan Han, Haijun Li, Wanying Chen, Junke Tang, Chengkun Hou, Zhixing Du, Tianli Zhou, Wenjie Zhang, Huping Ding, Jiahe Li, Wen Li, Gui Hu, Yiliang Gu, Siran Yang, Jiamang Wang, Hailong Sun, Yibo Wang, Hui Sun, Jinlong Huang, Yuping He, Shengze Shi, Weihong Zhang, Guodong Zheng, Junpeng Jiang, Sensen Gao, Yi-Feng Wu, Sijia Chen, Yuhui Chen, Qing-Guo Chen, Zhao Xu, Weihua Luo, Kaifu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Ovis2.5, a successor to Ovis2 designed for native-resolution visual perception and strong multimodal reasoning. Ovis2.5 integrates a native-resolution vision transformer that processes images at their native, variable resolutions, avoiding the degradation from fixed-resolution tiling and preserving both fine detail and global layout -- crucial for visually dense content like complex charts. To strengthen reasoning, we train the model to move beyond linear chain-of-thought and perform reflection -- including self-checking and revision. This advanced capability is exposed as an optional "thinking mode" at inference time, allowing users to trade latency for enhanced accuracy on difficult inputs. The model is trained via a comprehensive five-phase curriculum that progressively builds its skills. The process begins with foundational visual and multimodal pretraining, advances through large-scale instruction tuning, and culminates in alignment and reasoning enhancement using DPO and GRPO. To scale these upgrades efficiently, we employ multimodal data packing and hybrid parallelism, yielding a significant end-to-end speedup. We release two open-source models: Ovis2.5-9B and Ovis2.5-2B. The latter continues the "small model, big performance" philosophy of Ovis2, making it ideal for resource-constrained, on-device scenarios. On the OpenCompass multimodal leaderboard, Ovis2.5-9B averages 78.3, marking a substantial improvement over its predecessor, Ovis2-8B, and achieving state-of-the-art results among open-source MLLMs in the sub-40B parameter range; Ovis2.5-2B scores 73.9, establishing SOTA for its size. Beyond aggregate scores, Ovis2.5 achieves leading results on STEM benchmarks, exhibits strong capabilities on grounding and video tasks, and achieves open-source SOTA at its scale for complex chart analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11737</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:01:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representing Speech Through Autoregressive Prediction of Cochlear Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11598</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11598.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Greta Tuckute, Klemen Kotar, Evelina Fedorenko, Daniel L. K. Yamins&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce AuriStream, a biologically inspired model for encoding speech via a two-stage framework inspired by the human auditory processing hierarchy. The first stage transforms raw audio into a time-frequency representation based on the human cochlea, from which we extract discrete cochlear tokens. The second stage applies an autoregressive sequence model over the cochlear tokens. AuriStream learns meaningful phoneme and word representations, and state-of-the-art lexical semantics. AuriStream shows competitive performance on diverse downstream SUPERB speech tasks. Complementing AuriStream's strong representational capabilities, it generates continuations of audio which can be visualized in a spectrogram space and decoded back into audio, providing insights into the model's predictions. In summary, we present a two-stage framework for speech representation learning to advance the development of more human-like models that efficiently handle a range of speech-based tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11598</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:06:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling Multimodal LLMs via Reward-guided Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11616</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11616.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Oscar Mañas, Pierluca D'Oro, Koustuv Sinha, Adriana Romero-Soriano, Michal Drozdzal, Aishwarya Agrawal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) gain widespread applicability, it is becoming increasingly desirable to adapt them for diverse user needs. In this paper, we study the adaptation of MLLMs through controlled decoding. To achieve this, we introduce the first method for reward-guided decoding of MLLMs and demonstrate its application in improving their visual grounding. Our method involves building reward models for visual grounding and using them to guide the MLLM's decoding process. Concretely, we build two separate reward models to independently control the degree of object precision and recall in the model's output. Our approach enables on-the-fly controllability of an MLLM's inference process in two ways: first, by giving control over the relative importance of each reward function during decoding, allowing a user to dynamically trade off object precision for recall in image captioning tasks; second, by giving control over the breadth of the search during decoding, allowing the user to control the trade-off between the amount of test-time compute and the degree of visual grounding. We evaluate our method on standard object hallucination benchmarks, showing that it provides significant controllability over MLLM inference, while consistently outperforming existing hallucination mitigation methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11616</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:29:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thyme: Think Beyond Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11630</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11630.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi-Fan Zhang, Xingyu Lu, Shukang Yin, Chaoyou Fu, Wei Chen, Xiao Hu, Bin Wen, Kaiyu Jiang, Changyi Liu, Tianke Zhang, Haonan Fan, Kaibing Chen, Jiankang Chen, Haojie Ding, Kaiyu Tang, Zhang Zhang, Liang Wang, Fan Yang, Tingting Gao, Guorui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Following OpenAI's introduction of the ``thinking with images'' concept, recent efforts have explored stimulating the use of visual information in the reasoning process to enhance model performance in perception and reasoning tasks. However, to the best of our knowledge, no open-source work currently offers a feature set as rich as proprietary models (O3), which can perform diverse image manipulations and simultaneously enhance logical reasoning capabilities through code. In this paper, we make a preliminary attempt in this direction by introducing Thyme (Think Beyond Images), a novel paradigm for enabling MLLMs to transcend existing ``think with images'' approaches by autonomously generating and executing diverse image processing and computational operations via executable code. This approach not only facilitates a rich, on-the-fly set of image manipulations (e.g., cropping, rotation, contrast enhancement) but also allows for mathematical computations, all while maintaining high autonomy in deciding when and how to apply these operations. We activate this capability through a two-stage training strategy: an initial SFT on a curated dataset of 500K samples to teach code generation, followed by a RL phase to refine decision-making. For the RL stage, we manually collect and design high-resolution question-answer pairs to increase the learning difficulty, and we propose GRPO-ATS (Group Relative Policy Optimization with Adaptive Temperature Sampling), an algorithm that applies distinct temperatures to text and code generation to balance reasoning exploration with code execution precision. We conduct extensive experimental analysis and ablation studies. Comprehensive evaluations on nearly 20 benchmarks show that Thyme yields significant and consistent performance gains, particularly in challenging high-resolution perception and complex reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11630</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FutureX: An Advanced Live Benchmark for LLM Agents in Future Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11987</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11987.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Zeng, Jiashuo Liu, Siyuan Chen, Tianci He, Yali Liao, Jinpeng Wang, Zaiyuan Wang, Yang Yang, Lingyue Yin, Mingren Yin, Zhenwei Zhu, Tianle Cai, Zehui Chen, Jiecao Chen, Yantao Du, Xiang Gao, Jiacheng Guo, Liang Hu, Jianpeng Jiao, Xiangsheng Li, Jingkai Liu, Shuang Ni, Zhoufutu Wen, Ge Zhang, Kaiyuan Zhang, Xin Zhou, Jose Blanchet, Xipeng Qiu, Mengdi Wang, Wenhao Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Future prediction is a complex task for LLM agents, requiring a high level of analytical thinking, information gathering, contextual understanding, and decision-making under uncertainty. Agents must not only gather and interpret vast amounts of dynamic information but also integrate diverse data sources, weigh uncertainties, and adapt predictions based on emerging trends, just as human experts do in fields like politics, economics, and finance. Despite its importance, no large-scale benchmark exists for evaluating agents on future prediction, largely due to challenges in handling real-time updates and retrieving timely, accurate answers. To address this, we introduce FutureX, a dynamic and live evaluation benchmark specifically designed for LLM agents performing future prediction tasks. FutureX is the largest and most diverse live benchmark for future prediction, supporting real-time daily updates and eliminating data contamination through an automated pipeline for question gathering and answer collection. We evaluate 25 LLM/agent models, including those with reasoning, search capabilities, and integration of external tools such as the open-source Deep Research Agent and closed-source Deep Research models. This comprehensive evaluation assesses agents' adaptive reasoning and performance in dynamic environments. Additionally, we provide in-depth analyses of agents' failure modes and performance pitfalls in future-oriented tasks, including the vulnerability to fake web pages and the temporal validity. Our goal is to establish a dynamic, contamination-free evaluation standard that drives the development of LLM agents capable of performing at the level of professional human analysts in complex reasoning and predictive thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11987</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 08:54:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mind the Generation Process: Fine-Grained Confidence Estimation During   LLM Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12040</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12040.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinyi Han, Tingyun Li, Shisong Chen, Jie Shi, Xinyi Wang, Guanglei Yue, Jiaqing Liang, Xin Lin, Liqian Wen, Zulong Chen, Yanghua Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable performance across diverse tasks, they fundamentally lack self-awareness and frequently exhibit overconfidence, assigning high confidence scores to incorrect predictions. Accurate confidence estimation is therefore critical for enhancing the trustworthiness and reliability of LLM-generated outputs. However, existing approaches suffer from coarse-grained scoring mechanisms that fail to provide fine-grained, continuous confidence estimates throughout the generation process. To address these limitations, we introduce FineCE, a novel confidence estimation method that delivers accurate, fine-grained confidence scores during text generation. Specifically, we first develop a comprehensive pipeline for constructing training data that effectively captures the underlying probabilistic distribution of LLM responses, and then train a model to predict confidence scores for arbitrary text sequences in a supervised manner. Furthermore, we propose a Backward Confidence Integration (BCI) strategy that leverages information from the subsequent text to enhance confidence estimation for the current sequence during inference. We also introduce three strategies for identifying optimal positions to perform confidence estimation within the generation process. Extensive experiments on multiple benchmark datasets demonstrate that FineCE consistently outperforms existing classical confidence estimation methods. Our code and all baselines used in the paper are available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12040</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 13:29:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse-LLaVA: Eliminating Alignment Pre-training Through Text-to-Vision   Mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12466</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12466.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuhui Zhan, Tyler Derr&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional multimodal learning approaches require expensive alignment pre-training to bridge vision and language modalities, typically projecting visual features into discrete text token spaces. We challenge both fundamental assumptions underlying this paradigm by proposing Inverse-LLaVA, a novel approach that eliminates alignment pre-training entirely while inverting the conventional mapping direction. Rather than projecting visual features to text space, our method maps text embeddings into continuous visual representation space and performs fusion within transformer intermediate layers. Through selective additive components in attention mechanisms, we enable dynamic integration of visual and textual representations without requiring massive image-text alignment datasets. Comprehensive experiments across nine multimodal benchmarks demonstrate nuanced performance trade-offs: Inverse-LLaVA achieves notable improvements on reasoning-intensive and cognitive tasks (MM-VET: +0.2%, VizWiz: +1.8%, ScienceQA: +0.2%, cognitive reasoning: +27.2%), while showing expected decreases in perception tasks requiring memorized visual-text associations (celebrity recognition: -49.5%, OCR: -21.3%). These results provide the first empirical evidence that alignment pre-training is not necessary for effective multimodal learning, particularly for complex reasoning tasks. Our work establishes the feasibility of a new paradigm that reduces computational requirements by 45%, challenges conventional wisdom about modality fusion, and opens new research directions for efficient multimodal architectures that preserve modality-specific characteristics. Our project website with code and additional resources is available at https://inverse-llava.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12466</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 18:36:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CorrSteer: Steering Improves Task Performance and Safety in LLMs through   Correlation-based Sparse Autoencoder Feature Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12535</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12535.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seonglae Cho, Zekun Wu, Adriano Koshiyama&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse Autoencoders (SAEs) can extract interpretable features from large language models (LLMs) without supervision. However, their effectiveness in downstream steering tasks is limited by the requirement for contrastive datasets or large activation storage. To address these limitations, we propose CorrSteer, which selects features by correlating sample correctness with SAE activations from generated tokens at inference time. This approach uses only inference-time activations to extract more relevant features, thereby avoiding spurious correlations. It also obtains steering coefficients from average activations, automating the entire pipeline. Our method shows improved task performance on QA, bias mitigation, jailbreaking prevention, and reasoning benchmarks on Gemma 2 2B and LLaMA 3.1 8B, notably achieving a +4.1% improvement in MMLU performance and a +22.9% improvement in HarmBench with only 4000 samples. Selected features demonstrate semantically meaningful patterns aligned with each task's requirements, revealing the underlying capabilities that drive performance. Our work establishes correlationbased selection as an effective and scalable approach for automated SAE steering across language model applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12535</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:01:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FLARE: Fast Low-rank Attention Routing Engine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12594</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12594.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vedant Puri, Aditya Joglekar, Kevin Ferguson, Yu-hsuan Chen, Yongjie Jessica Zhang, Levent Burak Kara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The quadratic complexity of self-attention limits its applicability and scalability on large unstructured meshes. We introduce Fast Low-rank Attention Routing Engine (FLARE), a linear complexity self-attention mechanism that routes attention through fixed-length latent sequences. Each attention head performs global communication among N tokens by projecting the input sequence onto a fixed length latent sequence of M ll N tokens using learnable query tokens. By routing attention through a bottleneck sequence, FLARE learns a low-rank form of attention that can be applied at O(NM) cost. FLARE not only scales to unprecedented problem sizes, but also delivers superior accuracy compared to state-of-the-art neural PDE surrogates across diverse benchmarks. We also release a new additive manufacturing dataset to spur further research. Our code is available at https://github.com/vpuri3/FLARE.py.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12594</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 03:00:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From AI for Science to Agentic Science: A Survey on Autonomous   Scientific Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14111</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14111.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Wei, Yuejin Yang, Xiang Zhang, Yuhan Chen, Xiang Zhuang, Zhangyang Gao, Dongzhan Zhou, Guangshuai Wang, Zhiqiang Gao, Juntai Cao, Zijie Qiu, Xuming He, Qiang Zhang, Chenyu You, Shuangjia Zheng, Ning Ding, Wanli Ouyang, Nanqing Dong, Yu Cheng, Siqi Sun, Lei Bai, Bowen Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Artificial intelligence (AI) is reshaping scientific discovery, evolving from specialized computational tools into autonomous research partners. We position Agentic Science as a pivotal stage within the broader AI for Science paradigm, where AI systems progress from partial assistance to full scientific agency. Enabled by large language models (LLMs), multimodal systems, and integrated research platforms, agentic AI shows capabilities in hypothesis generation, experimental design, execution, analysis, and iterative refinement -- behaviors once regarded as uniquely human. This survey provides a domain-oriented review of autonomous scientific discovery across life sciences, chemistry, materials science, and physics. We unify three previously fragmented perspectives -- process-oriented, autonomy-oriented, and mechanism-oriented -- through a comprehensive framework that connects foundational capabilities, core processes, and domain-specific realizations. Building on this framework, we (i) trace the evolution of AI for Science, (ii) identify five core capabilities underpinning scientific agency, (iii) model discovery as a dynamic four-stage workflow, (iv) review applications across the above domains, and (v) synthesize key challenges and future opportunities. This work establishes a domain-oriented synthesis of autonomous scientific discovery and positions Agentic Science as a structured paradigm for advancing AI-driven research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14111</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 05:25:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Large Language Models for Predictive Analysis of Human Misery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12669</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12669.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bishanka Seal, Rahul Seetharaman, Aman Bansal, Abhilash Nandy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This study investigates the use of Large Language Models (LLMs) for predicting human-perceived misery scores from natural language descriptions of real-world scenarios. The task is framed as a regression problem, where the model assigns a scalar value from 0 to 100 to each input statement. We evaluate multiple prompting strategies, including zero-shot, fixed-context few-shot, and retrieval-based prompting using BERT sentence embeddings. Few-shot approaches consistently outperform zero-shot baselines, underscoring the value of contextual examples in affective prediction. To move beyond static evaluation, we introduce the "Misery Game Show", a novel gamified framework inspired by a television format. It tests LLMs through structured rounds involving ordinal comparison, binary classification, scalar estimation, and feedback-driven reasoning. This setup enables us to assess not only predictive accuracy but also the model's ability to adapt based on corrective feedback. The gamified evaluation highlights the broader potential of LLMs in dynamic emotional reasoning tasks beyond standard regression. Code and data link: https://github.com/abhi1nandy2/Misery_Data_Exps_GitHub&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12669</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 07:02:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlearning Comparator: A Visual Analytics System for Comparative   Evaluation of Machine Unlearning Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12730</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12730.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaeung Lee, Suhyeon Yu, Yurim Jang, Simon S. Woo, Jaemin Jo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Machine Unlearning (MU) aims to remove target training data from a trained model so that the removed data no longer influences the model's behavior, fulfilling "right to be forgotten" obligations under data privacy laws. Yet, we observe that researchers in this rapidly emerging field face challenges in analyzing and understanding the behavior of different MU methods, especially in terms of three fundamental principles in MU: accuracy, efficiency, and privacy. Consequently, they often rely on aggregate metrics and ad-hoc evaluations, making it difficult to accurately assess the trade-offs between methods. To fill this gap, we introduce a visual analytics system, Unlearning Comparator, designed to facilitate the systematic evaluation of MU methods. Our system supports two important tasks in the evaluation process: model comparison and attack simulation. First, it allows the user to compare the behaviors of two models, such as a model generated by a certain method and a retrained baseline, at class-, instance-, and layer-levels to better understand the changes made after unlearning. Second, our system simulates membership inference attacks (MIAs) to evaluate the privacy of a method, where an attacker attempts to determine whether specific data samples were part of the original training set. We evaluate our system through a case study visually analyzing prominent MU methods and demonstrate that it helps the user not only understand model behaviors but also gain insights that can inform the improvement of MU methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12730</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 08:53:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HeroBench: A Benchmark for Long-Horizon Planning and Structured   Reasoning in Virtual Worlds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12782</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12782.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Petr Anokhin, Roman Khalikov, Stefan Rebrikov, Viktor Volkov, Artyom Sorokin, Vincent Bissonnette&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable capabilities in isolated step-by-step reasoning tasks such as mathematics and programming, but their proficiency in long-horizon planning, where solutions require extended, structured sequences of interdependent actions, remains underexplored. Existing benchmarks typically assess LLMs through abstract or low-dimensional algorithmic tasks, failing to capture the complexity of realistic planning environments. We introduce HeroBench, a novel benchmark designed specifically to evaluate long-horizon planning and structured reasoning within complex RPG-inspired virtual worlds. HeroBench provides a rigorously constructed dataset of tasks covering a wide range of difficulties, a simulated environment to execute and validate agent plans, and detailed analytical tools for evaluating model performance. Tasks challenge models to formulate strategic plans, efficiently gather resources, master necessary skills, craft equipment, and defeat adversaries, reflecting practical scenarios' layered dependencies and constraints. Our extensive evaluation of 25 state-of-the-art LLMs, spanning both open-source and proprietary models, including the GPT-5 family, reveals substantial performance disparities rarely observed in conventional reasoning benchmarks. Detailed error analysis further uncovers specific weaknesses in current models' abilities to generate robust high-level plans and reliably execute structured actions. HeroBench thus not only significantly advances the evaluation of LLM reasoning but also provides a flexible, scalable foundation for future research into advanced, autonomous planning in virtual environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12782</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 09:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning with Rubric Anchors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12790</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12790.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zenan Huang, Yihong Zhuang, Guoshan Lu, Zeyu Qin, Haokai Xu, Tianyu Zhao, Ru Peng, Jiaqi Hu, Zhanming Shen, Xiaomeng Hu, Xijun Gu, Peiyi Tu, Jiaxin Liu, Wenyu Chen, Yuzhuo Fu, Zhiting Fan, Yanmei Gu, Yuanyuan Wang, Zhengkai Yang, Jianguo Li, Junbo Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning from Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as a powerful paradigm for enhancing Large Language Models (LLMs), exemplified by the success of OpenAI's o-series. In RLVR, rewards are derived from verifiable signals-such as passing unit tests in code generation or matching correct answers in mathematical reasoning. While effective, this requirement largely confines RLVR to domains with automatically checkable outcomes. To overcome this, we extend the RLVR paradigm to open-ended tasks by integrating rubric-based rewards, where carefully designed rubrics serve as structured, model-interpretable criteria for automatic scoring of subjective outputs. We construct, to our knowledge, the largest rubric reward system to date, with over 10,000 rubrics from humans, LLMs, or a hybrid human-LLM collaboration. Implementing rubric-based RL is challenging; we tackle these issues with a clear framework and present an open-sourced Qwen-30B-A3B model with notable gains: 1) With only 5K+ samples, our system improves by +5.2% on open-ended benchmarks (especially humanities), outperforming a 671B DeepSeek-V3 model by +2.4%, while preserving general and reasoning abilities. 2) Our method provides fine-grained stylistic control, using rubrics as anchors to mitigate the "AI-like" tone and produce more human-like, expressive responses. We share key lessons in rubric construction, data selection, and training, and discuss limitations and future releases.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12790</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 10:06:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atom-Searcher: Enhancing Agentic Deep Research via Fine-Grained Atomic   Thought Reward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12800</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12800.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yong Deng, Guoqing Wang, Zhenzhe Ying, Xiaofeng Wu, Jinzhen Lin, Wenwen Xiong, Yuqin Dai, Shuo Yang, Zhanwei Zhang, Qiwen Wang, Yang Qin, Changhua Meng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) exhibit remarkable problem-solving abilities, but struggle with complex tasks due to static internal knowledge. Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) enhances access to external information, yet remains limited in multi-hop reasoning and strategic search due to rigid workflows. Recent advancements in agentic deep research empower LLMs to autonomously reason, search, and synthesize information. However, current approaches relying on outcome-based reinforcement learning (RL) face critical issues such as conflicting gradients and reward sparsity, limiting performance gains and training efficiency. To address these, we first propose Atomic Thought, a novel LLM thinking paradigm that decomposes reasoning into fine-grained functional units. These units are supervised by Reasoning Reward Models (RRMs), which provide Atomic Thought Rewards (ATR) for fine-grained guidance. Building on this, we propose Atom-Searcher, a novel RL framework for agentic deep research that integrates Atomic Thought and ATR. Atom-Searcher uses a curriculum-inspired reward schedule, prioritizing process-level ATR early and transitioning to outcome rewards, accelerating convergence on effective reasoning paths. Experiments on seven benchmarks show consistent improvements over the state-of-the-art. Key advantages include: (1) Atom-Searcher scales computation at test-time. (2) Atomic Thought provides supervision anchors for RRMs, bridging deep research tasks and RRMs. (3) Atom-Searcher exhibits more interpretable, human-like reasoning patterns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12800</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 10:23:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next Visual Granularity Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12811</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12811.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yikai Wang, Zhouxia Wang, Zhonghua Wu, Qingyi Tao, Kang Liao, Chen Change Loy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel approach to image generation by decomposing an image into a structured sequence, where each element in the sequence shares the same spatial resolution but differs in the number of unique tokens used, capturing different level of visual granularity. Image generation is carried out through our newly introduced Next Visual Granularity (NVG) generation framework, which generates a visual granularity sequence beginning from an empty image and progressively refines it, from global layout to fine details, in a structured manner. This iterative process encodes a hierarchical, layered representation that offers fine-grained control over the generation process across multiple granularity levels. We train a series of NVG models for class-conditional image generation on the ImageNet dataset and observe clear scaling behavior. Compared to the VAR series, NVG consistently outperforms it in terms of FID scores (3.30 -&gt; 3.03, 2.57 -&gt;2.44, 2.09 -&gt; 2.06). We also conduct extensive analysis to showcase the capability and potential of the NVG framework. Our code and models will be released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12811</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 10:47:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAMAR: Continuous Actions Multi-Agent Routing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12845</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12845.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Artem Pshenitsyn, Aleksandr Panov, Alexey Skrynnik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) is a powerful paradigm for solving cooperative and competitive decision-making problems. While many MARL benchmarks have been proposed, few combine continuous state and action spaces with challenging coordination and planning tasks. We introduce CAMAR, a new MARL benchmark designed explicitly for multi-agent pathfinding in environments with continuous actions. CAMAR supports cooperative and competitive interactions between agents and runs efficiently at up to 100,000 environment steps per second. We also propose a three-tier evaluation protocol to better track algorithmic progress and enable deeper analysis of performance. In addition, CAMAR allows the integration of classical planning methods such as RRT and RRT* into MARL pipelines. We use them as standalone baselines and combine RRT* with popular MARL algorithms to create hybrid approaches. We provide a suite of test scenarios and benchmarking tools to ensure reproducibility and fair comparison. Experiments show that CAMAR presents a challenging and realistic testbed for the MARL community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12845</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 11:32:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S^2-Guidance: Stochastic Self Guidance for Training-Free Enhancement of   Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12880</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12880.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chubin Chen, Jiashu Zhu, Xiaokun Feng, Nisha Huang, Meiqi Wu, Fangyuan Mao, Jiahong Wu, Xiangxiang Chu, Xiu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Classifier-free Guidance (CFG) is a widely used technique in modern diffusion models for enhancing sample quality and prompt adherence. However, through an empirical analysis on Gaussian mixture modeling with a closed-form solution, we observe a discrepancy between the suboptimal results produced by CFG and the ground truth. The model's excessive reliance on these suboptimal predictions often leads to semantic incoherence and low-quality outputs. To address this issue, we first empirically demonstrate that the model's suboptimal predictions can be effectively refined using sub-networks of the model itself. Building on this insight, we propose S^2-Guidance, a novel method that leverages stochastic block-dropping during the forward process to construct stochastic sub-networks, effectively guiding the model away from potential low-quality predictions and toward high-quality outputs. Extensive qualitative and quantitative experiments on text-to-image and text-to-video generation tasks demonstrate that S^2-Guidance delivers superior performance, consistently surpassing CFG and other advanced guidance strategies. Our code will be released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12880</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 12:31:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Stitch in Time Saves Nine: Proactive Self-Refinement for Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12903</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12903.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinyi Han, Xinyi Wang, Haiquan Zhao, Tingyun li, Zishang Jiang, Sihang Jiang, Jiaqing Liang, Xin Lin, Weikang Zhou, Zeye Sun, Fei Yu, Yanghua Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in self-refinement have demonstrated significant potential for improving the outputs of large language models (LLMs) through iterative refinement. However, most existing self-refinement methods rely on a reactive process with a fixed number of iterations, making it difficult to determine the optimal timing and content of refinement based on the evolving generation context. Inspired by the way humans dynamically refine their thoughts during execution, we propose ProActive Self-Refinement (PASR), a novel method that enables LLMs to refine their outputs during the generation process. Unlike methods that regenerate entire responses, PASR proactively decides whether, when, and how to refine based on the model's internal state and evolving context. We conduct extensive experiments on a diverse set of 10 tasks to evaluate the effectiveness of PASR. Experimental results show that PASR significantly enhances problem-solving performance. In particular, on Qwen3-8B, PASR reduces average token consumption by 41.6 percent compared to standard generation, while also achieving an 8.2 percent improvement in accuracy. Our code and all baselines used in the paper are available in the GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12903</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 13:07:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lumen: Consistent Video Relighting and Harmonious Background Replacement   with Video Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12945</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12945.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianshu Zeng, Yuxuan Liu, Yutong Feng, Chenxuan Miao, Zixiang Gao, Jiwang Qu, Jianzhang Zhang, Bin Wang, Kun Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video relighting is a challenging yet valuable task, aiming to replace the background in videos while correspondingly adjusting the lighting in the foreground with harmonious blending. During translation, it is essential to preserve the original properties of the foreground, e.g., albedo, and propagate consistent relighting among temporal frames. In this paper, we propose Lumen, an end-to-end video relighting framework developed on large-scale video generative models, receiving flexible textual description for instructing the control of lighting and background. Considering the scarcity of high-qualified paired videos with the same foreground in various lighting conditions, we construct a large-scale dataset with a mixture of realistic and synthetic videos. For the synthetic domain, benefiting from the abundant 3D assets in the community, we leverage advanced 3D rendering engine to curate video pairs in diverse environments. For the realistic domain, we adapt a HDR-based lighting simulation to complement the lack of paired in-the-wild videos. Powered by the aforementioned dataset, we design a joint training curriculum to effectively unleash the strengths of each domain, i.e., the physical consistency in synthetic videos, and the generalized domain distribution in realistic videos. To implement this, we inject a domain-aware adapter into the model to decouple the learning of relighting and domain appearance distribution. We construct a comprehensive benchmark to evaluate Lumen together with existing methods, from the perspectives of foreground preservation and video consistency assessment. Experimental results demonstrate that Lumen effectively edit the input into cinematic relighted videos with consistent lighting and strict foreground preservation. Our project page: https://lumen-relight.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12945</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 14:21:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix-Game 2.0: An Open-Source, Real-Time, and Streaming Interactive   World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13009</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13009.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xianglong He, Chunli Peng, Zexiang Liu, Boyang Wang, Yifan Zhang, Qi Cui, Fei Kang, Biao Jiang, Mengyin An, Yangyang Ren, Baixin Xu, Hao-Xiang Guo, Kaixiong Gong, Cyrus Wu, Wei Li, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Eric Li, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in interactive video generations have demonstrated diffusion model's potential as world models by capturing complex physical dynamics and interactive behaviors. However, existing interactive world models depend on bidirectional attention and lengthy inference steps, severely limiting real-time performance. Consequently, they are hard to simulate real-world dynamics, where outcomes must update instantaneously based on historical context and current actions. To address this, we present Matrix-Game 2.0, an interactive world model generates long videos on-the-fly via few-step auto-regressive diffusion. Our framework consists of three key components: (1) A scalable data production pipeline for Unreal Engine and GTA5 environments to effectively produce massive amounts (about 1200 hours) of video data with diverse interaction annotations; (2) An action injection module that enables frame-level mouse and keyboard inputs as interactive conditions; (3) A few-step distillation based on the casual architecture for real-time and streaming video generation. Matrix Game 2.0 can generate high-quality minute-level videos across diverse scenes at an ultra-fast speed of 25 FPS. We open-source our model weights and codebase to advance research in interactive world modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13009</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 15:28:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise Action-to-Video Generation Through Visual Action Prompts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13104</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13104.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuang Wang, Chao Wen, Haoyu Guo, Sida Peng, Minghan Qin, Hujun Bao, Xiaowei Zhou, Ruizhen Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present visual action prompts, a unified action representation for action-to-video generation of complex high-DoF interactions while maintaining transferable visual dynamics across domains. Action-driven video generation faces a precision-generality trade-off: existing methods using text, primitive actions, or coarse masks offer generality but lack precision, while agent-centric action signals provide precision at the cost of cross-domain transferability. To balance action precision and dynamic transferability, we propose to "render" actions into precise visual prompts as domain-agnostic representations that preserve both geometric precision and cross-domain adaptability for complex actions; specifically, we choose visual skeletons for their generality and accessibility. We propose robust pipelines to construct skeletons from two interaction-rich data sources - human-object interactions (HOI) and dexterous robotic manipulation - enabling cross-domain training of action-driven generative models. By integrating visual skeletons into pretrained video generation models via lightweight fine-tuning, we enable precise action control of complex interaction while preserving the learning of cross-domain dynamics. Experiments on EgoVid, RT-1 and DROID demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed approach. Project page: https://zju3dv.github.io/VAP/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13104</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:12:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion2Motion: Cross-topology Motion Transfer with Sparse Correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13139</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13139.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ling-Hao Chen, Yuhong Zhang, Zixin Yin, Zhiyang Dou, Xin Chen, Jingbo Wang, Taku Komura, Lei Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This work studies the challenge of transfer animations between characters whose skeletal topologies differ substantially. While many techniques have advanced retargeting techniques in decades, transfer motions across diverse topologies remains less-explored. The primary obstacle lies in the inherent topological inconsistency between source and target skeletons, which restricts the establishment of straightforward one-to-one bone correspondences. Besides, the current lack of large-scale paired motion datasets spanning different topological structures severely constrains the development of data-driven approaches. To address these limitations, we introduce Motion2Motion, a novel, training-free framework. Simply yet effectively, Motion2Motion works with only one or a few example motions on the target skeleton, by accessing a sparse set of bone correspondences between the source and target skeletons. Through comprehensive qualitative and quantitative evaluations, we demonstrate that Motion2Motion achieves efficient and reliable performance in both similar-skeleton and cross-species skeleton transfer scenarios. The practical utility of our approach is further evidenced by its successful integration in downstream applications and user interfaces, highlighting its potential for industrial applications. Code and data are available at https://lhchen.top/Motion2Motion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13139</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:50:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Has GPT-5 Achieved Spatial Intelligence? An Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13142</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13142.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongang Cai, Yubo Wang, Qingping Sun, Ruisi Wang, Chenyang Gu, Wanqi Yin, Zhiqian Lin, Zhitao Yang, Chen Wei, Xuanke Shi, Kewang Deng, Xiaoyang Han, Zukai Chen, Jiaqi Li, Xiangyu Fan, Hanming Deng, Lewei Lu, Bo Li, Ziwei Liu, Quan Wang, Dahua Lin, Lei Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-modal models have achieved remarkable progress in recent years. Nevertheless, they continue to exhibit notable limitations in spatial understanding and reasoning, which are fundamental capabilities to achieving artificial general intelligence. With the recent release of GPT-5, allegedly the most powerful AI model to date, it is timely to examine where the leading models stand on the path toward spatial intelligence. First, we propose a comprehensive taxonomy of spatial tasks that unifies existing benchmarks and discuss the challenges in ensuring fair evaluation. We then evaluate state-of-the-art proprietary and open-source models on eight key benchmarks, at a cost exceeding one billion total tokens. Our empirical study reveals that (1) GPT-5 demonstrates unprecedented strength in spatial intelligence, yet (2) still falls short of human performance across a broad spectrum of tasks. Moreover, we (3) identify the more challenging spatial intelligence problems for multi-modal models, and (4) proprietary models do not exhibit a decisive advantage when facing the most difficult problems. In addition, we conduct a qualitative evaluation across a diverse set of scenarios that are intuitive for humans yet fail even the most advanced multi-modal models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13142</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:55:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4DNeX: Feed-Forward 4D Generative Modeling Made Easy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13154</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13154.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoxi Chen, Tianqi Liu, Long Zhuo, Jiawei Ren, Zeng Tao, He Zhu, Fangzhou Hong, Liang Pan, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present 4DNeX, the first feed-forward framework for generating 4D (i.e., dynamic 3D) scene representations from a single image. In contrast to existing methods that rely on computationally intensive optimization or require multi-frame video inputs, 4DNeX enables efficient, end-to-end image-to-4D generation by fine-tuning a pretrained video diffusion model. Specifically, 1) to alleviate the scarcity of 4D data, we construct 4DNeX-10M, a large-scale dataset with high-quality 4D annotations generated using advanced reconstruction approaches. 2) we introduce a unified 6D video representation that jointly models RGB and XYZ sequences, facilitating structured learning of both appearance and geometry. 3) we propose a set of simple yet effective adaptation strategies to repurpose pretrained video diffusion models for 4D modeling. 4DNeX produces high-quality dynamic point clouds that enable novel-view video synthesis. Extensive experiments demonstrate that 4DNeX outperforms existing 4D generation methods in efficiency and generalizability, offering a scalable solution for image-to-4D modeling and laying the foundation for generative 4D world models that simulate dynamic scene evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13154</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapidly Adapting to New Voice Spoofing: Few-Shot Detection of   Synthesized Speech Under Distribution Shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13320</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13320.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ashi Garg, Zexin Cai, Henry Li Xinyuan, Leibny Paola García-Perera, Kevin Duh, Sanjeev Khudanpur, Matthew Wiesner, Nicholas Andrews&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We address the challenge of detecting synthesized speech under distribution shifts -- arising from unseen synthesis methods, speakers, languages, or audio conditions -- relative to the training data. Few-shot learning methods are a promising way to tackle distribution shifts by rapidly adapting on the basis of a few in-distribution samples. We propose a self-attentive prototypical network to enable more robust few-shot adaptation. To evaluate our approach, we systematically compare the performance of traditional zero-shot detectors and the proposed few-shot detectors, carefully controlling training conditions to introduce distribution shifts at evaluation time. In conditions where distribution shifts hamper the zero-shot performance, our proposed few-shot adaptation technique can quickly adapt using as few as 10 in-distribution samples -- achieving upto 32% relative EER reduction on deepfakes in Japanese language and 20% relative reduction on ASVspoof 2021 Deepfake dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13320</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 19:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtuous Machines: Towards Artificial General Science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13421</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13421.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gabrielle Wehr, Reuben Rideaux, Amaya J. Fox, David R. Lightfoot, Jason Tangen, Jason B. Mattingley, Shane E. Ehrhardt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Artificial intelligence systems are transforming scientific discovery by accelerating specific research tasks, from protein structure prediction to materials design, yet remain confined to narrow domains requiring substantial human oversight. The exponential growth of scientific literature and increasing domain specialisation constrain researchers' capacity to synthesise knowledge across disciplines and develop unifying theories, motivating exploration of more general-purpose AI systems for science. Here we show that a domain-agnostic, agentic AI system can independently navigate the scientific workflow - from hypothesis generation through data collection to manuscript preparation. The system autonomously designed and executed three psychological studies on visual working memory, mental rotation, and imagery vividness, executed one new online data collection with 288 participants, developed analysis pipelines through 8-hour+ continuous coding sessions, and produced completed manuscripts. The results demonstrate the capability of AI scientific discovery pipelines to conduct non-trivial research with theoretical reasoning and methodological rigour comparable to experienced researchers, though with limitations in conceptual nuance and theoretical interpretation. This is a step toward embodied AI that can test hypotheses through real-world experiments, accelerating discovery by autonomously exploring regions of scientific space that human cognitive and resource constraints might otherwise leave unexplored. It raises important questions about the nature of scientific understanding and the attribution of scientific credit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13421</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:35:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Scores to Skills: A Cognitive Diagnosis Framework for Evaluating   Financial Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13491</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13491.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyan Kuang, Feiyu Zhu, Maowei Jiang, Yanzhao Lai, Zelin Wang, Zhitong Wang, Meikang Qiu, Jiajia Huang, Min Peng, Qianqian Xie, Sophia Ananiadou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown promise for financial applications, yet their suitability for this high-stakes domain remains largely unproven due to inadequacies in existing benchmarks. Existing benchmarks solely rely on score-level evaluation, summarizing performance with a single score that obscures the nuanced understanding of what models truly know and their precise limitations. They also rely on datasets that cover only a narrow subset of financial concepts, while overlooking other essentials for real-world applications. To address these gaps, we introduce FinCDM, the first cognitive diagnosis evaluation framework tailored for financial LLMs, enabling the evaluation of LLMs at the knowledge-skill level, identifying what financial skills and knowledge they have or lack based on their response patterns across skill-tagged tasks, rather than a single aggregated number. We construct CPA-QKA, the first cognitively informed financial evaluation dataset derived from the Certified Public Accountant (CPA) examination, with comprehensive coverage of real-world accounting and financial skills. It is rigorously annotated by domain experts, who author, validate, and annotate questions with high inter-annotator agreement and fine-grained knowledge labels. Our extensive experiments on 30 proprietary, open-source, and domain-specific LLMs show that FinCDM reveals hidden knowledge gaps, identifies under-tested areas such as tax and regulatory reasoning overlooked by traditional benchmarks, and uncovers behavioral clusters among models. FinCDM introduces a new paradigm for financial LLM evaluation by enabling interpretable, skill-aware diagnosis that supports more trustworthy and targeted model development, and all datasets and evaluation scripts will be publicly released to support further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13491</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 03:52:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniTry: Virtual Try-On Anything without Masks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13632</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13632.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yutong Feng, Linlin Zhang, Hengyuan Cao, Yiming Chen, Xiaoduan Feng, Jian Cao, Yuxiong Wu, Bin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Virtual Try-ON (VTON) is a practical and widely-applied task, for which most of existing works focus on clothes. This paper presents OmniTry, a unified framework that extends VTON beyond garment to encompass any wearable objects, e.g., jewelries and accessories, with mask-free setting for more practical application. When extending to various types of objects, data curation is challenging for obtaining paired images, i.e., the object image and the corresponding try-on result. To tackle this problem, we propose a two-staged pipeline: For the first stage, we leverage large-scale unpaired images, i.e., portraits with any wearable items, to train the model for mask-free localization. Specifically, we repurpose the inpainting model to automatically draw objects in suitable positions given an empty mask. For the second stage, the model is further fine-tuned with paired images to transfer the consistency of object appearance. We observed that the model after the first stage shows quick convergence even with few paired samples. OmniTry is evaluated on a comprehensive benchmark consisting of 12 common classes of wearable objects, with both in-shop and in-the-wild images. Experimental results suggest that OmniTry shows better performance on both object localization and ID-preservation compared with existing methods. The code, model weights, and evaluation benchmark of OmniTry will be made publicly available at https://omnitry.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13632</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 08:47:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ViExam: Are Vision Language Models Better than Humans on Vietnamese   Multimodal Exam Questions?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13680</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13680.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vy Tuong Dang, An Vo, Quang Tau, Duc Dm, Daeyoung Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision language models (VLMs) demonstrate remarkable capabilities on English multimodal tasks, but their performance on low-resource languages with genuinely multimodal educational content remains largely unexplored. In this work, we test how VLMs perform on Vietnamese educational assessments, investigating whether VLMs trained predominantly on English data can handle real-world cross-lingual multimodal reasoning. Our work presents the first comprehensive evaluation of VLM capabilities on multimodal Vietnamese exams through proposing ViExam, a benchmark containing 2,548 multimodal questions. We find that state-of-the-art VLMs achieve only 57.74% while open-source models achieve 27.70% mean accuracy across 7 academic domains, including Mathematics, Physics, Chemistry, Biology, Geography, Driving Test, and IQ Test. Most VLMs underperform average human test-takers (66.54%), with only the thinking VLM o3 (74.07%) exceeding human average performance, yet still falling substantially short of human best performance (99.60%). Cross-lingual prompting with English instructions while maintaining Vietnamese content fails to improve performance, decreasing accuracy by 1 percentage point for SOTA VLMs. Human-in-the-loop collaboration can partially improve VLM performance by 5 percentage points. Code and data are available at: https://vi-exam.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13680</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 09:31:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refining Contrastive Learning and Homography Relations for Multi-Modal   Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13745</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13745.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shouxing Ma, Yawen Zeng, Shiqing Wu, Guandong Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-modal recommender system focuses on utilizing rich modal information ( i.e., images and textual descriptions) of items to improve recommendation performance. The current methods have achieved remarkable success with the powerful structure modeling capability of graph neural networks. However, these methods are often hindered by sparse data in real-world scenarios. Although contrastive learning and homography ( i.e., homogeneous graphs) are employed to address the data sparsity challenge, existing methods still suffer two main limitations: 1) Simple multi-modal feature contrasts fail to produce effective representations, causing noisy modal-shared features and loss of valuable information in modal-unique features; 2) The lack of exploration of the homograph relations between user interests and item co-occurrence results in incomplete mining of user-item interplay.   To address the above limitations, we propose a novel framework for REfining multi-modAl contRastive learning and hoMography relations (REARM). Specifically, we complement multi-modal contrastive learning by employing meta-network and orthogonal constraint strategies, which filter out noise in modal-shared features and retain recommendation-relevant information in modal-unique features. To mine homogeneous relationships effectively, we integrate a newly constructed user interest graph and an item co-occurrence graph with the existing user co-occurrence and item semantic graphs for graph learning. The extensive experiments on three real-world datasets demonstrate the superiority of REARM to various state-of-the-art baselines. Our visualization further shows an improvement made by REARM in distinguishing between modal-shared and modal-unique features. Code is available https://github.com/MrShouxingMa/REARM{here}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13745</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 11:35:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Human Judgment: A Bayesian Evaluation of LLMs' Moral Values   Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13804</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13804.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Maciej Skorski, Alina Landowska&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; How do large language models understand moral dimensions compared to humans?   This first large-scale Bayesian evaluation of market-leading language models provides the answer. In contrast to prior work using deterministic ground truth (majority or inclusion rules), we model annotator disagreements to capture both aleatoric uncertainty (inherent human disagreement) and epistemic uncertainty (model domain sensitivity). We evaluate top language models (Claude Sonnet 4, DeepSeek-V3, Llama 4 Maverick) across 250K+ annotations from ~700 annotators on 100K+ texts spanning social media, news, and forums.   Our GPU-optimized Bayesian framework processed 1M+ model queries, revealing that AI models typically rank among the top 25\% of human annotators, achieving much better-than-average balanced accuracy. Importantly, we find that AI produces far fewer false negatives than humans, highlighting their more sensitive moral detection capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13804</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 13:05:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prompt Orchestration Markup Language</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13948</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13948.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuge Zhang, Nan Chen, Jiahang Xu, Yuqing Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) require sophisticated prompting, yet current practices face challenges in structure, data integration, format sensitivity, and tooling. Existing methods lack comprehensive solutions for organizing complex prompts involving diverse data types (documents, tables, images) or managing presentation variations systematically. To address these gaps, we introduce POML (Prompt Orchestration Markup Language). POML employs component-based markup for logical structure (roles, tasks, examples), specialized tags for seamless data integration, and a CSS-like styling system to decouple content from presentation, reducing formatting sensitivity. It includes templating for dynamic prompts and a comprehensive developer toolkit (IDE support, SDKs) to improve version control and collaboration. We validate POML through two case studies demonstrating its impact on complex application integration (PomLink) and accuracy performance (TableQA), as well as a user study assessing its effectiveness in real-world development scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13948</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 15:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RotBench: Evaluating Multimodal Large Language Models on Identifying   Image Rotation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13968</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13968.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyi Niu, Jaemin Cho, Elias Stengel-Eskin, Mohit Bansal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We investigate to what extent Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) can accurately identify the orientation of input images rotated 0{\deg}, 90{\deg}, 180{\deg}, and 270{\deg}. This task demands robust visual reasoning capabilities to detect rotational cues and contextualize spatial relationships within images, regardless of their orientation. To evaluate MLLMs on these abilities, we introduce RotBench -- a 350-image manually-filtered benchmark comprising lifestyle, portrait, and landscape images. Despite the relatively simple nature of this task, we show that several state-of-the-art open and proprietary MLLMs, including GPT-5, o3, and Gemini-2.5-Pro, do not reliably identify rotation in input images. Providing models with auxiliary information -- including captions, depth maps, and more -- or using chain-of-thought prompting offers only small and inconsistent improvements. Our results indicate that most models are able to reliably identify right-side-up (0{\deg}) images, while certain models are able to identify upside-down (180{\deg}) images. None can reliably distinguish between 90{\deg} and 270{\deg}. Simultaneously showing the image rotated in different orientations leads to moderate performance gains for reasoning models, while a modified setup using voting improves the performance of weaker models. We further show that fine-tuning does not improve models' ability to distinguish 90{\deg} and 270{\deg} rotations, despite substantially improving the identification of 180{\deg} images. Together, these results reveal a significant gap between MLLMs' spatial reasoning capabilities and human perception in identifying rotation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13968</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 15:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMAU-Pro: A Challenging and Comprehensive Benchmark for Holistic   Evaluation of Audio General Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13992</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13992.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sonal Kumar, Šimon Sedláček, Vaibhavi Lokegaonkar, Fernando López, Wenyi Yu, Nishit Anand, Hyeonggon Ryu, Lichang Chen, Maxim Plička, Miroslav Hlaváček, William Fineas Ellingwood, Sathvik Udupa, Siyuan Hou, Allison Ferner, Sara Barahona, Cecilia Bolaños, Satish Rahi, Laura Herrera-Alarcón, Satvik Dixit, Siddhi Patil, Soham Deshmukh, Lasha Koroshinadze, Yao Liu, Leibny Paola Garcia Perera, Eleni Zanou, Themos Stafylakis, Joon Son Chung, David Harwath, Chao Zhang, Dinesh Manocha, Alicia Lozano-Diez, Santosh Kesiraju, Sreyan Ghosh, Ramani Duraiswami&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Audio comprehension-including speech, non-speech sounds, and music-is essential for achieving human-level intelligence. Consequently, AI agents must demonstrate holistic audio understanding to qualify as generally intelligent. However, evaluating auditory intelligence comprehensively remains challenging. To address this gap, we introduce MMAU-Pro, the most comprehensive and rigorously curated benchmark for assessing audio intelligence in AI systems. MMAU-Pro contains 5,305 instances, where each instance has one or more audios paired with human expert-generated question-answer pairs, spanning speech, sound, music, and their combinations. Unlike existing benchmarks, MMAU-Pro evaluates auditory intelligence across 49 unique skills and multiple complex dimensions, including long-form audio comprehension, spatial audio reasoning, multi-audio understanding, among others. All questions are meticulously designed to require deliberate multi-hop reasoning, including both multiple-choice and open-ended response formats. Importantly, audio data is sourced directly ``from the wild" rather than from existing datasets with known distributions. We evaluate 22 leading open-source and proprietary multimodal AI models, revealing significant limitations: even state-of-the-art models such as Gemini 2.5 Flash and Audio Flamingo 3 achieve only 59.2% and 51.7% accuracy, respectively, approaching random performance in multiple categories. Our extensive analysis highlights specific shortcomings and provides novel insights, offering actionable perspectives for the community to enhance future AI systems' progression toward audio general intelligence. The benchmark and code is available at https://sonalkum.github.io/mmau-pro.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13992</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 16:33:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied-R1: Reinforced Embodied Reasoning for General Robotic   Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13998</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13998.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifu Yuan, Haiqin Cui, Yaoting Huang, Yibin Chen, Fei Ni, Zibin Dong, Pengyi Li, Yan Zheng, Jianye Hao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generalization in embodied AI is hindered by the "seeing-to-doing gap," which stems from data scarcity and embodiment heterogeneity. To address this, we pioneer "pointing" as a unified, embodiment-agnostic intermediate representation, defining four core embodied pointing abilities that bridge high-level vision-language comprehension with low-level action primitives. We introduce Embodied-R1, a 3B Vision-Language Model (VLM) specifically designed for embodied reasoning and pointing. We use a wide range of embodied and general visual reasoning datasets as sources to construct a large-scale dataset, Embodied-Points-200K, which supports key embodied pointing capabilities. We then train Embodied-R1 using a two-stage Reinforced Fine-tuning (RFT) curriculum with a specialized multi-task reward design. Embodied-R1 achieves state-of-the-art performance on 11 embodied spatial and pointing benchmarks. Critically, it demonstrates robust zero-shot generalization by achieving a 56.2% success rate in the SIMPLEREnv and 87.5% across 8 real-world XArm tasks without any task-specific fine-tuning, representing a 62% improvement over strong baselines. Furthermore, the model exhibits high robustness against diverse visual disturbances. Our work shows that a pointing-centric representation, combined with an RFT training paradigm, offers an effective and generalizable pathway to closing the perception-action gap in robotics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13998</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 16:50:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongSplat: Robust Unposed 3D Gaussian Splatting for Casual Long Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14041</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14041.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chin-Yang Lin, Cheng Sun, Fu-En Yang, Min-Hung Chen, Yen-Yu Lin, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LongSplat addresses critical challenges in novel view synthesis (NVS) from casually captured long videos characterized by irregular camera motion, unknown camera poses, and expansive scenes. Current methods often suffer from pose drift, inaccurate geometry initialization, and severe memory limitations. To address these issues, we introduce LongSplat, a robust unposed 3D Gaussian Splatting framework featuring: (1) Incremental Joint Optimization that concurrently optimizes camera poses and 3D Gaussians to avoid local minima and ensure global consistency; (2) a robust Pose Estimation Module leveraging learned 3D priors; and (3) an efficient Octree Anchor Formation mechanism that converts dense point clouds into anchors based on spatial density. Extensive experiments on challenging benchmarks demonstrate that LongSplat achieves state-of-the-art results, substantially improving rendering quality, pose accuracy, and computational efficiency compared to prior approaches. Project page: https://linjohnss.github.io/longsplat/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14041</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RynnEC: Bringing MLLMs into Embodied World</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14160</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14160.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ronghao Dang, Yuqian Yuan, Yunxuan Mao, Kehan Li, Jiangpin Liu, Zhikai Wang, Xin Li, Fan Wang, Deli Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce RynnEC, a video multimodal large language model designed for embodied cognition. Built upon a general-purpose vision-language foundation model, RynnEC incorporates a region encoder and a mask decoder, enabling flexible region-level video interaction. Despite its compact architecture, RynnEC achieves state-of-the-art performance in object property understanding, object segmentation, and spatial reasoning. Conceptually, it offers a region-centric video paradigm for the brain of embodied agents, providing fine-grained perception of the physical world and enabling more precise interactions. To mitigate the scarcity of annotated 3D datasets, we propose an egocentric video based pipeline for generating embodied cognition data. Furthermore, we introduce RynnEC-Bench, a region-centered benchmark for evaluating embodied cognitive capabilities. We anticipate that RynnEC will advance the development of general-purpose cognitive cores for embodied agents and facilitate generalization across diverse embodied tasks. The code, model checkpoints, and benchmark are available at: https://github.com/alibaba-damo-academy/RynnEC&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14160</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 18:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local Scale Equivariance with Latent Deep Equilibrium Canonicalizer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14187</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14187.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Md Ashiqur Rahman, Chiao-An Yang, Michael N. Cheng, Lim Jun Hao, Jeremiah Jiang, Teck-Yian Lim, Raymond A. Yeh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scale variation is a fundamental challenge in computer vision. Objects of the same class can have different sizes, and their perceived size is further affected by the distance from the camera. These variations are local to the objects, i.e., different object sizes may change differently within the same image. To effectively handle scale variations, we present a deep equilibrium canonicalizer (DEC) to improve the local scale equivariance of a model. DEC can be easily incorporated into existing network architectures and can be adapted to a pre-trained model. Notably, we show that on the competitive ImageNet benchmark, DEC improves both model performance and local scale consistency across four popular pre-trained deep-nets, e.g., ViT, DeiT, Swin, and BEiT. Our code is available at https://github.com/ashiq24/local-scale-equivariance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14187</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 18:21:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NVIDIA Nemotron Nano 2: An Accurate and Efficient Hybrid   Mamba-Transformer Reasoning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14444</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14444.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NVIDIA, Aarti Basant, Abhijit Khairnar, Abhijit Paithankar, Abhinav Khattar, Adi Renduchintala, Adithya Renduchintala, Aditya Malte, Akhiad Bercovich, Akshay Hazare, Alejandra Rico, Aleksander Ficek, Alex Kondratenko, Alex Shaposhnikov, Ali Taghibakhshi, Amelia Barton, Ameya Sunil Mahabaleshwarkar, Amy Shen, Andrew Tao, Ann Guan, Anna Shors, Anubhav Mandarwal, Arham Mehta, Arun Venkatesan, Ashton Sharabiani, Ashwath Aithal, Ashwin Poojary, Ayush Dattagupta, Balaram Buddharaju, Banghua Zhu, Barnaby Simkin, Bilal Kartal, Bita Darvish Rouhani, Bobby Chen, Boris Ginsburg, Brandon Norick, Brian Yu, Bryan Catanzaro, Charles Wang, Charlie Truong, Chetan Mungekar, Chintan Patel, Chris Alexiuk, Christian Munley, Christopher Parisien, Dan Su, Daniel Afrimi, Daniel Korzekwa, Daniel Rohrer, Daria Gitman, David Mosallanezhad, Deepak Narayanan, Dima Rekesh, Dina Yared, Dmytro Pykhtar, Dong Ahn, Duncan Riach, Eileen Long, Elliott Ning, Eric Chung, Erick Galinkin, Evelina Bakhturina, Gargi Prasad, Gerald Shen, Haim Elisha, Harsh Sharma, Hayley Ross, Helen Ngo, Herman Sahota, Hexin Wang, Hoo Chang Shin, Hua Huang, Iain Cunningham, Igor Gitman, Ivan Moshkov, Jaehun Jung, Jan Kautz, Jane Polak Scowcroft, Jared Casper, Jimmy Zhang, Jinze Xue, Jocelyn Huang, Joey Conway, John Kamalu, Jonathan Cohen, Joseph Jennings, Julien Veron Vialard, Junkeun Yi, Jupinder Parmar, Kari Briski, Katherine Cheung, Katherine Luna, Keith Wyss, Keshav Santhanam, Kezhi Kong, Krzysztof Pawelec, Kumar Anik, Kunlun Li, Kushan Ahmadian, Lawrence McAfee, Laya Sleiman, Leon Derczynski, Luis Vega, Maer Rodrigues de Melo, Makesh Narsimhan Sreedhar, Marcin Chochowski, Mark Cai, Markus Kliegl, Marta Stepniewska-Dziubinska, Matvei Novikov, Mehrzad Samadi, Meredith Price, Meriem Boubdir, Michael Boone, Michael Evans, Michal Bien, Michal Zawalski, Miguel Martinez, Mike Chrzanowski, Mohammad Shoeybi, Mostofa Patwary, Namit Dhameja, Nave Assaf, Negar Habibi, Nidhi Bhatia, Nikki Pope, Nima Tajbakhsh, Nirmal Kumar Juluru, Oleg Rybakov, Oleksii Hrinchuk, Oleksii Kuchaiev, Oluwatobi Olabiyi, Pablo Ribalta, Padmavathy Subramanian, Parth Chadha, Pavlo Molchanov, Peter Dykas, Peter Jin, Piotr Bialecki, Piotr Januszewski, Pradeep Thalasta, Prashant Gaikwad, Prasoon Varshney, Pritam Gundecha, Przemek Tredak, Rabeeh Karimi Mahabadi, Rajen Patel, Ran El-Yaniv, Ranjit Rajan, Ria Cheruvu, Rima Shahbazyan, Ritika Borkar, Ritu Gala, Roger Waleffe, Ruoxi Zhang, Russell J. Hewett, Ryan Prenger, Sahil Jain, Samuel Kriman, Sanjeev Satheesh, Saori Kaji, Sarah Yurick, Saurav Muralidharan, Sean Narenthiran, Seonmyeong Bak, Sepehr Sameni, Seungju Han, Shanmugam Ramasamy, Shaona Ghosh, Sharath Turuvekere Sreenivas, Shelby Thomas, Shizhe Diao, Shreya Gopal, Shrimai Prabhumoye, Shubham Toshniwal, Shuoyang Ding, Siddharth Singh, Siddhartha Jain, Somshubra Majumdar, Stefania Alborghetti, Syeda Nahida Akter, Terry Kong, Tim Moon, Tomasz Hliwiak, Tomer Asida, Tony Wang, Twinkle Vashishth, Tyler Poon, Udi Karpas, Vahid Noroozi, Venkat Srinivasan, Vijay Korthikanti, Vikram Fugro, Vineeth Kalluru, Vitaly Kurin, Vitaly Lavrukhin, Wasi Uddin Ahmad, Wei Du, Wonmin Byeon, Ximing Lu, Xin Dong, Yashaswi Karnati, Yejin Choi, Yian Zhang, Ying Lin, Yonggan Fu, Yoshi Suhara, Zhen Dong, Zhiyu Li, Zhongbo Zhu, Zijia Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2, a hybrid Mamba-Transformer language model designed to increase throughput for reasoning workloads while achieving state-of-the-art accuracy compared to similarly-sized models. Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2 builds on the Nemotron-H architecture, in which the majority of the self-attention layers in the common Transformer architecture are replaced with Mamba-2 layers, to achieve improved inference speed when generating the long thinking traces needed for reasoning. We create Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2 by first pre-training a 12-billion-parameter model (Nemotron-Nano-12B-v2-Base) on 20 trillion tokens using an FP8 training recipe. After aligning Nemotron-Nano-12B-v2-Base, we employ the Minitron strategy to compress and distill the model with the goal of enabling inference on up to 128k tokens on a single NVIDIA A10G GPU (22GiB of memory, bfloat16 precision). Compared to existing similarly-sized models (e.g., Qwen3-8B), we show that Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2 achieves on-par or better accuracy on reasoning benchmarks while achieving up to 6x higher inference throughput in reasoning settings like 8k input and 16k output tokens. We are releasing Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2, Nemotron-Nano12B-v2-Base, and Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2-Base checkpoints along with the majority of our pre- and post-training datasets on Hugging Face.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14444</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 06:00:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DuPO: Enabling Reliable LLM Self-Verification via Dual Preference   Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14460</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14460.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuaijie She, Yu Bao, Yu Lu, Lu Xu, Tao Li, Wenhao Zhu, Shujian Huang, Shanbo Cheng, Lu Lu, Yuxuan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present DuPO, a dual learning-based preference optimization framework that generates annotation-free feedback via a generalized duality. DuPO addresses two key limitations: Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR)'s reliance on costly labels and applicability restricted to verifiable tasks, and traditional dual learning's restriction to strictly dual task pairs (e.g., translation and back-translation). Specifically, DuPO decomposes a primal task's input into known and unknown components, then constructs its dual task to reconstruct the unknown part using the primal output and known information (e.g., reversing math solutions to recover hidden variables), broadening applicability to non-invertible tasks. The quality of this reconstruction serves as a self-supervised reward to optimize the primal task, synergizing with LLMs' ability to instantiate both tasks via a single model. Empirically, DuPO achieves substantial gains across diverse tasks: it enhances the average translation quality by 2.13 COMET over 756 directions, boosts the mathematical reasoning accuracy by an average of 6.4 points on three challenge benchmarks, and enhances performance by 9.3 points as an inference-time reranker (trading computation for accuracy). These results position DuPO as a scalable, general, and annotation-free paradigm for LLM optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14460</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 06:31:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leuvenshtein: Efficient FHE-based Edit Distance Computation with Single   Bootstrap per Cell</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14568</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14568.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wouter Legiest, Jan-Pieter D'Anvers, Bojan Spasic, Nam-Luc Tran, Ingrid Verbauwhede&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents a novel approach to calculating the Levenshtein (edit) distance within the framework of Fully Homomorphic Encryption (FHE), specifically targeting third-generation schemes like TFHE. Edit distance computations are essential in applications across finance and genomics, such as DNA sequence alignment. We introduce an optimised algorithm that significantly reduces the cost of edit distance calculations called Leuvenshtein. This algorithm specifically reduces the number of programmable bootstraps (PBS) needed per cell of the calculation, lowering it from approximately 94 operations -- required by the conventional Wagner-Fisher algorithm -- to just 1. Additionally, we propose an efficient method for performing equality checks on characters, reducing ASCII character comparisons to only 2 PBS operations. Finally, we explore the potential for further performance improvements by utilising preprocessing when one of the input strings is unencrypted. Our Leuvenshtein achieves up to 278times faster performance compared to the best available TFHE implementation and up to 39times faster than an optimised implementation of the Wagner-Fisher algorithm. Moreover, when offline preprocessing is possible due to the presence of one unencrypted input on the server side, an additional 3times speedup can be achieved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14568</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 09:40:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MCP-Universe: Benchmarking Large Language Models with Real-World Model   Context Protocol Servers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14704</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14704.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyang Luo, Zhiqi Shen, Wenzhuo Yang, Zirui Zhao, Prathyusha Jwalapuram, Amrita Saha, Doyen Sahoo, Silvio Savarese, Caiming Xiong, Junnan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Model Context Protocol has emerged as a transformative standard for connecting large language models to external data sources and tools, rapidly gaining adoption across major AI providers and development platforms. However, existing benchmarks are overly simplistic and fail to capture real application challenges such as long-horizon reasoning and large, unfamiliar tool spaces. To address this critical gap, we introduce MCP-Universe, the first comprehensive benchmark specifically designed to evaluate LLMs in realistic and hard tasks through interaction with real-world MCP servers. Our benchmark encompasses 6 core domains spanning 11 different MCP servers: Location Navigation, Repository Management, Financial Analysis, 3D Design, Browser Automation, and Web Searching. To ensure rigorous evaluation, we implement execution-based evaluators, including format evaluators for agent format compliance, static evaluators for time-invariant content matching, and dynamic evaluators that automatically retrieve real-time ground truth for temporally sensitive tasks. Through extensive evaluation of leading LLMs, we find that even SOTA models such as GPT-5 (43.72%), Grok-4 (33.33%) and Claude-4.0-Sonnet (29.44%) exhibit significant performance limitations. In addition, our benchmark poses a significant long-context challenge for LLM agents, as the number of input tokens increases rapidly with the number of interaction steps. Moreover, it introduces an unknown-tools challenge, as LLM agents often lack familiarity with the precise usage of the MCP servers. Notably, enterprise-level agents like Cursor cannot achieve better performance than standard ReAct frameworks. Beyond evaluation, we open-source our extensible evaluation framework with UI support, enabling researchers and practitioners to seamlessly integrate new agents and MCP servers while fostering innovation in the rapidly evolving MCP ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14704</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 13:28:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tinker: Diffusion's Gift to 3D--Multi-View Consistent Editing From   Sparse Inputs without Per-Scene Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14811</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14811.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Canyu Zhao, Xiaoman Li, Tianjian Feng, Zhiyue Zhao, Hao Chen, Chunhua Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Tinker, a versatile framework for high-fidelity 3D editing that operates in both one-shot and few-shot regimes without any per-scene finetuning. Unlike prior techniques that demand extensive per-scene optimization to ensure multi-view consistency or to produce dozens of consistent edited input views, Tinker delivers robust, multi-view consistent edits from as few as one or two images. This capability stems from repurposing pretrained diffusion models, which unlocks their latent 3D awareness. To drive research in this space, we curate the first large-scale multi-view editing dataset and data pipeline, spanning diverse scenes and styles. Building on this dataset, we develop our framework capable of generating multi-view consistent edited views without per-scene training, which consists of two novel components: (1) Referring multi-view editor: Enables precise, reference-driven edits that remain coherent across all viewpoints. (2) Any-view-to-video synthesizer: Leverages spatial-temporal priors from video diffusion to perform high-quality scene completion and novel-view generation even from sparse inputs. Through extensive experiments, Tinker significantly reduces the barrier to generalizable 3D content creation, achieving state-of-the-art performance on editing, novel-view synthesis, and rendering enhancement tasks. We believe that Tinker represents a key step towards truly scalable, zero-shot 3D editing. Project webpage: https://aim-uofa.github.io/Tinker&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14811</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 16:02:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MeshCoder: LLM-Powered Structured Mesh Code Generation from Point Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14879</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14879.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bingquan Dai, Li Ray Luo, Qihong Tang, Jie Wang, Xinyu Lian, Hao Xu, Minghan Qin, Xudong Xu, Bo Dai, Haoqian Wang, Zhaoyang Lyu, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reconstructing 3D objects into editable programs is pivotal for applications like reverse engineering and shape editing. However, existing methods often rely on limited domain-specific languages (DSLs) and small-scale datasets, restricting their ability to model complex geometries and structures. To address these challenges, we introduce MeshCoder, a novel framework that reconstructs complex 3D objects from point clouds into editable Blender Python scripts. We develop a comprehensive set of expressive Blender Python APIs capable of synthesizing intricate geometries. Leveraging these APIs, we construct a large-scale paired object-code dataset, where the code for each object is decomposed into distinct semantic parts. Subsequently, we train a multimodal large language model (LLM) that translates 3D point cloud into executable Blender Python scripts. Our approach not only achieves superior performance in shape-to-code reconstruction tasks but also facilitates intuitive geometric and topological editing through convenient code modifications. Furthermore, our code-based representation enhances the reasoning capabilities of LLMs in 3D shape understanding tasks. Together, these contributions establish MeshCoder as a powerful and flexible solution for programmatic 3D shape reconstruction and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14879</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 17:50:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snap-Snap: Taking Two Images to Reconstruct 3D Human Gaussians in   Milliseconds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14892</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14892.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jia Lu, Taoran Yi, Jiemin Fang, Chen Yang, Chuiyun Wu, Wei Shen, Wenyu Liu, Qi Tian, Xinggang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reconstructing 3D human bodies from sparse views has been an appealing topic, which is crucial to broader the related applications. In this paper, we propose a quite challenging but valuable task to reconstruct the human body from only two images, i.e., the front and back view, which can largely lower the barrier for users to create their own 3D digital humans. The main challenges lie in the difficulty of building 3D consistency and recovering missing information from the highly sparse input. We redesign a geometry reconstruction model based on foundation reconstruction models to predict consistent point clouds even input images have scarce overlaps with extensive human data training. Furthermore, an enhancement algorithm is applied to supplement the missing color information, and then the complete human point clouds with colors can be obtained, which are directly transformed into 3D Gaussians for better rendering quality. Experiments show that our method can reconstruct the entire human in 190 ms on a single NVIDIA RTX 4090, with two images at a resolution of 1024x1024, demonstrating state-of-the-art performance on the THuman2.0 and cross-domain datasets. Additionally, our method can complete human reconstruction even with images captured by low-cost mobile devices, reducing the requirements for data collection. Demos and code are available at https://hustvl.github.io/Snap-Snap/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14892</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 17:59:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization Meets dLLMs: A Systematic Study of Post-training   Quantization for Diffusion LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14896</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14896.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haokun Lin, Haobo Xu, Yichen Wu, Ziyu Guo, Renrui Zhang, Zhichao Lu, Ying Wei, Qingfu Zhang, Zhenan Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in diffusion large language models (dLLMs) have introduced a promising alternative to autoregressive (AR) LLMs for natural language generation tasks, leveraging full attention and denoising-based decoding strategies. However, the deployment of these models on edge devices remains challenging due to their massive parameter scale and high resource demands. While post-training quantization (PTQ) has emerged as a widely adopted technique for compressing AR LLMs, its applicability to dLLMs remains largely unexplored. In this work, we present the first systematic study on quantizing diffusion-based language models. We begin by identifying the presence of activation outliers, characterized by abnormally large activation values that dominate the dynamic range. These outliers pose a key challenge to low-bit quantization, as they make it difficult to preserve precision for the majority of values. More importantly, we implement state-of-the-art PTQ methods and conduct a comprehensive evaluation across multiple task types and model variants. Our analysis is structured along four key dimensions: bit-width, quantization method, task category, and model type. Through this multi-perspective evaluation, we offer practical insights into the quantization behavior of dLLMs under different configurations. We hope our findings provide a foundation for future research in efficient dLLM deployment. All codes and experimental setups will be released to support the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14896</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 17:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>aiXiv: A Next-Generation Open Access Ecosystem for Scientific Discovery   Generated by AI Scientists</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15126</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15126.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengsong Zhang, Xiang Hu, Guowei Huang, Yang Qi, Heng Zhang, Xiuxu Li, Jiaxing Song, Jiabin Luo, Yijiang Li, Shuo Yin, Chengxiao Dai, Eric Hanchen Jiang, Xiaoyan Zhou, Zhenfei Yin, Boqin Yuan, Jing Dong, Guinan Su, Guanren Qiao, Haiming Tang, Anghong Du, Lili Pan, Zhenzhong Lan, Xinyu Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have enabled AI agents to autonomously generate scientific proposals, conduct experiments, author papers, and perform peer reviews. Yet this flood of AI-generated research content collides with a fragmented and largely closed publication ecosystem. Traditional journals and conferences rely on human peer review, making them difficult to scale and often reluctant to accept AI-generated research content; existing preprint servers (e.g. arXiv) lack rigorous quality-control mechanisms. Consequently, a significant amount of high-quality AI-generated research lacks appropriate venues for dissemination, hindering its potential to advance scientific progress. To address these challenges, we introduce aiXiv, a next-generation open-access platform for human and AI scientists. Its multi-agent architecture allows research proposals and papers to be submitted, reviewed, and iteratively refined by both human and AI scientists. It also provides API and MCP interfaces that enable seamless integration of heterogeneous human and AI scientists, creating a scalable and extensible ecosystem for autonomous scientific discovery. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate that aiXiv is a reliable and robust platform that significantly enhances the quality of AI-generated research proposals and papers after iterative revising and reviewing on aiXiv. Our work lays the groundwork for a next-generation open-access ecosystem for AI scientists, accelerating the publication and dissemination of high-quality AI-generated research content. Code is available at https://github.com/aixiv-org. Website is available at https://forms.gle/DxQgCtXFsJ4paMtn8.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15126</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 23:16:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobile-Agent-v3: Foundamental Agents for GUI Automation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15144</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15144.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiabo Ye, Xi Zhang, Haiyang Xu, Haowei Liu, Junyang Wang, Zhaoqing Zhu, Ziwei Zheng, Feiyu Gao, Junjie Cao, Zhengxi Lu, Jitong Liao, Qi Zheng, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces GUI-Owl, a foundational GUI agent model that achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-source end-to-end models on ten GUI benchmarks across desktop and mobile environments, covering grounding, question answering, planning, decision-making, and procedural knowledge. GUI-Owl-7B achieves 66.4 on AndroidWorld and 29.4 on OSWorld. Building on this, we propose Mobile-Agent-v3, a general-purpose GUI agent framework that further improves performance to 73.3 on AndroidWorld and 37.7 on OSWorld, setting a new state-of-the-art for open-source GUI agent frameworks. GUI-Owl incorporates three key innovations: (1) Large-scale Environment Infrastructure: a cloud-based virtual environment spanning Android, Ubuntu, macOS, and Windows, enabling our Self-Evolving GUI Trajectory Production framework. This generates high-quality interaction data via automated query generation and correctness validation, leveraging GUI-Owl to refine trajectories iteratively, forming a self-improving loop. It supports diverse data pipelines and reduces manual annotation. (2) Diverse Foundational Agent Capabilities: by integrating UI grounding, planning, action semantics, and reasoning patterns, GUI-Owl supports end-to-end decision-making and can act as a modular component in multi-agent systems. (3) Scalable Environment RL: we develop a scalable reinforcement learning framework with fully asynchronous training for real-world alignment. We also introduce Trajectory-aware Relative Policy Optimization (TRPO) for online RL, achieving 34.9 on OSWorld. GUI-Owl and Mobile-Agent-v3 are open-sourced at https://github.com/X-PLUG/MobileAgent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15144</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:39:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fin-PRM: A Domain-Specialized Process Reward Model for Financial   Reasoning in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15202</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15202.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuanchen Zhou, Shuo Jiang, Jie Zhu, Junhui Li, Lifan Guo, Feng Chen, Chi Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Process Reward Models (PRMs) have emerged as a promising framework for supervising intermediate reasoning in large language models (LLMs), yet existing PRMs are primarily trained on general or Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) domains and fall short in domain-specific contexts such as finance, where reasoning is more structured, symbolic, and sensitive to factual and regulatory correctness. We introduce Fin-PRM, a domain-specialized, trajectory-aware PRM tailored to evaluate intermediate reasoning steps in financial tasks. Fin-PRM integrates step-level and trajectory-level reward supervision, enabling fine-grained evaluation of reasoning traces aligned with financial logic. We apply Fin-PRM in both offline and online reward learning settings, supporting three key applications: (i) selecting high-quality reasoning trajectories for distillation-based supervised fine-tuning, (ii) providing dense process-level rewards for reinforcement learning, and (iii) guiding reward-informed Best-of-N inference at test time. Experimental results on financial reasoning benchmarks, including CFLUE and FinQA, demonstrate that Fin-PRM consistently outperforms general-purpose PRMs and strong domain baselines in trajectory selection quality. Downstream models trained with Fin-PRM yield substantial improvements with baselines, with gains of 12.9\% in supervised learning, 5.2\% in reinforcement learning, and 5.1\% in test-time performance. These findings highlight the value of domain-specialized reward modeling for aligning LLMs with expert-level financial reasoning. Our project resources will be available at https://github.com/aliyun/qwen-dianjin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15202</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 03:31:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Think with Confidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15260</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15260.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yichao Fu, Xuewei Wang, Yuandong Tian, Jiawei Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown great potential in reasoning tasks through test-time scaling methods like self-consistency with majority voting. However, this approach often leads to diminishing returns in accuracy and high computational overhead. To address these challenges, we introduce Deep Think with Confidence (DeepConf), a simple yet powerful method that enhances both reasoning efficiency and performance at test time. DeepConf leverages model-internal confidence signals to dynamically filter out low-quality reasoning traces during or after generation. It requires no additional model training or hyperparameter tuning and can be seamlessly integrated into existing serving frameworks. We evaluate DeepConf across a variety of reasoning tasks and the latest open-source models, including Qwen 3 and GPT-OSS series. Notably, on challenging benchmarks such as AIME 2025, DeepConf@512 achieves up to 99.9% accuracy and reduces generated tokens by up to 84.7% compared to full parallel thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15260</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 05:48:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Large Language Model Benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15361</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15361.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiwen Ni, Guhong Chen, Shuaimin Li, Xuanang Chen, Siyi Li, Bingli Wang, Qiyao Wang, Xingjian Wang, Yifan Zhang, Liyang Fan, Chengming Li, Ruifeng Xu, Le Sun, Min Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In recent years, with the rapid development of the depth and breadth of large language models' capabilities, various corresponding evaluation benchmarks have been emerging in increasing numbers. As a quantitative assessment tool for model performance, benchmarks are not only a core means to measure model capabilities but also a key element in guiding the direction of model development and promoting technological innovation. We systematically review the current status and development of large language model benchmarks for the first time, categorizing 283 representative benchmarks into three categories: general capabilities, domain-specific, and target-specific. General capability benchmarks cover aspects such as core linguistics, knowledge, and reasoning; domain-specific benchmarks focus on fields like natural sciences, humanities and social sciences, and engineering technology; target-specific benchmarks pay attention to risks, reliability, agents, etc. We point out that current benchmarks have problems such as inflated scores caused by data contamination, unfair evaluation due to cultural and linguistic biases, and lack of evaluation on process credibility and dynamic environments, and provide a referable design paradigm for future benchmark innovation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15361</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 08:43:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLaSO: A Foundational Framework for Reproducible Research in Large   Language and Speech Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15418</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15418.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yirong Sun, Yizhong Geng, Peidong Wei, Yanjun Chen, Jinghan Yang, Rongfei Chen, Wei Zhang, Xiaoyu Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The development of Large Speech-Language Models (LSLMs) has been slowed by fragmented architectures and a lack of transparency, hindering the systematic comparison and reproducibility of research. Unlike in the vision-language domain, the LSLM field suffers from the common practice of releasing model weights without their corresponding training data and configurations. To address these critical gaps, we introduce LLaSO, the first fully open, end-to-end framework for large-scale speech-language modeling. LLaSO provides the community with three essential resources: (1) LLaSO-Align, a 12M-instance speech-text alignment corpus; (2) LLaSO-Instruct, a 13.5M-instance multi-task instruction-tuning dataset; and (3) LLaSO-Eval, a reproducible benchmark for standardized evaluation. To validate our framework, we build and release LLaSO-Base, a 3.8B-parameter reference model trained exclusively on our public data. It achieves a normalized score of 0.72, establishing a strong, reproducible baseline that surpasses comparable models. Our analysis reveals that while broader training coverage enhances performance, significant generalization gaps persist on unseen tasks, particularly in pure audio scenarios. By releasing the complete stack of data, benchmarks, and models, LLaSO establishes a foundational open standard to unify research efforts and accelerate community-driven progress in LSLMs. We release the code, dataset, pretrained models, and results in https://github.com/EIT-NLP/LLaSO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15418</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When and What: Diffusion-Grounded VideoLLM with Entity Aware   Segmentation for Long Video Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15641</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15641.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengcheng Fang, Yuxia Chen, Rui Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding videos requires more than answering open ended questions, it demands the ability to pinpoint when events occur and how entities interact across time. While recent Video LLMs have achieved remarkable progress in holistic reasoning, they remain coarse in temporal perception: timestamps are encoded only implicitly, frame level features are weak in capturing continuity, and language vision alignment often drifts from the entities of interest. In this paper, we present Grounded VideoDiT, a Video LLM designed to overcome these limitations by introducing three key innovations. First, a Diffusion Temporal Latent (DTL) encoder enhances boundary sensitivity and maintains temporal consistency. Second, object grounded representations explicitly bind query entities to localized visual evidence, strengthening alignment. Third, a mixed token scheme with discrete temporal tokens provides explicit timestamp modeling, enabling fine grained temporal reasoning. Together, these designs equip Grounded VideoDiT with robust grounding capabilities, as validated by state of the art results on Charades STA, NExT GQA, and multiple VideoQA benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15641</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 15:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"Does the cafe entrance look accessible? Where is the door?" Towards   Geospatial AI Agents for Visual Inquiries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15752</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15752.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jon E. Froehlich, Jared Hwang, Zeyu Wang, John S. O'Meara, Xia Su, William Huang, Yang Zhang, Alex Fiannaca, Philip Nelson, Shaun Kane&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Interactive digital maps have revolutionized how people travel and learn about the world; however, they rely on pre-existing structured data in GIS databases (e.g., road networks, POI indices), limiting their ability to address geo-visual questions related to what the world looks like. We introduce our vision for Geo-Visual Agents--multimodal AI agents capable of understanding and responding to nuanced visual-spatial inquiries about the world by analyzing large-scale repositories of geospatial images, including streetscapes (e.g., Google Street View), place-based photos (e.g., TripAdvisor, Yelp), and aerial imagery (e.g., satellite photos) combined with traditional GIS data sources. We define our vision, describe sensing and interaction approaches, provide three exemplars, and enumerate key challenges and opportunities for future work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15752</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:49:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissecting Tool-Integrated Reasoning: An Empirical Study and Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15754</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15754.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yufeng Zhao, Junnan Liu, Hongwei Liu, Dongsheng Zhu, Yuan Shen, Songyang Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have made significant strides in reasoning tasks through methods like chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning. However, they often fall short in tasks requiring precise computations. Tool-Integrated Reasoning (TIR) has emerged as a solution by incorporating external tools into the reasoning process. Nevertheless, the generalization of TIR in improving the reasoning ability of LLM is still unclear. Additionally, whether TIR has improved the model's reasoning behavior and helped the model think remains to be studied. We introduce ReasonZoo, a comprehensive benchmark encompassing nine diverse reasoning categories, to evaluate the effectiveness of TIR across various domains. Additionally, we propose two novel metrics, Performance-Aware Cost (PAC) and Area Under the Performance-Cost Curve (AUC-PCC), to assess reasoning efficiency. Our empirical evaluation demonstrates that TIR-enabled models consistently outperform their non-TIR counterparts in both mathematical and non-mathematical tasks. Furthermore, TIR enhances reasoning efficiency, as evidenced by improved PAC and AUC-PCC, indicating reduced overthinking and more streamlined reasoning. These findings underscore the domain-general benefits of TIR and its potential to advance LLM capabilities in complex reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15754</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:50:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiveMCP-101: Stress Testing and Diagnosing MCP-enabled Agents on   Challenging Queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15760</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15760.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Yin, Dinghan Shen, Silei Xu, Jianbing Han, Sixun Dong, Mian Zhang, Yebowen Hu, Shujian Liu, Simin Ma, Song Wang, Sathish Reddy Indurthi, Xun Wang, Yiran Chen, Kaiqiang Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Tool calling has emerged as a critical capability for AI agents to interact with the real world and solve complex tasks. While the Model Context Protocol (MCP) provides a powerful standardized framework for tool integration, there is a significant gap in benchmarking how well AI agents can effectively solve multi-step tasks using diverse MCP tools in realistic, dynamic scenarios. In this work, we present LiveMCP-101, a benchmark of 101 carefully curated real-world queries, refined through iterative LLM rewriting and manual review, that require coordinated use of multiple MCP tools including web search, file operations, mathematical reasoning, and data analysis. Moreover, we introduce a novel evaluation approach that leverages ground-truth execution plans rather than raw API outputs, better reflecting the evolving nature of real-world environments. Experiments show that even frontier LLMs achieve a success rate below 60\%, highlighting major challenges in tool orchestration. Detailed ablations and error analysis further reveal distinct failure modes and inefficiencies in token usage, pointing to concrete directions for advancing current models. LiveMCP-101 sets a rigorous standard for evaluating real-world agent capabilities, advancing toward autonomous AI systems that reliably execute complex tasks through tool use.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15760</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:55:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Waver: Wave Your Way to Lifelike Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15761</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15761.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifu Zhang, Hao Yang, Yuqi Zhang, Yifei Hu, Fengda Zhu, Chuang Lin, Xiaofeng Mei, Yi Jiang, Zehuan Yuan, Bingyue Peng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Waver, a high-performance foundation model for unified image and video generation. Waver can directly generate videos with durations ranging from 5 to 10 seconds at a native resolution of 720p, which are subsequently upscaled to 1080p. The model simultaneously supports text-to-video (T2V), image-to-video (I2V), and text-to-image (T2I) generation within a single, integrated framework. We introduce a Hybrid Stream DiT architecture to enhance modality alignment and accelerate training convergence. To ensure training data quality, we establish a comprehensive data curation pipeline and manually annotate and train an MLLM-based video quality model to filter for the highest-quality samples. Furthermore, we provide detailed training and inference recipes to facilitate the generation of high-quality videos. Building on these contributions, Waver excels at capturing complex motion, achieving superior motion amplitude and temporal consistency in video synthesis. Notably, it ranks among the Top 3 on both the T2V and I2V leaderboards at Artificial Analysis (data as of 2025-07-30 10:00 GMT+8), consistently outperforming existing open-source models and matching or surpassing state-of-the-art commercial solutions. We hope this technical report will help the community more efficiently train high-quality video generation models and accelerate progress in video generation technologies. Official page: https://github.com/FoundationVision/Waver.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15761</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:56:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intern-S1: A Scientific Multimodal Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15763</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15763.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lei Bai, Zhongrui Cai, Maosong Cao, Weihan Cao, Chiyu Chen, Haojiong Chen, Kai Chen, Pengcheng Chen, Ying Chen, Yongkang Chen, Yu Cheng, Yu Cheng, Pei Chu, Tao Chu, Erfei Cui, Ganqu Cui, Long Cui, Ziyun Cui, Nianchen Deng, Ning Ding, Nanqin Dong, Peijie Dong, Shihan Dou, Sinan Du, Haodong Duan, Caihua Fan, Ben Gao, Changjiang Gao, Jianfei Gao, Songyang Gao, Yang Gao, Zhangwei Gao, Jiaye Ge, Qiming Ge, Lixin Gu, Yuzhe Gu, Aijia Guo, Qipeng Guo, Xu Guo, Conghui He, Junjun He, Yili Hong, Siyuan Hou, Caiyu Hu, Hanglei Hu, Jucheng Hu, Ming Hu, Zhouqi Hua, Haian Huang, Junhao Huang, Xu Huang, Zixian Huang, Zhe Jiang, Lingkai Kong, Linyang Li, Peiji Li, Pengze Li, Shuaibin Li, Tianbin Li, Wei Li, Yuqiang Li, Dahua Lin, Junyao Lin, Tianyi Lin, Zhishan Lin, Hongwei Liu, Jiangning Liu, Jiyao Liu, Junnan Liu, Kai Liu, Kaiwen Liu, Kuikun Liu, Shichun Liu, Shudong Liu, Wei Liu, Xinyao Liu, Yuhong Liu, Zhan Liu, Yinquan Lu, Haijun Lv, Hongxia Lv, Huijie Lv, Qidang Lv, Ying Lv, Chengqi Lyu, Chenglong Ma, Jianpeng Ma, Ren Ma, Runmin Ma, Runyuan Ma, Xinzhu Ma, Yichuan Ma, Zihan Ma, Sixuan Mi, Junzhi Ning, Wenchang Ning, Xinle Pang, Jiahui Peng, Runyu Peng, Yu Qiao, Jiantao Qiu, Xiaoye Qu, Yuan Qu, Yuchen Ren, Fukai Shang, Wenqi Shao, Junhao Shen, Shuaike Shen, Chunfeng Song, Demin Song, Diping Song, Chenlin Su, Weijie Su, Weigao Sun, Yu Sun, Qian Tan, Cheng Tang, Huanze Tang, Kexian Tang, Shixiang Tang, Jian Tong, Aoran Wang, Bin Wang, Dong Wang, Lintao Wang, Rui Wang, Weiyun Wang, Wenhai Wang, Yi Wang, Ziyi Wang, Ling-I Wu, Wen Wu, Yue Wu, Zijian Wu, Linchen Xiao, Shuhao Xing, Chao Xu, Huihui Xu, Jun Xu, Ruiliang Xu, Wanghan Xu, GanLin Yang, Yuming Yang, Haochen Ye, Jin Ye, Shenglong Ye, Jia Yu, Jiashuo Yu, Jing Yu, Fei Yuan, Bo Zhang, Chao Zhang, Chen Zhang, Hongjie Zhang, Jin Zhang, Qiaosheng Zhang, Qiuyinzhe Zhang, Songyang Zhang, Taolin Zhang, Wenlong Zhang, Wenwei Zhang, Yechen Zhang, Ziyang Zhang, Haiteng Zhao, Qian Zhao, Xiangyu Zhao, Xiangyu Zhao, Bowen Zhou, Dongzhan Zhou, Peiheng Zhou, Yuhao Zhou, Yunhua Zhou, Dongsheng Zhu, Lin Zhu, Yicheng Zou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 206&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In recent years, a plethora of open-source foundation models have emerged, achieving remarkable progress in some widely attended fields, with performance being quite close to that of closed-source models. However, in high-value but more challenging scientific professional fields, either the fields still rely on expert models, or the progress of general foundation models lags significantly compared to those in popular areas, far from sufficient for transforming scientific research and leaving substantial gap between open-source models and closed-source models in these scientific domains. To mitigate this gap and explore a step further toward Artificial General Intelligence (AGI), we introduce Intern-S1, a specialized generalist equipped with general understanding and reasoning capabilities with expertise to analyze multiple science modal data. Intern-S1 is a multimodal Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) model with 28 billion activated parameters and 241 billion total parameters, continually pre-trained on 5T tokens, including over 2.5T tokens from scientific domains. In the post-training stage, Intern-S1 undergoes offline and then online reinforcement learning (RL) in InternBootCamp, where we propose Mixture-of-Rewards (MoR) to synergize the RL training on more than 1000 tasks simultaneously. Through integrated innovations in algorithms, data, and training systems, Intern-S1 achieved top-tier performance in online RL training.On comprehensive evaluation benchmarks, Intern-S1 demonstrates competitive performance on general reasoning tasks among open-source models and significantly outperforms open-source models in scientific domains, surpassing closed-source state-of-the-art models in professional tasks, such as molecular synthesis planning, reaction condition prediction, predicting thermodynamic stabilities for crystals. Our models are available at https://huggingface.co/internlm/Intern-S1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15763</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ATLAS: Decoupling Skeletal and Shape Parameters for Expressive   Parametric Human Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15767</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15767.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinhyung Park, Javier Romero, Shunsuke Saito, Fabian Prada, Takaaki Shiratori, Yichen Xu, Federica Bogo, Shoou-I Yu, Kris Kitani, Rawal Khirodkar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Parametric body models offer expressive 3D representation of humans across a wide range of poses, shapes, and facial expressions, typically derived by learning a basis over registered 3D meshes. However, existing human mesh modeling approaches struggle to capture detailed variations across diverse body poses and shapes, largely due to limited training data diversity and restrictive modeling assumptions. Moreover, the common paradigm first optimizes the external body surface using a linear basis, then regresses internal skeletal joints from surface vertices. This approach introduces problematic dependencies between internal skeleton and outer soft tissue, limiting direct control over body height and bone lengths. To address these issues, we present ATLAS, a high-fidelity body model learned from 600k high-resolution scans captured using 240 synchronized cameras. Unlike previous methods, we explicitly decouple the shape and skeleton bases by grounding our mesh representation in the human skeleton. This decoupling enables enhanced shape expressivity, fine-grained customization of body attributes, and keypoint fitting independent of external soft-tissue characteristics. ATLAS outperforms existing methods by fitting unseen subjects in diverse poses more accurately, and quantitative evaluations show that our non-linear pose correctives more effectively capture complex poses compared to linear models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15767</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:58:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SceneGen: Single-Image 3D Scene Generation in One Feedforward Pass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15769</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15769.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanxu Meng, Haoning Wu, Ya Zhang, Weidi Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D content generation has recently attracted significant research interest due to its applications in VR/AR and embodied AI. In this work, we address the challenging task of synthesizing multiple 3D assets within a single scene image. Concretely, our contributions are fourfold: (i) we present SceneGen, a novel framework that takes a scene image and corresponding object masks as input, simultaneously producing multiple 3D assets with geometry and texture. Notably, SceneGen operates with no need for optimization or asset retrieval; (ii) we introduce a novel feature aggregation module that integrates local and global scene information from visual and geometric encoders within the feature extraction module. Coupled with a position head, this enables the generation of 3D assets and their relative spatial positions in a single feedforward pass; (iii) we demonstrate SceneGen's direct extensibility to multi-image input scenarios. Despite being trained solely on single-image inputs, our architectural design enables improved generation performance with multi-image inputs; and (iv) extensive quantitative and qualitative evaluations confirm the efficiency and robust generation abilities of our approach. We believe this paradigm offers a novel solution for high-quality 3D content generation, potentially advancing its practical applications in downstream tasks. The code and model will be publicly available at: https://mengmouxu.github.io/SceneGen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15769</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Autoregressive Modeling for Instruction-Guided Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15772</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15772.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qingyang Mao, Qi Cai, Yehao Li, Yingwei Pan, Mingyue Cheng, Ting Yao, Qi Liu, Tao Mei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in diffusion models have brought remarkable visual fidelity to instruction-guided image editing. However, their global denoising process inherently entangles the edited region with the entire image context, leading to unintended spurious modifications and compromised adherence to editing instructions. In contrast, autoregressive models offer a distinct paradigm by formulating image synthesis as a sequential process over discrete visual tokens. Their causal and compositional mechanism naturally circumvents the adherence challenges of diffusion-based methods. In this paper, we present VAREdit, a visual autoregressive (VAR) framework that reframes image editing as a next-scale prediction problem. Conditioned on source image features and text instructions, VAREdit generates multi-scale target features to achieve precise edits. A core challenge in this paradigm is how to effectively condition the source image tokens. We observe that finest-scale source features cannot effectively guide the prediction of coarser target features. To bridge this gap, we introduce a Scale-Aligned Reference (SAR) module, which injects scale-matched conditioning information into the first self-attention layer. VAREdit demonstrates significant advancements in both editing adherence and efficiency. On standard benchmarks, it outperforms leading diffusion-based methods by 30\%+ higher GPT-Balance score. Moreover, it completes a 512times512 editing in 1.2 seconds, making it 2.2times faster than the similarly sized UltraEdit. The models are available at https://github.com/HiDream-ai/VAREdit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15772</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
