<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:12:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>RoboChallenge: Large-scale Real-robot Evaluation of Embodied Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17950</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.17950.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Adina Yakefu, Bin Xie, Chongyang Xu, Enwen Zhang, Erjin Zhou, Fan Jia, Haitao Yang, Haoqiang Fan, Haowei Zhang, Hongyang Peng, Jing Tan, Junwen Huang, Kai Liu, Kaixin Liu, Kefan Gu, Qinglun Zhang, Ruitao Zhang, Saike Huang, Shen Cheng, Shuaicheng Liu, Tiancai Wang, Tiezhen Wang, Wei Sun, Wenbin Tang, Yajun Wei, Yang Chen, Youqiang Gui, Yucheng Zhao, Yunchao Ma, Yunfei Wei, Yunhuan Yang, Yutong Guo, Ze Chen, Zhengyuan Du, Ziheng Zhang, Ziming Liu, Ziwei Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Testing on real machines is indispensable for robotic control algorithms. In the context of learning-based algorithms, especially VLA models, demand for large-scale evaluation, i.e. testing a large number of models on a large number of tasks, is becoming increasingly urgent. However, doing this right is highly non-trivial, especially when scalability and reproducibility is taken into account. In this report, we describe our methodology for constructing RoboChallenge, an online evaluation system to test robotic control algorithms, and our survey of recent state-of-the-art VLA models using our initial benchmark Table30.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17950</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 17:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D2D: Detector-to-Differentiable Critic for Improved Numeracy in   Text-to-Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19278</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.19278.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nobline Yoo, Olga Russakovsky, Ye Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-image (T2I) diffusion models have achieved strong performance in semantic alignment, yet they still struggle with generating the correct number of objects specified in prompts. Existing approaches typically incorporate auxiliary counting networks as external critics to enhance numeracy. However, since these critics must provide gradient guidance during generation, they are restricted to regression-based models that are inherently differentiable, thus excluding detector-based models with superior counting ability, whose count-via-enumeration nature is non-differentiable. To overcome this limitation, we propose Detector-to-Differentiable (D2D), a novel framework that transforms non-differentiable detection models into differentiable critics, thereby leveraging their superior counting ability to guide numeracy generation. Specifically, we design custom activation functions to convert detector logits into soft binary indicators, which are then used to optimize the noise prior at inference time with pre-trained T2I models. Our extensive experiments on SDXL-Turbo, SD-Turbo, and Pixart-DMD across four benchmarks of varying complexity (low-density, high-density, and multi-object scenarios) demonstrate consistent and substantial improvements in object counting accuracy (e.g., boosting up to 13.7% on D2D-Small, a 400-prompt, low-density benchmark), with minimal degradation in overall image quality and computational overhead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19278</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 06:27:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rank-GRPO: Training LLM-based Conversational Recommender Systems with   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20150</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.20150.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yaochen Zhu, Harald Steck, Dawen Liang, Yinhan He, Jundong Li, Nathan Kallus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are reshaping the recommender system paradigm by enabling users to express preferences and receive recommendations through conversations. Yet, aligning LLMs to the recommendation task remains challenging: pretrained LLMs often generate out-of-catalog items, violate required output formats, and their ranking quality degrades sharply toward the end of the generated list. To this end, we propose ConvRec-R1, a two-stage framework for end-to-end training of LLM-based conversational recommender systems. In Stage 1, we construct a behavioral-cloning dataset with a Remap-Reflect-Adjust pipeline, which produces high-quality, catalog-grounded demonstrations from powerful blackbox LLMs to warm-start the RL training. In Stage 2, we propose Rank-GRPO, a principled extension of group relative policy optimization (GRPO) tailored to tasks with rank-style outputs. Rank-GRPO treats each rank in the recommendation list as the unit instead of token (too fine-grained) or sequence (too coarse), redefining rewards to remove non-causal credit assignment and introducing a rank-level importance ratio based on the geometric mean of rank-wise token probabilities to stabilize policy updates. Experiments on the public Reddit-v2 dataset show that ConvRec-R1 converges faster and achieves higher Recall and NDCG than GRPO-style baselines. Code and datasets are released at https://github.com/yaochenzhu/Rank-GRPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20150</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 02:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Every Activation Boosted: Scaling General Reasoner to 1 Trillion Open   Language Foundation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22115</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22115.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ling-Team, Ang Li, Ben Liu, Binbin Hu, Bing Li, Bingwei Zeng, Borui Ye, Caizhi Tang, Changxin Tian, Chao Huang, Chao Zhang, Chen Qian, Chenchen Ju, Chenchen Li, Chengfu Tang, Chili Fu, Chunshao Ren, Chunwei Wu, Cong Zhang, Cunyin Peng, Dafeng Xu, Daixin Wang, Dalong Zhang, Dingnan Jin, Dingyuan Zhu, Dongke Hu, Fangzheng Zhao, Feifan Wu, Feng Zhu, Gangshan Wang, Haitao Zhang, Hailin Zhao, Hanxiao Zhang, Hanzi Wang, Hao Qian, Haoyi Yu, Heng Zhang, Hongliang Zhang, Hongzhi Luan, Huirong Dong, Huizhong Li, Jia Li, Jia Liu, Jialong Zhu, Jian Sha, Jianping Wei, Jiaolong Yang, Jieyue Ma, Jiewei Wu, Jinjing Huang, Jingyun Tian, Jingyuan Zhang, Jinquan Sun, Juanhui Tu, Jun Liu, Jun Xu, Jun Zhou, Junjie Ou, Junpeng Fang, Kaihong Zhang, Kaiqin Hu, Ke Shi, Kun Tang, Kunlong Chen, Lanyin Mei, Lei Liang, Lei Xu, Libo Zhang, Lin Ju, Lin Yuan, Ling Zhong, Lintao Ma, Lu Liu, Lu Yu, Lun Cai, Meiqi Zhu, Mengying Li, Min Chen, Minghao Xue, Minghong Cai, Mingming Yin, Peijie Jiang, Peilong Zhao, Pingping Liu, Qian Zhao, Qing Cui, Qingxiang Huang, Qingyuan Yang, Quankun Yu, Shaowei Wei, Shijie Lian, Shoujian Zheng, Shun Song, Shungen Zhang, Shuo Zhang, Siyuan Li, Song Liu, Ting Guo, Tong Zhao, Wanli Gu, Weichang Wu, Weiguang Han, Wenjing Fang, Wubin Wang, Xiang Shu, Xiao Shi, Xiaoshun Lan, Xiaolu Zhang, Xiaqing Sun, Xin Zhao, Xingyu Lu, Xiong Xu, Xudong Wang, Xudong Wang, Xuemin Yang, Yajie Yang, Yang Xiang, Yanzhe Li, Yi Zhang, Yilong Wang, Yingxue Li, Yongzhen Guo, Yuzhuo Fu, Yuanyuan Wang, Yue Yang, Yue Yu, Yufeng Deng, Yun Zhang, Yunfei Xu, Yuqi Zhang, Yuxiao He, Zengke Gui, Zhaoxin Huan, Zhaoyang Wang, Zhibo Zhu, Zhihao Wang, Zhiqiang Zhang, Zhoufei Wang, Zihang Zeng, Ziqi Liu, Zitao Xuan, Zuoli Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Ling 2.0, a series reasoning-oriented language foundation built upon the principle that every activation boosts reasoning capability. Designed to scale from tens of billions to one trillion parameters under a unified Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) paradigm, Ling 2.0 emphasizes high sparsity, cross-scale consistency, and efficiency guided by empirical scaling laws. The series includes three non-thinking (instruct) models - Ling-mini-2.0, Ling-flash-2.0, and Ling-1T - ranging from 16B to 1T total parameters and achieving up to 7-fold active-compute efficiency compared with dense counterparts. Ling 2.0 integrates coordinated innovations across model architecture, pre-training, post-training, and infrastructure: a high-sparsity MoE with MTP for efficient reasoning, reasoning-oriented data and mid-training CoT activation, reinforcement-based fine-tuning (DFT, Evo-CoT), and full-scale FP8 training with fine-grained heterogeneous pipelines. At the trillion scale, Ling-1T establishes a new Pareto frontier of reasoning accuracy versus computational efficiency, demonstrating that sparse activation, when properly aligned with reasoning objectives, enables scalable and efficient intelligence. Collectively, Ling 2.0 provides a coherent, open, and efficient foundation for advancing future reasoning and thinking models, including the Ring series built upon the same base.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22115</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 01:51:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Underappreciated Power of Vision Models for Graph Structural   Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24788</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24788.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinjian Zhao, Wei Pang, Zhongkai Xue, Xiangru Jian, Lei Zhang, Yaoyao Xu, Xiaozhuang Song, Shu Wu, Tianshu Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graph Neural Networks operate through bottom-up message-passing, fundamentally differing from human visual perception, which intuitively captures global structures first. We investigate the underappreciated potential of vision models for graph understanding, finding they achieve performance comparable to GNNs on established benchmarks while exhibiting distinctly different learning patterns. These divergent behaviors, combined with limitations of existing benchmarks that conflate domain features with topological understanding, motivate our introduction of GraphAbstract. This benchmark evaluates models' ability to perceive global graph properties as humans do: recognizing organizational archetypes, detecting symmetry, sensing connectivity strength, and identifying critical elements. Our results reveal that vision models significantly outperform GNNs on tasks requiring holistic structural understanding and maintain generalizability across varying graph scales, while GNNs struggle with global pattern abstraction and degrade with increasing graph size. This work demonstrates that vision models possess remarkable yet underutilized capabilities for graph structural understanding, particularly for problems requiring global topological awareness and scale-invariant reasoning. These findings open new avenues to leverage this underappreciated potential for developing more effective graph foundation models for tasks dominated by holistic pattern recognition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24788</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 05:11:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Multimodal Positional Encoding in Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23095</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23095.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jie Huang, Xuejing Liu, Sibo Song, Ruibing Hou, Hong Chang, Junyang Lin, Shuai Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal position encoding is essential for vision-language models, yet there has been little systematic investigation into multimodal position encoding. We conduct a comprehensive analysis of multimodal Rotary Positional Embedding (RoPE) by examining its two core components: position design and frequency allocation. Through extensive experiments, we identify three key guidelines: positional coherence, full frequency utilization, and preservation of textual priors-ensuring unambiguous layout, rich representation, and faithful transfer from the pre-trained LLM. Based on these insights, we propose Multi-Head RoPE (MHRoPE) and MRoPE-Interleave (MRoPE-I), two simple and plug-and-play variants that require no architectural changes. Our methods consistently outperform existing approaches across diverse benchmarks, with significant improvements in both general and fine-grained multimodal understanding. Code will be avaliable at https://github.com/JJJYmmm/Multimodal-RoPEs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23095</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 08:00:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MR-Align: Meta-Reasoning Informed Factuality Alignment for Large   Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24794</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24794.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinming Wang, Jian Xu, Bin Yu, Sheng Lian, Hongzhu Yi, Yi Chen, Yingjian Zhu, Boran Wang, Hongming Yang, Han Hu, Xu-Yao Zhang, Cheng-Lin Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs) show strong capabilities in complex reasoning, yet their marginal gains on evidence-dependent factual questions are limited. We find this limitation is partially attributable to a reasoning-answer hit gap, where the model identifies the correct facts during reasoning but fails to incorporate them into the final response, thereby reducing factual fidelity. To address this issue, we propose MR-ALIGN, a Meta-Reasoning informed alignment framework that enhances factuality without relying on external verifiers. MR-ALIGN quantifies state transition probabilities along the model's thinking process and constructs a transition-aware implicit reward that reinforces beneficial reasoning patterns while suppressing defective ones at the atomic thinking segments. This re-weighting reshapes token-level signals into probability-aware segment scores, encouraging coherent reasoning trajectories that are more conducive to factual correctness. Empirical evaluations across four factual QA datasets and one long-form factuality benchmark show that MR-ALIGN consistently improves accuracy and truthfulness while reducing misleading reasoning. These results highlight that aligning the reasoning process itself, rather than merely the outputs, is pivotal for advancing factuality in LRMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24794</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 15:00:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Efficient Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24795</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24795.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoshu Yu, Bo Wang, Pengpeng Zeng, Haonan Zhang, Ji Zhang, Lianli Gao, Jingkuan Song, Nicu Sebe, Heng Tao Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action models (VLAs) represent a significant frontier in embodied intelligence, aiming to bridge digital knowledge with physical-world interaction. While these models have demonstrated remarkable generalist capabilities, their deployment is severely hampered by the substantial computational and data requirements inherent to their underlying large-scale foundation models. Motivated by the urgent need to address these challenges, this survey presents the first comprehensive review of Efficient Vision-Language-Action models (Efficient VLAs) across the entire data-model-training process. Specifically, we introduce a unified taxonomy to systematically organize the disparate efforts in this domain, categorizing current techniques into three core pillars: (1) Efficient Model Design, focusing on efficient architectures and model compression; (2) Efficient Training, which reduces computational burdens during model learning; and (3) Efficient Data Collection, which addresses the bottlenecks in acquiring and utilizing robotic data. Through a critical review of state-of-the-art methods within this framework, this survey not only establishes a foundational reference for the community but also summarizes representative applications, delineates key challenges, and charts a roadmap for future research. We maintain a continuously updated project page to track our latest developments: https://evla-survey.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24795</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:57:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Objects: Contextual Synthetic Data Generation for Fine-Grained   Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24078</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24078.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; William Yang, Xindi Wu, Zhiwei Deng, Esin Tureci, Olga Russakovsky&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-image (T2I) models are increasingly used for synthetic dataset generation, but generating effective synthetic training data for classification remains challenging. Fine-tuning a T2I model with a few real examples can help improve the quality of synthetic training data; however, it may also cause overfitting and reduce diversity in the generated samples. We propose a fine-tuning strategy BOB (BeyondOBjects) to mitigate these concerns for fine-grained classification. Given a small set of real examples, we first extract class-agnostic attributes such as scene background and object pose. We then explicitly condition on these attributes during fine-tuning of the T2I model and marginalize them out during generation. This design mitigates overfitting, preserves the T2I model's generative prior, reduces estimation errors, and further minimizes unintended inter-class associations. Extensive experiments across multiple T2I models, backbones, and datasets show that our method achieves state-of-the-art performance in low-shot fine-grained classification when augmented with synthetic data. Concretely, BOB outperforms DataDream by 7.4% on the Aircraft dataset (from 50.0% to 57.4% when fine-tuning a CLIP classifier with five real images augmented with 100 synthetic images). In three of the four benchmarks, fine-tuning downstream models with 5 real images augmented with BOB achieves better performance than fine-tuning with 10 real images. Collectively, BOB outperforms prior art in 18 of 24 experimental settings, with 2+% accuracy improvements in 14 of these settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24078</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 05:40:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OS-Sentinel: Towards Safety-Enhanced Mobile GUI Agents via Hybrid   Validation in Realistic Workflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24411</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24411.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qiushi Sun, Mukai Li, Zhoumianze Liu, Zhihui Xie, Fangzhi Xu, Zhangyue Yin, Kanzhi Cheng, Zehao Li, Zichen Ding, Qi Liu, Zhiyong Wu, Zhuosheng Zhang, Ben Kao, Lingpeng Kong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Computer-using agents powered by Vision-Language Models (VLMs) have demonstrated human-like capabilities in operating digital environments like mobile platforms. While these agents hold great promise for advancing digital automation, their potential for unsafe operations, such as system compromise and privacy leakage, is raising significant concerns. Detecting these safety concerns across the vast and complex operational space of mobile environments presents a formidable challenge that remains critically underexplored. To establish a foundation for mobile agent safety research, we introduce MobileRisk-Live, a dynamic sandbox environment accompanied by a safety detection benchmark comprising realistic trajectories with fine-grained annotations. Built upon this, we propose OS-Sentinel, a novel hybrid safety detection framework that synergistically combines a Formal Verifier for detecting explicit system-level violations with a VLM-based Contextual Judge for assessing contextual risks and agent actions. Experiments show that OS-Sentinel achieves 10%-30% improvements over existing approaches across multiple metrics. Further analysis provides critical insights that foster the development of safer and more reliable autonomous mobile agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24411</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 13:22:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RiddleBench: A New Generative Reasoning Benchmark for LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24932</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24932.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Deepon Halder, Alan Saji, Thanmay Jayakumar, Ratish Puduppully, Anoop Kunchukuttan, Raj Dabre&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models have demonstrated strong performance on many established reasoning benchmarks. However, these benchmarks primarily evaluate structured skills like quantitative problem-solving, leaving a gap in assessing flexible, multifaceted reasoning abilities that are central to human intelligence. These abilities require integrating logical deduction with spatial awareness and constraint satisfaction, which current evaluations do not measure well. To address this, we introduce RiddleBench, a benchmark of 1,737 challenging puzzles in English designed to probe these core reasoning capabilities. Evaluation of state-of-the-art models on RiddleBench shows fundamental weaknesses. Even top proprietary models like Gemini 2.5 Pro, o3, and Claude 4 Sonnet achieve accuracy just above 60% (60.30%, 63.37%, and 63.16%). Analysis further reveals deep failures, including hallucination cascades (accepting flawed reasoning from other models) and poor self-correction due to a strong self-confirmation bias. Their reasoning is also fragile, with performance degrading significantly when constraints are reordered or irrelevant information is introduced. RiddleBench functions as a diagnostic tool for these issues and as a resource for guiding the development of more robust and reliable language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24932</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 19:58:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SemCoT: Accelerating Chain-of-Thought Reasoning through   Semantically-Aligned Implicit Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24940</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24940.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yinhan He, Wendy Zheng, Yaochen Zhu, Zaiyi Zheng, Lin Su, Sriram Vasudevan, Qi Guo, Liangjie Hong, Jundong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The verbosity of Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning hinders its mass deployment in efficiency-critical applications. Recently, implicit CoT approaches have emerged, which encode reasoning steps within LLM's hidden embeddings (termed ``implicit reasoning'') rather than explicit tokens. This approach accelerates CoT by reducing the reasoning length and bypassing some LLM components. However, existing implicit CoT methods face two significant challenges: (1) they fail to preserve the semantic alignment between the implicit reasoning (when transformed to natural language) and the ground-truth reasoning, resulting in a significant CoT performance degradation, and (2) they focus on reducing the length of the implicit reasoning; however, they neglect the considerable time cost for an LLM to generate one individual implicit reasoning token. To tackle these challenges, we propose a novel semantically-aligned implicit CoT framework termed SemCoT. In particular, for the first challenge, we design a contrastively trained sentence transformer that evaluates semantic alignment between implicit and explicit reasoning, which is used to enforce semantic preservation during implicit reasoning optimization. To address the second challenge, we introduce an efficient implicit reasoning generator by finetuning a lightweight language model using knowledge distillation. This generator is guided by our sentence transformer to distill ground-truth reasoning into semantically aligned implicit reasoning, while also optimizing for accuracy. SemCoT is the first approach that enhances CoT efficiency by jointly optimizing token-level generation speed and preserving semantic alignment with ground-truth reasoning. Extensive experiments demonstrate the superior performance of SemCoT compared to state-of-the-art methods in both efficiency and effectiveness. Our code can be found at https://github.com/YinhanHe123/SemCoT/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24940</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 20:11:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Simulation with Video Foundation Models for Physical AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00062</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00062.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NVIDIA, Arslan Ali, Junjie Bai, Maciej Bala, Yogesh Balaji, Aaron Blakeman, Tiffany Cai, Jiaxin Cao, Tianshi Cao, Elizabeth Cha, Yu-Wei Chao, Prithvijit Chattopadhyay, Mike Chen, Yongxin Chen, Yu Chen, Shuai Cheng, Yin Cui, Jenna Diamond, Yifan Ding, Jiaojiao Fan, Linxi Fan, Liang Feng, Francesco Ferroni, Sanja Fidler, Xiao Fu, Ruiyuan Gao, Yunhao Ge, Jinwei Gu, Aryaman Gupta, Siddharth Gururani, Imad El Hanafi, Ali Hassani, Zekun Hao, Jacob Huffman, Joel Jang, Pooya Jannaty, Jan Kautz, Grace Lam, Xuan Li, Zhaoshuo Li, Maosheng Liao, Chen-Hsuan Lin, Tsung-Yi Lin, Yen-Chen Lin, Huan Ling, Ming-Yu Liu, Xian Liu, Yifan Lu, Alice Luo, Qianli Ma, Hanzi Mao, Kaichun Mo, Seungjun Nah, Yashraj Narang, Abhijeet Panaskar, Lindsey Pavao, Trung Pham, Morteza Ramezanali, Fitsum Reda, Scott Reed, Xuanchi Ren, Haonan Shao, Yue Shen, Stella Shi, Shuran Song, Bartosz Stefaniak, Shangkun Sun, Shitao Tang, Sameena Tasmeen, Lyne Tchapmi, Wei-Cheng Tseng, Jibin Varghese, Andrew Z. Wang, Hao Wang, Haoxiang Wang, Heng Wang, Ting-Chun Wang, Fangyin Wei, Jiashu Xu, Dinghao Yang, Xiaodong Yang, Haotian Ye, Seonghyeon Ye, Xiaohui Zeng, Jing Zhang, Qinsheng Zhang, Kaiwen Zheng, Andrew Zhu, Yuke Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce [Cosmos-Predict2.5], the latest generation of the Cosmos World Foundation Models for Physical AI. Built on a flow-based architecture, [Cosmos-Predict2.5] unifies Text2World, Image2World, and Video2World generation in a single model and leverages [Cosmos-Reason1], a Physical AI vision-language model, to provide richer text grounding and finer control of world simulation. Trained on 200M curated video clips and refined with reinforcement learning-based post-training, [Cosmos-Predict2.5] achieves substantial improvements over [Cosmos-Predict1] in video quality and instruction alignment, with models released at 2B and 14B scales. These capabilities enable more reliable synthetic data generation, policy evaluation, and closed-loop simulation for robotics and autonomous systems. We further extend the family with [Cosmos-Transfer2.5], a control-net style framework for Sim2Real and Real2Real world translation. Despite being 3.5times smaller than [Cosmos-Transfer1], it delivers higher fidelity and robust long-horizon video generation. Together, these advances establish [Cosmos-Predict2.5] and [Cosmos-Transfer2.5] as versatile tools for scaling embodied intelligence. To accelerate research and deployment in Physical AI, we release source code, pretrained checkpoints, and curated benchmarks under the NVIDIA Open Model License at https://github.com/nvidia-cosmos/cosmos-predict2.5 and https://github.com/nvidia-cosmos/cosmos-transfer2.5. We hope these open resources lower the barrier to adoption and foster innovation in building the next generation of embodied intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00062</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 22:44:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monopoly Deal: A Benchmark Environment for Bounded One-Sided Response   Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25080</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25080.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Will Wolf&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Card games are widely used to study sequential decision-making under uncertainty, with real-world analogues in negotiation, finance, and cybersecurity. These games typically fall into three categories based on the flow of control: strictly sequential (players alternate single actions), deterministic response (some actions trigger a fixed outcome), and unbounded reciprocal response (alternating counterplays are permitted). A less-explored but strategically rich structure is the bounded one-sided response, where a player's action briefly transfers control to the opponent, who must satisfy a fixed condition through one or more moves before the turn resolves. We term games featuring this mechanism Bounded One-Sided Response Games (BORGs). We introduce a modified version of Monopoly Deal as a benchmark environment that isolates this dynamic, where a Rent action forces the opponent to choose payment assets. The gold-standard algorithm, Counterfactual Regret Minimization (CFR), converges on effective strategies without novel algorithmic extensions. A lightweight full-stack research platform unifies the environment, a parallelized CFR runtime, and a human-playable web interface. The trained CFR agent and source code are available at https://monopolydeal.ai.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25080</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 01:38:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INT v.s. FP: A Comprehensive Study of Fine-Grained Low-bit Quantization   Formats</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25602</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25602.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengzhao Chen, Meng Wu, Hui Jin, Zhihang Yuan, Jing Liu, Chaoyi Zhang, Yunshui Li, Jie Huang, Jin Ma, Zeyue Xue, Zhiheng Liu, Xingyan Bin, Ping Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern AI hardware, such as Nvidia's Blackwell architecture, is increasingly embracing low-precision floating-point (FP) formats to handle the pervasive activation outliers in Large Language Models (LLMs). Despite this industry trend, a unified comparison of FP and integer (INT) quantization across varying granularities has been missing, leaving algorithm and hardware co-design without clear guidance. This paper fills that gap by systematically investigating the trade-offs between FP and INT formats. We reveal a critical performance crossover: while FP excels in coarse-grained quantization, the comparison at fine-grained (block-wise) levels is more nuanced. Our comprehensive comparison demonstrates that for popular 8-bit fine-grained formats (e.g., MX with block size 32), MXINT8 is superior to its FP counterpart in both algorithmic accuracy and hardware efficiency. However, for 4-bit formats, FP (e.g., MXFP4, NVFP4) often holds an accuracy advantage , though we show that NVINT4 can surpass NVFP4 when outlier-mitigation techniques like Hadamard rotation are applied. We also introduce a symmetric clipping method that resolves gradient bias in fine-grained low-bit INT training, enabling nearly lossless performance for MXINT8 training. These findings challenge the current hardware trajectory, demonstrating that a one-size-fits-all FP approach is suboptimal and advocating that fine-grained INT formats, particularly MXINT8, offer a better balance of accuracy, power, and efficiency for future AI accelerators.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25602</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 15:11:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Blind Your VLA: Aligning Visual Representations for OOD   Generalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25616</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25616.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nikita Kachaev, Mikhail Kolosov, Daniil Zelezetsky, Alexey K. Kovalev, Aleksandr I. Panov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The growing success of Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models stems from the promise that pretrained Vision-Language Models (VLMs) can endow agents with transferable world knowledge and vision-language (VL) grounding, laying a foundation for action models with broader generalization. Yet when these VLMs are adapted to the action modality, it remains unclear to what extent their original VL representations and knowledge are preserved. In this work, we conduct a systematic study of representation retention during VLA fine-tuning, showing that naive action fine-tuning leads to degradation of visual representations. To characterize and measure these effects, we probe VLA's hidden representations and analyze attention maps, further, we design a set of targeted tasks and methods that contrast VLA models with their counterpart VLMs, isolating changes in VL capabilities induced by action fine-tuning. We further evaluate a range of strategies for aligning visual representations and introduce a simple yet effective method that mitigates degradation and yields improved generalization to out-of-distribution (OOD) scenarios. Taken together, our analysis clarifies the trade-off between action fine-tuning and the degradation of VL representations and highlights practical approaches to recover inherited VL capabilities. Code is publicly available: https://blind-vla-paper.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25616</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 15:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ï€_RL: Online RL Fine-tuning for Flow-based   Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25889</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25889.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kang Chen, Zhihao Liu, Tonghe Zhang, Zhen Guo, Si Xu, Hao Lin, Hongzhi Zang, Quanlu Zhang, Zhaofei Yu, Guoliang Fan, Tiejun Huang, Yu Wang, Chao Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models enable robots to understand and perform complex tasks from multimodal input. Although recent work explores using reinforcement learning (RL) to automate the laborious data collection process in scaling supervised fine-tuning (SFT), applying large-scale RL to flow-based VLAs (e.g., pi_0, pi_{0.5}) remains challenging due to intractable action log-likelihoods from iterative denoising.   We address this challenge with pi_{RL}, an open-source framework for training flow-based VLAs in parallel simulation. pi_{RL} implements two RL algorithms: (1) {Flow-Noise} models the denoising process as a discrete-time MDP with a learnable noise network for exact log-likelihood computation. (2) {Flow-SDE} integrates denoising with agent-environment interaction, formulating a two-layer MDP that employs ODE-to-SDE conversion for efficient RL exploration.   We evaluate pi_{RL} on LIBERO and ManiSkill benchmarks. On LIBERO, pi_{RL} boosts few-shot SFT models pi_0 and pi_{0.5} from 57.6% to 97.6% and from 77.1% to 98.3%, respectively. In ManiSkill, we train pi_{RL} in 320 parallel environments, improving pi_0 from 41.6% to 85.7% and pi_{0.5} from 40.0% to 84.8% across 4352 pick-and-place tasks, demonstrating scalable multitask RL under heterogeneous simulation.   Overall, pi_{RL} achieves significant performance gains and stronger generalization over SFT-models, validating the effectiveness of online RL for flow-based VLAs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25889</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 18:37:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brain-IT: Image Reconstruction from fMRI via Brain-Interaction   Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25976</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25976.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Roman Beliy, Amit Zalcher, Jonathan Kogman, Navve Wasserman, Michal Irani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reconstructing images seen by people from their fMRI brain recordings provides a non-invasive window into the human brain. Despite recent progress enabled by diffusion models, current methods often lack faithfulness to the actual seen images. We present "Brain-IT", a brain-inspired approach that addresses this challenge through a Brain Interaction Transformer (BIT), allowing effective interactions between clusters of functionally-similar brain-voxels. These functional-clusters are shared by all subjects, serving as building blocks for integrating information both within and across brains. All model components are shared by all clusters &amp; subjects, allowing efficient training with a limited amount of data. To guide the image reconstruction, BIT predicts two complementary localized patch-level image features: (i)high-level semantic features which steer the diffusion model toward the correct semantic content of the image; and (ii)low-level structural features which help to initialize the diffusion process with the correct coarse layout of the image. BIT's design enables direct flow of information from brain-voxel clusters to localized image features. Through these principles, our method achieves image reconstructions from fMRI that faithfully reconstruct the seen images, and surpass current SotA approaches both visually and by standard objective metrics. Moreover, with only 1-hour of fMRI data from a new subject, we achieve results comparable to current methods trained on full 40-hour recordings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25976</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 21:21:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing Test-time Compute-optimal Scaling as an Optimizable Graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00086</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00086.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fali Wang, Jihai Chen, Shuhua Yang, Runxue Bao, Tianxiang Zhao, Zhiwei Zhang, Xianfeng Tang, Hui Liu, Qi He, Suhang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Test-Time Scaling (TTS) improves large language models (LLMs) by allocating additional computation during inference, typically through parallel, sequential, or hybrid scaling. However, prior studies often assume fixed collaboration architectures (e.g., topologies) and single-model usage, overlooking that optimal architectures and model combinations can vary across tasks. Therefore, we study the novel problem of searching for compute-optimal model combinations and architectures in TTS under a fixed budget. We formalize it as a multi-LLM collaboration graph, where nodes encode roles and LLM model assignments, and edges capture information flow. This problem is challenging because (i) the combinatorial search space is prohibitively large, and (ii) task-specific requirements demand tailored designs. To address these, we reformulate the problem as probabilistic graph optimization and, through pilot experiments, derive three empirical insights into TTS collaboration graphs. Guided by these insights, we propose Agent-REINFORCE, an LLM-agent-augmented framework that mirrors the REINFORCE pipeline by mapping sampling-gradient-update to sampling-feedback-update, where feedback serves as a textual gradient to update the probabilistic graph and efficiently search for optimal multi-LLM collaboration graphs. Experiments show that Agent-REINFORCE outperforms both traditional and LLM-based baselines in sample efficiency and search performance, and effectively identifies optimal graphs under joint objectives of accuracy and inference latency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00086</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 22:14:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PHUMA: Physically-Grounded Humanoid Locomotion Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26236</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26236.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kyungmin Lee, Sibeen Kim, Minho Park, Hyunseung Kim, Dongyoon Hwang, Hojoon Lee, Jaegul Choo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Motion imitation is a promising approach for humanoid locomotion, enabling agents to acquire humanlike behaviors. Existing methods typically rely on high-quality motion capture datasets such as AMASS, but these are scarce and expensive, limiting scalability and diversity. Recent studies attempt to scale data collection by converting large-scale internet videos, exemplified by Humanoid-X. However, they often introduce physical artifacts such as floating, penetration, and foot skating, which hinder stable imitation. In response, we introduce PHUMA, a Physically-grounded HUMAnoid locomotion dataset that leverages human video at scale, while addressing physical artifacts through careful data curation and physics-constrained retargeting. PHUMA enforces joint limits, ensures ground contact, and eliminates foot skating, producing motions that are both large-scale and physically reliable. We evaluated PHUMA in two sets of conditions: (i) imitation of unseen motion from self-recorded test videos and (ii) path following with pelvis-only guidance. In both cases, PHUMA-trained policies outperform Humanoid-X and AMASS, achieving significant gains in imitating diverse motions. The code is available at https://davian-robotics.github.io/PHUMA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26236</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 08:13:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MisSynth: Improving MISSCI Logical Fallacies Classification with   Synthetic Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26345</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26345.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mykhailo Poliakov, Nadiya Shvai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Health-related misinformation is very prevalent and potentially harmful. It is difficult to identify, especially when claims distort or misinterpret scientific findings. We investigate the impact of synthetic data generation and lightweight fine-tuning techniques on the ability of large language models (LLMs) to recognize fallacious arguments using the MISSCI dataset and framework. In this work, we propose MisSynth, a pipeline that applies retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) to produce synthetic fallacy samples, which are then used to fine-tune an LLM model. Our results show substantial accuracy gains with fine-tuned models compared to vanilla baselines. For instance, the LLaMA 3.1 8B fine-tuned model achieved an over 35% F1-score absolute improvement on the MISSCI test split over its vanilla baseline. We demonstrate that introducing synthetic fallacy data to augment limited annotated resources can significantly enhance zero-shot LLM classification performance on real-world scientific misinformation tasks, even with limited computational resources. The code and synthetic dataset are available on https://github.com/mxpoliakov/MisSynth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26345</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 10:52:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-Efficient RLVR via Off-Policy Influence Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26491</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26491.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Erle Zhu, Dazhi Jiang, Yuan Wang, Xujun Li, Jiale Cheng, Yuxian Gu, Yilin Niu, Aohan Zeng, Jie Tang, Minlie Huang, Hongning Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data selection is a critical aspect of Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) for enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). Current data selection methods are largely heuristic-based, lacking theoretical guarantees and generalizability. This work proposes a theoretically-grounded approach using influence functions to estimate the contribution of each data point to the learning objective. To overcome the prohibitive computational cost of policy rollouts required for online influence estimation, we introduce an off-policy influence estimation method that efficiently approximates data influence using pre-collected offline trajectories. Furthermore, to manage the high-dimensional gradients of LLMs, we employ sparse random projection to reduce dimensionality and improve storage and computation efficiency. Leveraging these techniques, we develop Curriculum RL with Off-Policy Influence guidance (CROPI), a multi-stage RL framework that iteratively selects the most influential data for the current policy. Experiments on models up to 7B parameters demonstrate that CROPI significantly accelerates training. On a 1.5B model, it achieves a 2.66x step-level acceleration while using only 10\% of the data per stage compared to full-dataset training. Our results highlight the substantial potential of influence-based data selection for efficient RLVR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26491</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 13:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Value Drifts: Tracing Value Alignment During LLM Post-Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26707</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26707.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mehar Bhatia, Shravan Nayak, Gaurav Kamath, Marius Mosbach, Karolina StaÅ„czak, Vered Shwartz, Siva Reddy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As LLMs occupy an increasingly important role in society, they are more and more confronted with questions that require them not only to draw on their general knowledge but also to align with certain human value systems. Therefore, studying the alignment of LLMs with human values has become a crucial field of inquiry. Prior work, however, mostly focuses on evaluating the alignment of fully trained models, overlooking the training dynamics by which models learn to express human values. In this work, we investigate how and at which stage value alignment arises during the course of a model's post-training. Our analysis disentangles the effects of post-training algorithms and datasets, measuring both the magnitude and time of value drifts during training. Experimenting with Llama-3 and Qwen-3 models of different sizes and popular supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and preference optimization datasets and algorithms, we find that the SFT phase generally establishes a model's values, and subsequent preference optimization rarely re-aligns these values. Furthermore, using a synthetic preference dataset that enables controlled manipulation of values, we find that different preference optimization algorithms lead to different value alignment outcomes, even when preference data is held constant. Our findings provide actionable insights into how values are learned during post-training and help to inform data curation, as well as the selection of models and algorithms for preference optimization to improve model alignment to human values.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26707</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:09:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do Vision-Language Models Measure Up? Benchmarking Visual Measurement   Reading with MeasureBench</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26865</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26865.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fenfen Lin, Yesheng Liu, Haiyu Xu, Chen Yue, Zheqi He, Mingxuan Zhao, Miguel Hu Chen, Jiakang Liu, JG Yao, Xi Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reading measurement instruments is effortless for humans and requires relatively little domain expertise, yet it remains surprisingly challenging for current vision-language models (VLMs) as we find in preliminary evaluation. In this work, we introduce MeasureBench, a benchmark on visual measurement reading covering both real-world and synthesized images of various types of measurements, along with an extensible pipeline for data synthesis. Our pipeline procedurally generates a specified type of gauge with controllable visual appearance, enabling scalable variation in key details such as pointers, scales, fonts, lighting, and clutter. Evaluation on popular proprietary and open-weight VLMs shows that even the strongest frontier VLMs struggle measurement reading in general. A consistent failure mode is indicator localization: models can read digits or labels but misidentify the key positions of pointers or alignments, leading to big numeric errors despite plausible textual reasoning. We have also conducted preliminary experiments with reinforcement learning over synthetic data, and find encouraging results on in-domain synthetic subset but less promising for real-world images. Our analysis highlights a fundamental limitation of current VLMs in fine-grained spatial grounding. We hope this resource can help future advances on visually grounded numeracy and precise spatial perception of VLMs, bridging the gap between recognizing numbers and measuring the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26865</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:20:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ThinkMorph: Emergent Properties in Multimodal Interleaved   Chain-of-Thought Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27492</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27492.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiawei Gu, Yunzhuo Hao, Huichen Will Wang, Linjie Li, Michael Qizhe Shieh, Yejin Choi, Ranjay Krishna, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 78&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal reasoning requires iterative coordination between language and vision, yet it remains unclear what constitutes a meaningful interleaved chain of thought. We posit that text and image thoughts should function as complementary, rather than isomorphic, modalities that mutually advance reasoning. Guided by this principle, we build ThinkMorph, a unified model fine-tuned on 24K high-quality interleaved reasoning traces spanning tasks with varying visual engagement. ThinkMorph learns to generate progressive text-image reasoning steps that concretely manipulate visual content while maintaining coherent verbal logic. It delivers large gains on vision-centric benchmarks (averaging 34.7% over the base model) and generalizes to out-of-domain tasks, matching or surpassing larger and proprietary VLMs. Beyond performance, ThinkMorph exhibits emergent multimodal intelligence, including unseen visual manipulation skills, adaptive switching between reasoning modes, and better test-time scaling through diversified multimodal thoughts.These findings suggest promising directions for characterizing the emergent capabilities of unified models for multimodal reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27492</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defeating the Training-Inference Mismatch via FP16</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26788</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26788.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Penghui Qi, Zichen Liu, Xiangxin Zhou, Tianyu Pang, Chao Du, Wee Sun Lee, Min Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) fine-tuning of large language models (LLMs) often suffers from instability due to the numerical mismatch between the training and inference policies. While prior work has attempted to mitigate this issue through algorithmic corrections or engineering alignments, we show that its root cause lies in the floating point precision itself. The widely adopted BF16, despite its large dynamic range, introduces large rounding errors that breaks the consistency between training and inference. In this work, we demonstrate that simply reverting to FP16 effectively eliminates this mismatch. The change is simple, fully supported by modern frameworks with only a few lines of code change, and requires no modification to the model architecture or learning algorithm. Our results suggest that using FP16 uniformly yields more stable optimization, faster convergence, and stronger performance across diverse tasks, algorithms and frameworks. We hope these findings motivate a broader reconsideration of precision trade-offs in RL fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26788</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:58:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Denario project: Deep knowledge AI agents for scientific discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26887</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26887.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Boris Bolliet, Pablo Villanueva-Domingo, Adrian E. Bayer, Aidan Acquah, Chetana Amancharla, Almog Barzilay-Siegal, Pablo Bermejo, Camille Bilodeau, Pablo CÃ¡rdenas RamÃ­rez, Miles Cranmer, Urbano L. FranÃ§a, ChangHoon Hahn, Yan-Fei Jiang, Raul Jimenez, Jun-Young Lee, Antonio Lerario, Osman Mamun, Thomas Meier, Anupam A. Ojha, Pavlos Protopapas, Shimanto Roy, David N. Spergel, Pedro TarancÃ³n-Ãlvarez, Ujjwal Tiwari, Matteo Viel, Digvijay Wadekar, Chi Wang, Bonny Y. Wang, Licong Xu, Yossi Yovel, Shuwen Yue, Wen-Han Zhou, Qiyao Zhu, Jiajun Zou, ÃÃ±igo Zubeldia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Denario, an AI multi-agent system designed to serve as a scientific research assistant. Denario can perform many different tasks, such as generating ideas, checking the literature, developing research plans, writing and executing code, making plots, and drafting and reviewing a scientific paper. The system has a modular architecture, allowing it to handle specific tasks, such as generating an idea, or carrying out end-to-end scientific analysis using Cmbagent as a deep-research backend. In this work, we describe in detail Denario and its modules, and illustrate its capabilities by presenting multiple AI-generated papers generated by it in many different scientific disciplines such as astrophysics, biology, biophysics, biomedical informatics, chemistry, material science, mathematical physics, medicine, neuroscience and planetary science. Denario also excels at combining ideas from different disciplines, and we illustrate this by showing a paper that applies methods from quantum physics and machine learning to astrophysical data. We report the evaluations performed on these papers by domain experts, who provided both numerical scores and review-like feedback. We then highlight the strengths, weaknesses, and limitations of the current system. Finally, we discuss the ethical implications of AI-driven research and reflect on how such technology relates to the philosophy of science. We publicly release the code at https://github.com/AstroPilot-AI/Denario. A Denario demo can also be run directly on the web at https://huggingface.co/spaces/astropilot-ai/Denario, and the full app will be deployed on the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26887</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 18:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NaviTrace: Evaluating Embodied Navigation of Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26909</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26909.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tim Windecker, Manthan Patel, Moritz Reuss, Richard Schwarzkopf, Cesar Cadena, Rudolf Lioutikov, Marco Hutter, Jonas Frey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language models demonstrate unprecedented performance and generalization across a wide range of tasks and scenarios. Integrating these foundation models into robotic navigation systems opens pathways toward building general-purpose robots. Yet, evaluating these models' navigation capabilities remains constrained by costly real-world trials, overly simplified simulations, and limited benchmarks. We introduce NaviTrace, a high-quality Visual Question Answering benchmark where a model receives an instruction and embodiment type (human, legged robot, wheeled robot, bicycle) and must output a 2D navigation trace in image space. Across 1000 scenarios and more than 3000 expert traces, we systematically evaluate eight state-of-the-art VLMs using a newly introduced semantic-aware trace score. This metric combines Dynamic Time Warping distance, goal endpoint error, and embodiment-conditioned penalties derived from per-pixel semantics and correlates with human preferences. Our evaluation reveals consistent gap to human performance caused by poor spatial grounding and goal localization. NaviTrace establishes a scalable and reproducible benchmark for real-world robotic navigation. The benchmark and leaderboard can be found at https://leggedrobotics.github.io/navitrace_webpage/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26909</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 18:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limits of Generalization in RLVR: Two Case Studies in Mathematical   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27044</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27044.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Md Tanvirul Alam, Nidhi Rastogi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Mathematical reasoning is a central challenge for large language models (LLMs), requiring not only correct answers but also faithful reasoning processes. Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as a promising approach for enhancing such capabilities; however, its ability to foster genuine reasoning remains unclear. We investigate RLVR on two combinatorial problems with fully verifiable solutions: Activity Scheduling and the Longest Increasing Subsequence, using carefully curated datasets with unique optima. Across multiple reward designs, we find that RLVR improves evaluation metrics but often by reinforcing superficial heuristics rather than acquiring new reasoning strategies. These findings highlight the limits of RLVR generalization, emphasizing the importance of benchmarks that disentangle genuine mathematical reasoning from shortcut exploitation and provide faithful measures of progress. Code available at https://github.com/xashru/rlvr-seq-generalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27044</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 23:16:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mask-to-Height: A YOLOv11-Based Architecture for Joint Building Instance   Segmentation and Height Classification from Satellite Imagery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27224</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27224.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mahmoud El Hussieni, BahadÄ±r K. GÃ¼ntÃ¼rk, Hasan F. AteÅŸ, OÄŸuz HanoÄŸlu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Accurate building instance segmentation and height classification are critical for urban planning, 3D city modeling, and infrastructure monitoring. This paper presents a detailed analysis of YOLOv11, the recent advancement in the YOLO series of deep learning models, focusing on its application to joint building extraction and discrete height classification from satellite imagery. YOLOv11 builds on the strengths of earlier YOLO models by introducing a more efficient architecture that better combines features at different scales, improves object localization accuracy, and enhances performance in complex urban scenes. Using the DFC2023 Track 2 dataset -- which includes over 125,000 annotated buildings across 12 cities -- we evaluate YOLOv11's performance using metrics such as precision, recall, F1 score, and mean average precision (mAP). Our findings demonstrate that YOLOv11 achieves strong instance segmentation performance with 60.4\% mAP@50 and 38.3\% mAP@50--95 while maintaining robust classification accuracy across five predefined height tiers. The model excels in handling occlusions, complex building shapes, and class imbalance, particularly for rare high-rise structures. Comparative analysis confirms that YOLOv11 outperforms earlier multitask frameworks in both detection accuracy and inference speed, making it well-suited for real-time, large-scale urban mapping. This research highlights YOLOv11's potential to advance semantic urban reconstruction through streamlined categorical height modeling, offering actionable insights for future developments in remote sensing and geospatial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27224</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 06:37:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order Linear Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27258</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27258.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Zhang, Zhen Qin, Quanquan Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The quadratic cost of scaled dot-product attention is a central obstacle to scaling autoregressive language models to long contexts. Linear-time attention and State Space Models (SSMs) provide scalable alternatives but are typically restricted to first-order or kernel-based approximations, which can limit expressivity. We introduce Higher-order Linear Attention (HLA), a causal, streaming mechanism that realizes higher interactions via compact prefix sufficient statistics. In the second-order case, HLA maintains a constant-size state and computes per-token outputs in linear time without materializing any n times n matrices. We give closed-form streaming identities, a strictly causal masked variant using two additional summaries, and a chunk-parallel training scheme based on associative scans that reproduces the activations of a serial recurrence exactly. We further outline extensions to third and higher orders. Collectively, these results position HLA as a principled, scalable building block that combines attention-like, data-dependent mixing with the efficiency of modern recurrent architectures. Project Page: https://github.com/yifanzhang-pro/HLA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27258</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 07:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HyperClick: Advancing Reliable GUI Grounding via Uncertainty Calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27266</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27266.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaojie Zhang, Pei Fu, Ruoceng Zhang, Jiahui Yang, Anan Du, Xiuwen Xi, Shaokang Wang, Ying Huang, Bin Qin, Zhenbo Luo, Jian Luan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autonomous Graphical User Interface (GUI) agents rely on accurate GUI grounding, which maps language instructions to on-screen coordinates, to execute user commands. However, current models, whether trained via supervised fine-tuning (SFT) or reinforcement fine-tuning (RFT), lack self-awareness of their capability boundaries, leading to overconfidence and unreliable predictions. We first systematically evaluate probabilistic and verbalized confidence in general and GUI-specific models, revealing a misalignment between confidence and actual accuracy, which is particularly critical in dynamic GUI automation tasks, where single errors can cause task failure. To address this, we propose HyperClick, a novel framework that enhances reliable GUI grounding through uncertainty calibration. HyperClick introduces a dual reward mechanism, combining a binary reward for correct actions with a truncated Gaussian-based spatial confidence modeling, calibrated using the Brier score. This approach jointly optimizes grounding accuracy and confidence reliability, fostering introspective self-criticism. Extensive experiments on seven challenge benchmarks show that HyperClick achieves state-of-the-art performance while providing well-calibrated confidence. By enabling explicit confidence calibration and introspective self-criticism, HyperClick reduces overconfidence and supports more reliable GUI automation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27266</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 08:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ToolScope: An Agentic Framework for Vision-Guided and Long-Horizon Tool   Use</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27363</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27363.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengjie Deng, Guanting Dong, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable problem-solving capabilities by autonomously integrating with external tools for collaborative reasoning. However, due to the inherently complex and diverse nature of multimodal information, enabling multimodal large language models (MLLMs) to flexibly and efficiently utilize external tools during reasoning remains an underexplored challenge. In this work, we introduce ToolScope, an agentic framework designed to unify global planning with local multimodal perception, adopting a specialized Perceive tool to mitigates visual context degradation in long-horizon VQA task. ToolScope comprises three primary components: the Global Navigator, the Agentic Executor, and the Response Synthesizer. The Global Navigator functions as a "telescope", offering high-level strategic guidance. The Agentic Executor operates iteratively to augment MLLM with local perception through the integration of external tools-Search, Code, and Perceive. Finally, the Response Synthesizer consolidates and organizes the reasoning process into a coherent, user-friendly output. We evaluate ToolScope on four VQA benchmarks across diverse domains, including VQA 2.0, ScienceQA, MAT-Search and MathVista. It demonstrates strong generalization capabilities, achieving an average performance improvement of up to +6.69% across all datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27363</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 10:51:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EBT-Policy: Energy Unlocks Emergent Physical Reasoning Capabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27545</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27545.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Travis Davies, Yiqi Huang, Alexi Gladstone, Yunxin Liu, Xiang Chen, Heng Ji, Huxian Liu, Luhui Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Implicit policies parameterized by generative models, such as Diffusion Policy, have become the standard for policy learning and Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models in robotics. However, these approaches often suffer from high computational cost, exposure bias, and unstable inference dynamics, which lead to divergence under distribution shifts. Energy-Based Models (EBMs) address these issues by learning energy landscapes end-to-end and modeling equilibrium dynamics, offering improved robustness and reduced exposure bias. Yet, policies parameterized by EBMs have historically struggled to scale effectively. Recent work on Energy-Based Transformers (EBTs) demonstrates the scalability of EBMs to high-dimensional spaces, but their potential for solving core challenges in physically embodied models remains underexplored. We introduce a new energy-based architecture, EBT-Policy, that solves core issues in robotic and real-world settings. Across simulated and real-world tasks, EBT-Policy consistently outperforms diffusion-based policies, while requiring less training and inference computation. Remarkably, on some tasks it converges within just two inference steps, a 50x reduction compared to Diffusion Policy's 100. Moreover, EBT-Policy exhibits emergent capabilities not seen in prior models, such as zero-shot recovery from failed action sequences using only behavior cloning and without explicit retry training. By leveraging its scalar energy for uncertainty-aware inference and dynamic compute allocation, EBT-Policy offers a promising path toward robust, generalizable robot behavior under distribution shifts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27545</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 15:21:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Universal Video Retrieval: Generalizing Video Embedding via   Synthesized Multimodal Pyramid Curriculum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27571</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27571.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuoning Guo, Mingxin Li, Yanzhao Zhang, Dingkun Long, Pengjun Xie, Xiaowen Chu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The prevailing video retrieval paradigm is structurally misaligned, as narrow benchmarks incentivize correspondingly limited data and single-task training. Therefore, universal capability is suppressed due to the absence of a diagnostic evaluation that defines and demands multi-dimensional generalization. To break this cycle, we introduce a framework built on the co-design of evaluation, data, and modeling. First, we establish the Universal Video Retrieval Benchmark (UVRB), a suite of 16 datasets designed not only to measure performance but also to diagnose critical capability gaps across tasks and domains. Second, guided by UVRB's diagnostics, we introduce a scalable synthesis workflow that generates 1.55 million high-quality pairs to populate the semantic space required for universality. Finally, we devise the Modality Pyramid, a curriculum that trains our General Video Embedder (GVE) by explicitly leveraging the latent interconnections within our diverse data. Extensive experiments show GVE achieves state-of-the-art zero-shot generalization on UVRB. In particular, our analysis reveals that popular benchmarks are poor predictors of general ability and that partially relevant retrieval is a dominant but overlooked scenario. Overall, our co-designed framework provides a practical path to escape the limited scope and advance toward truly universal video retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27571</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 15:54:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial-SSRL: Enhancing Spatial Understanding via Self-Supervised   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27606</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27606.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhong Liu, Beichen Zhang, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Long Xing, Xiaoyi Dong, Haodong Duan, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatial understanding remains a weakness of Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs). Existing supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and recent reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) pipelines depend on costly supervision, specialized tools, or constrained environments that limit scale. We introduce Spatial-SSRL, a self-supervised RL paradigm that derives verifiable signals directly from ordinary RGB or RGB-D images. Spatial-SSRL automatically formulates five pretext tasks that capture 2D and 3D spatial structure: shuffled patch reordering, flipped patch recognition, cropped patch inpainting, regional depth ordering, and relative 3D position prediction. These tasks provide ground-truth answers that are easy to verify and require no human or LVLM annotation. Training on our tasks substantially improves spatial reasoning while preserving general visual capabilities. On seven spatial understanding benchmarks in both image and video settings, Spatial-SSRL delivers average accuracy gains of 4.63% (3B) and 3.89% (7B) over the Qwen2.5-VL baselines. Our results show that simple, intrinsic supervision enables RLVR at scale and provides a practical route to stronger spatial intelligence in LVLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27606</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual-Stream Diffusion for World-Model Augmented Vision-Language-Action   Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27607</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27607.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; John Won, Kyungmin Lee, Huiwon Jang, Dongyoung Kim, Jinwoo Shin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, augmenting Vision-Language-Action models (VLAs) with world modeling has shown promise in improving robotic policy learning. However, it remains challenging to jointly predict next-state observations and action sequences because of the inherent difference between the two modalities. To address this, we propose DUal-STream diffusion (DUST), a world-model augmented VLA framework that handles the modality conflict and enhances the performance of VLAs across diverse tasks. Specifically, we propose a multimodal diffusion transformer architecture that explicitly maintains separate modality streams while still enabling cross-modal knowledge sharing. In addition, we introduce independent noise perturbations for each modality and a decoupled flow-matching loss. This design enables the model to learn the joint distribution in a bidirectional manner while avoiding the need for a unified latent space. Based on the decoupling of modalities during training, we also introduce a joint sampling method that supports test-time scaling, where action and vision tokens evolve asynchronously at different rates. Through experiments on simulated benchmarks such as RoboCasa and GR-1, DUST achieves up to 6% gains over baseline methods, while our test-time scaling approach provides an additional 2-5% boost. On real-world tasks with the Franka Research 3, DUST improves success rates by 13%, confirming its effectiveness beyond simulation. Furthermore, pre-training on action-free videos from BridgeV2 yields significant transfer gains on RoboCasa, underscoring DUST's potential for large-scale VLA pretraining.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27607</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:32:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Backdoor Attacks on MLLM Embodied Decision Making via Contrastive   Trigger Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27623</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27623.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qiusi Zhan, Hyeonjeong Ha, Rui Yang, Sirui Xu, Hanyang Chen, Liang-Yan Gui, Yu-Xiong Wang, Huan Zhang, Heng Ji, Daniel Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have advanced embodied agents by enabling direct perception, reasoning, and planning task-oriented actions from visual inputs. However, such vision driven embodied agents open a new attack surface: visual backdoor attacks, where the agent behaves normally until a visual trigger appears in the scene, then persistently executes an attacker-specified multi-step policy. We introduce BEAT, the first framework to inject such visual backdoors into MLLM-based embodied agents using objects in the environments as triggers. Unlike textual triggers, object triggers exhibit wide variation across viewpoints and lighting, making them difficult to implant reliably. BEAT addresses this challenge by (1) constructing a training set that spans diverse scenes, tasks, and trigger placements to expose agents to trigger variability, and (2) introducing a two-stage training scheme that first applies supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and then our novel Contrastive Trigger Learning (CTL). CTL formulates trigger discrimination as preference learning between trigger-present and trigger-free inputs, explicitly sharpening the decision boundaries to ensure precise backdoor activation. Across various embodied agent benchmarks and MLLMs, BEAT achieves attack success rates up to 80%, while maintaining strong benign task performance, and generalizes reliably to out-of-distribution trigger placements. Notably, compared to naive SFT, CTL boosts backdoor activation accuracy up to 39% under limited backdoor data. These findings expose a critical yet unexplored security risk in MLLM-based embodied agents, underscoring the need for robust defenses before real-world deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27623</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 16:50:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RDMA Point-to-Point Communication for LLM Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27656</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27656.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nandor Licker, Kevin Hu, Vladimir Zaytsev, Lequn Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Emerging Large Language Model (LLM) system patterns, such as disaggregated inference, Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) routing, and asynchronous reinforcement fine-tuning, require flexible point-to-point communication beyond simple collectives. Existing implementations are locked to specific Network Interface Controllers (NICs), hindering integration into inference engines and portability across hardware providers. We present TransferEngine, which bridges the functionality of common NICs to expose a uniform interface. TransferEngine exposes one-sided WriteImm operations with a ImmCounter primitive for completion notification, without ordering assumptions of network transport, transparently managing multiple NICs per GPU. We demonstrate peak throughput of 400 Gbps on both NVIDIA ConnectX-7 and AWS Elastic Fabric Adapter (EFA). We showcase TransferEngine through three production systems: (1) KvCache transfer for disaggregated inference with dynamic scaling, (2) RL weight updates achieving 1.3 seconds for trillion-parameter models, and (3) MoE dispatch/combine implementation exceeding DeepEP decode latency on ConnectX-7, with the first viable latencies on EFA. We demonstrate that our portable point-to-point communication complements collectives while avoiding lock-in.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27656</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 17:28:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phased DMD: Few-step Distribution Matching Distillation via Score   Matching within Subintervals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27684</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27684.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangyu Fan, Zesong Qiu, Zhuguanyu Wu, Fanzhou Wang, Zhiqian Lin, Tianxiang Ren, Dahua Lin, Ruihao Gong, Lei Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Distribution Matching Distillation (DMD) distills score-based generative models into efficient one-step generators, without requiring a one-to-one correspondence with the sampling trajectories of their teachers. However, limited model capacity causes one-step distilled models underperform on complex generative tasks, e.g., synthesizing intricate object motions in text-to-video generation. Directly extending DMD to multi-step distillation increases memory usage and computational depth, leading to instability and reduced efficiency. While prior works propose stochastic gradient truncation as a potential solution, we observe that it substantially reduces the generation diversity of multi-step distilled models, bringing it down to the level of their one-step counterparts. To address these limitations, we propose Phased DMD, a multi-step distillation framework that bridges the idea of phase-wise distillation with Mixture-of-Experts (MoE), reducing learning difficulty while enhancing model capacity. Phased DMD is built upon two key ideas: progressive distribution matching and score matching within subintervals. First, our model divides the SNR range into subintervals, progressively refining the model to higher SNR levels, to better capture complex distributions. Next, to ensure the training objective within each subinterval is accurate, we have conducted rigorous mathematical derivations. We validate Phased DMD by distilling state-of-the-art image and video generation models, including Qwen-Image (20B parameters) and Wan2.2 (28B parameters). Experimental results demonstrate that Phased DMD preserves output diversity better than DMD while retaining key generative capabilities. We will release our code and models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27684</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 17:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous Autoregressive Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27688</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27688.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenze Shao, Darren Li, Fandong Meng, Jie Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The efficiency of large language models (LLMs) is fundamentally limited by their sequential, token-by-token generation process. We argue that overcoming this bottleneck requires a new design axis for LLM scaling: increasing the semantic bandwidth of each generative step. To this end, we introduce Continuous Autoregressive Language Models (CALM), a paradigm shift from discrete next-token prediction to continuous next-vector prediction. CALM uses a high-fidelity autoencoder to compress a chunk of K tokens into a single continuous vector, from which the original tokens can be reconstructed with over 99.9\% accuracy. This allows us to model language as a sequence of continuous vectors instead of discrete tokens, which reduces the number of generative steps by a factor of K. The paradigm shift necessitates a new modeling toolkit; therefore, we develop a comprehensive likelihood-free framework that enables robust training, evaluation, and controllable sampling in the continuous domain. Experiments show that CALM significantly improves the performance-compute trade-off, achieving the performance of strong discrete baselines at a significantly lower computational cost. More importantly, these findings establish next-vector prediction as a powerful and scalable pathway towards ultra-efficient language models. Code: https://github.com/shaochenze/calm. Project: https://shaochenze.github.io/blog/2025/CALM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27688</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 17:58:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongCat-Flash-Omni Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00279</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00279.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Meituan LongCat Team, Bairui Wang, Bayan, Bin Xiao, Bo Zhang, Bolin Rong, Borun Chen, Chang Wan, Chao Zhang, Chen Huang, Chen Chen, Chen Chen, Chengxu Yang, Chengzuo Yang, Cong Han, Dandan Peng, Delian Ruan, Detai Xin, Disong Wang, Dongchao Yang, Fanfan Liu, Fengjiao Chen, Fengyu Yang, Gan Dong, Gang Huang, Gang Xu, Guanglu Wan, Guoqiang Tan, Guoqiao Yu, Haibo Qiu, Hao Lu, Hongbo Liu, Hongyu Xiang, Jiaheng Wu, Jian Yang, Jiaxing Liu, Jing Huang, Jingang Wang, Jinrui Ding, Juchao Jiang, Jun Kuang, Jun Wang, Junhui Mei, Ke Ding, Kefeng Zhang, Lei Chen, Liang Shi, Limeng Qiao, Liming Zheng, Lin Ma, Liuyang Guo, Liya Ma, Luying Sun, Man Gao, Mengshen Zhu, Miao Cao, Minliang Lin, Nuo Xu, Peng Shi, Qi Zhang, Qian Fang, Qian Wang, Qian Yang, Quanxiu Wang, Rongxiang Weng, Rongxin Guo, Ruoxuan Liang, Senbin Yang, Shanbo Xu, Shanglin Lei, Shengze Ye, Shimin Chen, Shuaiqi Chen, Shujie Hu, Shuo Li, Siqi Yang, Siyu Xu, Siyu Ren, Song Li, Songxiang Liu, Tianhao Bai, Tianye Dai, Wei Hong, Wei Wang, Weixiao Zhao, Wengang Cao, Wenlong Zhu, Wenlong He, Xi Su, Xi Nan, Xiaohan Zhao, Xiaohao Wang, Xiaoyu Zhao, Xiaoyu Wang, Xiaoyu Li, Xin Pan, Xin Chen, Xiusong Sun, Xu Xiang, Xudong Xing, Xuezhi Cao, Xunliang Cai, Yang Yang, Yanli Tan, Yao Yao, Yerui Sun, Yi Chen, Yifan Lu, Yin Gong, Yining Zhang, Yitian Chen, Yiyang Gan, Yuchen Tang, Yuchen Xie, Yueqian Wang, Yuewen Zheng, Yufei Zhang, Yufeng Zhong, Yulei Qian, Yuqi Peng, Yuwei Jiang, Zeyang Hu, Zheng Zhang, Zhengkun Tian, Zhiqing Hong, Zhixiong Zeng, Zhuqi Mi, Ziran Li, Ziwen Wang, Ziyi Zhao, Ziyuan Zhuang, Zizhe Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce LongCat-Flash-Omni, a state-of-the-art open-source omni-modal model with 560 billion parameters, excelling at real-time audio-visual interaction. By adopting a curriculum-inspired progressive training strategy that transitions from simpler to increasingly complex modality sequence modeling tasks, LongCat-Flash-Omni attains comprehensive multimodal capabilities while maintaining strong unimodal capability. Building upon LongCat-Flash, which adopts a high-performance Shortcut-connected Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture with zero-computation experts, LongCat-Flash-Omni integrates efficient multimodal perception and speech reconstruction modules. Despite its immense size of 560B parameters (with 27B activated), LongCat-Flash-Omni achieves low-latency real-time audio-visual interaction. For training infrastructure, we developed a modality-decoupled parallelism scheme specifically designed to manage the data and model heterogeneity inherent in large-scale multimodal training. This innovative approach demonstrates exceptional efficiency by sustaining over 90% of the throughput achieved by text-only training. Extensive evaluations show that LongCat-Flash-Omni achieves state-of-the-art performance on omni-modal benchmarks among open-source models. Furthermore, it delivers highly competitive results across a wide range of modality-specific tasks, including text, image, and video understanding, as well as audio understanding and generation. We provide a comprehensive overview of the model architecture design, training procedures, and data strategies, and open-source the model to foster future research and development in the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00279</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 21:58:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UME-R1: Exploring Reasoning-Driven Generative Multimodal Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00405</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00405.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhibin Lan, Liqiang Niu, Fandong Meng, Jie Zhou, Jinsong Su&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The remarkable success of multimodal large language models (MLLMs) has driven advances in multimodal embeddings, yet existing models remain inherently discriminative, limiting their ability to benefit from reasoning-driven generation paradigm. In this work, we pioneer the exploration of generative embeddings, unifying embedding tasks within a generative paradigm. We propose UME-R1, a universal multimodal embedding framework consisting of a two-stage training strategy: a cold-start supervised fine-tuning equips the model with reasoning capabilities and enables it to generate both discriminative and generative embeddings; a subsequent reinforcement learning enhances reasoning and further optimizes generative embedding quality. This pioneering work reveals four key insights: 1) generative embeddings unlock substantial performance gains over conventional discriminative embeddings by leveraging the powerful generative reasoning capabilities of MLLMs; 2) discriminative and generative embeddings are complementary, whose combined oracle performance far exceeding that of either alone; 3) RL can effectively enhance generative embeddings, establishing a scalable optimization paradigm.; 4) repeated sampling at inference boosts downstream task coverage (pass@k), highlighting the inference-time scalability potential of generative embeddings. Evaluated on the MMEB-V2 benchmark across 78 tasks spanning video, image, and visual documents, UME-R1 significantly outperforms conventional discriminative embedding models and offers a foundation for more interpretable, reasoning-driven generative multimodal embeddings. Our code, models, and datasets will be publicly available at https://github.com/XMUDeepLIT/UME-R1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00405</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 05:04:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>iFlyBot-VLA Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01914</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01914.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuan Zhang, Chenyu Xue, Wenjie Xu, Chao Ji, Jiajia wu, Jia Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce iFlyBot-VLA, a large-scale Vision-Language-Action (VLA) model trained under a novel framework. The main contributions are listed as follows: (1) a latent action model thoroughly trained on large-scale human and robotic manipulation videos; (2) a dual-level action representation framework that jointly supervises both the Vision-Language Model (VLM) and the action expert during training; (3) a mixed training strategy that combines robot trajectory data with general QA and spatial QA datasets, effectively enhancing the 3D perceptual and reasoning capabilities of the VLM backbone. Specifically, the VLM is trained to predict two complementary forms of actions: latent actions, derived from our latent action model pretrained on cross-embodiment manipulation data, which capture implicit high-level intentions; and structured discrete action tokens, obtained through frequency-domain transformations of continuous control signals, which encode explicit low-level dynamics. This dual supervision aligns the representation spaces of language, vision, and action, enabling the VLM to directly contribute to action generation. Experimental results on the LIBERO Franka benchmark demonstrate the superiority of our frame-work, while real-world evaluations further show that iFlyBot-VLA achieves competitive success rates across diverse and challenging manipulation tasks. Furthermore, we plan to open-source a portion of our self-constructed dataset to support future research in the community&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01914</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 06:24:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenSIR: Open-Ended Self-Improving Reasoner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00602</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00602.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wai-Chung Kwan, Joshua Ong Jun Leang, Pavlos Vougiouklis, Jeff Z. Pan, Marco Valentino, Pasquale Minervini&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language model (LLM) reasoning through reinforcement learning rely on annotated datasets for verifiable rewards, which may limit models' ability to surpass human-level performance. While self-play offers a promising alternative, existing approaches depend on external verifiers or cannot learn open-endedly. We present Open-Ended Self-Improving Reasoner (OpenSIR), a self-play framework where an LLM learns to generate and solve novel problems by alternating teacher and student roles without external supervision. To generate novel problems, OpenSIR optimises for both difficulty and diversity, rewarding problems that challenge appropriately while exploring distinct concepts, enabling open-ended mathematical discovery. Starting from a single trivial seed problem, OpenSIR substantially improves instruction models: Llama-3.2-3B-Instruct advances from 73.9 to 78.3 on GSM8K, and from 28.8 to 34.4 on College Math, while Gemma-2-2B-Instruct rises from 38.5 to 58.7 on GSM8K. Our analyses reveal that OpenSIR achieves open-ended learning through co-evolving teacher-student roles that adaptively calibrate difficulty and drive diverse exploration, progressing autonomously from basic to advanced mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00602</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 16:08:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GUI-AIMA: Aligning Intrinsic Multimodal Attention with a Context Anchor   for GUI Grounding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00810</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00810.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shijie Zhou, Viet Dac Lai, Hao Tan, Jihyung Kil, Wanrong Zhu, Changyou Chen, Ruiyi Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graphical user interface (GUI) grounding is a key function of computer-use agents, which maps natural-language instructions to actionable screen regions. Existing approaches based on Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) typically formulate it as a text-based coordinate generation task, yet directly generating precise coordinates from visual inputs remains challenging and computationally intensive. An intuitive way to implement GUI grounding is to first select visual patches relevant to the instructions and then determine the precise click location within those patches. Based on the observations that general MLLMs have some native grounding capability, nested within their attentions, we propose GUI-AIMA, an attention-based and coordinate-free supervised fine-tuning framework for efficient GUI grounding. GUI-AIMA aligns the intrinsic multimodal attention of MLLMs with patch-wise grounding signals. These signals are calculated adaptively for diverse user instructions by multi-head aggregation on simplified query-visual attention matrices. Besides, its coordinate-free manner can easily integrate a plug-and-play zoom-in stage. GUI-AIMA-3B was trained with only 85k screenshots, demonstrating exceptional data efficiency and verifying that light training can trigger the native grounding capability of MLLMs. It achieves state-of-the-art performance among 3B models, attaining an average accuracy of 58.6% on ScreenSpot-Pro and 62.2% on OSWorld-G. Project page: https://github.com/sjz5202/GUI-AIMA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00810</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 05:34:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CodeClash: Benchmarking Goal-Oriented Software Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00839</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00839.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; John Yang, Kilian Lieret, Joyce Yang, Carlos E. Jimenez, Ofir Press, Ludwig Schmidt, Diyi Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current benchmarks for coding evaluate language models (LMs) on concrete, well-specified tasks such as fixing specific bugs or writing targeted tests. However, human programmers do not spend all day incessantly addressing isolated tasks. Instead, real-world software development is grounded in the pursuit of high-level goals, like improving user retention or reducing costs. Evaluating whether LMs can also iteratively develop code to better accomplish open-ended objectives without any explicit guidance remains an open challenge. To address this, we introduce CodeClash, a benchmark where LMs compete in multi-round tournaments to build the best codebase for achieving a competitive objective. Each round proceeds in two phases: agents edit their code, then their codebases compete head-to-head in a code arena that determines winners based on objectives like score maximization, resource acquisition, or survival. Whether it's writing notes, scrutinizing documentation, analyzing competition logs, or creating test suites, models must decide for themselves how to improve their codebases both absolutely and against their opponents. We run 1680 tournaments (25,200 rounds total) to evaluate 8 LMs across 6 arenas. Our results reveal that while models exhibit diverse development styles, they share fundamental limitations in strategic reasoning. Models also struggle with long-term codebase maintenance, as repositories become progressively messy and redundant. These limitations are stark: top models lose every round against expert human programmers. We open-source CodeClash to advance the study of autonomous, goal-oriented code development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00839</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 07:42:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EVTAR: End-to-End Try on with Additional Unpaired Visual Reference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00956</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00956.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liuzhuozheng Li, Yue Gong, Shanyuan Liu, Bo Cheng, Yuhang Ma, Liebucha Wu, Dengyang Jiang, Zanyi Wang, Dawei Leng, Yuhui Yin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose EVTAR, an End-to-End Virtual Try-on model with Additional Reference, that directly fits the target garment onto the person image while incorporating reference images to enhance try-on accuracy. Most existing virtual try-on approaches rely on complex inputs such as agnostic person images, human pose, densepose, or body keypoints, making them labor-intensive and impractical for real-world applications. In contrast, EVTAR adopts a two-stage training strategy, enabling simple inference with only the source image and the target garment inputs. Our model generates try-on results without masks, densepose, or segmentation maps. Moreover, EVTAR leverages additional reference images of different individuals wearing the same clothes to preserve garment texture and fine-grained details better. This mechanism is analogous to how humans consider reference models when choosing outfits, thereby simulating a more realistic and high-quality dressing effect. We enrich the training data with supplementary references and unpaired person images to support these capabilities. We evaluate EVTAR on two widely used benchmarks and diverse tasks, and the results consistently validate the effectiveness of our approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00956</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 14:32:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shorter but not Worse: Frugal Reasoning via Easy Samples as Length   Regularizers in Math RLVR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01937</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01937.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abdelaziz Bounhar, Hadi Abdine, Evan Dufraisse, Ahmad Chamma, Amr Mohamed, Dani Bouch, Michalis Vazirgiannis, Guokan Shang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) trained for step-by-step reasoning often become excessively verbose, raising inference cost. Standard Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) pipelines filter out ``easy'' problems for training efficiency, leaving the model to train primarily on harder problems that require longer reasoning chains. This skews the output length distribution upward, resulting in a model that conflates ``thinking longer'' with ``thinking better''. In this work, we show that retaining and modestly up-weighting moderately easy problems acts as an implicit length regularizer. Exposing the model to solvable short-chain tasks constrains its output distribution and prevents runaway verbosity. The result is \emph{emergent brevity for free}: the model learns to solve harder problems without inflating the output length,  despite the absence of any explicit length penalization. RLVR experiments using this approach on Qwen3-4B-Thinking-2507 (with a 16k token limit) achieve baseline pass@1 AIME25 accuracy while generating solutions that are, on average, nearly twice as short. The code is available at https://github.com/MBZUAI-Paris/Frugal-AI{GitHub}, with datasets and models on https://huggingface.co/collections/MBZUAI-Paris/k2-think-mini-68dcfa8b114686a4bd3dc2bc{Hugging Face}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01937</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 17:29:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AthenaBench: A Dynamic Benchmark for Evaluating LLMs in Cyber Threat   Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01144</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01144.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Md Tanvirul Alam, Dipkamal Bhusal, Salman Ahmad, Nidhi Rastogi, Peter Worth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated strong capabilities in natural language reasoning, yet their application to Cyber Threat Intelligence (CTI) remains limited. CTI analysis involves distilling large volumes of unstructured reports into actionable knowledge, a process where LLMs could substantially reduce analyst workload. CTIBench introduced a comprehensive benchmark for evaluating LLMs across multiple CTI tasks. In this work, we extend CTIBench by developing AthenaBench, an enhanced benchmark that includes an improved dataset creation pipeline, duplicate removal, refined evaluation metrics, and a new task focused on risk mitigation strategies. We evaluate twelve LLMs, including state-of-the-art proprietary models such as GPT-5 and Gemini-2.5 Pro, alongside seven open-source models from the LLaMA and Qwen families. While proprietary LLMs achieve stronger results overall, their performance remains subpar on reasoning-intensive tasks, such as threat actor attribution and risk mitigation, with open-source models trailing even further behind. These findings highlight fundamental limitations in the reasoning capabilities of current LLMs and underscore the need for models explicitly tailored to CTI workflows and automation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01144</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 01:45:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ROVER: Benchmarking Reciprocal Cross-Modal Reasoning for Omnimodal   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01163</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01163.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yongyuan Liang, Wei Chow, Feng Li, Ziqiao Ma, Xiyao Wang, Jiageng Mao, Jiuhai Chen, Jiatao Gu, Yue Wang, Furong Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified multimodal models (UMMs) have emerged as a powerful paradigm for seamlessly unifying text and image understanding and generation. However, prevailing evaluations treat these abilities in isolation, such that tasks with multimodal inputs and outputs are scored primarily through unimodal reasoning, i.e., textual benchmarks emphasize language-based reasoning, while visual benchmarks emphasize reasoning outcomes manifested in the pixels. We introduce ROVER to address this pressing need to test reciprocal cross-modal reasoning, the use of one modality to guide, verify, or refine outputs in the other, an ability central to the vision of unified multimodal intelligence. ROVER is a human-annotated benchmark that explicitly targets reciprocal cross-modal reasoning, which contains 1312 tasks grounded in 1876 images, spanning two complementary settings. Verbally-augmented reasoning for visual generation evaluates whether models can use verbal prompts and reasoning chains to guide faithful image synthesis. Visually-augmented reasoning for verbal generation evaluates whether models can generate intermediate visualizations that strengthen their own reasoning processes for question answering. Experiments on 17 unified models reveal two key findings: (i) Cross-modal reasoning determines visual generation quality, with interleaved models significantly outperforming non-interleaved ones; notably, combining strong unimodal models fails to achieve comparable reasoning. (ii) Models show dissociation between physical and symbolic reasoning: they succeed at interpreting perceptual concepts literally but fail to construct visual abstractions for symbolic tasks, where faulty reasoning harms performance. These results highlight reciprocal cross-modal reasoning as a critical frontier for enabling true omnimodal generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01163</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 02:27:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forget BIT, It is All about TOKEN: Towards Semantic Information Theory   for LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01202</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01202.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bo Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in numerous real-world applications. While the vast majority of research conducted from an experimental perspective is progressing rapidly, it demands substantial computational power, data, and other resources. Therefore, how to open the black-box of LLMs from a theoretical standpoint has become a critical challenge. This paper takes the theory of rate-distortion function, directed information, and Granger causality as its starting point to investigate the information-theoretic principles behind LLMs, leading to the development of semantic information theory for LLMs, where the fundamental unit is token, rather than bits that lacks any semantic meaning. By defining the probabilistic model of LLMs, we discuss structure-agnostic information-theoretic measures, such as the directed rate-distortion function in pre-training, the directed rate-reward function in post-training, and the semantic information flow in inference phase. This paper also delves deeply into the theory of token-level semantic embedding and the information-theoretically optimal vectorization method. Thereafter, we propose a general definition of autoregression LLM, where the Transformer architecture and its performance such as ELBO, generalization error bound, memory capacity, and semantic information measures can be derived theoretically. Other architectures, such as Mamba/Mamba2 and LLaDA, are also discussed in our framework. Consequently, this paper provides a theoretical framework for understanding LLMs from the perspective of semantic information theory, which also offers the necessary theoretical tools for further in-depth research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01202</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 03:56:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MotionStream: Real-Time Video Generation with Interactive Motion   Controls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01266</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01266.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Joonghyuk Shin, Zhengqi Li, Richard Zhang, Jun-Yan Zhu, Jaesik Park, Eli Schechtman, Xun Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current motion-conditioned video generation methods suffer from prohibitive latency (minutes per video) and non-causal processing that prevents real-time interaction. We present MotionStream, enabling sub-second latency with up to 29 FPS streaming generation on a single GPU. Our approach begins by augmenting a text-to-video model with motion control, which generates high-quality videos that adhere to the global text prompt and local motion guidance, but does not perform inference on the fly. As such, we distill this bidirectional teacher into a causal student through Self Forcing with Distribution Matching Distillation, enabling real-time streaming inference. Several key challenges arise when generating videos of long, potentially infinite time-horizons: (1) bridging the domain gap from training on finite length and extrapolating to infinite horizons, (2) sustaining high quality by preventing error accumulation, and (3) maintaining fast inference, without incurring growth in computational cost due to increasing context windows. A key to our approach is introducing carefully designed sliding-window causal attention, combined with attention sinks. By incorporating self-rollout with attention sinks and KV cache rolling during training, we properly simulate inference-time extrapolations with a fixed context window, enabling constant-speed generation of arbitrarily long videos. Our models achieve state-of-the-art results in motion following and video quality while being two orders of magnitude faster, uniquely enabling infinite-length streaming. With MotionStream, users can paint trajectories, control cameras, or transfer motion, and see results unfold in real-time, delivering a truly interactive experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01266</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 06:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinematify: Open-Vocabulary Synthesis of High-DoF Articulated Objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01294</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01294.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiawei Wang, Dingyou Wang, Jiaming Hu, Qixuan Zhang, Jingyi Yu, Lan Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A deep understanding of kinematic structures and movable components is essential for enabling robots to manipulate objects and model their own articulated forms. Such understanding is captured through articulated objects, which are essential for tasks such as physical simulation, motion planning, and policy learning. However, creating these models, particularly for objects with high degrees of freedom (DoF), remains a significant challenge. Existing methods typically rely on motion sequences or strong assumptions from hand-curated datasets, which hinders scalability. In this paper, we introduce Kinematify, an automated framework that synthesizes articulated objects directly from arbitrary RGB images or textual descriptions. Our method addresses two core challenges: (i) inferring kinematic topologies for high-DoF objects and (ii) estimating joint parameters from static geometry. To achieve this, we combine MCTS search for structural inference with geometry-driven optimization for joint reasoning, producing physically consistent and functionally valid descriptions. We evaluate Kinematify on diverse inputs from both synthetic and real-world environments, demonstrating improvements in registration and kinematic topology accuracy over prior work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01294</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 07:21:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniREditBench: A Unified Reasoning-based Image Editing Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01295</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01295.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Feng Han, Yibin Wang, Chenglin Li, Zheming Liang, Dianyi Wang, Yang Jiao, Zhipeng Wei, Chao Gong, Cheng Jin, Jingjing Chen, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multi-modal generative models have driven substantial improvements in image editing. However, current generative models still struggle with handling diverse and complex image editing tasks that require implicit reasoning, underscoring the need for a comprehensive benchmark to systematically assess their performance across various reasoning scenarios. Existing benchmarks primarily focus on single-object attribute transformation in realistic scenarios, which, while effective, encounter two key challenges: (1) they largely overlook multi-object interactions as well as game-world scenarios that involve human-defined rules, which are common in real-life applications; (2) they only rely on textual references to evaluate the generated images, potentially leading to systematic misjudgments, especially in complex reasoning scenarios. To this end, this work proposes UniREditBench, a unified benchmark for reasoning-based image editing evaluation. It comprises 2,700 meticulously curated samples, covering both real- and game-world scenarios across 8 primary dimensions and 18 sub-dimensions. To improve evaluation reliability, we introduce multimodal dual-reference evaluation, providing both textual and ground-truth image references for each sample assessment. Furthermore, we design an automated multi-scenario data synthesis pipeline and construct UniREdit-Data-100K, a large-scale synthetic dataset with high-quality chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning annotations. We fine-tune Bagel on this dataset and develop UniREdit-Bagel, demonstrating substantial improvements in both in-domain and out-of-distribution settings. Through thorough benchmarking of both open-source and closed-source image editing models, we reveal their strengths and weaknesses across various aspects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01295</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 07:24:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>left|,circlearrowright,text{BUS},right|: A Large and   Diverse Multimodal Benchmark for evaluating the ability of Vision-Language   Models to understand Rebus Puzzles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01340</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01340.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Trishanu Das, Abhilash Nandy, Khush Bajaj, Deepiha S&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding Rebus Puzzles (Rebus Puzzles use pictures, symbols, and letters to represent words or phrases creatively) requires a variety of skills such as image recognition, cognitive skills, commonsense reasoning, multi-step reasoning, image-based wordplay, etc., making this a challenging task for even current Vision-Language Models. In this paper, we present left|,circlearrowright,text{BUS},right|, a large and diverse benchmark of 1,333 English Rebus Puzzles containing different artistic styles and levels of difficulty, spread across 18 categories such as food, idioms, sports, finance, entertainment, etc. We also propose RebusDescProgICE, a model-agnostic framework which uses a combination of an unstructured description and code-based, structured reasoning, along with better, reasoning-based in-context example selection, improving the performance of Vision-Language Models on left|,circlearrowright,text{BUS},right| by 2.1-4.1% and 20-30% using closed-source and open-source models respectively compared to Chain-of-Thought Reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01340</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 08:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reg-DPO: SFT-Regularized Direct Preference Optimization with GT-Pair for   Improving Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01450</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01450.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jie Du, Xinyu Gong, Qingshan Tan, Wen Li, Yangming Cheng, Weitao Wang, Chenlu Zhan, Suhui Wu, Hao Zhang, Jun Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have identified Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) as an efficient and reward-free approach to improving video generation quality. However, existing methods largely follow image-domain paradigms and are mainly developed on small-scale models (approximately 2B parameters), limiting their ability to address the unique challenges of video tasks, such as costly data construction, unstable training, and heavy memory consumption. To overcome these limitations, we introduce a GT-Pair that automatically builds high-quality preference pairs by using real videos as positives and model-generated videos as negatives, eliminating the need for any external annotation. We further present Reg-DPO, which incorporates the SFT loss as a regularization term into the DPO objective to enhance training stability and generation fidelity. Additionally, by combining the FSDP framework with multiple memory optimization techniques, our approach achieves nearly three times higher training capacity than using FSDP alone. Extensive experiments on both I2V and T2V tasks across multiple datasets demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms existing approaches, delivering superior video generation quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01450</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 11:04:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discriminately Treating Motion Components Evolves Joint Depth and   Ego-Motion Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01502</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01502.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengtan Zhang, Zizhan Guo, Hongbo Zhao, Yi Feng, Zuyi Xiong, Yue Wang, Shaoyi Du, Hanli Wang, Rui Fan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unsupervised learning of depth and ego-motion, two fundamental 3D perception tasks, has made significant strides in recent years. However, most methods treat ego-motion as an auxiliary task, either mixing all motion types or excluding depth-independent rotational motions in supervision. Such designs limit the incorporation of strong geometric constraints, reducing reliability and robustness under diverse conditions. This study introduces a discriminative treatment of motion components, leveraging the geometric regularities of their respective rigid flows to benefit both depth and ego-motion estimation. Given consecutive video frames, network outputs first align the optical axes and imaging planes of the source and target cameras. Optical flows between frames are transformed through these alignments, and deviations are quantified to impose geometric constraints individually on each ego-motion component, enabling more targeted refinement. These alignments further reformulate the joint learning process into coaxial and coplanar forms, where depth and each translation component can be mutually derived through closed-form geometric relationships, introducing complementary constraints that improve depth robustness. DiMoDE, a general depth and ego-motion joint learning framework incorporating these designs, achieves state-of-the-art performance on multiple public datasets and a newly collected diverse real-world dataset, particularly under challenging conditions. Our source code will be publicly available at mias.group/DiMoDE upon publication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01502</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 12:14:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vote-in-Context: Turning VLMs into Zero-Shot Rank Fusers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01617</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01617.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohamed Eltahir, Ali Habibullah, Lama Ayash, Tanveer Hussain, Naeemullah Khan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In the retrieval domain, candidates' fusion from heterogeneous retrievers is a long-standing challenge, particularly for complex, multi-modal data such as videos. While typical fusion techniques are training-free, they rely solely on rank or score signals, disregarding candidates' representations. This work introduces Vote-in-Context (ViC), a generalized, training-free framework that re-thinks list-wise reranking and fusion as a zero-shot reasoning task for a Vision-Language Model (VLM). The core insight is to serialize both content evidence and retriever metadata directly within the VLM's prompt, allowing the model to adaptively weigh retriever consensus against visual-linguistic content. We demonstrate the generality of this framework by applying it to the challenging domain of cross-modal video retrieval. To this end, we introduce the S-Grid, a compact serialization map that represents each video as an image grid, optionally paired with subtitles to enable list-wise reasoning over video candidates. ViC is evaluated both as a single-list reranker, where it dramatically improves the precision of individual retrievers, and as an ensemble fuser, where it consistently outperforms strong baselines like CombSUM. Across video retrieval benchmarks including ActivityNet and VATEX, the framework establishes new state-of-the-art zero-shot retrieval performance, demonstrating its effectiveness in handling complex visual and temporal signals alongside text. In zero-shot settings, ViC achieves Recall@1 scores of 87.1% (t2v) / 89.0% (v2t) on MSR-VTT and 99.6% (v2t) on VATEX, representing massive gains of up to +40 Recall@1 over previous state-of-the-art baselines. We present ViC as a simple, reproducible, and highly effective recipe for turning modern VLMs into powerful zero-shot rerankers and fusers. Code and resources are publicly available at: https://github.com/mohammad2012191/ViC&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01617</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 14:25:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Actial: Activate Spatial Reasoning Ability of Multimodal Large Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoyu Zhan, Wenxuan Huang, Hao Sun, Xinyu Fu, Changfeng Ma, Shaosheng Cao, Bohan Jia, Shaohui Lin, Zhenfei Yin, Lei Bai, Wanli Ouyang, Yuanqi Li, Jie Guo, Yanwen Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have significantly improved 2D visual understanding, prompting interest in their application to complex 3D reasoning tasks. However, it remains unclear whether these models can effectively capture the detailed spatial information required for robust real-world performance, especially cross-view consistency, a key requirement for accurate 3D reasoning. Considering this issue, we introduce Viewpoint Learning, a task designed to evaluate and improve the spatial reasoning capabilities of MLLMs. We present the Viewpoint-100K dataset, consisting of 100K object-centric image pairs with diverse viewpoints and corresponding question-answer pairs. Our approach employs a two-stage fine-tuning strategy: first, foundational knowledge is injected to the baseline MLLM via Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) on Viewpoint-100K, resulting in significant improvements across multiple tasks; second, generalization is enhanced through Reinforcement Learning using the Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) algorithm on a broader set of questions. Additionally, we introduce a hybrid cold-start initialization method designed to simultaneously learn viewpoint representations and maintain coherent reasoning thinking. Experimental results show that our approach significantly activates the spatial reasoning ability of MLLM, improving performance on both in-domain and out-of-domain reasoning tasks. Our findings highlight the value of developing foundational spatial skills in MLLMs, supporting future progress in robotics, autonomous systems, and 3D scene understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01618</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 14:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniLumos: Fast and Unified Image and Video Relighting with   Physics-Plausible Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01678</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01678.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ropeway Liu, Hangjie Yuan, Bo Dong, Jiazheng Xing, Jinwang Wang, Rui Zhao, Yan Xing, Weihua Chen, Fan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Relighting is a crucial task with both practical demand and artistic value, and recent diffusion models have shown strong potential by enabling rich and controllable lighting effects. However, as they are typically optimized in semantic latent space, where proximity does not guarantee physical correctness in visual space, they often produce unrealistic results, such as overexposed highlights, misaligned shadows, and incorrect occlusions. We address this with UniLumos, a unified relighting framework for both images and videos that brings RGB-space geometry feedback into a flow matching backbone. By supervising the model with depth and normal maps extracted from its outputs, we explicitly align lighting effects with the scene structure, enhancing physical plausibility. Nevertheless, this feedback requires high-quality outputs for supervision in visual space, making standard multi-step denoising computationally expensive. To mitigate this, we employ path consistency learning, allowing supervision to remain effective even under few-step training regimes. To enable fine-grained relighting control and supervision, we design a structured six-dimensional annotation protocol capturing core illumination attributes. Building upon this, we propose LumosBench, a disentangled attribute-level benchmark that evaluates lighting controllability via large vision-language models, enabling automatic and interpretable assessment of relighting precision across individual dimensions. Extensive experiments demonstrate that UniLumos achieves state-of-the-art relighting quality with significantly improved physical consistency, while delivering a 20x speedup for both image and video relighting. Code is available at https://github.com/alibaba-damo-academy/Lumos-Custom.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01678</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 15:41:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Step Knowledge Interaction Analysis via Rank-2 Subspace   Disentanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01706</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01706.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sekh Mainul Islam, Pepa Atanasova, Isabelle Augenstein&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Natural Language Explanations (NLEs) describe how Large Language Models (LLMs) make decisions, drawing on both external Context Knowledge (CK) and Parametric Knowledge (PK) stored in model weights. Understanding their interaction is key to assessing the grounding of NLEs, yet it remains underexplored. Prior work has largely examined only single-step generation, typically the final answer, and has modelled PK and CK interaction only as a binary choice in a rank-1 subspace. This overlooks richer forms of interaction, such as complementary or supportive knowledge. We propose a novel rank-2 projection subspace that disentangles PK and CK contributions more accurately and use it for the first multi-step analysis of knowledge interactions across longer NLE sequences. Experiments on four QA datasets and three open-weight instruction-tuned LLMs show that diverse knowledge interactions are poorly represented in a rank-1 subspace but are effectively captured in our rank-2 formulation. Our multi-step analysis reveals that hallucinated NLEs align strongly with the PK direction, context-faithful ones balance PK and CK, and Chain-of-Thought prompting for NLEs shifts generated NLEs toward CK by reducing PK reliance. This work provides the first framework for systematic studies of multi-step knowledge interactions in LLMs through a richer rank-2 subspace disentanglement. Code and data: https://github.com/copenlu/pk-ck-knowledge-disentanglement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01706</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 16:15:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Diffusion VLA: Vision-Language-Action Model via Joint Discrete   Denoising Diffusion Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01718</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01718.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiayi Chen, Wenxuan Song, Pengxiang Ding, Ziyang Zhou, Han Zhao, Feilong Tang, Donglin Wang, Haoang Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language-action (VLA) models aim to understand natural language instructions and visual observations and to execute corresponding actions as an embodied agent. Recent work integrates future images into the understanding-acting loop, yielding unified VLAs that jointly understand, generate, and act -- reading text and images and producing future images and actions. However, these models either rely on external experts for modality unification or treat image generation and action prediction as separate processes, limiting the benefits of direct synergy between these tasks. Our core philosophy is to optimize generation and action jointly through a synchronous denoising process, where the iterative refinement enables actions to evolve from initialization, under constant and sufficient visual guidance. We ground this philosophy in our proposed Unified Diffusion VLA and Joint Discrete Denoising Diffusion Process (JD3P), which is a joint diffusion process that integrates multiple modalities into a single denoising trajectory to serve as the key mechanism enabling understanding, generation, and acting to be intrinsically synergistic. Our model and theory are built on a unified tokenized space of all modalities and a hybrid attention mechanism. We further propose a two-stage training pipeline and several inference-time techniques that optimize performance and efficiency. Our approach achieves state-of-the-art performance on benchmarks such as CALVIN, LIBERO, and SimplerEnv with 4times faster inference than autoregressive methods, and we demonstrate its effectiveness through in-depth analysis and real-world evaluations. Our project page is available at https://irpn-eai.github.io/UD-VLA.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01718</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 16:26:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Far Are Surgeons from Surgical World Models? A Pilot Study on   Zero-shot Surgical Video Generation with Expert Assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01775</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01775.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhen Chen, Qing Xu, Jinlin Wu, Biao Yang, Yuhao Zhai, Geng Guo, Jing Zhang, Yinlu Ding, Nassir Navab, Jiebo Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Foundation models in video generation are demonstrating remarkable capabilities as potential world models for simulating the physical world. However, their application in high-stakes domains like surgery, which demand deep, specialized causal knowledge rather than general physical rules, remains a critical unexplored gap. To systematically address this challenge, we present SurgVeo, the first expert-curated benchmark for video generation model evaluation in surgery, and the Surgical Plausibility Pyramid (SPP), a novel, four-tiered framework tailored to assess model outputs from basic appearance to complex surgical strategy. On the basis of the SurgVeo benchmark, we task the advanced Veo-3 model with a zero-shot prediction task on surgical clips from laparoscopic and neurosurgical procedures. A panel of four board-certified surgeons evaluates the generated videos according to the SPP. Our results reveal a distinct "plausibility gap": while Veo-3 achieves exceptional Visual Perceptual Plausibility, it fails critically at higher levels of the SPP, including Instrument Operation Plausibility, Environment Feedback Plausibility, and Surgical Intent Plausibility. This work provides the first quantitative evidence of the chasm between visually convincing mimicry and causal understanding in surgical AI. Our findings from SurgVeo and the SPP establish a crucial foundation and roadmap for developing future models capable of navigating the complexities of specialized, real-world healthcare domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01775</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 17:28:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TIR-Bench: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Agentic Thinking-with-Images   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01833</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01833.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Li, Jike Zhong, Shitian Zhao, Haoquan Zhang, Shaoheng Lin, Yuxiang Lai, Wei Chen, Konstantinos Psounis, Kaipeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The frontier of visual reasoning is shifting toward models like OpenAI o3, which can intelligently create and operate tools to transform images for problem-solving, also known as thinking-with-images in chain-of-thought. Yet existing benchmarks fail to fully capture this advanced capability. Even Visual Search, the most common benchmark for current thinking-with-images methods, tests only basic operations such as localization and cropping, offering little insight into more complex, dynamic, and tool-dependent reasoning. We introduce TIR-Bench, a comprehensive benchmark for evaluating agentic thinking-with-images across 13 diverse tasks, each requiring novel tool use for image processing and manipulation in chain-of-thought. We evaluate 22 multimodal large language models (MLLMs), from leading open-sourced and proprietary models to those with explicit tool-use augmentation. Results show that TIR-Bench is universally challenging, and strong performance requires genuine thinking-with-images capabilities. Finally, we present a pilot study comparing direct versus agentic fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01833</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 18:40:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Robust Mathematical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01846</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01846.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Thang Luong, Dawsen Hwang, Hoang H. Nguyen, Golnaz Ghiasi, Yuri Chervonyi, Insuk Seo, Junsu Kim, Garrett Bingham, Jonathan Lee, Swaroop Mishra, Alex Zhai, Clara Huiyi Hu, Henryk Michalewski, Jimin Kim, Jeonghyun Ahn, Junhwi Bae, Xingyou Song, Trieu H. Trinh, Quoc V. Le, Junehyuk Jung&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Finding the right north-star metrics is highly critical for advancing the mathematical reasoning capabilities of foundation models, especially given that existing evaluations are either too easy or only focus on getting correct short answers. To address these issues, we present IMO-Bench, a suite of advanced reasoning benchmarks, vetted by a panel of top specialists and that specifically targets the level of the International Mathematical Olympiad (IMO), the most prestigious venue for young mathematicians. IMO-AnswerBench first tests models on 400 diverse Olympiad problems with verifiable short answers. IMO-Proof Bench is the next-level evaluation for proof-writing capabilities, which includes both basic and advanced IMO level problems as well as detailed grading guidelines to facilitate automatic grading. These benchmarks played a crucial role in our historic achievement of the gold-level performance at IMO 2025 with Gemini Deep Think (Luong and Lockhart, 2025). Our model achieved 80.0% on IMO-AnswerBench and 65.7% on the advanced IMO-Proof Bench, surpassing the best non-Gemini models by large margins of 6.9% and 42.4% respectively. We also showed that autograders built with Gemini reasoning correlate well with human evaluations and construct IMO-GradingBench, with 1000 human gradings on proofs, to enable further progress in automatic evaluation of long-form answers. We hope that IMO-Bench will help the community towards advancing robust mathematical reasoning and release it at https://imobench.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01846</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 18:53:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trove: A Flexible Toolkit for Dense Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01857</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01857.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Reza Esfandiarpoor, Max Zuo, Stephen H. Bach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Trove, an easy-to-use open-source retrieval toolkit that simplifies research experiments without sacrificing flexibility or speed. For the first time, we introduce efficient data management features that load and process (filter, select, transform, and combine) retrieval datasets on the fly, with just a few lines of code. This gives users the flexibility to easily experiment with different dataset configurations without the need to compute and store multiple copies of large datasets. Trove is highly customizable: in addition to many built-in options, it allows users to freely modify existing components or replace them entirely with user-defined objects. It also provides a low-code and unified pipeline for evaluation and hard negative mining, which supports multi-node execution without any code changes. Trove's data management features reduce memory consumption by a factor of 2.6. Moreover, Trove's easy-to-use inference pipeline incurs no overhead, and inference times decrease linearly with the number of available nodes. Most importantly, we demonstrate how Trove simplifies retrieval experiments and allows for arbitrary customizations, thus facilitating exploratory research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01857</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TabDSR: Decompose, Sanitize, and Reason for Complex Numerical Reasoning   in Tabular Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02219</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02219.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Changjiang Jiang, Fengchang Yu, Haihua Chen, Wei Lu, Jin Zeng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Complex reasoning over tabular data is crucial in real-world data analysis, yet large language models (LLMs) often underperform due to complex queries, noisy data, and limited numerical capabilities. To address these issues, we propose \method, a framework consisting of: (1) a query decomposer that breaks down complex questions, (2) a table sanitizer that cleans and filters noisy tables, and (3) a program-of-thoughts (PoT)-based reasoner that generates executable code to derive the final answer from the sanitized table. To ensure unbiased evaluation and mitigate data leakage, we introduce a new dataset, CalTab151, specifically designed for complex numerical reasoning over tables. Experimental results demonstrate that \method consistently outperforms existing methods, achieving state-of-the-art (SOTA) performance with 8.79%, 6.08%, and 19.87% accuracy improvement on TAT-QA, TableBench, and \method, respectively. Moreover, our framework integrates seamlessly with mainstream LLMs, providing a robust solution for complex tabular numerical reasoning. These findings highlight the effectiveness of our framework in enhancing LLM performance for complex tabular numerical reasoning. Data and code are available upon request.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02219</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 03:13:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Modalities Conflict: How Unimodal Reasoning Uncertainty Governs   Preference Dynamics in MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02243</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02243.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuoran Zhang, Tengyue Wang, Xilin Gong, Yang Shi, Haotian Wang, Di Wang, Lijie Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) must resolve conflicts when different modalities provide contradictory information, a process we term modality following. Prior work measured this behavior only with coarse dataset-level statistics, overlooking the influence of model's confidence in unimodal reasoning. In this paper, we introduce a new framework that decomposes modality following into two fundamental factors: relative reasoning uncertainty (the case-specific confidence gap between unimodal predictions) and inherent modality preference( a model's stable bias when uncertainties are balanced). To validate this framework, we construct a controllable dataset that systematically varies the reasoning difficulty of visual and textual inputs. Using entropy as a fine-grained uncertainty metric, we uncover a universal law: the probability of following a modality decreases monotonically as its relative uncertainty increases. At the relative difficulty level where the model tends to follow both modalities with comparable probability what we call the balance point, a practical indicator of the model's inherent preference. Unlike traditional macro-level ratios, this measure offers a more principled and less confounded way to characterize modality bias, disentangling it from unimodal capabilities and dataset artifacts. Further, by probing layer-wise predictions, we reveal the internal mechanism of oscillation: in ambiguous regions near the balance point, models vacillate between modalities across layers, explaining externally observed indecision. Together, these findings establish relative uncertainty and inherent preference as the two governing principles of modality following, offering both a quantitative framework and mechanistic insight into how MLLMs resolve conflicting information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02243</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 04:11:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAIL-RL: Guiding MLLMs in When and How to Think via Dual-Reward RL   Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02280</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02280.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fangxun Shu, Yongjie Ye, Yue Liao, Zijian Kang, Weijie Yin, Jiacong Wang, Xiao Liang, Shuicheng Yan, Chao Feng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SAIL-RL, a reinforcement learning (RL) post-training framework that enhances the reasoning capabilities of multimodal large language models (MLLMs) by teaching them when and how to think. Existing approaches are limited by outcome-only supervision, which rewards correct answers without ensuring sound reasoning, and by uniform thinking strategies, which often lead to overthinking on simple tasks and underthinking on complex ones. SAIL-RL addresses these challenges with a dual reward system: the Thinking Reward, which evaluates reasoning quality through factual grounding, logical coherence, and answer consistency, and the Judging Reward, which adaptively determines whether deep reasoning or direct answering is appropriate. Experiments on the state-of-the-art SAIL-VL2 show that SAIL-RL improves reasoning and multimodal understanding benchmarks at both 4B and 8B scales, achieving competitive performance against commercial closed-source models such as GPT-4o, and substantially reduces hallucinations, establishing it as a principled framework for building more reliable and adaptive MLLMs. The code will be available at https://github.com/BytedanceDouyinContent/SAIL-RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02280</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 05:34:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sequential Edge: Inverse-Entropy Voting Beats Parallel   Self-Consistency at Matched Compute</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02309</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02309.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aman Sharma, Paras Chopra&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We revisit test-time scaling for language model reasoning and ask a fundamental question: at equal token budget and compute, is it better to run multiple independent chains in parallel, or to run fewer chains that iteratively refine through sequential steps? Through comprehensive evaluation across 5 state-of-the-art open source models and 3 challenging reasoning benchmarks, we find that sequential scaling where chains explicitly build upon previous attempts consistently outperforms the dominant parallel self-consistency paradigm in 95.6% of configurations with gains in accuracy upto 46.7%. Further, we introduce inverse-entropy weighted voting, a novel training-free method to further boost the accuracy of sequential scaling. By weighing answers in proportion to the inverse entropy of their reasoning chains, we increase our success rate over parallel majority and establish it as the optimal test-time scaling strategy. Our findings fundamentally challenge the parallel reasoning orthodoxy that has dominated test-time scaling since Wang et al.'s self-consistency decoding (Wang et al., 2022), positioning sequential refinement as the robust default for modern LLM reasoning and necessitating a paradigm shift in how we approach inference-time optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02309</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 06:48:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LTD-Bench: Evaluating Large Language Models by Letting Them Draw</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02347</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02347.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liuhao Lin, Ke Li, Zihan Xu, Yuchen Shi, Yulei Qin, Yan Zhang, Xing Sun, Rongrong Ji&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current evaluation paradigms for large language models (LLMs) represent a critical blind spot in AI research--relying on opaque numerical metrics that conceal fundamental limitations in spatial reasoning while providing no intuitive understanding of model capabilities. This deficiency creates a dangerous disconnect between reported performance and practical abilities, particularly for applications requiring physical world understanding. We introduce LTD-Bench, a breakthrough benchmark that transforms LLM evaluation from abstract scores to directly observable visual outputs by requiring models to generate drawings through dot matrices or executable code. This approach makes spatial reasoning limitations immediately apparent even to non-experts, bridging the fundamental gap between statistical performance and intuitive assessment. LTD-Bench implements a comprehensive methodology with complementary generation tasks (testing spatial imagination) and recognition tasks (assessing spatial perception) across three progressively challenging difficulty levels, methodically evaluating both directions of the critical language-spatial mapping. Our extensive experiments with state-of-the-art models expose an alarming capability gap: even LLMs achieving impressive results on traditional benchmarks demonstrate profound deficiencies in establishing bidirectional mappings between language and spatial concept--a fundamental limitation that undermines their potential as genuine world models. Furthermore, LTD-Bench's visual outputs enable powerful diagnostic analysis, offering a potential approach to investigate model similarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02347</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 08:11:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Let Multimodal Embedders Learn When to Augment Query via Adaptive Query   Augmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02358</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02358.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wongyu Kim, Hochang Lee, Sanghak Lee, Yoonsung Kim, Jaehyun Park&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Query augmentation makes queries more meaningful by appending further information to the queries to find relevant documents. Current studies have proposed Large Language Model (LLM)-based embedders, which learn representation for embedding and generation for query augmentation in a multi-task manner by leveraging the generative capabilities of LLM. During inference, these jointly trained embedders have conducted query augmentation followed by embedding, showing effective results. However, augmenting every query leads to substantial embedding latency and query augmentation can be detrimental to performance for some queries. Also, previous methods have not been explored in multimodal environments. To tackle these problems, we propose M-Solomon, a universal multimodal embedder that can adaptively determine when to augment queries. Our approach first divides the queries of the training datasets into two groups at the dataset level. One includes queries that require augmentation and the other includes queries that do not. Then, we introduces a synthesis process that generates appropriate augmentations for queries that require them by leveraging a powerful Multimodal LLM (MLLM). Next, we present adaptive query augmentation. Through this step, M-Solomon can conduct query augmentation only when necessary by learning to generate synthetic augmentations with the prefix /augment for queries that demand them and to generate the simple string /embed for others. Experimental results showed that M-Solomon not only surpassed the baseline without augmentation by a large margin but also outperformed the baseline that always used augmentation, providing much faster embedding latency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02358</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 08:24:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiveSecBench: A Dynamic and Culturally-Relevant AI Safety Benchmark for   LLMs in Chinese Context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02366</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02366.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yudong Li, Zhongliang Yang, Kejiang Chen, Wenxuan Wang, Tianxin Zhang, Sifang Wan, Kecheng Wang, Haitian Li, Xu Wang, Lefan Cheng, Youdan Yang, Baocheng Chen, Ziyu Liu, Yufei Sun, Liyan Wu, Wenya Wen, Xingchi Gu, Peiru Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we propose LiveSecBench, a dynamic and continuously updated safety benchmark specifically for Chinese-language LLM application scenarios. LiveSecBench evaluates models across six critical dimensions (Legality, Ethics, Factuality, Privacy, Adversarial Robustness, and Reasoning Safety) rooted in the Chinese legal and social frameworks. This benchmark maintains relevance through a dynamic update schedule that incorporates new threat vectors, such as the planned inclusion of Text-to-Image Generation Safety and Agentic Safety in the next update. For now, LiveSecBench (v251030) has evaluated 18 LLMs, providing a landscape of AI safety in the context of Chinese language. The leaderboard is publicly accessible at https://livesecbench.intokentech.cn/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02366</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 08:44:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AyurParam: A State-of-the-Art Bilingual Language Model for Ayurveda</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02374</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02374.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohd Nauman, Sravan Gvm, Vijay Devane, Shyam Pawar, Viraj Thakur, Kundeshwar Pundalik, Piyush Sawarkar, Rohit Saluja, Maunendra Desarkar, Ganesh Ramakrishnan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current large language models excel at broad, general-purpose tasks, but consistently underperform when exposed to highly specialized domains that require deep cultural, linguistic, and subject-matter expertise. In particular, traditional medical systems such as Ayurveda embody centuries of nuanced textual and clinical knowledge that mainstream LLMs fail to accurately interpret or apply. We introduce AyurParam-2.9B, a domain-specialized, bilingual language model fine-tuned from Param-1-2.9B using an extensive, expertly curated Ayurveda dataset spanning classical texts and clinical guidance. AyurParam's dataset incorporates context-aware, reasoning, and objective-style Q&amp;A in both English and Hindi, with rigorous annotation protocols for factual precision and instructional clarity. Benchmarked on BhashaBench-Ayur, AyurParam not only surpasses all open-source instruction-tuned models in its size class (1.5--3B parameters), but also demonstrates competitive or superior performance compared to much larger models. The results from AyurParam highlight the necessity for authentic domain adaptation and high-quality supervision in delivering reliable, culturally congruent AI for specialized medical knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02374</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 08:53:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChartM^3: A Multi-Stage Code-Driven Pipeline for Constructing   Multi-Dimensional and Multi-Step Visual Reasoning Data in Chart Comprehension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02415</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02415.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Duo Xu, Hao Cheng, Xin Lin, Zhen Xie, Hao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Complex chart understanding tasks demand advanced visual recognition and reasoning capabilities from multimodal large language models (MLLMs). However, current research provides limited coverage of complex chart scenarios and computation-intensive reasoning tasks prevalent in real-world applications. This study proposes an automated multi-stage code-driven pipeline for systematically generating visual reasoning datasets to address these limitations. The pipeline integrates retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) to retrieve professional chart templates and employs chain-of-thought (CoT) strategies to generate reasoning codes that simulate real data distributions, thereby driving chart rendering and question-related statistical computations. Through model-based evaluation, the pipeline enhances chart diversity and data quality. Using this framework, we construct ChartM^3, a multi-dimensional and multi-step dataset containing 38K charts and 142K Q&amp;A pairs for training, along with 2,871 high-quality evaluation samples for enabling practical performance assessment. Supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and reinforcement learning (RL) experiments demonstrate that our dataset significantly improves reasoning capabilities and cross-domain generalization performance, enabling smaller models to achieve performance comparable to larger-scale models in complex chart comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02415</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 09:45:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BRAINS: A Retrieval-Augmented System for Alzheimer's Detection and   Monitoring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02490</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02490.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rajan Das Gupta, Md Kishor Morol, Nafiz Fahad, Md Tanzib Hosain, Sumaya Binte Zilani Choya, Md Jakir Hossen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As the global burden of Alzheimer's disease (AD) continues to grow, early and accurate detection has become increasingly critical, especially in regions with limited access to advanced diagnostic tools. We propose BRAINS (Biomedical Retrieval-Augmented Intelligence for Neurodegeneration Screening) to address this challenge. This novel system harnesses the powerful reasoning capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs) for Alzheimer's detection and monitoring. BRAINS features a dual-module architecture: a cognitive diagnostic module and a case-retrieval module. The Diagnostic Module utilizes LLMs fine-tuned on cognitive and neuroimaging datasets -- including MMSE, CDR scores, and brain volume metrics -- to perform structured assessments of Alzheimer's risk. Meanwhile, the Case Retrieval Module encodes patient profiles into latent representations and retrieves similar cases from a curated knowledge base. These auxiliary cases are fused with the input profile via a Case Fusion Layer to enhance contextual understanding. The combined representation is then processed with clinical prompts for inference. Evaluations on real-world datasets demonstrate BRAINS effectiveness in classifying disease severity and identifying early signs of cognitive decline. This system not only shows strong potential as an assistive tool for scalable, explainable, and early-stage Alzheimer's disease detection, but also offers hope for future applications in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02490</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 11:27:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Visual Input Be Compressed? A Visual Token Compression Benchmark for   Large Multimodal Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02650</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02650.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianfan Peng, Yuntao Du, Pengzhou Ji, Shijie Dong, Kailin Jiang, Mingchuan Ma, Yijun Tian, Jinhe Bi, Qian Li, Wei Du, Feng Xiao, Lizhen Cui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large multimodal models (LMMs) often suffer from severe inference inefficiency due to the large number of visual tokens introduced by image encoders. While recent token compression methods, such as pruning and merging, have shown promise in reducing redundancy, their evaluation remains fragmented and inconsistent. In this work, we present UniPruneBench, a unified and extensible benchmark for visual token pruning in multimodal LLMs. UniPruneBench provides standardized protocols across six ability dimensions and ten datasets, covering ten representative compression algorithms and three families of LMMs (LLaVA-v1.5, Intern-VL3, and Qwen2.5-VL). Beyond task accuracy, it incorporates system-level metrics such as runtime and prefilling latency to provide a holistic view. Our experiments uncover several key findings: (1) random pruning is a surprisingly strong baseline, (2) no single method consistently outperforms others across scenarios, (3) pruning sensitivity varies significantly across tasks, with OCR being most vulnerable, and (4) pruning ratio is the dominant factor governing performance degradation. We believe UniPruneBench will serve as a reliable foundation for future research on efficient multimodal modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02650</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 15:17:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Collaboration Gap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02687</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02687.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tim R. Davidson, Adam Fourney, Saleema Amershi, Robert West, Eric Horvitz, Ece Kamar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The trajectory of AI development suggests that we will increasingly rely on agent-based systems composed of independently developed agents with different information, privileges, and tools. The success of these systems will critically depend on effective collaboration among these heterogeneous agents, even under partial observability. Despite intense interest, few empirical studies have evaluated such agent-agent collaboration at scale. We propose a collaborative maze-solving benchmark that (i) isolates collaborative capabilities, (ii) modulates problem complexity, (iii) enables scalable automated grading, and (iv) imposes no output-format constraints, preserving ecological plausibility. Using this framework, we evaluate 32 leading open- and closed-source models in solo, homogeneous, and heterogeneous pairings. Our results reveal a "collaboration gap": models that perform well solo often degrade substantially when required to collaborate. Collaboration can break down dramatically; for instance, small distilled models that solve mazes well alone may fail almost completely in certain pairings. We find that starting with the stronger agent often improves outcomes, motivating a "relay inference" approach where the stronger agent leads before handing off to the weaker one, closing much of the gap. Our findings argue for (1) collaboration-aware evaluation, (2) training strategies developed to enhance collaborative capabilities, and (3) interaction design that reliably elicits agents' latent skills, guidance that applies to AI-AI and human-AI collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02687</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 16:10:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VidEmo: Affective-Tree Reasoning for Emotion-Centric Video Foundation   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02712</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02712.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhicheng Zhang, Weicheng Wang, Yongjie Zhu, Wenyu Qin, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Jufeng Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding and predicting emotion from videos has gathered significant attention in recent studies, driven by advancements in video large language models (VideoLLMs). While advanced methods have made progress in video emotion analysis, the intrinsic nature of emotions poses significant challenges. Emotions are characterized by dynamic and cues-dependent properties, making it difficult to understand complex and evolving emotional states with reasonable rationale. To tackle these challenges, we propose a novel affective cues-guided reasoning framework that unifies fundamental attribute perception, expression analysis, and high-level emotional understanding in a stage-wise manner. At the core of our approach is a family of video emotion foundation models (VidEmo), specifically designed for emotion reasoning and instruction-following. These models undergo a two-stage tuning process: first, curriculum emotion learning for injecting emotion knowledge, followed by affective-tree reinforcement learning for emotion reasoning. Moreover, we establish a foundational data infrastructure and introduce a emotion-centric fine-grained dataset (Emo-CFG) consisting of 2.1M diverse instruction-based samples. Emo-CFG includes explainable emotional question-answering, fine-grained captions, and associated rationales, providing essential resources for advancing emotion understanding tasks. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach achieves competitive performance, setting a new milestone across 15 face perception tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02712</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 16:31:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CostBench: Evaluating Multi-Turn Cost-Optimal Planning and Adaptation in   Dynamic Environments for LLM Tool-Use Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02734</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02734.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiayu Liu, Cheng Qian, Zhaochen Su, Qing Zong, Shijue Huang, Bingxiang He, Yi R. Fung&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current evaluations of Large Language Model (LLM) agents primarily emphasize task completion, often overlooking resource efficiency and adaptability. This neglects a crucial capability: agents' ability to devise and adjust cost-optimal plans in response to changing environments. To bridge this gap, we introduce CostBench, a scalable, cost-centric benchmark designed to evaluate agents' economic reasoning and replanning abilities. Situated in the travel-planning domain, CostBench comprises tasks solvable via multiple sequences of atomic and composite tools with diverse, customizable costs. It also supports four types of dynamic blocking events, such as tool failures and cost changes, to simulate real-world unpredictability and necessitate agents to adapt in real time. Evaluating leading open-sourced and proprietary models on CostBench reveals a substantial gap in cost-aware planning: agents frequently fail to identify cost-optimal solutions in static settings, with even GPT-5 achieving less than 75% exact match rate on the hardest tasks, and performance further dropping by around 40% under dynamic conditions. By diagnosing these weaknesses, CostBench lays the groundwork for developing future agents that are both economically rational and robust.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02734</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 16:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VCode: a Multimodal Coding Benchmark with SVG as Symbolic Visual   Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02778</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02778.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kevin Qinghong Lin, Yuhao Zheng, Hangyu Ran, Dantong Zhu, Dongxing Mao, Linjie Li, Philip Torr, Alex Jinpeng Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 95&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Code has emerged as a precise and executable medium for reasoning and action in the agent era. Yet, progress has largely focused on language-centric tasks such as program synthesis and debugging, leaving visual-centric coding underexplored. Inspired by how humans reason over sketches, we advocate SVG code as a compact, interpretable, and executable visual representation. We introduce VCode, a benchmark that reframes multimodal understanding as code generation: given an image, a model must produce SVG that preserves symbolic meaning for downstream reasoning. VCode covers three domains - general commonsense (MM-Vet), professional disciplines (MMMU), and visual-centric perception (CV-Bench). To assess symbolic fidelity, we propose CodeVQA, a novel evaluation protocol in which a policy model answers questions over rendered SVGs; correct answers indicate faithful symbolic preservation. Empirically, frontier VLMs struggle to generate faithful SVGs, revealing a persistent gap between language-centric and visual-centric coding. To close this gap, we introduce VCoder, an agentic framework that augments VLMs along two axes: (i) Thinking with Revision, which iteratively analyzes discrepancies and refines SVG code; and (ii) Acting with Visual Tools, where detectors and parsers supply structured cues such as objects, shapes, and text beyond the model's intrinsic capacity. Across benchmarks, frontier VLMs with strong reasoning capabilities score well overall yet remain limited in professional knowledge and 3D reasoning. VCoder delivers a 12.3-point overall gain over the top-performing Claude-4-Opus. Human studies show that both humans and VLMs perform worse on rendered SVGs, their consistency reveals the promise of symbolic visual representation. The benchmark and code are available at https://github.com/CSU-JPG/VCode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02778</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 18:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Visualizing is the First Step to Reasoning: MIRA, a Benchmark for   Visual Chain-of-Thought</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02779</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02779.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiyang Zhou, Haoqin Tu, Zijun Wang, Zeyu Wang, Niklas Muennighoff, Fan Nie, Yejin Choi, James Zou, Chaorui Deng, Shen Yan, Haoqi Fan, Cihang Xie, Huaxiu Yao, Qinghao Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose MIRA, a new benchmark designed to evaluate models in scenarios where generating intermediate visual images is essential for successful reasoning. Unlike traditional CoT methods that rely solely on text, tasks in MIRA require models to generate and utilize intermediate images - such as sketches, structural diagrams, or path drawings - to guide their reasoning process. This setup closely mirrors how humans solve complex problems through "drawing to think". To solve this, MIRA focuses on tasks that are intrinsically challenging and involve complex structures, spatial relationships, or reasoning steps that are difficult to express through language alone. To ensure that our evaluation data is of high-quality, we include 546 multimodal problems, annotated with intermediate visual images and final answers. We also propose a unified evaluation protocol for MIRA that spans three levels of evaluation input: direct input with image and question only, text-only CoT input with image and thinking prompts, and Visual-CoT input with both annotated image clues and textual thinking prompts. To probe the upper bound of model capacity on our benchmark, we also report pass@k and majority voting accuracies under different k settings. Experimental results show that existing multimodal large language models, including strongest private models as well as strong open-weight models, perform poorly when relying solely on textual prompts. However, when intermediate visual cues are provided, model performance improves consistently, yielding an average relative gain of 33.7% across all models and tasks. We also probe the upper bound by expanding the search space and designing textual prompts aligned with Visual-CoT, but both yield only limited improvements compared to our Visual-CoT setting. These results underscore the critical role of imagined visual information in enabling successful reasoning on MIRA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02779</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 18:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TabTune: A Unified Library for Inference and Fine-Tuning Tabular   Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02802</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02802.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aditya Tanna, Pratinav Seth, Mohamed Bouadi, Utsav Avaiya, Vinay Kumar Sankarapu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Tabular foundation models represent a growing paradigm in structured data learning, extending the benefits of large-scale pretraining to tabular domains. However, their adoption remains limited due to heterogeneous preprocessing pipelines, fragmented APIs, inconsistent fine-tuning procedures, and the absence of standardized evaluation for deployment-oriented metrics such as calibration and fairness. We present TabTune, a unified library that standardizes the complete workflow for tabular foundation models through a single interface. TabTune provides consistent access to seven state-of-the-art models supporting multiple adaptation strategies, including zero-shot inference, meta-learning, supervised fine-tuning (SFT), and parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT). The framework automates model-aware preprocessing, manages architectural heterogeneity internally, and integrates evaluation modules for performance, calibration, and fairness. Designed for extensibility and reproducibility, TabTune enables consistent benchmarking of adaptation strategies of tabular foundation models. The library is open source and available at https://github.com/Lexsi-Labs/TabTune .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02802</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 18:25:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orion-MSP: Multi-Scale Sparse Attention for Tabular In-Context Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02818</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02818.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohamed Bouadi, Pratinav Seth, Aditya Tanna, Vinay Kumar Sankarapu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Tabular data remain the predominant format for real-world applications. Yet, developing effective neural models for tabular data remains challenging due to heterogeneous feature types and complex interactions occurring at multiple scales. Recent advances in tabular in-context learning (ICL), such as TabPFN and TabICL, have achieved state-of-the-art performance comparable to gradient-boosted trees (GBTs) without task-specific fine-tuning. However, current architectures exhibit key limitations: (1) single-scale feature processing that overlooks hierarchical dependencies, (2) dense attention with quadratic scaling in table width, and (3) strictly sequential component processing that prevents iterative representation refinement and cross-component communication. To address these challenges, we introduce Orion-MSP, a tabular ICL architecture featuring three key innovations: (1) multi-scale processing to capture hierarchical feature interactions; (2) block-sparse attention combining windowed, global, and random patterns for scalable efficiency and long-range connectivity; and (3) a Perceiver-style memory enabling safe bidirectional information flow across components. Across diverse benchmarks, Orion-MSP matches or surpasses state-of-the-art performance while scaling effectively to high-dimensional tables, establishing a new standard for efficient tabular in-context learning. The model is publicly available at https://github.com/Lexsi-Labs/Orion-MSP .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02818</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 18:43:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TWIST2: Scalable, Portable, and Holistic Humanoid Data Collection System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02832</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02832.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanjie Ze, Siheng Zhao, Weizhuo Wang, Angjoo Kanazawa, Rocky Duan, Pieter Abbeel, Guanya Shi, Jiajun Wu, C. Karen Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large-scale data has driven breakthroughs in robotics, from language models to vision-language-action models in bimanual manipulation. However, humanoid robotics lacks equally effective data collection frameworks. Existing humanoid teleoperation systems either use decoupled control or depend on expensive motion capture setups. We introduce TWIST2, a portable, mocap-free humanoid teleoperation and data collection system that preserves full whole-body control while advancing scalability. Our system leverages PICO4U VR for obtaining real-time whole-body human motions, with a custom 2-DoF robot neck (cost around $250) for egocentric vision, enabling holistic human-to-humanoid control. We demonstrate long-horizon dexterous and mobile humanoid skills and we can collect 100 demonstrations in 15 minutes with an almost 100% success rate. Building on this pipeline, we propose a hierarchical visuomotor policy framework that autonomously controls the full humanoid body based on egocentric vision. Our visuomotor policy successfully demonstrates whole-body dexterous manipulation and dynamic kicking tasks. The entire system is fully reproducible and open-sourced at https://yanjieze.com/TWIST2 . Our collected dataset is also open-sourced at https://twist-data.github.io .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02832</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 18:58:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEGO-Eval: Towards Fine-Grained Evaluation on Synthesizing 3D Embodied   Environments with Tool Augmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03001</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03001.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gyeom Hwangbo, Hyungjoo Chae, Minseok Kang, Hyeonjong Ju, Soohyun Oh, Jinyoung Yeo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite recent progress in using Large Language Models (LLMs) for automatically generating 3D scenes, generated scenes often lack realistic spatial layouts and object attributes found in real-world environments. As this problem stems from insufficiently detailed, coarse-grained instructions, advancing 3D scene synthesis guided by more detailed, fine-grained instructions that reflect real-world environments becomes crucial. Without such realistic scenes, training embodied agents in unrealistic environments can lead them to learn priors that diverge significantly from real-world physics and semantics, degrading their performance when deployed. Thus, verifying the alignment between the fine-grained instruction and the generated scene is essential for effective learning. However, current evaluation methods, such as CLIPScore and vision-language models (VLMs), often fail to reliably assess such alignment. This shortcoming arises primarily from their shallow understanding of 3D scenes, which often leads to improperly grounded scene components. To address this, we introduce LEGO-Eval, an evaluation framework equipped with diverse tools designed to explicitly ground scene components, enabling more accurate alignment assessments. We also present LEGO-Bench, a benchmark of detailed instructions that specify complex layouts and attributes of real-world environments. Experiments demonstrate that LEGO-Eval outperforms VLM-as-a-judge by 0.41 F1 score in assessing scene-instruction alignment. Benchmarking with LEGO-Bench reveals significant limitations in current generation methods. Across all evaluated approaches, success rates reached at most 10% in generating scenes that fully align with fine-grained instructions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 21:13:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MME-CC: A Challenging Multi-Modal Evaluation Benchmark of Cognitive   Capacity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03146</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03146.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaiyuan Zhang, Chenghao Yang, Zhoufutu Wen, Sihang Yuan, Qiuyue Wang, Chaoyi Huang, Guosheng Zhu, He Wang, Huawenyu Lu, Jianing Wen, Jianpeng Jiao, Lishu Luo, Longxiang Liu, Sijin Wu, Xiaolei Zhu, Xuanliang Zhang, Ge Zhang, Yi Lin, Guang Shi, Chaoyou Fu, Wenhao Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As reasoning models scale rapidly, the essential role of multimodality in human cognition has come into sharp relief, driving a growing need to probe vision-centric cognitive behaviors. Yet, existing multimodal benchmarks either overemphasize textual reasoning or fall short of systematically capturing vision-centric cognitive behaviors, leaving the cognitive capacity of MLLMs insufficiently assessed. To address this limitation, we introduce MME-CC (Multi-Modal Evaluation benchmark of Cognitive Capacity), a vision-grounded benchmark that organizes 11 representative reasoning tasks into three fundamental categories of visual information: spatial, geometric, and knowledge-based reasoning, and provides fine-grained analyses of MLLMs' cognitive capacity across these dimensions. Based on MME-CC, we conduct extensive experiments over 16 representative MLLMs. Our study reveals that closed-source models currently lead overall (e.g., 42.66 for Gemini-2.5-Pro vs. 30.45 for GLM-4.5V), while spatial and geometric reasoning remain broadly weak (less than or equal to 30%). We further identify common error patterns, including orientation mistakes, fragile cross-view identity persistence, and poor adherence to counterfactual instructions, and observe that Chain-of-Thought typically follows a three-stage process (extract -&gt; reason -&gt; verify) with heavy reliance on visual extraction. We hope this work catalyzes a shift toward treating the cognitive capacity of MLLMs as central to both evaluation and model design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03146</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 03:09:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Language Models are Super Data Learners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03276</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03276.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinjie Ni, Qian Liu, Longxu Dou, Chao Du, Zili Wang, Hang Yan, Tianyu Pang, Michael Qizhe Shieh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 95&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Under strictly controlled pre-training settings, we observe a Crossover: when unique data is limited, diffusion language models (DLMs) consistently surpass autoregressive (AR) models by training for more epochs. The crossover shifts later with more or higher-quality data, earlier with larger models, and persists across dense and sparse architectures. We attribute the gains to three compounding factors: (1) any-order modeling, (2) super-dense compute from iterative bidirectional denoising, and (3) built-in Monte Carlo augmentation; input or parameter noise improves AR under data constraint but cannot close the gap. At scale, a 1.7B DLM trained with a ~1.5T-token compute budget on 10B unique Python tokens overtakes an AR coder trained with strictly matched settings. In addition, a 1B-parameter DLM achieves &gt; 56% accuracy on HellaSwag and &gt; 33% on MMLU using only 1B tokens, without any special tricks, just by repeating standard pre-training data. We also show that rising validation cross-entropy does not imply degraded downstream performance in this regime.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03276</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 08:17:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniAVGen: Unified Audio and Video Generation with Asymmetric Cross-Modal   Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03334</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03334.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guozhen Zhang, Zixiang Zhou, Teng Hu, Ziqiao Peng, Youliang Zhang, Yi Chen, Yuan Zhou, Qinglin Lu, Limin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Due to the lack of effective cross-modal modeling, existing open-source audio-video generation methods often exhibit compromised lip synchronization and insufficient semantic consistency. To mitigate these drawbacks, we propose UniAVGen, a unified framework for joint audio and video generation. UniAVGen is anchored in a dual-branch joint synthesis architecture, incorporating two parallel Diffusion Transformers (DiTs) to build a cohesive cross-modal latent space. At its heart lies an Asymmetric Cross-Modal Interaction mechanism, which enables bidirectional, temporally aligned cross-attention, thus ensuring precise spatiotemporal synchronization and semantic consistency. Furthermore, this cross-modal interaction is augmented by a Face-Aware Modulation module, which dynamically prioritizes salient regions in the interaction process. To enhance generative fidelity during inference, we additionally introduce Modality-Aware Classifier-Free Guidance, a novel strategy that explicitly amplifies cross-modal correlation signals. Notably, UniAVGen's robust joint synthesis design enables seamless unification of pivotal audio-video tasks within a single model, such as joint audio-video generation and continuation, video-to-audio dubbing, and audio-driven video synthesis. Comprehensive experiments validate that, with far fewer training samples (1.3M vs. 30.1M), UniAVGen delivers overall advantages in audio-video synchronization, timbre consistency, and emotion consistency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03334</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 10:06:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step-Audio-EditX Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03601</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03601.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chao Yan, Boyong Wu, Peng Yang, Pengfei Tan, Guoqiang Hu, Yuxin Zhang, Xiangyu, Zhang, Fei Tian, Xuerui Yang, Xiangyu Zhang, Daxin Jiang, Gang Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Step-Audio-EditX, the first open-source LLM-based audio model excelling at expressive and iterative audio editing encompassing emotion, speaking style, and paralinguistics alongside robust zero-shot text-to-speech (TTS) capabilities.Our core innovation lies in leveraging only large-margin synthetic data, which circumvents the need for embedding-based priors or auxiliary modules. This large-margin learning approach enables both iterative control and high expressivity across voices, and represents a fundamental pivot from the conventional focus on representation-level disentanglement. Evaluation results demonstrate that Step-Audio-EditX surpasses both MiniMax-2.6-hd and Doubao-Seed-TTS-2.0 in emotion editing and other fine-grained control tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03601</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 16:22:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiveTradeBench: Seeking Real-World Alpha with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03628</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03628.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haofei Yu, Fenghai Li, Jiaxuan You&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) achieve strong performance across benchmarks--from knowledge quizzes and math reasoning to web-agent tasks--but these tests occur in static settings, lacking real dynamics and uncertainty. Consequently, they evaluate isolated reasoning or problem-solving rather than decision-making under uncertainty. To address this, we introduce LiveTradeBench, a live trading environment for evaluating LLM agents in realistic and evolving markets. LiveTradeBench follows three design principles: (i) Live data streaming of market prices and news, eliminating dependence on offline backtesting and preventing information leakage while capturing real-time uncertainty; (ii) a portfolio-management abstraction that extends control from single-asset actions to multi-asset allocation, integrating risk management and cross-asset reasoning; and (iii) multi-market evaluation across structurally distinct environments--U.S. stocks and Polymarket prediction markets--differing in volatility, liquidity, and information flow. At each step, an agent observes prices, news, and its portfolio, then outputs percentage allocations that balance risk and return. Using LiveTradeBench, we run 50-day live evaluations of 21 LLMs across families. Results show that (1) high LMArena scores do not imply superior trading outcomes; (2) models display distinct portfolio styles reflecting risk appetite and reasoning dynamics; and (3) some LLMs effectively leverage live signals to adapt decisions. These findings expose a gap between static evaluation and real-world competence, motivating benchmarks that test sequential decision making and consistency under live uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03628</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 16:47:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grounded Misunderstandings in Asymmetric Dialogue: A Perspectivist   Annotation Scheme for MapTask</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03718</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03718.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nan Li, Albert Gatt, Massimo Poesio&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Collaborative dialogue relies on participants incrementally establishing common ground, yet in asymmetric settings they may believe they agree while referring to different entities. We introduce a perspectivist annotation scheme for the HCRC MapTask corpus (Anderson et al., 1991) that separately captures speaker and addressee grounded interpretations for each reference expression, enabling us to trace how understanding emerges, diverges, and repairs over time. Using a scheme-constrained LLM annotation pipeline, we obtain 13k annotated reference expressions with reliability estimates and analyze the resulting understanding states. The results show that full misunderstandings are rare once lexical variants are unified, but multiplicity discrepancies systematically induce divergences, revealing how apparent grounding can mask referential misalignment. Our framework provides both a resource and an analytic lens for studying grounded misunderstanding and for evaluating (V)LLMs' capacity to model perspective-dependent grounding in collaborative dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03718</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 18:52:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Agent Learning via Experience Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03773</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03773.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaorun Chen, Zhuokai Zhao, Kai Zhang, Bo Liu, Qi Qi, Yifan Wu, Tarun Kalluri, Sara Cao, Yuanhao Xiong, Haibo Tong, Huaxiu Yao, Hengduo Li, Jiacheng Zhu, Xian Li, Dawn Song, Bo Li, Jason Weston, Dat Huynh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While reinforcement learning (RL) can empower large language model (LLM) agents by enabling self-improvement through interaction, its practical adoption remains challenging due to costly rollouts, limited task diversity, unreliable reward signals, and infrastructure complexity, all of which obstruct the collection of scalable experience data. To address these challenges, we introduce DreamGym, the first unified framework designed to synthesize diverse experiences with scalability in mind to enable effective online RL training for autonomous agents. Rather than relying on expensive real-environment rollouts, DreamGym distills environment dynamics into a reasoning-based experience model that derives consistent state transitions and feedback signals through step-by-step reasoning, enabling scalable agent rollout collection for RL. To improve the stability and quality of transitions, DreamGym leverages an experience replay buffer initialized with offline real-world data and continuously enriched with fresh interactions to actively support agent training. To improve knowledge acquisition, DreamGym adaptively generates new tasks that challenge the current agent policy, enabling more effective online curriculum learning. Experiments across diverse environments and agent backbones demonstrate that DreamGym substantially improves RL training, both in fully synthetic settings and in sim-to-real transfer scenarios. On non-RL-ready tasks like WebArena, DreamGym outperforms all baselines by over 30%. And in RL-ready but costly settings, it matches GRPO and PPO performance using only synthetic interactions. When transferring a policy trained purely on synthetic experiences to real-environment RL, DreamGym yields significant additional performance gains while requiring far fewer real-world interactions, providing a scalable warm-start strategy for general-purpose RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03773</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 18:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contamination Detection for VLMs using Multi-Modal Semantic Perturbation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03774</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03774.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaden Park, Mu Cai, Feng Yao, Jingbo Shang, Soochahn Lee, Yong Jae Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Vision-Language Models (VLMs) have achieved state-of-the-art performance on numerous benchmark tasks. However, the use of internet-scale, often proprietary, pretraining corpora raises a critical concern for both practitioners and users: inflated performance due to test-set leakage. While prior works have proposed mitigation strategies such as decontamination of pretraining data and benchmark redesign for LLMs, the complementary direction of developing detection methods for contaminated VLMs remains underexplored. To address this gap, we deliberately contaminate open-source VLMs on popular benchmarks and show that existing detection approaches either fail outright or exhibit inconsistent behavior. We then propose a novel simple yet effective detection method based on multi-modal semantic perturbation, demonstrating that contaminated models fail to generalize under controlled perturbations. Finally, we validate our approach across multiple realistic contamination strategies, confirming its robustness and effectiveness. The code and perturbed dataset will be released publicly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03774</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 18:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NVIDIA Nemotron Nano V2 VL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03929</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03929.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NVIDIA, Amala Sanjay Deshmukh, Kateryna Chumachenko, Tuomas Rintamaki, Matthieu Le, Tyler Poon, Danial Mohseni Taheri, Ilia Karmanov, Guilin Liu, Jarno Seppanen, Guo Chen, Karan Sapra, Zhiding Yu, Adi Renduchintala, Charles Wang, Peter Jin, Arushi Goel, Mike Ranzinger, Lukas Voegtle, Philipp Fischer, Timo Roman, Wei Ping, Boxin Wang, Zhuolin Yang, Nayeon Lee, Shaokun Zhang, Fuxiao Liu, Zhiqi Li, Di Zhang, Greg Heinrich, Hongxu, Yin, Song Han, Pavlo Molchanov, Parth Mannan, Yao Xu, Jane Polak Scowcroft, Tom Balough, Subhashree Radhakrishnan, Paris Zhang, Sean Cha, Ratnesh Kumar, Zaid Pervaiz Bhat, Jian Zhang, Darragh Hanley, Pritam Biswas, Jesse Oliver, Kevin Vasques, Roger Waleffe, Duncan Riach, Oluwatobi Olabiyi, Ameya Sunil Mahabaleshwarkar, Bilal Kartal, Pritam Gundecha, Khanh Nguyen, Alexandre Milesi, Eugene Khvedchenia, Ran Zilberstein, Ofri Masad, Natan Bagrov, Nave Assaf, Tomer Asida, Daniel Afrimi, Amit Zuker, Netanel Haber, Zhiyu Cheng, Jingyu, Xin, Di, Wu, Nik Spirin, Maryam Moosaei, Roman Ageev, Vanshil Atul Shah, Yuting Wu, Daniel Korzekwa, Unnikrishnan Kizhakkemadam Sreekumar, Wanli Jiang, Padmavathy Subramanian, Alejandra Rico, Sandip Bhaskar, Saeid Motiian, Kedi Wu, Annie Surla, Chia-Chih Chen, Hayden Wolff, Matthew Feinberg, Melissa Corpuz, Marek Wawrzos, Eileen Long, Aastha Jhunjhunwala, Paul Hendricks, Farzan Memarian, Benika Hall, Xin-Yu Wang, David Mosallanezhad, Soumye Singhal, Luis Vega, Katherine Cheung, Krzysztof Pawelec, Michael Evans, Katherine Luna, Jie Lou, Erick Galinkin, Akshay Hazare, Kaustubh Purandare, Ann Guan, Anna Warno, Chen Cui, Yoshi Suhara, Shibani Likhite, Seph Mard, Meredith Price, Laya Sleiman, Saori Kaji, Udi Karpas, Kari Briski, Joey Conway, Michael Lightstone, Jan Kautz, Mohammad Shoeybi, Mostofa Patwary, Jonathen Cohen, Oleksii Kuchaiev, Andrew Tao, Bryan Catanzaro&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Nemotron Nano V2 VL, the latest model of the Nemotron vision-language series designed for strong real-world document understanding, long video comprehension, and reasoning tasks. Nemotron Nano V2 VL delivers significant improvements over our previous model, Llama-3.1-Nemotron-Nano-VL-8B, across all vision and text domains through major enhancements in model architecture, datasets, and training recipes. Nemotron Nano V2 VL builds on Nemotron Nano V2, a hybrid Mamba-Transformer LLM, and innovative token reduction techniques to achieve higher inference throughput in long document and video scenarios. We are releasing model checkpoints in BF16, FP8, and FP4 formats and sharing large parts of our datasets, recipes and training code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03929</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 00:10:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Vision-Driven Reactive Soccer Skills for Humanoid Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03996</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03996.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yushi Wang, Changsheng Luo, Penghui Chen, Jianran Liu, Weijian Sun, Tong Guo, Kechang Yang, Biao Hu, Yangang Zhang, Mingguo Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humanoid soccer poses a representative challenge for embodied intelligence, requiring robots to operate within a tightly coupled perception-action loop. However, existing systems typically rely on decoupled modules, resulting in delayed responses and incoherent behaviors in dynamic environments, while real-world perceptual limitations further exacerbate these issues. In this work, we present a unified reinforcement learning-based controller that enables humanoid robots to acquire reactive soccer skills through the direct integration of visual perception and motion control. Our approach extends Adversarial Motion Priors to perceptual settings in real-world dynamic environments, bridging motion imitation and visually grounded dynamic control. We introduce an encoder-decoder architecture combined with a virtual perception system that models real-world visual characteristics, allowing the policy to recover privileged states from imperfect observations and establish active coordination between perception and action. The resulting controller demonstrates strong reactivity, consistently executing coherent and robust soccer behaviors across various scenarios, including real RoboCup matches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03996</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 02:40:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Strong Lottery Ticket Hypothesis for Multi-Head Attention Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04217</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04217.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hikari Otsuka, Daiki Chijiwa, Yasuyuki Okoshi, Daichi Fujiki, Susumu Takeuchi, Masato Motomura&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The strong lottery ticket hypothesis (SLTH) conjectures that high-performing subnetworks, called strong lottery tickets (SLTs), are hidden in randomly initialized neural networks. Although recent theoretical studies have established the SLTH across various neural architectures, the SLTH for transformer architectures still lacks theoretical understanding. In particular, the current theory of the SLTH does not yet account for the multi-head attention (MHA) mechanism, a core component of transformers. To address this gap, we introduce a theoretical analysis of the existence of SLTs within MHAs. We prove that, if a randomly initialized MHA of H heads and input dimension d has the hidden dimension O(dlog(Hd^{3/2})) for the key and value, it contains an SLT that approximates an arbitrary MHA with the same input dimension with high probability. Furthermore, by leveraging this theory for MHAs, we extend the SLTH to transformers without normalization layers. We empirically validate our theoretical findings, demonstrating that the approximation error between the SLT within a source model (MHA and transformer) and an approximate target counterpart decreases exponentially by increasing the hidden dimension of the source model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04217</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 09:29:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GUI-360: A Comprehensive Dataset and Benchmark for Computer-Using Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04307</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04307.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jian Mu, Chaoyun Zhang, Chiming Ni, Lu Wang, Bo Qiao, Kartik Mathur, Qianhui Wu, Yuhang Xie, Xiaojun Ma, Mengyu Zhou, Si Qin, Liqun Li, Yu Kang, Minghua Ma, Qingwei Lin, Saravan Rajmohan, Dongmei Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce GUI-360^circ, a large-scale, comprehensive dataset and benchmark suite designed to advance computer-using agents (CUAs). CUAs present unique challenges and is constrained by three persistent gaps: a scarcity of real-world CUA tasks, the lack of automated collection-and-annotation pipelines for multi-modal trajectories, and the absence of a unified benchmark that jointly evaluates GUI grounding, screen parsing, and action prediction.   GUI-360^circ addresses these gaps with an LLM-augmented, largely automated pipeline for query sourcing, environment-template construction, task instantiation, batched execution, and LLM-driven quality filtering. The released corpus contains over 1.2M executed action steps across thousands of trajectories in popular Windows office applications, and includes full-resolution screenshots, accessibility metadata when available, instantiated goals, intermediate reasoning traces, and both successful and failed action trajectories. The dataset supports three canonical tasks, GUI grounding, screen parsing, and action prediction, and a hybrid GUI+API action space that reflects modern agent designs. Benchmarking state-of-the-art vision--language models on GUI-360^circ reveals substantial out-of-the-box shortcomings in grounding and action prediction; supervised fine-tuning and reinforcement learning yield significant gains but do not close the gap to human-level reliability. We release GUI-360^circ and accompanying code to facilitate reproducible research and accelerate progress on robust desktop CUAs.   The full dataset has been made public on https://huggingface.co/datasets/vyokky/GUI-360.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04307</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 12:19:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V-Thinker: Interactive Thinking with Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04460</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04460.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runqi Qiao, Qiuna Tan, Minghan Yang, Guanting Dong, Peiqing Yang, Shiqiang Lang, Enhui Wan, Xiaowan Wang, Yida Xu, Lan Yang, Chong Sun, Chen Li, Honggang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 81&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Empowering Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) to deeply integrate image interaction with long-horizon reasoning capabilities remains a long-standing challenge in this field. Recent advances in vision-centric reasoning explore a promising "Thinking with Images" paradigm for LMMs, marking a shift from image-assisted reasoning to image-interactive thinking. While this milestone enables models to focus on fine-grained image regions, progress remains constrained by limited visual tool spaces and task-specific workflow designs. To bridge this gap, we present V-Thinker, a general-purpose multimodal reasoning assistant that enables interactive, vision-centric thinking through end-to-end reinforcement learning. V-Thinker comprises two key components: (1) a Data Evolution Flywheel that automatically synthesizes, evolves, and verifies interactive reasoning datasets across three dimensions-diversity, quality, and difficulty; and (2) a Visual Progressive Training Curriculum that first aligns perception via point-level supervision, then integrates interactive reasoning through a two-stage reinforcement learning framework. Furthermore, we introduce VTBench, an expert-verified benchmark targeting vision-centric interactive reasoning tasks. Extensive experiments demonstrate that V-Thinker consistently outperforms strong LMM-based baselines in both general and interactive reasoning scenarios, providing valuable insights for advancing image-interactive reasoning applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04460</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 15:32:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking with Video: Video Generation as a Promising Multimodal   Reasoning Paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04570</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04570.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingqi Tong, Yurong Mou, Hangcheng Li, Mingzhe Li, Yongzhuo Yang, Ming Zhang, Qiguang Chen, Tianyi Liang, Xiaomeng Hu, Yining Zheng, Xinchi Chen, Jun Zhao, Xuanjing Huang, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 161&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; "Thinking with Text" and "Thinking with Images" paradigm significantly improve the reasoning ability of large language models (LLMs) and Vision Language Models (VLMs). However, these paradigms have inherent limitations. (1) Images capture only single moments and fail to represent dynamic processes or continuous changes, and (2) The separation of text and vision as distinct modalities, hindering unified multimodal understanding and generation. To overcome these limitations, we introduce "Thinking with Video", a new paradigm that leverages video generation models, such as Sora-2, to bridge visual and textual reasoning in a unified temporal framework. To support this exploration, we developed the Video Thinking Benchmark (VideoThinkBench). VideoThinkBench encompasses two task categories: (1) vision-centric tasks (e.g., Eyeballing Puzzles), and (2) text-centric tasks (e.g., subsets of GSM8K, MMMU). Our evaluation establishes Sora-2 as a capable reasoner. On vision-centric tasks, Sora-2 is generally comparable to state-of-the-art (SOTA) VLMs, and even surpasses VLMs on several tasks, such as Eyeballing Games. On text-centric tasks, Sora-2 achieves 92% accuracy on MATH, and 75.53% accuracy on MMMU. Furthermore, we systematically analyse the source of these abilities. We also find that self-consistency and in-context learning can improve Sora-2's performance. In summary, our findings demonstrate that the video generation model is the potential unified multimodal understanding and generation model, positions "thinking with video" as a unified multimodal reasoning paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04570</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:25:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jr. AI Scientist and Its Risk Report: Autonomous Scientific Exploration   from a Baseline Paper</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04583</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04583.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Atsuyuki Miyai, Mashiro Toyooka, Takashi Otonari, Zaiying Zhao, Kiyoharu Aizawa&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding the current capabilities and risks of AI Scientist systems is essential for ensuring trustworthy and sustainable AI-driven scientific progress while preserving the integrity of the academic ecosystem. To this end, we develop Jr. AI Scientist, a state-of-the-art autonomous AI scientist system that mimics the core research workflow of a novice student researcher: Given the baseline paper from the human mentor, it analyzes its limitations, formulates novel hypotheses for improvement, validates them through rigorous experimentation, and writes a paper with the results. Unlike previous approaches that assume full automation or operate on small-scale code, Jr. AI Scientist follows a well-defined research workflow and leverages modern coding agents to handle complex, multi-file implementations, leading to scientifically valuable contributions. For evaluation, we conducted automated assessments using AI Reviewers, author-led evaluations, and submissions to Agents4Science, a venue dedicated to AI-driven scientific contributions. The findings demonstrate that Jr. AI Scientist generates papers receiving higher review scores than existing fully automated systems. Nevertheless, we identify important limitations from both the author evaluation and the Agents4Science reviews, indicating the potential risks of directly applying current AI Scientist systems and key challenges for future research. Finally, we comprehensively report various risks identified during development. We hope these insights will deepen understanding of current progress and risks in AI Scientist development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04583</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:37:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmark Designers Should "Train on the Test Set" to Expose Exploitable   Non-Visual Shortcuts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04655</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04655.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ellis Brown, Jihan Yang, Shusheng Yang, Rob Fergus, Saining Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Robust benchmarks are crucial for evaluating Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs). Yet we find that models can ace many multimodal benchmarks without strong visual understanding, instead exploiting biases, linguistic priors, and superficial patterns. This is especially problematic for vision-centric benchmarks that are meant to require visual inputs. We adopt a diagnostic principle for benchmark design: if a benchmark can be gamed, it will be. Designers should therefore try to ``game'' their own benchmarks first, using diagnostic and debiasing procedures to systematically identify and mitigate non-visual biases. Effective diagnosis requires directly ``training on the test set'' -- probing the released test set for its intrinsic, exploitable patterns.   We operationalize this standard with two components. First, we diagnose benchmark susceptibility using a ``Test-set Stress-Test'' (TsT) methodology. Our primary diagnostic tool involves fine-tuning a powerful Large Language Model via k-fold cross-validation on exclusively the non-visual, textual inputs of the test set to reveal shortcut performance and assign each sample a bias score s(x). We complement this with a lightweight Random Forest-based diagnostic operating on hand-crafted features for fast, interpretable auditing. Second, we debias benchmarks by filtering high-bias samples using an ``Iterative Bias Pruning'' (IBP) procedure. Applying this framework to four benchmarks -- VSI-Bench, CV-Bench, MMMU, and VideoMME -- we uncover pervasive non-visual biases. As a case study, we apply our full framework to create VSI-Bench-Debiased, demonstrating reduced non-visual solvability and a wider vision-blind performance gap than the original.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04655</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:43:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SIMS-V: Simulated Instruction-Tuning for Spatial Video Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04668</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04668.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ellis Brown, Arijit Ray, Ranjay Krishna, Ross Girshick, Rob Fergus, Saining Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite impressive high-level video comprehension, multimodal language models struggle with spatial reasoning across time and space. While current spatial training approaches rely on real-world video data, obtaining diverse footage with precise spatial annotations remains a bottleneck. To alleviate this bottleneck, we present SIMS-V -- a systematic data-generation framework that leverages the privileged information of 3D simulators to create spatially-rich video training data for multimodal language models. Using this framework, we investigate which properties of simulated data drive effective real-world transfer through systematic ablations of question types, mixes, and scales. We identify a minimal set of three question categories (metric measurement, perspective-dependent reasoning, and temporal tracking) that prove most effective for developing transferable spatial intelligence, outperforming comprehensive coverage despite using fewer question types. These insights enable highly efficient training: our 7B-parameter video LLM fine-tuned on just 25K simulated examples outperforms the larger 72B baseline and achieves competitive performance with proprietary models on rigorous real-world spatial reasoning benchmarks. Our approach demonstrates robust generalization, maintaining performance on general video understanding while showing substantial improvements on embodied and real-world spatial tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04668</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:53:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cambrian-S: Towards Spatial Supersensing in Video</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04670</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04670.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shusheng Yang, Jihan Yang, Pinzhi Huang, Ellis Brown, Zihao Yang, Yue Yu, Shengbang Tong, Zihan Zheng, Yifan Xu, Muhan Wang, Daohan Lu, Rob Fergus, Yann LeCun, Li Fei-Fei, Saining Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We argue that progress in true multimodal intelligence calls for a shift from reactive, task-driven systems and brute-force long context towards a broader paradigm of supersensing. We frame spatial supersensing as four stages beyond linguistic-only understanding: semantic perception (naming what is seen), streaming event cognition (maintaining memory across continuous experiences), implicit 3D spatial cognition (inferring the world behind pixels), and predictive world modeling (creating internal models that filter and organize information). Current benchmarks largely test only the early stages, offering narrow coverage of spatial cognition and rarely challenging models in ways that require true world modeling. To drive progress in spatial supersensing, we present VSI-SUPER, a two-part benchmark: VSR (long-horizon visual spatial recall) and VSC (continual visual spatial counting). These tasks require arbitrarily long video inputs yet are resistant to brute-force context expansion. We then test data scaling limits by curating VSI-590K and training Cambrian-S, achieving +30% absolute improvement on VSI-Bench without sacrificing general capabilities. Yet performance on VSI-SUPER remains limited, indicating that scale alone is insufficient for spatial supersensing. We propose predictive sensing as a path forward, presenting a proof-of-concept in which a self-supervised next-latent-frame predictor leverages surprise (prediction error) to drive memory and event segmentation. On VSI-SUPER, this approach substantially outperforms leading proprietary baselines, showing that spatial supersensing requires models that not only see but also anticipate, select, and organize experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04670</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:55:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
