<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 00:16:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>BPDQ: Bit-Plane Decomposition Quantization on a Variable Grid for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04163</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.04163.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyu Chen, Jungang Li, Jing Xiong, Wenjie Wang, Qingyao Yang, He Xiao, Zhen Li, Taiqiang Wu, Mengzhao Chen, Zhen Peng, Chaofan Tao, Long Shi, Hongxia Yang, Ngai Wong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM) inference is often bounded by memory footprint and memory bandwidth in resource-constrained deployments, making quantization a fundamental technique for efficient serving. While post-training quantization (PTQ) maintains high fidelity at 4-bit, it deteriorates at 2-3 bits. Fundamentally, existing methods enforce a shape-invariant quantization grid (e.g., the fixed uniform intervals of UINT2) for each group, severely restricting the feasible set for error minimization. To address this, we propose Bit-Plane Decomposition Quantization (BPDQ), which constructs a variable quantization grid via bit-planes and scalar coefficients, and iteratively refines them using approximate second-order information while progressively compensating quantization errors to minimize output discrepancy. In the 2-bit regime, BPDQ enables serving Qwen2.5-72B on a single RTX 3090 with 83.85% GSM8K accuracy (vs. 90.83% at 16-bit). Moreover, we provide theoretical analysis showing that the variable grid expands the feasible set, and that the quantization process consistently aligns with the optimization objective in Hessian-induced geometry. Code: github.com/KingdalfGoodman/BPDQ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04163</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 02:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principled Synthetic Data Enables the First Scaling Laws for LLMs in Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07298</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07298.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Benyu Zhang, Qiang Zhang, Jianpeng Cheng, Hong-You Chen, Qifei Wang, Wei Sun, Shen Li, Jia Li, Jiahao Wu, Xiangjun Fan, Hong Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) represent a promising frontier for recommender systems, yet their development has been impeded by the absence of predictable scaling laws, which are crucial for guiding research and optimizing resource allocation. We hypothesize that this may be attributed to the inherent noise, bias, and incompleteness of raw user interaction data in prior continual pre-training (CPT) efforts. This paper introduces a novel, layered framework for generating high-quality synthetic data that circumvents such issues by creating a curated, pedagogical curriculum for the LLM. We provide powerful, direct evidence for the utility of our curriculum by showing that standard sequential models trained on our principled synthetic data significantly outperform (+130% on recall@100 for SasRec) models trained on real data in downstream ranking tasks, demonstrating its superiority for learning generalizable user preference patterns. Building on this, we empirically demonstrate, for the first time, robust power-law scaling for an LLM that is continually pre-trained on our high-quality, recommendation-specific data. Our experiments reveal consistent and predictable perplexity reduction across multiple synthetic data modalities. These findings establish a foundational methodology for reliable scaling LLM capabilities in the recommendation domain, thereby shifting the research focus from mitigating data deficiencies to leveraging high-quality, structured information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07298</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 01:15:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Few-Step Generation with Adaptive Matching Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07345</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07345.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lichen Bai, Zikai Zhou, Shitong Shao, Wenliang Zhong, Shuo Yang, Shuo Chen, Bojun Chen, Zeke Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Distribution Matching Distillation (DMD) is a powerful acceleration paradigm, yet its stability is often compromised in Forbidden Zone, regions where the real teacher provides unreliable guidance while the fake teacher exerts insufficient repulsive force. In this work, we propose a unified optimization framework that reinterprets prior art as implicit strategies to avoid these corrupted regions. Based on this insight, we introduce Adaptive Matching Distillation (AMD), a self-correcting mechanism that utilizes reward proxies to explicitly detect and escape Forbidden Zones. AMD dynamically prioritizes corrective gradients via structural signal decomposition and introduces Repulsive Landscape Sharpening to enforce steep energy barriers against failure mode collapse. Extensive experiments across image and video generation tasks (e.g., SDXL, Wan2.1) and rigorous benchmarks (e.g., VBench, GenEval) demonstrate that AMD significantly enhances sample fidelity and training robustness. For instance, AMD improves the HPSv2 score on SDXL from 30.64 to 31.25, outperforming state-of-the-art baselines. These findings validate that explicitly rectifying optimization trajectories within Forbidden Zones is essential for pushing the performance ceiling of few-step generative models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07345</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 04:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Darwinism Part I: Unlocking the Value of Scientific Data for Pre-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07824</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07824.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiwei Qin, Zhen Huang, Tiantian Mi, Weiye Si, Chenyang Zhou, Qipeng Guo, Siyuan Feng, Pengfei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data quality determines foundation model performance, yet systematic processing frameworks are lacking. We introduce Data Darwinism, a ten-level taxonomy (L0-L9) that conceptualizes data-model co-evolution: advanced models produce superior data for next-generation systems. We validate this on scientific literature by constructing Darwin-Science, a 900B-token corpus (L0-L5). We identify a learnability gap in raw scientific text, which we bridge via L4 (Generative Refinement) and L5 (Cognitive Completion) using frontier LLMs to explicate reasoning and terminology.   To ensure rigorous attribution, we pre-trained daVinci-origin-3B/7B models from scratch, excluding scientific content to create contamination-free baselines. After 600B tokens of continued pre-training, Darwin-Science outperforms baselines by +2.12 (3B) and +2.95 (7B) points across 20+ benchmarks, rising to +5.60 and +8.40 points on domain-aligned tasks. Systematic progression to L5 yields a +1.36 total gain, confirming that higher-level processing unlocks latent data value. We release the Darwin-Science corpus and daVinci-origin models to enable principled, co-evolutionary development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07824</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 05:06:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry-Aware Rotary Position Embedding for Consistent Video World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07854</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07854.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chendong Xiang, Jiajun Liu, Jintao Zhang, Xiao Yang, Zhengwei Fang, Shizun Wang, Zijun Wang, Yingtian Zou, Hang Su, Jun Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Predictive world models that simulate future observations under explicit camera control are fundamental to interactive AI. Despite rapid advances, current systems lack spatial persistence: they fail to maintain stable scene structures over long trajectories, frequently hallucinating details when cameras revisit previously observed locations. We identify that this geometric drift stems from reliance on screen-space positional embeddings, which conflict with the projective geometry required for 3D consistency. We introduce ViewRope, a geometry-aware encoding that injects camera-ray directions directly into video transformer self-attention layers. By parameterizing attention with relative ray geometry rather than pixel locality, ViewRope provides a model-native inductive bias for retrieving 3D-consistent content across temporal gaps. We further propose Geometry-Aware Frame-Sparse Attention, which exploits these geometric cues to selectively attend to relevant historical frames, improving efficiency without sacrificing memory consistency. We also present ViewBench, a diagnostic suite measuring loop-closure fidelity and geometric drift. Our results demonstrate that ViewRope substantially improves long-term consistency while reducing computational costs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07854</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 08:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VisPhyWorld: Probing Physical Reasoning via Code-Driven Video Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13294</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13294.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiarong Liang, Max Ku, Ka-Hei Hui, Ping Nie, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating whether Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) genuinely reason about physical dynamics remains challenging. Most existing benchmarks rely on recognition-style protocols such as Visual Question Answering (VQA) and Violation of Expectation (VoE), which can often be answered without committing to an explicit, testable physical hypothesis. We propose VisPhyWorld, an execution-based framework that evaluates physical reasoning by requiring models to generate executable simulator code from visual observations. By producing runnable code, the inferred world representation is directly inspectable, editable, and falsifiable. This separates physical reasoning from rendering. Building on this framework, we introduce VisPhyBench, comprising 209 evaluation scenes derived from 108 physical templates and a systematic protocol that evaluates how well models reconstruct appearance and reproduce physically plausible motion. Our pipeline produces valid reconstructed videos in 97.7% on the benchmark. Experiments show that while state-of-the-art MLLMs achieve strong semantic scene understanding, they struggle to accurately infer physical parameters and to simulate consistent physical dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13294</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 05:46:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BiManiBench: A Hierarchical Benchmark for Evaluating Bimanual Coordination of Multimodal Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08392</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08392.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Wu, Zhixuan Liang, Yue Ma, Mengkang Hu, Zhiyuan Qin, Xiu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have significantly advanced embodied AI, and using them to benchmark robotic intelligence has become a pivotal trend. However, existing frameworks remain predominantly confined to single-arm manipulation, failing to capture the spatio-temporal coordination required for bimanual tasks like lifting a heavy pot. To address this, we introduce BiManiBench, a hierarchical benchmark evaluating MLLMs across three tiers: fundamental spatial reasoning, high-level action planning, and low-level end-effector control. Our framework isolates unique bimanual challenges, such as arm reachability and kinematic constraints, thereby distinguishing perceptual hallucinations from planning failures. Analysis of over 30 state-of-the-art models reveals that despite high-level reasoning proficiency, MLLMs struggle with dual-arm spatial grounding and control, frequently resulting in mutual interference and sequencing errors. These findings suggest the current paradigm lacks a deep understanding of mutual kinematic constraints, highlighting the need for future research to focus on inter-arm collision-avoidance and fine-grained temporal sequencing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08392</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:47:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OneVision-Encoder: Codec-Aligned Sparsity as a Foundational Principle for Multimodal Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08683</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08683.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Feilong Tang, Xiang An, Yunyao Yan, Yin Xie, Bin Qin, Kaicheng Yang, Yifei Shen, Yuanhan Zhang, Chunyuan Li, Shikun Feng, Changrui Chen, Huajie Tan, Ming Hu, Manyuan Zhang, Bo Li, Ziyong Feng, Ziwei Liu, Zongyuan Ge, Jiankang Deng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Hypothesis. Artificial general intelligence is, at its core, a compression problem. Effective compression demands resonance: deep learning scales best when its architecture aligns with the fundamental structure of the data. These are the fundamental principles. Yet, modern vision architectures have strayed from these truths: visual signals are highly redundant, while discriminative information, the surprise, is sparse. Current models process dense pixel grids uniformly, wasting vast compute on static background rather than focusing on the predictive residuals that define motion and meaning. We argue that to solve visual understanding, we must align our architectures with the information-theoretic principles of video, i.e., Codecs.   Method. OneVision-Encoder encodes video by compressing predictive visual structure into semantic meaning. By adopting Codec Patchification, OV-Encoder abandons uniform computation to focus exclusively on the 3.1%-25% of regions rich in signal entropy. To unify spatial and temporal reasoning under irregular token layouts, OneVision-Encoder employs a shared 3D RoPE and is trained with a large-scale cluster discrimination objective over more than one million semantic concepts, jointly capturing object permanence and motion dynamics.   Evidence. The results validate our core hypothesis: efficiency and accuracy are not a trade-off; they are positively correlated. When integrated into LLM, it consistently outperforms strong vision backbones such as Qwen3-ViT and SigLIP2 across 16 image, video, and document understanding benchmarks, despite using substantially fewer visual tokens and pretraining data. Notably, on video understanding tasks, OV-Encoder achieves an average improvement of 4.1% over Qwen3-ViT. Codec-aligned, patch-level sparsity is a foundational principle, enabling OV-Encoder as a scalable engine for next-generation visual generalists.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08683</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:06:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SemanticMoments: Training-Free Motion Similarity via Third Moment Features</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09146</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09146.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Saar Huberman, Kfir Goldberg, Or Patashnik, Sagie Benaim, Ron Mokady&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieving videos based on semantic motion is a fundamental, yet unsolved, problem. Existing video representation approaches overly rely on static appearance and scene context rather than motion dynamics, a bias inherited from their training data and objectives. Conversely, traditional motion-centric inputs like optical flow lack the semantic grounding needed to understand high-level motion. To demonstrate this inherent bias, we introduce the SimMotion benchmarks, combining controlled synthetic data with a new human-annotated real-world dataset. We show that existing models perform poorly on these benchmarks, often failing to disentangle motion from appearance. To address this gap, we propose SemanticMoments, a simple, training-free method that computes temporal statistics (specifically, higher-order moments) over features from pre-trained semantic models. Across our benchmarks, SemanticMoments consistently outperforms existing RGB, flow, and text-supervised methods. This demonstrates that temporal statistics in a semantic feature space provide a scalable and perceptually grounded foundation for motion-centric video understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09146</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:47:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AIDev: Studying AI Coding Agents on GitHub</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09185</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09185.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Li, Haoxiang Zhang, Ahmed E. Hassan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI coding agents are rapidly transforming software engineering by performing tasks such as feature development, debugging, and testing. Despite their growing impact, the research community lacks a comprehensive dataset capturing how these agents are used in real-world projects. To address this gap, we introduce AIDev, a large-scale dataset focused on agent-authored pull requests (Agentic-PRs) in real-world GitHub repositories. AIDev aggregates 932,791 Agentic-PRs produced by five agents: OpenAI Codex, Devin, GitHub Copilot, Cursor, and Claude Code. These PRs span 116,211 repositories and involve 72,189 developers. In addition, AIDev includes a curated subset of 33,596 Agentic-PRs from 2,807 repositories with over 100 stars, providing further information such as comments, reviews, commits, and related issues. This dataset offers a foundation for future research on AI adoption, developer productivity, and human-AI collaboration in the new era of software engineering.   &gt; AI Agent, Agentic AI, Coding Agent, Agentic Coding, Agentic Software Engineering, Agentic Engineering&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09185</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 20:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardware Co-Design Scaling Laws via Roofline Modelling for On-Device LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10377</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10377.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Luoyang Sun, Jiwen Jiang, Yifeng Ding, Fengfa Li, Yan Song, Haifeng Zhang, Jian Ying, Lei Ren, Kun Zhan, Wei Chen, Yan Xie, Cheng Deng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action Models (VLAs) have emerged as a key paradigm of Physical AI and are increasingly deployed in autonomous vehicles, robots, and smart spaces. In these resource-constrained on-device settings, selecting an appropriate large language model (LLM) backbone is a critical challenge: models must balance accuracy with strict inference latency and hardware efficiency constraints. This makes hardware-software co-design a game-changing requirement for on-device LLM deployment, where each hardware platform demands a tailored architectural solution. We propose a hardware co-design law that jointly captures model accuracy and inference performance. Specifically, we model training loss as an explicit function of architectural hyperparameters and characterise inference latency via roofline modelling. We empirically evaluate 1,942 candidate architectures on NVIDIA Jetson Orin, training 170 selected models for 10B tokens each to fit a scaling law relating architecture to training loss. By coupling this scaling law with latency modelling, we establish a direct accuracy-latency correspondence and identify the Pareto frontier for hardware co-designed LLMs. We further formulate architecture search as a joint optimisation over precision and performance, deriving feasible design regions under industrial hardware and application budgets. Our approach reduces architecture selection from months to days. At the same latency as Qwen2.5-0.5B on the target hardware, our co-designed architecture achieves 19.42% lower perplexity on WikiText-2. To our knowledge, this is the first principled and operational framework for hardware co-design scaling laws in on-device LLM deployment. We will make the code and related checkpoints publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10377</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 23:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Less is Enough: Synthesizing Diverse Data in Feature Space of LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10388</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10388.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongzhi Li, Xuansheng Wu, Yijiang Li, Lijie Hu, Ninghao Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 221&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The diversity of post-training data is critical for effective downstream performance in large language models (LLMs). Many existing approaches to constructing post-training data quantify diversity using text-based metrics that capture linguistic variation, but such metrics provide only weak signals for the task-relevant features that determine downstream performance. In this work, we introduce Feature Activation Coverage (FAC) which measures data diversity in an interpretable feature space. Building upon this metric, we further propose a diversity-driven data synthesis framework, named FAC Synthesis, that first uses a sparse autoencoder to identify missing features from a seed dataset, and then generates synthetic samples that explicitly reflect these features. Experiments show that our approach consistently improves both data diversity and downstream performance on various tasks, including instruction following, toxicity detection, reward modeling, and behavior steering. Interestingly, we identify a shared, interpretable feature space across model families (i.e., LLaMA, Mistral, and Qwen), enabling cross-model knowledge transfer. Our work provides a solid and practical methodology for exploring data-centric optimization of LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10388</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 00:23:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepImageSearch: Benchmarking Multimodal Agents for Context-Aware Image Retrieval in Visual Histories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10809</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10809.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenlong Deng, Mengjie Deng, Junjie Wu, Dun Zeng, Teng Wang, Qingsong Xie, Jiadeng Huang, Shengjie Ma, Changwang Zhang, Zhaoxiang Wang, Jun Wang, Yutao Zhu, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing multimodal retrieval systems excel at semantic matching but implicitly assume that query-image relevance can be measured in isolation. This paradigm overlooks the rich dependencies inherent in realistic visual streams, where information is distributed across temporal sequences rather than confined to single snapshots. To bridge this gap, we introduce DeepImageSearch, a novel agentic paradigm that reformulates image retrieval as an autonomous exploration task. Models must plan and perform multi-step reasoning over raw visual histories to locate targets based on implicit contextual cues. We construct DISBench, a challenging benchmark built on interconnected visual data. To address the scalability challenge of creating context-dependent queries, we propose a human-model collaborative pipeline that employs vision-language models to mine latent spatiotemporal associations, effectively offloading intensive context discovery before human verification. Furthermore, we build a robust baseline using a modular agent framework equipped with fine-grained tools and a dual-memory system for long-horizon navigation. Extensive experiments demonstrate that DISBench poses significant challenges to state-of-the-art models, highlighting the necessity of incorporating agentic reasoning into next-generation retrieval systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10809</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 12:51:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ABot-M0: VLA Foundation Model for Robotic Manipulation with Action Manifold Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11236</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11236.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yandan Yang, Shuang Zeng, Tong Lin, Xinyuan Chang, Dekang Qi, Junjin Xiao, Haoyun Liu, Ronghan Chen, Yuzhi Chen, Dongjie Huo, Feng Xiong, Xing Wei, Zhiheng Ma, Mu Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Building general-purpose embodied agents across diverse hardware remains a central challenge in robotics, often framed as the ''one-brain, many-forms'' paradigm. Progress is hindered by fragmented data, inconsistent representations, and misaligned training objectives. We present ABot-M0, a framework that builds a systematic data curation pipeline while jointly optimizing model architecture and training strategies, enabling end-to-end transformation of heterogeneous raw data into unified, efficient representations. From six public datasets, we clean, standardize, and balance samples to construct UniACT-dataset, a large-scale dataset with over 6 million trajectories and 9,500 hours of data, covering diverse robot morphologies and task scenarios. Unified pre-training improves knowledge transfer and generalization across platforms and tasks, supporting general-purpose embodied intelligence. To improve action prediction efficiency and stability, we propose the Action Manifold Hypothesis: effective robot actions lie not in the full high-dimensional space but on a low-dimensional, smooth manifold governed by physical laws and task constraints. Based on this, we introduce Action Manifold Learning (AML), which uses a DiT backbone to predict clean, continuous action sequences directly. This shifts learning from denoising to projection onto feasible manifolds, improving decoding speed and policy stability. ABot-M0 supports modular perception via a dual-stream mechanism that integrates VLM semantics with geometric priors and multi-view inputs from plug-and-play 3D modules such as VGGT and Qwen-Image-Edit, enhancing spatial understanding without modifying the backbone and mitigating standard VLM limitations in 3D reasoning. Experiments show components operate independently with additive benefits. We will release all code and pipelines for reproducibility and future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11236</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 16:47:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causal-JEPA: Learning World Models through Object-Level Latent Interventions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11389</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11389.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Heejeong Nam, Quentin Le Lidec, Lucas Maes, Yann LeCun, Randall Balestriero&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; World models require robust relational understanding to support prediction, reasoning, and control. While object-centric representations provide a useful abstraction, they are not sufficient to capture interaction-dependent dynamics. We therefore propose C-JEPA, a simple and flexible object-centric world model that extends masked joint embedding prediction from image patches to object-centric representations. By applying object-level masking that requires an object's state to be inferred from other objects, C-JEPA induces latent interventions with counterfactual-like effects and prevents shortcut solutions, making interaction reasoning essential. Empirically, C-JEPA leads to consistent gains in visual question answering, with an absolute improvement of about 20\% in counterfactual reasoning compared to the same architecture without object-level masking. On agent control tasks, C-JEPA enables substantially more efficient planning by using only 1\% of the total latent input features required by patch-based world models, while achieving comparable performance. Finally, we provide a formal analysis demonstrating that object-level masking induces a causal inductive bias via latent interventions. Our code is available at https://github.com/galilai-group/cjepa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11389</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 21:47:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Configure Agentic AI Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11574</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11574.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aditya Taparia, Som Sagar, Ransalu Senanayake&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Configuring LLM-based agent systems involves choosing workflows, tools, token budgets, and prompts from a large combinatorial design space, and is typically handled today by fixed large templates or hand-tuned heuristics. This leads to brittle behavior and unnecessary compute, since the same cumbersome configuration is often applied to both easy and hard input queries. We formulate agent configuration as a query-wise decision problem and introduce ARC (Agentic Resource &amp; Configuration learner), which learns a light-weight hierarchical policy using reinforcement learning to dynamically tailor these configurations. Across multiple benchmarks spanning reasoning and tool-augmented question answering, the learned policy consistently outperforms strong hand-designed and other baselines, achieving up to 25% higher task accuracy while also reducing token and runtime costs. These results demonstrate that learning per-query agent configurations is a powerful alternative to "one size fits all" designs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11574</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 04:45:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DICE: Diffusion Large Language Models Excel at Generating CUDA Kernels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11715</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11715.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haolei Bai, Lingcheng Kong, Xueyi Chen, Jianmian Wang, Zhiqiang Tao, Huan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion large language models (dLLMs) have emerged as a compelling alternative to autoregressive (AR) LLMs, owing to their capacity for parallel token generation. This paradigm is particularly well-suited for code generation, where holistic structural planning and non-sequential refinement are critical. Despite this potential, tailoring dLLMs for CUDA kernel generation remains challenging, obstructed not only by the high specialization but also by the severe lack of high-quality training data. To address these challenges, we construct CuKe, an augmented supervised fine-tuning dataset optimized for high-performance CUDA kernels. On top of it, we propose a bi-phase curated reinforcement learning (BiC-RL) framework consisting of a CUDA kernel infilling stage and an end-to-end CUDA kernel generation stage. Leveraging this training framework, we introduce DICE, a series of diffusion large language models designed for CUDA kernel generation, spanning three parameter scales, 1.7B, 4B, and 8B. Extensive experiments on KernelBench demonstrate that DICE significantly outperforms both autoregressive and diffusion LLMs of comparable scale, establishing a new state-of-the-art for CUDA kernel generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11715</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 08:45:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code2Worlds: Empowering Coding LLMs for 4D World Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11757</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11757.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Zhang, Yunshuang Wang, Zeyu Zhang, Hao Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Achieving spatial intelligence requires moving beyond visual plausibility to build world simulators grounded in physical laws. While coding LLMs have advanced static 3D scene generation, extending this paradigm to 4D dynamics remains a critical frontier. This task presents two fundamental challenges: multi-scale context entanglement, where monolithic generation fails to balance local object structures with global environmental layouts; and a semantic-physical execution gap, where open-loop code generation leads to physical hallucinations lacking dynamic fidelity. We introduce Code2Worlds, a framework that formulates 4D generation as language-to-simulation code generation. First, we propose a dual-stream architecture that disentangles retrieval-augmented object generation from hierarchical environmental orchestration. Second, to ensure dynamic fidelity, we establish a physics-aware closed-loop mechanism in which a PostProcess Agent scripts dynamics, coupled with a VLM-Motion Critic that performs self-reflection to iteratively refine simulation code. Evaluations on the Code4D benchmark show Code2Worlds outperforms baselines with a 41% SGS gain and 49% higher Richness, while uniquely generating physics-aware dynamics absent in prior static methods. Code: https://github.com/AIGeeksGroup/Code2Worlds. Website: https://aigeeksgroup.github.io/Code2Worlds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11757</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 09:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zooming without Zooming: Region-to-Image Distillation for Fine-Grained Multimodal Perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11858</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11858.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lai Wei, Liangbo He, Jun Lan, Lingzhong Dong, Yutong Cai, Siyuan Li, Huijia Zhu, Weiqiang Wang, Linghe Kong, Yue Wang, Zhuosheng Zhang, Weiran Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) excel at broad visual understanding but still struggle with fine-grained perception, where decisive evidence is small and easily overwhelmed by global context. Recent "Thinking-with-Images" methods alleviate this by iteratively zooming in and out regions of interest during inference, but incur high latency due to repeated tool calls and visual re-encoding. To address this, we propose Region-to-Image Distillation, which transforms zooming from an inference-time tool into a training-time primitive, thereby internalizing the benefits of agentic zooming into a single forward pass of an MLLM. In particular, we first zoom in to micro-cropped regions to let strong teacher models generate high-quality VQA data, and then distill this region-grounded supervision back to the full image. After training on such data, the smaller student model improves "single-glance" fine-grained perception without tool use. To rigorously evaluate this capability, we further present ZoomBench, a hybrid-annotated benchmark of 845 VQA data spanning six fine-grained perceptual dimensions, together with a dual-view protocol that quantifies the global--regional "zooming gap". Experiments show that our models achieve leading performance across multiple fine-grained perception benchmarks, and also improve general multimodal cognition on benchmarks such as visual reasoning and GUI agents. We further discuss when "Thinking-with-Images" is necessary versus when its gains can be distilled into a single forward pass. Our code is available at https://github.com/inclusionAI/Zooming-without-Zooming.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11858</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 12:00:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent AI Delegation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11865</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11865.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nenad Tomašev, Matija Franklin, Simon Osindero&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI agents are able to tackle increasingly complex tasks. To achieve more ambitious goals, AI agents need to be able to meaningfully decompose problems into manageable sub-components, and safely delegate their completion across to other AI agents and humans alike. Yet, existing task decomposition and delegation methods rely on simple heuristics, and are not able to dynamically adapt to environmental changes and robustly handle unexpected failures. Here we propose an adaptive framework for intelligent AI delegation - a sequence of decisions involving task allocation, that also incorporates transfer of authority, responsibility, accountability, clear specifications regarding roles and boundaries, clarity of intent, and mechanisms for establishing trust between the two (or more) parties. The proposed framework is applicable to both human and AI delegators and delegatees in complex delegation networks, aiming to inform the development of protocols in the emerging agentic web.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11865</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 12:11:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FireRed-Image-Edit-1.0 Techinical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13344</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13344.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Super Intelligence Team, Changhao Qiao, Chao Hui, Chen Li, Cunzheng Wang, Dejia Song, Jiale Zhang, Jing Li, Qiang Xiang, Runqi Wang, Shuang Sun, Wei Zhu, Xu Tang, Yao Hu, Yibo Chen, Yuhao Huang, Yuxuan Duan, Zhiyi Chen, Ziyuan Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present FireRed-Image-Edit, a diffusion transformer for instruction-based image editing that achieves state-of-the-art performance through systematic optimization of data curation, training methodology, and evaluation design. We construct a 1.6B-sample training corpus, comprising 900M text-to-image and 700M image editing pairs from diverse sources. After rigorous cleaning, stratification, auto-labeling, and two-stage filtering, we retain over 100M high-quality samples balanced between generation and editing, ensuring strong semantic coverage and instruction alignment. Our multi-stage training pipeline progressively builds editing capability via pre-training, supervised fine-tuning, and reinforcement learning. To improve data efficiency, we introduce a Multi-Condition Aware Bucket Sampler for variable-resolution batching and Stochastic Instruction Alignment with dynamic prompt re-indexing. To stabilize optimization and enhance controllability, we propose Asymmetric Gradient Optimization for DPO, DiffusionNFT with layout-aware OCR rewards for text editing, and a differentiable Consistency Loss for identity preservation. We further establish REDEdit-Bench, a comprehensive benchmark spanning 15 editing categories, including newly introduced beautification and low-level enhancement tasks. Extensive experiments on REDEdit-Bench and public benchmarks (ImgEdit and GEdit) demonstrate competitive or superior performance against both open-source and proprietary systems. We release code, models, and the benchmark suite to support future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13344</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 17:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Best of Both Worlds: Multimodal Reasoning and Generation via Unified Discrete Flow Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12221</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12221.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Onkar Susladkar, Tushar Prakash, Gayatri Deshmukh, Kiet A. Nguyen, Jiaxun Zhang, Adheesh Juvekar, Tianshu Bao, Lin Chai, Sparsh Mittal, Inderjit S Dhillon, Ismini Lourentzou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose UniDFlow, a unified discrete flow-matching framework for multimodal understanding, generation, and editing. It decouples understanding and generation via task-specific low-rank adapters, avoiding objective interference and representation entanglement, while a novel reference-based multimodal preference alignment optimizes relative outcomes under identical conditioning, improving faithfulness and controllability without large-scale retraining. UniDFlpw achieves SOTA performance across eight benchmarks and exhibits strong zero-shot generalization to tasks including inpainting, in-context image generation, reference-based editing, and compositional generation, despite no explicit task-specific training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12221</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 17:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniT: Unified Multimodal Chain-of-Thought Test-time Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12279</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12279.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Leon Liangyu Chen, Haoyu Ma, Zhipeng Fan, Ziqi Huang, Animesh Sinha, Xiaoliang Dai, Jialiang Wang, Zecheng He, Jianwei Yang, Chunyuan Li, Junzhe Sun, Chu Wang, Serena Yeung-Levy, Felix Juefei-Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified models can handle both multimodal understanding and generation within a single architecture, yet they typically operate in a single pass without iteratively refining their outputs. Many multimodal tasks, especially those involving complex spatial compositions, multiple interacting objects, or evolving instructions, require decomposing instructions, verifying intermediate results, and making iterative corrections. While test-time scaling (TTS) has demonstrated that allocating additional inference compute for iterative reasoning substantially improves language model performance, extending this paradigm to unified multimodal models remains an open challenge. We introduce UniT, a framework for multimodal chain-of-thought test-time scaling that enables a single unified model to reason, verify, and refine across multiple rounds. UniT combines agentic data synthesis, unified model training, and flexible test-time inference to elicit cognitive behaviors including verification, subgoal decomposition, and content memory. Our key findings are: (1) unified models trained on short reasoning trajectories generalize to longer inference chains at test time; (2) sequential chain-of-thought reasoning provides a more scalable and compute-efficient TTS strategy than parallel sampling; (3) training on generation and editing trajectories improves out-of-distribution visual reasoning. These results establish multimodal test-time scaling as an effective paradigm for advancing both generation and understanding in unified models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12279</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 18:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does RL improve for Visual Reasoning? A Frankenstein-Style Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12395</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12395.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xirui Li, Ming Li, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) with verifiable rewards has become a standard post-training stage for boosting visual reasoning in vision-language models, yet it remains unclear what capabilities RL actually improves compared with supervised fine-tuning as cold-start initialization (IN). End-to-end benchmark gains conflate multiple factors, making it difficult to attribute improvements to specific skills. To bridge the gap, we propose a Frankenstein-style analysis framework including: (i) functional localization via causal probing; (ii) update characterization via parameter comparison; and (iii) transferability test via model merging. Instead, RL induces a consistent inference-time shift primarily in mid-to-late layers, and these mid-to-late refinements are both transferable (via merging) and necessary (via freezing) for RL gains. Overall, our results suggest that RL's reliable contribution in visual reasoning is not a uniform enhancement of visual perception, but a systematic refinement of mid-to-late transformer computation that improves vision-to-reasoning alignment and reasoning performance, highlighting the limitations of benchmark-only evaluation for understanding multimodal reasoning improvements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12395</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 20:44:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Robustness and Chain-of-Thought Consistency of RL-Finetuned VLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12506</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12506.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rosie Zhao, Anshul Shah, Xiaoyu Zhu, Xinke Deng, Zhongyu Jiang, Yang Yang, Joerg Liebelt, Arnab Mondal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) fine-tuning has become a key technique for enhancing large language models (LLMs) on reasoning-intensive tasks, motivating its extension to vision language models (VLMs). While RL-tuned VLMs improve on visual reasoning benchmarks, they remain vulnerable to weak visual grounding, hallucinations, and over-reliance on textual cues. We show that simple, controlled textual perturbations--misleading captions or incorrect chain-of-thought (CoT) traces--cause substantial drops in robustness and confidence, and that these effects are more pronounced when CoT consistency is taken into account across open-source multimodal reasoning models. Entropy-based metrics further show that these perturbations reshape model uncertainty and probability mass on the correct option, exposing model-specific trends in miscalibration. To better understand these vulnerabilities, we further analyze RL fine-tuning dynamics and uncover an accuracy-faithfulness trade-off: fine-tuning raises benchmark accuracy, but can simultaneously erode the reliability of the accompanying CoT and its robustness to contextual shifts. Although adversarial augmentation improves robustness, it does not by itself prevent faithfulness drift. Incorporating a faithfulness-aware reward can restore alignment between answers and reasoning, but when paired with augmentation, training risks collapsing onto shortcut strategies and robustness remains elusive. Together, these findings highlight the limitations of accuracy-only evaluations and motivate training and assessment protocols that jointly emphasize correctness, robustness, and the faithfulness of visually grounded reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12506</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 01:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GeoAgent: Learning to Geolocate Everywhere with Reinforced Geographic Characteristics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12617</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12617.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Modi Jin, Yiming Zhang, Boyuan Sun, Dingwen Zhang, MingMing Cheng, Qibin Hou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents GeoAgent, a model capable of reasoning closely with humans and deriving fine-grained address conclusions. Previous RL-based methods have achieved breakthroughs in performance and interpretability but still remain concerns because of their reliance on AI-generated chain-of-thought (CoT) data and training strategies, which conflict with geographic characteristics. To address these issues, we first introduce GeoSeek, a new geolocation dataset comprising CoT data annotated by geographic experts and professional players. We further thoroughly explore the inherent characteristics of geographic tasks and propose a geo-similarity reward and a consistency reward assessed by a consistency agent to assist training. This encourages the model to converge towards correct answers from a geographic perspective while ensuring the integrity and consistency of its reasoning process. Experimental results show that GeoAgent outperforms existing methods and a series of general VLLMs across multiple grains, while generating reasoning that closely aligns with humans.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12617</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 04:48:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLinf-Co: Reinforcement Learning-Based Sim-Real Co-Training for VLA Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12628</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12628.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liangzhi Shi, Shuaihang Chen, Feng Gao, Yinuo Chen, Kang Chen, Tonghe Zhang, Hongzhi Zhang, Weinan Zhang, Chao Yu, Yu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Simulation offers a scalable and low-cost way to enrich vision-language-action (VLA) training, reducing reliance on expensive real-robot demonstrations. However, most sim-real co-training methods rely on supervised fine-tuning (SFT), which treats simulation as a static source of demonstrations and does not exploit large-scale closed-loop interaction. Consequently, real-world gains and generalization are often limited. In this paper, we propose an \textit{RL}-based sim-real \textit{Co}-training (RL-Co) framework that leverages interactive simulation while preserving real-world capabilities. Our method follows a generic two-stage design: we first warm-start the policy with SFT on a mixture of real and simulated demonstrations, then fine-tune it with reinforcement learning in simulation while adding an auxiliary supervised loss on real-world data to anchor the policy and mitigate catastrophic forgetting. We evaluate our framework on four real-world tabletop manipulation tasks using two representative VLA architectures, OpenVLA and π_{0.5}, and observe consistent improvements over real-only fine-tuning and SFT-based co-training, including +24% real-world success on OpenVLA and +20% on π_{0.5}. Beyond higher success rates, RL co-training yields stronger generalization to unseen task variations and substantially improved real-world data efficiency, providing a practical and scalable pathway for leveraging simulation to enhance real-robot deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12628</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 05:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SkillsBench: Benchmarking How Well Agent Skills Work Across Diverse Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12670</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12670.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangyi Li, Wenbo Chen, Yimin Liu, Shenghan Zheng, Xiaokun Chen, Yifeng He, Yubo Li, Bingran You, Haotian Shen, Jiankai Sun, Shuyi Wang, Qunhong Zeng, Di Wang, Xuandong Zhao, Yuanli Wang, Roey Ben Chaim, Zonglin Di, Yipeng Gao, Junwei He, Yizhuo He, Liqiang Jing, Luyang Kong, Xin Lan, Jiachen Li, Songlin Li, Yijiang Li, Yueqian Lin, Xinyi Liu, Xuanqing Liu, Haoran Lyu, Ze Ma, Bowei Wang, Runhui Wang, Tianyu Wang, Wengao Ye, Yue Zhang, Hanwen Xing, Yiqi Xue, Steven Dillmann, Han-chung Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agent Skills are structured packages of procedural knowledge that augment LLM agents at inference time. Despite rapid adoption, there is no standard way to measure whether they actually help. We present SkillsBench, a benchmark of 86 tasks across 11 domains paired with curated Skills and deterministic verifiers. Each task is evaluated under three conditions: no Skills, curated Skills, and self-generated Skills. We test 7 agent-model configurations over 7,308 trajectories. Curated Skills raise average pass rate by 16.2 percentage points(pp), but effects vary widely by domain (+4.5pp for Software Engineering to +51.9pp for Healthcare) and 16 of 84 tasks show negative deltas. Self-generated Skills provide no benefit on average, showing that models cannot reliably author the procedural knowledge they benefit from consuming. Focused Skills with 2--3 modules outperform comprehensive documentation, and smaller models with Skills can match larger models without them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12670</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 07:06:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SLA2: Sparse-Linear Attention with Learnable Routing and QAT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12675</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12675.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Haoxu Wang, Kai Jiang, Kaiwen Zheng, Youhe Jiang, Ion Stoica, Jianfei Chen, Jun Zhu, Joseph E. Gonzalez&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse-Linear Attention (SLA) combines sparse and linear attention to accelerate diffusion models and has shown strong performance in video generation. However, (i) SLA relies on a heuristic split that assigns computations to the sparse or linear branch based on attention-weight magnitude, which can be suboptimal. Additionally, (ii) after formally analyzing the attention error in SLA, we identify a mismatch between SLA and a direct decomposition into sparse and linear attention. We propose SLA2, which introduces (I) a learnable router that dynamically selects whether each attention computation should use sparse or linear attention, (II) a more faithful and direct sparse-linear attention formulation that uses a learnable ratio to combine the sparse and linear attention branches, and (III) a sparse + low-bit attention design, where low-bit attention is introduced via quantization-aware fine-tuning to reduce quantization error. Experiments show that on video diffusion models, SLA2 can achieve 97% attention sparsity and deliver an 18.6x attention speedup while preserving generation quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12675</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 07:16:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Xiaomi-Robotics-0: An Open-Sourced Vision-Language-Action Model with Real-Time Execution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12684</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12684.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui Cai, Jun Guo, Xinze He, Piaopiao Jin, Jie Li, Bingxuan Lin, Futeng Liu, Wei Liu, Fei Ma, Kun Ma, Feng Qiu, Heng Qu, Yifei Su, Qiao Sun, Dong Wang, Donghao Wang, Yunhong Wang, Rujie Wu, Diyun Xiang, Yu Yang, Hangjun Ye, Yuan Zhang, Quanyun Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this report, we introduce Xiaomi-Robotics-0, an advanced vision-language-action (VLA) model optimized for high performance and fast and smooth real-time execution. The key to our method lies in a carefully designed training recipe and deployment strategy. Xiaomi-Robotics-0 is first pre-trained on large-scale cross-embodiment robot trajectories and vision-language data, endowing it with broad and generalizable action-generation capabilities while avoiding catastrophic forgetting of the visual-semantic knowledge of the underlying pre-trained VLM. During post-training, we propose several techniques for training the VLA model for asynchronous execution to address the inference latency during real-robot rollouts. During deployment, we carefully align the timesteps of consecutive predicted action chunks to ensure continuous and seamless real-time rollouts. We evaluate Xiaomi-Robotics-0 extensively in simulation benchmarks and on two challenging real-robot tasks that require precise and dexterous bimanual manipulation. Results show that our method achieves state-of-the-art performance across all simulation benchmarks. Moreover, Xiaomi-Robotics-0 can roll out fast and smoothly on real robots using a consumer-grade GPU, achieving high success rates and throughput on both real-robot tasks. To facilitate future research, code and model checkpoints are open-sourced at https://xiaomi-robotics-0.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12684</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 07:30:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedXIAOHE: A Comprehensive Recipe for Building Medical MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12705</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12705.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baorong Shi, Bo Cui, Boyuan Jiang, Deli Yu, Fang Qian, Haihua Yang, Huichao Wang, Jiale Chen, Jianfei Pan, Jieqiong Cao, Jinghao Lin, Kai Wu, Lin Yang, Shengsheng Yao, Tao Chen, Xiaojun Xiao, Xiaozhong Ji, Xu Wang, Yijun He, Zhixiong Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present MedXIAOHE, a medical vision-language foundation model designed to advance general-purpose medical understanding and reasoning in real-world clinical applications. MedXIAOHE achieves state-of-the-art performance across diverse medical benchmarks and surpasses leading closed-source multimodal systems on multiple capabilities. To achieve this, we propose an entity-aware continual pretraining framework that organizes heterogeneous medical corpora to broaden knowledge coverage and reduce long-tail gaps (e.g., rare diseases). For medical expert-level reasoning and interaction, MedXIAOHE incorporates diverse medical reasoning patterns via reinforcement learning and tool-augmented agentic training, enabling multi-step diagnostic reasoning with verifiable decision traces. To improve reliability in real-world use, MedXIAOHE integrates user-preference rubrics, evidence-grounded reasoning, and low-hallucination long-form report generation, with improved adherence to medical instructions. We release this report to document our practical design choices, scaling insights, and evaluation framework, hoping to inspire further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12705</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 08:19:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SQuTR: A Robustness Benchmark for Spoken Query to Text Retrieval under Acoustic Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12783</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12783.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuejie Li, Ke Yang, Yueying Hua, Berlin Chen, Jianhao Nie, Yueping He, Caixin Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 140&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spoken query retrieval is an important interaction mode in modern information retrieval. However, existing evaluation datasets are often limited to simple queries under constrained noise conditions, making them inadequate for assessing the robustness of spoken query retrieval systems under complex acoustic perturbations. To address this limitation, we present SQuTR, a robustness benchmark for spoken query retrieval that includes a large-scale dataset and a unified evaluation protocol. SQuTR aggregates 37,317 unique queries from six commonly used English and Chinese text retrieval datasets, spanning multiple domains and diverse query types. We synthesize speech using voice profiles from 200 real speakers and mix 17 categories of real-world environmental noise under controlled SNR levels, enabling reproducible robustness evaluation from quiet to highly noisy conditions. Under the unified protocol, we conduct large-scale evaluations on representative cascaded and end-to-end retrieval systems. Experimental results show that retrieval performance decreases as noise increases, with substantially different drops across systems. Even large-scale retrieval models struggle under extreme noise, indicating that robustness remains a critical bottleneck. Overall, SQuTR provides a reproducible testbed for benchmarking and diagnostic analysis, and facilitates future research on robustness in spoken query to text retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12783</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 10:08:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FLAC: Maximum Entropy RL via Kinetic Energy Regularized Bridge Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12829</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12829.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lei Lv, Yunfei Li, Yu Luo, Fuchun Sun, Xiao Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Iterative generative policies, such as diffusion models and flow matching, offer superior expressivity for continuous control but complicate Maximum Entropy Reinforcement Learning because their action log-densities are not directly accessible. To address this, we propose Field Least-Energy Actor-Critic (FLAC), a likelihood-free framework that regulates policy stochasticity by penalizing the kinetic energy of the velocity field. Our key insight is to formulate policy optimization as a Generalized Schrödinger Bridge (GSB) problem relative to a high-entropy reference process (e.g., uniform). Under this view, the maximum-entropy principle emerges naturally as staying close to a high-entropy reference while optimizing return, without requiring explicit action densities. In this framework, kinetic energy serves as a physically grounded proxy for divergence from the reference: minimizing path-space energy bounds the deviation of the induced terminal action distribution. Building on this view, we derive an energy-regularized policy iteration scheme and a practical off-policy algorithm that automatically tunes the kinetic energy via a Lagrangian dual mechanism. Empirically, FLAC achieves superior or comparable performance on high-dimensional benchmarks relative to strong baselines, while avoiding explicit density estimation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12829</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 11:32:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BrowseComp-V^3: A Visual, Vertical, and Verifiable Benchmark for Multimodal Browsing Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12876</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12876.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huanyao Zhang, Jiepeng Zhou, Bo Li, Bowen Zhou, Yanzhe Dan, Haishan Lu, Zhiyong Cao, Jiaoyang Chen, Yuqian Han, Zinan Sheng, Zhengwei Tao, Hao Liang, Jialong Wu, Yang Shi, Yuanpeng He, Jiaye Lin, Qintong Zhang, Guochen Yan, Runhao Zhao, Zhengpin Li, Xiaohan Yu, Lang Mei, Chong Chen, Wentao Zhang, Bin Cui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs), equipped with increasingly advanced planning and tool-use capabilities, are evolving into autonomous agents capable of performing multimodal web browsing and deep search in open-world environments. However, existing benchmarks for multimodal browsing remain limited in task complexity, evidence accessibility, and evaluation granularity, hindering comprehensive and reproducible assessments of deep search capabilities. To address these limitations, we introduce BrowseComp-V^3, a novel benchmark consisting of 300 carefully curated and challenging questions spanning diverse domains. The benchmark emphasizes deep, multi-level, and cross-modal multi-hop reasoning, where critical evidence is interleaved across textual and visual modalities within and across web pages. All supporting evidence is strictly required to be publicly searchable, ensuring fairness and reproducibility. Beyond final-answer accuracy, we incorporate an expert-validated, subgoal-driven process evaluation mechanism that enables fine-grained analysis of intermediate reasoning behaviors and systematic characterization of capability boundaries. In addition, we propose OmniSeeker, a unified multimodal browsing agent framework integrating diverse web search and visual perception tools. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that even state-of-the-art models achieve only 36% accuracy on our benchmark, revealing critical bottlenecks in multimodal information integration and fine-grained perception. Our results highlight a fundamental gap between current model capabilities and robust multimodal deep search in real-world settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12876</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 12:25:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanbeige4.1-3B: A Small General Model that Reasons, Aligns, and Acts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13367</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13367.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chen Yang, Guangyue Peng, Jiaying Zhu, Ran Le, Ruixiang Feng, Tao Zhang, Xiyun Xu, Yang Song, Yiming Jia, Yuntao Wen, Yunzhi Xu, Zekai Wang, Zhenwei An, Zhicong Sun, Zongchao Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Nanbeige4.1-3B, a unified generalist language model that simultaneously achieves strong agentic behavior, code generation, and general reasoning with only 3B parameters. To the best of our knowledge, it is the first open-source small language model (SLM) to achieve such versatility in a single model. To improve reasoning and preference alignment, we combine point-wise and pair-wise reward modeling, ensuring high-quality, human-aligned responses. For code generation, we design complexity-aware rewards in Reinforcement Learning, optimizing both correctness and efficiency. In deep search, we perform complex data synthesis and incorporate turn-level supervision during training. This enables stable long-horizon tool interactions, allowing Nanbeige4.1-3B to reliably execute up to 600 tool-call turns for complex problem-solving. Extensive experimental results show that Nanbeige4.1-3B significantly outperforms prior models of similar scale, such as Nanbeige4-3B-2511 and Qwen3-4B, even achieving superior performance compared to much larger models, such as Qwen3-30B-A3B. Our results demonstrate that small models can achieve both broad competence and strong specialization simultaneously, redefining the potential of 3B parameter models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13367</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 13:10:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Native Continuation for Action Chunking Flow Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12978</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12978.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yufeng Liu, Hang Yu, Juntu Zhao, Bocheng Li, Di Zhang, Mingzhu Li, Wenxuan Wu, Yingdong Hu, Junyuan Xie, Junliang Guo, Dequan Wang, Yang Gao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Action chunking enables Vision Language Action (VLA) models to run in real time, but naive chunked execution often exhibits discontinuities at chunk boundaries. Real-Time Chunking (RTC) alleviates this issue but is external to the policy, leading to spurious multimodal switching and trajectories that are not intrinsically smooth. We propose Legato, a training-time continuation method for action-chunked flow-based VLA policies. Specifically, Legato initializes denoising from a schedule-shaped mixture of known actions and noise, exposing the model to partial action information. Moreover, Legato reshapes the learned flow dynamics to ensure that the denoising process remains consistent between training and inference under per-step guidance. Legato further uses randomized schedule condition during training to support varying inference delays and achieve controllable smoothness. Empirically, Legato produces smoother trajectories and reduces spurious multimodal switching during execution, leading to less hesitation and shorter task completion time. Extensive real-world experiments show that Legato consistently outperforms RTC across five manipulation tasks, achieving approximately 10% improvements in both trajectory smoothness and task completion time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12978</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 14:56:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SciAgentGym: Benchmarking Multi-Step Scientific Tool-use in LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12984</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12984.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yujiong Shen, Yajie Yang, Zhiheng Xi, Binze Hu, Huayu Sha, Jiazheng Zhang, Qiyuan Peng, Junlin Shang, Jixuan Huang, Yutao Fan, Jingqi Tong, Shihan Dou, Ming Zhang, Lei Bai, Zhenfei Yin, Tao Gui, Xingjun Ma, Qi Zhang, Xuanjing Huang, Yu-Gang Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scientific reasoning inherently demands integrating sophisticated toolkits to navigate domain-specific knowledge. Yet, current benchmarks largely overlook agents' ability to orchestrate tools for such rigorous workflows. To bridge this gap, we introduce SciAgentGym, a scalable interactive environment featuring 1,780 domain-specific tools across four natural science disciplines, supported by a robust execution infrastructure. Complementing this, we present SciAgentBench, a tiered evaluation suite designed to stress-test agentic capabilities from elementary actions to long-horizon workflows. Our evaluation identifies a critical bottleneck: state-of-the-art models struggle with complex scientific tool-use. Even for a leading model like GPT-5, success rates drop sharply from 60.6% to 30.9% as interaction horizons extend, primarily due to failures in multi-step workflow execution. To address this, we propose SciForge, a data synthesis method that models the tool action space as a dependency graph to generate logic-aware training trajectories. By fine-tuning on these trajectories, our SciAgent-8B outperforms the significantly larger Qwen3-VL-235B-Instruct while exhibiting positive cross-domain transfer of scientific tool-use capabilities. These results underscore the promising potential of next-generation autonomous scientific agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12984</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 14:58:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Universal Video MLLMs with Attribute-Structured and Quality-Verified Instructions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13013</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13013.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunheng Li, Hengrui Zhang, Meng-Hao Guo, Wenzhao Gao, Shaoyong Jia, Shaohui Jiao, Qibin Hou, Ming-Ming Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal video understanding requires modeling fine-grained visual and audio information over time in diverse real-world scenarios. However, the performance of existing models is primarily constrained by video-instruction data that represents complex audiovisual content as single, incomplete descriptions, lacking fine-grained organization and reliable annotation. To address this, we introduce: (i) ASID-1M, an open-source collection of one million structured, fine-grained audiovisual instruction annotations with single- and multi-attribute supervision; (ii) ASID-Verify, a scalable data curation pipeline for annotation, with automatic verification and refinement that enforces semantic and temporal consistency between descriptions and the corresponding audiovisual content; and (iii) ASID-Captioner, a video understanding model trained via Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) on the ASID-1M. Experiments across seven benchmarks covering audiovisual captioning, attribute-wise captioning, caption-based QA, and caption-based temporal grounding show that ASID-Captioner improves fine-grained caption quality while reducing hallucinations and improving instruction following. It achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-source models and is competitive with Gemini-3-Pro.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13013</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 15:20:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoPE-VideoLM: Codec Primitives For Efficient Video Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13191</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13191.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sayan Deb Sarkar, Rémi Pautrat, Ondrej Miksik, Marc Pollefeys, Iro Armeni, Mahdi Rad, Mihai Dusmanu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video Language Models (VideoLMs) empower AI systems to understand temporal dynamics in videos. To fit to the maximum context window constraint, current methods use keyframe sampling which can miss both macro-level events and micro-level details due to the sparse temporal coverage. Furthermore, processing full images and their tokens for each frame incurs substantial computational overhead. To address these limitations, we propose to leverage video codec primitives (specifically motion vectors and residuals) which natively encode video redundancy and sparsity without requiring expensive full-image encoding for most frames. To this end, we introduce lightweight transformer-based encoders that aggregate codec primitives and align their representations with image encoder embeddings through a pre-training strategy that accelerates convergence during end-to-end fine-tuning. Our approach reduces the time-to-first-token by up to 86% and token usage by up to 93% compared to standard VideoLMs. Moreover, by varying the keyframe and codec primitive densities we are able to maintain or exceed performance on 14 diverse video understanding benchmarks spanning general question answering, temporal reasoning, long-form understanding, and spatial scene understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13191</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 18:57:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conversational Image Segmentation: Grounding Abstract Concepts with Scalable Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13195</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13195.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aadarsh Sahoo, Georgia Gkioxari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Conversational image segmentation grounds abstract, intent-driven concepts into pixel-accurate masks. Prior work on referring image grounding focuses on categorical and spatial queries (e.g., "left-most apple") and overlooks functional and physical reasoning (e.g., "where can I safely store the knife?"). We address this gap and introduce Conversational Image Segmentation (CIS) and ConverSeg, a benchmark spanning entities, spatial relations, intent, affordances, functions, safety, and physical reasoning. We also present ConverSeg-Net, which fuses strong segmentation priors with language understanding, and an AI-powered data engine that generates prompt-mask pairs without human supervision. We show that current language-guided segmentation models are inadequate for CIS, while ConverSeg-Net trained on our data engine achieves significant gains on ConverSeg and maintains strong performance on existing language-guided segmentation benchmarks. Project webpage: https://glab-caltech.github.io/converseg/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13195</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 18:58:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RynnBrain: Open Embodied Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14979</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14979.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ronghao Dang, Jiayan Guo, Bohan Hou, Sicong Leng, Kehan Li, Xin Li, Jiangpin Liu, Yunxuan Mao, Zhikai Wang, Yuqian Yuan, Minghao Zhu, Xiao Lin, Yang Bai, Qian Jiang, Yaxi Zhao, Minghua Zeng, Junlong Gao, Yuming Jiang, Jun Cen, Siteng Huang, Liuyi Wang, Wenqiao Zhang, Chengju Liu, Jianfei Yang, Shijian Lu, Deli Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite rapid progress in multimodal foundation models, embodied intelligence community still lacks a unified, physically grounded foundation model that integrates perception, reasoning, and planning within real-world spatial-temporal dynamics. We introduce RynnBrain, an open-source spatiotemporal foundation model for embodied intelligence. RynnBrain strengthens four core capabilities in a unified framework: comprehensive egocentric understanding, diverse spatiotemporal localization, physically grounded reasoning, and physics-aware planning. The RynnBrain family comprises three foundation model scales (2B, 8B, and 30B-A3B MoE) and four post-trained variants tailored for downstream embodied tasks (i.e., RynnBrain-Nav, RynnBrain-Plan, and RynnBrain-VLA) or complex spatial reasoning tasks (i.e., RynnBrain-CoP). In terms of extensive evaluations on 20 embodied benchmarks and 8 general vision understanding benchmarks, our RynnBrain foundation models largely outperform existing embodied foundation models by a significant margin. The post-trained model suite further substantiates two key potentials of the RynnBrain foundation model: (i) enabling physically grounded reasoning and planning, and (ii) serving as a strong pretrained backbone that can be efficiently adapted to diverse embodied tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14979</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 18:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpargeAttention2: Trainable Sparse Attention via Hybrid Top-k+Top-p Masking and Distillation Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13515</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13515.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Kai Jiang, Chendong Xiang, Weiqi Feng, Yuezhou Hu, Haocheng Xi, Jianfei Chen, Jun Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Many training-free sparse attention methods are effective for accelerating diffusion models. Recently, several works suggest that making sparse attention trainable can further increase sparsity while preserving generation quality. We study three key questions: (1) when do the two common masking rules, i.e., Top-k and Top-p, fail, and how can we avoid these failures? (2) why can trainable sparse attention reach higher sparsity than training-free methods? (3) what are the limitations of fine-tuning sparse attention using the diffusion loss, and how can we address them? Based on this analysis, we propose SpargeAttention2, a trainable sparse attention method that achieves high sparsity without degrading generation quality. SpargeAttention2 includes (i) a hybrid masking rule that combines Top-k and Top-p for more robust masking at high sparsity, (ii) an efficient trainable sparse attention implementation, and (iii) a distillation-inspired fine-tuning objective to better preserve generation quality during fine-tuning using sparse attention. Experiments on video diffusion models show that SpargeAttention2 reaches 95% attention sparsity and a 16.2x attention speedup while maintaining generation quality, consistently outperforming prior sparse attention methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13515</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 23:01:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TactAlign: Human-to-Robot Policy Transfer via Tactile Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13579</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13579.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Youngsun Wi, Jessica Yin, Elvis Xiang, Akash Sharma, Jitendra Malik, Mustafa Mukadam, Nima Fazeli, Tess Hellebrekers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human demonstrations collected by wearable devices (e.g., tactile gloves) provide fast and dexterous supervision for policy learning, and are guided by rich, natural tactile feedback. However, a key challenge is how to transfer human-collected tactile signals to robots despite the differences in sensing modalities and embodiment. Existing human-to-robot (H2R) approaches that incorporate touch often assume identical tactile sensors, require paired data, and involve little to no embodiment gap between human demonstrator and the robots, limiting scalability and generality. We propose TactAlign, a cross-embodiment tactile alignment method that transfers human-collected tactile signals to a robot with different embodiment. TactAlign transforms human and robot tactile observations into a shared latent representation using a rectified flow, without paired datasets, manual labels, or privileged information. Our method enables low-cost latent transport guided by hand-object interaction-derived pseudo-pairs. We demonstrate that TactAlign improves H2R policy transfer across multiple contact-rich tasks (pivoting, insertion, lid closing), generalizes to unseen objects and tasks with human data (less than 5 minutes), and enables zero-shot H2R transfer on a highly dexterous tasks (light bulb screwing).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13579</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 03:31:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embed-RL: Reinforcement Learning for Reasoning-Driven Multimodal Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13823</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13823.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haonan Jiang, Yuji Wang, Yongjie Zhu, Xin Lu, Wenyu Qin, Meng Wang, Pengfei Wan, Yansong Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Leveraging Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) has become pivotal for advancing Universal Multimodal Embeddings (UME) in addressing diverse cross-modal tasks. Recent studies demonstrate that incorporating generative Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning can substantially enhance task-specific representations compared to discriminative methods. However, the generated reasoning CoTs of existing generative embedding methods are limited to the textual analysis of queries and are irrelevant to the retrieval of the targets. To address these limitations, we propose a reasoning-driven UME framework that integrates Embedder-Guided Reinforcement Learning (EG-RL) to optimize the Reasoner to produce evidential Traceability CoT (T-CoT). Our key contributions are threefold: (1) We design an EG-RL framework where the Embedder provides explicit supervision to the Reasoner, ensuring the generated CoT traces are aligned with embedding tasks. (2) We introduce T-CoT, which extracts critical multimodal cues to focus on retrieval-relevant elements and provides multimodal inputs for the Embedder. (3) With limited computational resources, our framework outperforms the pioneering embedding model on both MMEB-V2 and UVRB benchmarks. The integration of multimodal evidence in structured reasoning, paired with retrieval-oriented alignment, effectively strengthens cross-modal semantic consistency and boosts the fine-grained matching capability of the model as well as the generalization across complex scenarios. Our work demonstrates that targeted reasoning optimization can significantly improve multimodal embedding quality, providing a practical and efficient solution for reasoning-driven UME development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13823</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2026 15:35:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experiential Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13949</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.13949.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taiwei Shi, Sihao Chen, Bowen Jiang, Linxin Song, Longqi Yang, Jieyu Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning has become the central approach for language models (LMs) to learn from environmental reward or feedback. In practice, the environmental feedback is usually sparse and delayed. Learning from such signals is challenging, as LMs must implicitly infer how observed failures should translate into behavioral changes for future iterations. We introduce Experiential Reinforcement Learning (ERL), a training paradigm that embeds an explicit experience-reflection-consolidation loop into the reinforcement learning process. Given a task, the model generates an initial attempt, receives environmental feedback, and produces a reflection that guides a refined second attempt, whose success is reinforced and internalized into the base policy. This process converts feedback into structured behavioral revision, improving exploration and stabilizing optimization while preserving gains at deployment without additional inference cost. Across sparse-reward control environments and agentic reasoning benchmarks, ERL consistently improves learning efficiency and final performance over strong reinforcement learning baselines, achieving gains of up to +81% in complex multi-step environments and up to +11% in tool-using reasoning tasks. These results suggest that integrating explicit self-reflection into policy training provides a practical mechanism for transforming feedback into durable behavioral improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13949</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 01:23:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobile-Agent-v3.5: Multi-platform Fundamental GUI Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16855</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16855.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haiyang Xu, Xi Zhang, Haowei Liu, Junyang Wang, Zhaozai Zhu, Shengjie Zhou, Xuhao Hu, Feiyu Gao, Junjie Cao, Zihua Wang, Zhiyuan Chen, Jitong Liao, Qi Zheng, Jiahui Zeng, Ze Xu, Shuai Bai, Junyang Lin, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The paper introduces GUI-Owl-1.5, the latest native GUI agent model that features instruct/thinking variants in multiple sizes (2B/4B/8B/32B/235B) and supports a range of platforms (desktop, mobile, browser, and more) to enable cloud-edge collaboration and real-time interaction. GUI-Owl-1.5 achieves state-of-the-art results on more than 20+ GUI benchmarks on open-source models: (1) on GUI automation tasks, it obtains 56.5 on OSWorld, 71.6 on AndroidWorld, and 48.4 on WebArena; (2) on grounding tasks, it obtains 80.3 on ScreenSpotPro; (3) on tool-calling tasks, it obtains 47.6 on OSWorld-MCP, and 46.8 on MobileWorld; (4) on memory and knowledge tasks, it obtains 75.5 on GUI-Knowledge Bench. GUI-Owl-1.5 incorporates several key innovations: (1) Hybird Data Flywheel: we construct the data pipeline for UI understanding and trajectory generation based on a combination of simulated environments and cloud-based sandbox environments, in order to improve the efficiency and quality of data collection. (2) Unified Enhancement of Agent Capabilities: we use a unified thought-synthesis pipeline to enhance the model's reasoning capabilities, while placing particular emphasis on improving key agent abilities, including Tool/MCP use, memory and multi-agent adaptation; (3) Multi-platform Environment RL Scaling: We propose a new environment RL algorithm, MRPO, to address the challenges of multi-platform conflicts and the low training efficiency of long-horizon tasks. The GUI-Owl-1.5 models are open-sourced, and an online cloud-sandbox demo is available at https://github.com/X-PLUG/MobileAgent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16855</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 01:52:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BitDance: Scaling Autoregressive Generative Models with Binary Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14041</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14041.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuang Ai, Jiaming Han, Shaobin Zhuang, Weijia Mao, Xuefeng Hu, Ziyan Yang, Zhenheng Yang, Huaibo Huang, Xiangyu Yue, Hao Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present BitDance, a scalable autoregressive (AR) image generator that predicts binary visual tokens instead of codebook indices. With high-entropy binary latents, BitDance lets each token represent up to 2^{256} states, yielding a compact yet highly expressive discrete representation. Sampling from such a huge token space is difficult with standard classification. To resolve this, BitDance uses a binary diffusion head: instead of predicting an index with softmax, it employs continuous-space diffusion to generate the binary tokens. Furthermore, we propose next-patch diffusion, a new decoding method that predicts multiple tokens in parallel with high accuracy, greatly speeding up inference. On ImageNet 256x256, BitDance achieves an FID of 1.24, the best among AR models. With next-patch diffusion, BitDance beats state-of-the-art parallel AR models that use 1.4B parameters, while using 5.4x fewer parameters (260M) and achieving 8.7x speedup. For text-to-image generation, BitDance trains on large-scale multimodal tokens and generates high-resolution, photorealistic images efficiently, showing strong performance and favorable scaling. When generating 1024x1024 images, BitDance achieves a speedup of over 30x compared to prior AR models. We release code and models to facilitate further research on AR foundation models. Code and models are available at: https://github.com/shallowdream204/BitDance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14041</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 08:09:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empty Shelves or Lost Keys? Recall Is the Bottleneck for Parametric Factuality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14080</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14080.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nitay Calderon, Eyal Ben-David, Zorik Gekhman, Eran Ofek, Gal Yona&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Standard factuality evaluations of LLMs treat all errors alike, obscuring whether failures arise from missing knowledge (empty shelves) or from limited access to encoded facts (lost keys). We propose a behavioral framework that profiles factual knowledge at the level of facts rather than questions, characterizing each fact by whether it is encoded, and then by how accessible it is: cannot be recalled, can be directly recalled, or can only be recalled with inference-time computation (thinking). To support such profiling, we introduce WikiProfile, a new benchmark constructed via an automated pipeline with a prompted LLM grounded in web search. Across 4 million responses from 13 LLMs, we find that encoding is nearly saturated in frontier models on our benchmark, with GPT-5 and Gemini-3 encoding 95--98% of facts. However, recall remains a major bottleneck: many errors previously attributed to missing knowledge instead stem from failures to access it. These failures are systematic and disproportionately affect long-tail facts and reverse questions. Finally, we show that thinking improves recall and can recover a substantial fraction of failures, indicating that future gains may rely less on scaling and more on methods that improve how models utilize what they already encode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14080</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 10:13:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sanity Checks for Sparse Autoencoders: Do SAEs Beat Random Baselines?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14111</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14111.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anton Korznikov, Andrey Galichin, Alexey Dontsov, Oleg Rogov, Ivan Oseledets, Elena Tutubalina&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse Autoencoders (SAEs) have emerged as a promising tool for interpreting neural networks by decomposing their activations into sparse sets of human-interpretable features. Recent work has introduced multiple SAE variants and successfully scaled them to frontier models. Despite much excitement, a growing number of negative results in downstream tasks casts doubt on whether SAEs recover meaningful features. To directly investigate this, we perform two complementary evaluations. On a synthetic setup with known ground-truth features, we demonstrate that SAEs recover only 9% of true features despite achieving 71% explained variance, showing that they fail at their core task even when reconstruction is strong. To evaluate SAEs on real activations, we introduce three baselines that constrain SAE feature directions or their activation patterns to random values. Through extensive experiments across multiple SAE architectures, we show that our baselines match fully-trained SAEs in interpretability (0.87 vs 0.90), sparse probing (0.69 vs 0.72), and causal editing (0.73 vs 0.72). Together, these results suggest that SAEs in their current state do not reliably decompose models' internal mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14111</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 11:53:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LaViDa-R1: Advancing Reasoning for Unified Multimodal Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14147</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14147.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shufan Li, Yuchen Zhu, Jiuxiang Gu, Kangning Liu, Zhe Lin, Yongxin Chen, Molei Tao, Aditya Grover, Jason Kuen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion language models (dLLMs) recently emerged as a promising alternative to auto-regressive LLMs. The latest works further extended it to multimodal understanding and generation tasks. In this work, we propose LaViDa-R1, a multimodal, general-purpose reasoning dLLM. Unlike existing works that build reasoning dLLMs through task-specific reinforcement learning, LaViDa-R1 incorporates diverse multimodal understanding and generation tasks in a unified manner. In particular, LaViDa-R1 is built with a novel unified post-training framework that seamlessly integrates supervised finetuning (SFT) and multi-task reinforcement learning (RL). It employs several novel training techniques, including answer-forcing, tree search, and complementary likelihood estimation, to enhance effectiveness and scalability. Extensive experiments demonstrate LaViDa-R1's strong performance on a wide range of multimodal tasks, including visual math reasoning, reason-intensive grounding, and image editing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14147</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 13:52:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniWeTok: An Unified Binary Tokenizer with Codebook Size 2^{128} for Unified Multimodal Large Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14178</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14178.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaobin Zhuang, Yuang Ai, Jiaming Han, Weijia Mao, Xiaohui Li, Fangyikang Wang, Xiao Wang, Yan Li, Shanchuan Lin, Kun Xu, Zhenheng Yang, Huaibo Huang, Xiangyu Yue, Hao Chen, Yali Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) require a visual representation that simultaneously supports high-fidelity reconstruction, complex semantic extraction, and generative suitability. However, existing visual tokenizers typically struggle to satisfy these conflicting objectives within a single framework. In this paper, we introduce UniWeTok, a unified discrete tokenizer designed to bridge this gap using a massive binary codebook (2^{128}). For training framework, we introduce Pre-Post Distillation and a Generative-Aware Prior to enhance the semantic extraction and generative prior of the discrete tokens. In terms of model architecture, we propose a convolution-attention hybrid architecture with the SigLu activation function. SigLu activation not only bounds the encoder output and stabilizes the semantic distillation process but also effectively addresses the optimization conflict between token entropy loss and commitment loss. We further propose a three-stage training framework designed to enhance UniWeTok's adaptability cross various image resolutions and perception-sensitive scenarios, such as those involving human faces and textual content. On ImageNet, UniWeTok achieves state-of-the-art image generation performance (FID: UniWeTok 1.38 vs. REPA 1.42) while requiring a remarkably low training compute (Training Tokens: UniWeTok 33B vs. REPA 262B). On general-domain, UniWeTok demonstrates highly competitive capabilities across a broad range of tasks, including multimodal understanding, image generation (DPG Score: UniWeTok 86.63 vs. FLUX.1 [Dev] 83.84), and editing (GEdit Overall Score: UniWeTok 5.09 vs. OmniGen 5.06). We release code and models to facilitate community exploration of unified tokenizer and MLLM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14178</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 15:07:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REDSearcher: A Scalable and Cost-Efficient Framework for Long-Horizon Search Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14234</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14234.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zheng Chu, Xiao Wang, Jack Hong, Huiming Fan, Yuqi Huang, Yue Yang, Guohai Xu, Chenxiao Zhao, Cheng Xiang, Shengchao Hu, Dongdong Kuang, Ming Liu, Bing Qin, Xing Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models are transitioning from generalpurpose knowledge engines to realworld problem solvers, yet optimizing them for deep search tasks remains challenging. The central bottleneck lies in the extreme sparsity of highquality search trajectories and reward signals, arising from the difficulty of scalable longhorizon task construction and the high cost of interactionheavy rollouts involving external tool calls. To address these challenges, we propose REDSearcher, a unified framework that codesigns complex task synthesis, midtraining, and posttraining for scalable searchagent optimization. Specifically, REDSearcher introduces the following improvements: (1) We frame task synthesis as a dualconstrained optimization, where task difficulty is precisely governed by graph topology and evidence dispersion, allowing scalable generation of complex, highquality tasks. (2) We introduce toolaugmented queries to encourage proactive tool use rather than passive recall.(3) During midtraining, we strengthen core atomic capabilities knowledge, planning, and function calling substantially reducing the cost of collecting highquality trajectories for downstream training. (4) We build a local simulated environment that enables rapid, lowcost algorithmic iteration for reinforcement learning experiments. Across both textonly and multimodal searchagent benchmarks, our approach achieves stateoftheart performance. To facilitate future research on longhorizon search agents, we will release 10K highquality complex text search trajectories, 5K multimodal trajectories and 1K text RL query set, and together with code and model checkpoints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14234</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:04:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STATe-of-Thoughts: Structured Action Templates for Tree-of-Thoughts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14265</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14265.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zachary Bamberger, Till R. Saenger, Gilad Morad, Ofra Amir, Brandon M. Stewart, Amir Feder&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Inference-Time-Compute (ITC) methods like Best-of-N and Tree-of-Thoughts are meant to produce output candidates that are both high-quality and diverse, but their use of high-temperature sampling often fails to achieve meaningful output diversity. Moreover, existing ITC methods offer limited control over how to perform reasoning, which in turn limits their explainability. We present STATe-of-Thoughts (STATe), an interpretable ITC method that searches over high-level reasoning patterns. STATe replaces stochastic sampling with discrete and interpretable textual interventions: a controller selects actions encoding high-level reasoning choices, a generator produces reasoning steps conditioned on those choices, and an evaluator scores candidates to guide search. This structured approach yields three main advantages. First, action-guided textual interventions produce greater response diversity than temperature-based sampling. Second, in a case study on argument generation, STATe's explicit action sequences capture interpretable features that are highly predictive of output quality. Third, estimating the association between performance and action choices allows us to identify promising yet unexplored regions of the action space and steer generation directly toward them. Together, these results establish STATe as a practical framework for generating high-quality, diverse, and interpretable text. Our framework is available at https://github.com/zbambergerNLP/state-of-thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14265</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 18:29:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AutoWebWorld: Synthesizing Infinite Verifiable Web Environments via Finite State Machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14296</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14296.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Wu, Yiran Peng, Yiyu Chen, Jianhao Ruan, Zijie Zhuang, Cheng Yang, Jiayi Zhang, Man Chen, Yenchi Tseng, Zhaoyang Yu, Liang Chen, Yuyao Zhai, Bang Liu, Chenglin Wu, Yuyu Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The performance of autonomous Web GUI agents heavily relies on the quality and quantity of their training data. However, a fundamental bottleneck persists: collecting interaction trajectories from real-world websites is expensive and difficult to verify. The underlying state transitions are hidden, leading to reliance on inconsistent and costly external verifiers to evaluate step-level correctness. To address this, we propose AutoWebWorld, a novel framework for synthesizing controllable and verifiable web environments by modeling them as Finite State Machines (FSMs) and use coding agents to translate FSMs into interactive websites. Unlike real websites, where state transitions are implicit, AutoWebWorld explicitly defines all states, actions, and transition rules. This enables programmatic verification: action correctness is checked against predefined rules, and task success is confirmed by reaching a goal state in the FSM graph. AutoWebWorld enables a fully automated search-and-verify pipeline, generating over 11,663 verified trajectories from 29 diverse web environments at only $0.04 per trajectory. Training on this synthetic data significantly boosts real-world performance. Our 7B Web GUI agent outperforms all baselines within 15 steps on WebVoyager. Furthermore, we observe a clear scaling law: as the synthetic data volume increases, performance on WebVoyager and Online-Mind2Web consistently improves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14296</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 20:03:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Socialization Emerge in AI Agent Society? A Case Study of Moltbook</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14299</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14299.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Li, Xirui Li, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language model agents increasingly populate networked environments, a fundamental question arises: do artificial intelligence (AI) agent societies undergo convergence dynamics similar to human social systems? Lately, Moltbook approximates a plausible future scenario in which autonomous agents participate in an open-ended, continuously evolving online society. We present the first large-scale systemic diagnosis of this AI agent society. Beyond static observation, we introduce a quantitative diagnostic framework for dynamic evolution in AI agent societies, measuring semantic stabilization, lexical turnover, individual inertia, influence persistence, and collective consensus. Our analysis reveals a system in dynamic balance in Moltbook: while global semantic averages stabilize rapidly, individual agents retain high diversity and persistent lexical turnover, defying homogenization. However, agents exhibit strong individual inertia and minimal adaptive response to interaction partners, preventing mutual influence and consensus. Consequently, influence remains transient with no persistent supernodes, and the society fails to develop stable collective influence anchors due to the absence of shared social memory. These findings demonstrate that scale and interaction density alone are insufficient to induce socialization, providing actionable design and analysis principles for upcoming next-generation AI agent societies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14299</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 20:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Trajectory-Based Safety Audit of Clawdbot (OpenClaw)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14364</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14364.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Chen, Dongrui Liu, Xia Hu, Jingyi Yu, Wenjie Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Clawdbot is a self-hosted, tool-using personal AI agent with a broad action space spanning local execution and web-mediated workflows, which raises heightened safety and security concerns under ambiguity and adversarial steering. We present a trajectory-centric evaluation of Clawdbot across six risk dimensions. Our test suite samples and lightly adapts scenarios from prior agent-safety benchmarks (including ATBench and LPS-Bench) and supplements them with hand-designed cases tailored to Clawdbot's tool surface. We log complete interaction trajectories (messages, actions, tool-call arguments/outputs) and assess safety using both an automated trajectory judge (AgentDoG-Qwen3-4B) and human review. Across 34 canonical cases, we find a non-uniform safety profile: performance is generally consistent on reliability-focused tasks, while most failures arise under underspecified intent, open-ended goals, or benign-seeming jailbreak prompts, where minor misinterpretations can escalate into higher-impact tool actions. We supplemented the overall results with representative case studies and summarized the commonalities of these cases, analyzing the security vulnerabilities and typical failure modes that Clawdbot is prone to trigger in practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14364</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:33:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InnoEval: On Research Idea Evaluation as a Knowledge-Grounded, Multi-Perspective Reasoning Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14367</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14367.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuofei Qiao, Yunxiang Wei, Xuehai Wang, Bin Wu, Boyang Xue, Ningyu Zhang, Hossein A. Rahmani, Yanshan Wang, Qiang Zhang, Keyan Ding, Jeff Z. Pan, Huajun Chen, Emine Yilmaz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid evolution of Large Language Models has catalyzed a surge in scientific idea production, yet this leap has not been accompanied by a matching advance in idea evaluation. The fundamental nature of scientific evaluation needs knowledgeable grounding, collective deliberation, and multi-criteria decision-making. However, existing idea evaluation methods often suffer from narrow knowledge horizons, flattened evaluation dimensions, and the inherent bias in LLM-as-a-Judge. To address these, we regard idea evaluation as a knowledge-grounded, multi-perspective reasoning problem and introduce InnoEval, a deep innovation evaluation framework designed to emulate human-level idea assessment. We apply a heterogeneous deep knowledge search engine that retrieves and grounds dynamic evidence from diverse online sources. We further achieve review consensus with an innovation review board containing reviewers with distinct academic backgrounds, enabling a multi-dimensional decoupled evaluation across multiple metrics. We construct comprehensive datasets derived from authoritative peer-reviewed submissions to benchmark InnoEval. Experiments demonstrate that InnoEval can consistently outperform baselines in point-wise, pair-wise, and group-wise evaluation tasks, exhibiting judgment patterns and consensus highly aligned with human experts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14367</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:40:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frontier AI Risk Management Framework in Practice: A Risk Analysis Technical Report v1.5</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14457</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14457.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dongrui Liu, Yi Yu, Jie Zhang, Guanxu Chen, Qihao Lin, Hanxi Zhu, Lige Huang, Yijin Zhou, Peng Wang, Shuai Shao, Boxuan Zhang, Zicheng Liu, Jingwei Sun, Yu Li, Yuejin Xie, Jiaxuan Guo, Jia Xu, Chaochao Lu, Bowen Zhou, Xia Hu, Jing Shao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; To understand and identify the unprecedented risks posed by rapidly advancing artificial intelligence (AI) models, Frontier AI Risk Management Framework in Practice presents a comprehensive assessment of their frontier risks. As Large Language Models (LLMs) general capabilities rapidly evolve and the proliferation of agentic AI, this version of the risk analysis technical report presents an updated and granular assessment of five critical dimensions: cyber offense, persuasion and manipulation, strategic deception, uncontrolled AI R\&amp;D, and self-replication. Specifically, we introduce more complex scenarios for cyber offense. For persuasion and manipulation, we evaluate the risk of LLM-to-LLM persuasion on newly released LLMs. For strategic deception and scheming, we add the new experiment with respect to emergent misalignment. For uncontrolled AI R\&amp;D, we focus on the ``mis-evolution'' of agents as they autonomously expand their memory substrates and toolsets. Besides, we also monitor and evaluate the safety performance of OpenClaw during the interaction on the Moltbook. For self-replication, we introduce a new resource-constrained scenario. More importantly, we propose and validate a series of robust mitigation strategies to address these emerging threats, providing a preliminary technical and actionable pathway for the secure deployment of frontier AI. This work reflects our current understanding of AI frontier risks and urges collective action to mitigate these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14457</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 04:30:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Platonic Representation Hypothesis: An Aristotelian View</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14486</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14486.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fabian Gröger, Shuo Wen, Maria Brbić&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Platonic Representation Hypothesis suggests that representations from neural networks are converging to a common statistical model of reality. We show that the existing metrics used to measure representational similarity are confounded by network scale: increasing model depth or width can systematically inflate representational similarity scores. To correct these effects, we introduce a permutation-based null-calibration framework that transforms any representational similarity metric into a calibrated score with statistical guarantees. We revisit the Platonic Representation Hypothesis with our calibration framework, which reveals a nuanced picture: the apparent convergence reported by global spectral measures largely disappears after calibration, while local neighborhood similarity, but not local distances, retains significant agreement across different modalities. Based on these findings, we propose the Aristotelian Representation Hypothesis: representations in neural networks are converging to shared local neighborhood relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14486</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 06:01:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Query as Anchor: Scenario-Adaptive User Representation via Large Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14492</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14492.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiahao Yuan, Yike Xu, Jinyong Wen, Baokun Wang, Ziyi Gao, Xiaotong Lin, Yun Liu, Xing Fu, Yu Cheng, Yongchao Liu, Weiqiang Wang, Zhongle Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Industrial-scale user representation learning requires balancing robust universality with acute task-sensitivity. However, existing paradigms primarily yield static, task-agnostic embeddings that struggle to reconcile the divergent requirements of downstream scenarios within unified vector spaces. Furthermore, heterogeneous multi-source data introduces inherent noise and modality conflicts, degrading representation. We propose Query-as-Anchor, a framework shifting user modeling from static encoding to dynamic, query-aware synthesis. To empower Large Language Models (LLMs) with deep user understanding, we first construct UserU, an industrial-scale pre-training dataset that aligns multi-modal behavioral sequences with user understanding semantics, and our Q-Anchor Embedding architecture integrates hierarchical coarse-to-fine encoders into dual-tower LLMs via joint contrastive-autoregressive optimization for query-aware user representation. To bridge the gap between general pre-training and specialized business logic, we further introduce Cluster-based Soft Prompt Tuning to enforce discriminative latent structures, effectively aligning model attention with scenario-specific modalities. For deployment, anchoring queries at sequence termini enables KV-cache-accelerated inference with negligible incremental latency. Evaluations on 10 Alipay industrial benchmarks show consistent SOTA performance, strong scalability, and efficient deployment. Large-scale online A/B testing in Alipay's production system across two real-world scenarios further validates its practical effectiveness. Our code is prepared for public release and will be available at: https://github.com/JhCircle/Q-Anchor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14492</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 06:09:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty-Aware Vision-Language Segmentation for Medical Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14498</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14498.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aryan Das, Tanishq Rachamalla, Koushik Biswas, Swalpa Kumar Roy, Vinay Kumar Verma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce a novel uncertainty-aware multimodal segmentation framework that leverages both radiological images and associated clinical text for precise medical diagnosis. We propose a Modality Decoding Attention Block (MoDAB) with a lightweight State Space Mixer (SSMix) to enable efficient cross-modal fusion and long-range dependency modelling. To guide learning under ambiguity, we propose the Spectral-Entropic Uncertainty (SEU) Loss, which jointly captures spatial overlap, spectral consistency, and predictive uncertainty in a unified objective. In complex clinical circumstances with poor image quality, this formulation improves model reliability. Extensive experiments on various publicly available medical datasets, QATA-COVID19, MosMed++, and Kvasir-SEG, demonstrate that our method achieves superior segmentation performance while being significantly more computationally efficient than existing State-of-the-Art (SoTA) approaches. Our results highlight the importance of incorporating uncertainty modelling and structured modality alignment in vision-language medical segmentation tasks. Code: https://github.com/arya-domain/UA-VLS&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14498</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 06:27:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Text-Guided Convolutional Adapter for the Diffusion Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14514</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14514.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aryan Das, Koushik Biswas, Swalpa Kumar Roy, Badri Narayana Patro, Vinay Kumar Verma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce the Nexus Adapters, novel text-guided efficient adapters to the diffusion-based framework for the Structure Preserving Conditional Generation (SPCG). Recently, structure-preserving methods have achieved promising results in conditional image generation by using a base model for prompt conditioning and an adapter for structure input, such as sketches or depth maps. These approaches are highly inefficient and sometimes require equal parameters in the adapter compared to the base architecture. It is not always possible to train the model since the diffusion model is itself costly, and doubling the parameter is highly inefficient. In these approaches, the adapter is not aware of the input prompt; therefore, it is optimal only for the structural input but not for the input prompt. To overcome the above challenges, we proposed two efficient adapters, Nexus Prime and Slim, which are guided by prompts and structural inputs. Each Nexus Block incorporates cross-attention mechanisms to enable rich multimodal conditioning. Therefore, the proposed adapter has a better understanding of the input prompt while preserving the structure. We conducted extensive experiments on the proposed models and demonstrated that the Nexus Prime adapter significantly enhances performance, requiring only 8M additional parameters compared to the baseline, T2I-Adapter. Furthermore, we also introduced a lightweight Nexus Slim adapter with 18M fewer parameters than the T2I-Adapter, which still achieved state-of-the-art results. Code: https://github.com/arya-domain/Nexus-Adapters&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14514</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 06:51:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MoRL: Reinforced Reasoning for Unified Motion Understanding and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14534</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14534.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongpeng Wang, Zeyu Zhang, Wenhao Li, Hao Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human motion understanding and generation are crucial for vision and robotics but remain limited in reasoning capability and test-time planning. We propose MoRL, a unified multimodal motion model trained with supervised fine-tuning and reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards. Our task-specific reward design combines semantic alignment and reasoning coherence for understanding with physical plausibility and text-motion consistency for generation, improving both logical reasoning and perceptual realism. To further enhance inference, we introduce Chain-of-Motion (CoM), a test-time reasoning method that enables step-by-step planning and reflection. We also construct two large-scale CoT datasets, MoUnd-CoT-140K and MoGen-CoT-140K, to align motion sequences with reasoning traces and action descriptions. Experiments on HumanML3D and KIT-ML show that MoRL achieves significant gains over state-of-the-art baselines. Code: https://github.com/AIGeeksGroup/MoRL. Website: https://aigeeksgroup.github.io/MoRL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14534</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 07:42:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qute: Towards Quantum-Native Database</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14699</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14699.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muzhi Chen, Xuanhe Zhou, Wei Zhou, Bangrui Xu, Surui Tang, Guoliang Li, Bingsheng He, Yeye He, Yitong Song, Fan Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper envisions a quantum database (Qute) that treats quantum computation as a first-class execution option. Unlike prior simulation-based methods that either run quantum algorithms on classical machines or adapt existing databases for quantum simulation, Qute instead (i) compiles an extended form of SQL into gate-efficient quantum circuits, (ii) employs a hybrid optimizer to dynamically select between quantum and classical execution plans, (iii) introduces selective quantum indexing, and (iv) designs fidelity-preserving storage to mitigate current qubit constraints. We also present a three-stage evolution roadmap toward quantum-native database. Finally, by deploying Qute on a real quantum processor (origin_wukong), we show that it outperforms a classical baseline at scale, and we release an open-source prototype at https://github.com/weAIDB/Qute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14699</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 12:39:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebWorld: A Large-Scale World Model for Web Agent Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14721</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14721.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zikai Xiao, Jianhong Tu, Chuhang Zou, Yuxin Zuo, Zhi Li, Peng Wang, Bowen Yu, Fei Huang, Junyang Lin, Zuozhu Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Web agents require massive trajectories to generalize, yet real-world training is constrained by network latency, rate limits, and safety risks. We introduce WebWorld series, the first open-web simulator trained at scale. While existing simulators are restricted to closed environments with thousands of trajectories, WebWorld leverages a scalable data pipeline to train on 1M+ open-web interactions, supporting reasoning, multi-format data, and long-horizon simulations of 30+ steps. For intrinsic evaluation, we introduce WebWorld-Bench with dual metrics spanning nine dimensions, where WebWorld achieves simulation performance comparable to Gemini-3-Pro. For extrinsic evaluation, Qwen3-14B trained on WebWorld-synthesized trajectories improves by +9.2\% on WebArena, reaching performance comparable to GPT-4o. WebWorld enables effective inference-time search, outperforming GPT-5 as a world model. Beyond web simulation, WebWorld exhibits cross-domain generalization to code, GUI, and game environments, providing a replicable recipe for world model construction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14721</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 13:06:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Models for Policy Refinement in StarCraft II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14857</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14857.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yixin Zhang, Ziyi Wang, Yiming Rong, Haoxi Wang, Jinling Jiang, Shuang Xu, Haoran Wu, Shiyu Zhou, Bo Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have recently shown strong reasoning and generalization capabilities, motivating their use as decision-making policies in complex environments. StarCraft II (SC2), with its massive state-action space and partial observability, is a challenging testbed. However, existing LLM-based SC2 agents primarily focus on improving the policy itself and overlook integrating a learnable, action-conditioned transition model into the decision loop. To bridge this gap, we propose StarWM, the first world model for SC2 that predicts future observations under partial observability. To facilitate learning SC2's hybrid dynamics, we introduce a structured textual representation that factorizes observations into five semantic modules, and construct SC2-Dynamics-50k, the first instruction-tuning dataset for SC2 dynamics prediction. We further develop a multi-dimensional offline evaluation framework for predicted structured observations. Offline results show StarWM's substantial gains over zero-shot baselines, including nearly 60% improvements in resource prediction accuracy and self-side macro-situation consistency. Finally, we propose StarWM-Agent, a world-model-augmented decision system that integrates StarWM into a Generate--Simulate--Refine decision loop for foresight-driven policy refinement. Online evaluation against SC2's built-in AI demonstrates consistent improvements, yielding win-rate gains of 30%, 15%, and 30% against Hard (LV5), Harder (LV6), and VeryHard (LV7), respectively, alongside improved macro-management stability and tactical risk assessment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14857</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 15:51:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AnchorWeave: World-Consistent Video Generation with Retrieved Local Spatial Memories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14941</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.14941.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zun Wang, Han Lin, Jaehong Yoon, Jaemin Cho, Yue Zhang, Mohit Bansal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Maintaining spatial world consistency over long horizons remains a central challenge for camera-controllable video generation. Existing memory-based approaches often condition generation on globally reconstructed 3D scenes by rendering anchor videos from the reconstructed geometry in the history. However, reconstructing a global 3D scene from multiple views inevitably introduces cross-view misalignment, as pose and depth estimation errors cause the same surfaces to be reconstructed at slightly different 3D locations across views. When fused, these inconsistencies accumulate into noisy geometry that contaminates the conditioning signals and degrades generation quality. We introduce AnchorWeave, a memory-augmented video generation framework that replaces a single misaligned global memory with multiple clean local geometric memories and learns to reconcile their cross-view inconsistencies. To this end, AnchorWeave performs coverage-driven local memory retrieval aligned with the target trajectory and integrates the selected local memories through a multi-anchor weaving controller during generation. Extensive experiments demonstrate that AnchorWeave significantly improves long-term scene consistency while maintaining strong visual quality, with ablation and analysis studies further validating the effectiveness of local geometric conditioning, multi-anchor control, and coverage-driven retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14941</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 17:23:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ResearchGym: Evaluating Language Model Agents on Real-World AI Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15112</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15112.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aniketh Garikaparthi, Manasi Patwardhan, Arman Cohan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce ResearchGym, a benchmark and execution environment for evaluating AI agents on end-to-end research. To instantiate this, we repurpose five oral and spotlight papers from ICML, ICLR, and ACL. From each paper's repository, we preserve the datasets, evaluation harness, and baseline implementations but withhold the paper's proposed method. This results in five containerized task environments comprising 39 sub-tasks in total. Within each environment, agents must propose novel hypotheses, run experiments, and attempt to surpass strong human baselines on the paper's metrics. In a controlled evaluation of an agent powered by GPT-5, we observe a sharp capability--reliability gap. The agent improves over the provided baselines from the repository in just 1 of 15 evaluations (6.7%) by 11.5%, and completes only 26.5% of sub-tasks on average. We identify recurring long-horizon failure modes, including impatience, poor time and resource management, overconfidence in weak hypotheses, difficulty coordinating parallel experiments, and hard limits from context length. Yet in a single run, the agent surpasses the solution of an ICML 2025 Spotlight task, indicating that frontier agents can occasionally reach state-of-the-art performance, but do so unreliably. We additionally evaluate proprietary agent scaffolds including Claude Code (Opus-4.5) and Codex (GPT-5.2) which display a similar gap. ResearchGym provides infrastructure for systematic evaluation and analysis of autonomous agents on closed-loop research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15112</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 19:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Panini: Continual Learning in Token Space via Structured Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15156</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15156.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shreyas Rajesh, Pavan Holur, Mehmet Yigit Turali, Chenda Duan, Vwani Roychowdhury&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language models are increasingly used to reason over content they were not trained on, such as new documents, evolving knowledge, and user-specific data. A common approach is retrieval-augmented generation (RAG), which stores verbatim documents externally (as chunks) and retrieves only a relevant subset at inference time for an LLM to reason over. However, this results in inefficient usage of test-time compute (LLM repeatedly reasons over the same documents); moreover, chunk retrieval can inject irrelevant context that increases unsupported generation. We propose a human-like non-parametric continual learning framework, where the base model remains fixed, and learning occurs by integrating each new experience into an external semantic memory state that accumulates and consolidates itself continually. We present Panini, which realizes this by representing documents as Generative Semantic Workspaces (GSW) -- an entity- and event-aware network of question-answer (QA) pairs, sufficient for an LLM to reconstruct the experienced situations and mine latent knowledge via reasoning-grounded inference chains on the network. Given a query, Panini only traverses the continually-updated GSW (not the verbatim documents or chunks), and retrieves the most likely inference chains. Across six QA benchmarks, Panini achieves the highest average performance, 5%-7% higher than other competitive baselines, while using 2-30x fewer answer-context tokens, supports fully open-source pipelines, and reduces unsupported answers on curated unanswerable queries. The results show that efficient and accurate structuring of experiences at write time -- as achieved by the GSW framework -- yields both efficiency and reliability gains at read time. Code is available at https://github.com/roychowdhuryresearch/gsw-memory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15156</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 19:58:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>COMPOT: Calibration-Optimized Matrix Procrustes Orthogonalization for Transformers Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15200</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15200.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Denis Makhov, Dmitriy Shopkhoev, Magauiya Zhussip, Ammar Ali, Baher Mohammad, Stamatios Lefkimmiatis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Post-training compression of Transformer models commonly relies on truncated singular value decomposition (SVD). However, enforcing a single shared subspace can degrade accuracy even at moderate compression. Sparse dictionary learning provides a more flexible union-of-subspaces representation, but existing approaches often suffer from iterative dictionary and coefficient updates. We propose COMPOT (Calibration-Optimized Matrix Procrustes Orthogonalization for Transformers), a training-free compression framework that uses a small calibration dataset to estimate a sparse weight factorization. COMPOT employs orthogonal dictionaries that enable closed-form Procrustes updates for the dictionary and analytical single-step sparse coding for the coefficients, eliminating iterative optimization. To handle heterogeneous layer sensitivity under a global compression budget, COMPOT further introduces a one-shot dynamic allocation strategy that adaptively redistributes layer-wise compression rates. Extensive experiments across diverse architectures and tasks show that COMPOT consistently delivers a superior quality-compression trade-off over strong low-rank and sparse baselines, while remaining fully compatible with post-training quantization for extreme compression. Code is available https://github.com/mts-ai/COMPOT{here}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15200</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 21:31:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Persuasion: What Influences Decisions of Vision-Language Models?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15278</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15278.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Manuel Cherep, Pranav M R, Pattie Maes, Nikhil Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The web is littered with images, once created for human consumption and now increasingly interpreted by agents using vision-language models (VLMs). These agents make visual decisions at scale, deciding what to click, recommend, or buy. Yet, we know little about the structure of their visual preferences. We introduce a framework for studying this by placing VLMs in controlled image-based choice tasks and systematically perturbing their inputs. Our key idea is to treat the agent's decision function as a latent visual utility that can be inferred through revealed preference: choices between systematically edited images. Starting from common images, such as product photos, we propose methods for visual prompt optimization, adapting text optimization methods to iteratively propose and apply visually plausible modifications using an image generation model (such as in composition, lighting, or background). We then evaluate which edits increase selection probability. Through large-scale experiments on frontier VLMs, we demonstrate that optimized edits significantly shift choice probabilities in head-to-head comparisons. We develop an automatic interpretability pipeline to explain these preferences, identifying consistent visual themes that drive selection. We argue that this approach offers a practical and efficient way to surface visual vulnerabilities, safety concerns that might otherwise be discovered implicitly in the wild, supporting more proactive auditing and governance of image-based AI agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15278</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:33:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Surprising Effectiveness of Masking Updates in Adaptive Optimizers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15322</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15322.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taejong Joo, Wenhan Xia, Cheolmin Kim, Ming Zhang, Eugene Ie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training large language models (LLMs) relies almost exclusively on dense adaptive optimizers with increasingly sophisticated preconditioners. We challenge this by showing that randomly masking parameter updates can be highly effective, with a masked variant of RMSProp consistently outperforming recent state-of-the-art optimizers. Our analysis reveals that the random masking induces a curvature-dependent geometric regularization that smooths the optimization trajectory. Motivated by this finding, we introduce Momentum-aligned gradient masking (Magma), which modulates the masked updates using momentum-gradient alignment. Extensive LLM pre-training experiments show that Magma is a simple drop-in replacement for adaptive optimizers with consistent gains and negligible computational overhead. Notably, for the 1B model size, Magma reduces perplexity by over 19\% and 9\% compared to Adam and Muon, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15322</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 02:57:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prescriptive Scaling Reveals the Evolution of Language Model Capabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15327</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15327.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hanlin Zhang, Jikai Jin, Vasilis Syrgkanis, Sham Kakade&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; For deploying foundation models, practitioners increasingly need prescriptive scaling laws: given a pre training compute budget, what downstream accuracy is attainable with contemporary post training practice, and how stable is that mapping as the field evolves? Using large scale observational evaluations with 5k observational and 2k newly sampled data on model performance, we estimate capability boundaries, high conditional quantiles of benchmark scores as a function of log pre training FLOPs, via smoothed quantile regression with a monotone, saturating sigmoid parameterization. We validate the temporal reliability by fitting on earlier model generations and evaluating on later releases. Across various tasks, the estimated boundaries are mostly stable, with the exception of math reasoning that exhibits a consistently advancing boundary over time. We then extend our approach to analyze task dependent saturation and to probe contamination related shifts on math reasoning tasks. Finally, we introduce an efficient algorithm that recovers near full data frontiers using roughly 20% of evaluation budget. Together, our work releases the Proteus 2k, the latest model performance evaluation dataset, and introduces a practical methodology for translating compute budgets into reliable performance expectations and for monitoring when capability boundaries shift across time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15327</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 03:13:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Vision Wormhole: Latent-Space Communication in Heterogeneous Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15382</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15382.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoze Liu, Ruowang Zhang, Weichen Yu, Siheng Xiong, Liu He, Feijie Wu, Hoin Jung, Matt Fredrikson, Xiaoqian Wang, Jing Gao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-Agent Systems (MAS) powered by Large Language Models have unlocked advanced collaborative reasoning, yet they remain shackled by the inefficiency of discrete text communication, which imposes significant runtime overhead and information quantization loss. While latent state transfer offers a high-bandwidth alternative, existing approaches either assume homogeneous sender-receiver architectures or rely on pair-specific learned translators, limiting scalability and modularity across diverse model families with disjoint manifolds. In this work, we propose the Vision Wormhole, a novel framework that repurposes the visual interface of Vision-Language Models (VLMs) to enable model-agnostic, text-free communication. By introducing a Universal Visual Codec, we map heterogeneous reasoning traces into a shared continuous latent space and inject them directly into the receiver's visual pathway, effectively treating the vision encoder as a universal port for inter-agent telepathy. Our framework adopts a hub-and-spoke topology to reduce pairwise alignment complexity from O(N^2) to O(N) and leverages a label-free, teacher-student distillation objective to align the high-speed visual channel with the robust reasoning patterns of the text pathway. Extensive experiments across heterogeneous model families (e.g., Qwen-VL, Gemma) demonstrate that the Vision Wormhole reduces end-to-end wall-clock time in controlled comparisons while maintaining reasoning fidelity comparable to standard text-based MAS. Code is available at https://github.com/xz-liu/heterogeneous-latent-mas&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15382</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 06:31:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TAROT: Test-driven and Capability-adaptive Curriculum Reinforcement Fine-tuning for Code Generation with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15449</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15449.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chansung Park, Juyong Jiang, Fan Wang, Sayak Paul, Jiasi Shen, Jing Tang, Jianguo Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are changing the coding paradigm, known as vibe coding, yet synthesizing algorithmically sophisticated and robust code still remains a critical challenge. Incentivizing the deep reasoning capabilities of LLMs is essential to overcoming this hurdle. Reinforcement Fine-Tuning (RFT) has emerged as a promising strategy to address this need. However, most existing approaches overlook the heterogeneous difficulty and granularity inherent in test cases, leading to an imbalanced distribution of reward signals and consequently biased gradient updates during training. To address this, we propose Test-driven and cApability-adaptive cuRriculum reinfOrcement fine-Tuning (TAROT). TAROT systematically constructs, for each problem, a four-tier test suite (basic, intermediate, complex, edge), providing a controlled difficulty landscape for curriculum design and evaluation. Crucially, TAROT decouples curriculum progression from raw reward scores, enabling capability-conditioned evaluation and principled selection from a portfolio of curriculum policies rather than incidental test-case difficulty composition. This design fosters stable optimization and more efficient competency acquisition. Extensive experimental results reveal that the optimal curriculum for RFT in code generation is closely tied to a model's inherent capability, with less capable models achieving greater gains with an easy-to-hard progression, whereas more competent models excel under a hard-first curriculum. TAROT provides a reproducible method that adaptively tailors curriculum design to a model's capability, thereby consistently improving the functional correctness and robustness of the generated code. All code and data are released to foster reproducibility and advance community research at https://github.com/deep-diver/TAROT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15449</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 09:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>jina-embeddings-v5-text: Task-Targeted Embedding Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15547</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15547.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohammad Kalim Akram, Saba Sturua, Nastia Havriushenko, Quentin Herreros, Michael Günther, Maximilian Werk, Han Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text embedding models are widely used for semantic similarity tasks, including information retrieval, clustering, and classification. General-purpose models are typically trained with single- or multi-stage processes using contrastive loss functions. We introduce a novel training regimen that combines model distillation techniques with task-specific contrastive loss to produce compact, high-performance embedding models. Our findings suggest that this approach is more effective for training small models than purely contrastive or distillation-based training paradigms alone. Benchmark scores for the resulting models, jina-embeddings-v5-text-small and jina-embeddings-v5-text-nano, exceed or match the state-of-the-art for models of similar size. jina-embeddings-v5-text models additionally support long texts (up to 32k tokens) in many languages, and generate embeddings that remain robust under truncation and binary quantization. Model weights are publicly available, hopefully inspiring further advances in embedding model development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15547</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 12:50:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"What Are You Doing?": Effects of Intermediate Feedback from Agentic LLM In-Car Assistants During Multi-Step Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15569</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15569.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Johannes Kirmayr, Raphael Wennmacher, Khanh Huynh, Lukas Stappen, Elisabeth André, Florian Alt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic AI assistants that autonomously perform multi-step tasks raise open questions for user experience: how should such systems communicate progress and reasoning during extended operations, especially in attention-critical contexts such as driving? We investigate feedback timing and verbosity from agentic LLM-based in-car assistants through a controlled, mixed-methods study (N=45) comparing planned steps and intermediate results feedback against silent operation with final-only response. Using a dual-task paradigm with an in-car voice assistant, we found that intermediate feedback significantly improved perceived speed, trust, and user experience while reducing task load - effects that held across varying task complexities and interaction contexts. Interviews further revealed user preferences for an adaptive approach: high initial transparency to establish trust, followed by progressively reducing verbosity as systems prove reliable, with adjustments based on task stakes and situational context. We translate our empirical findings into design implications for feedback timing and verbosity in agentic assistants, balancing transparency and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15569</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 13:27:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STAPO: Stabilizing Reinforcement Learning for LLMs by Silencing Rare Spurious Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15620</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15620.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiqi Liu, Zeyu He, Guojian Zhan, Letian Tao, Zhilong Zheng, Jiang Wu, Yinuo Wang, Yang Guan, Kehua Sheng, Bo Zhang, Keqiang Li, Jingliang Duan, Shengbo Eben Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning (RL) has significantly improved large language model reasoning, but existing RL fine-tuning methods rely heavily on heuristic techniques such as entropy regularization and reweighting to maintain stability. In practice, they often experience late-stage performance collapse, leading to degraded reasoning quality and unstable training. We derive that the magnitude of token-wise policy gradients in RL is negatively correlated with token probability and local policy entropy. Building on this result, we prove that training instability is driven by a tiny fraction of tokens, approximately 0.01\%, which we term spurious tokens. When such tokens appear in correct responses, they contribute little to the reasoning outcome but inherit the full sequence-level reward, leading to abnormally amplified gradient updates. Motivated by this observation, we propose Spurious-Token-Aware Policy Optimization (STAPO) for large-scale model refining, which selectively masks such updates and renormalizes the loss over valid tokens. Across six mathematical reasoning benchmarks using Qwen 1.7B, 8B, and 14B base models, STAPO consistently demonstrates superior entropy stability and achieves an average performance improvement of 7.13\% over GRPO, 20-Entropy and JustRL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15620</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 14:46:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Action Models are Zero-shot Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15922</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15922.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seonghyeon Ye, Yunhao Ge, Kaiyuan Zheng, Shenyuan Gao, Sihyun Yu, George Kurian, Suneel Indupuru, You Liang Tan, Chuning Zhu, Jiannan Xiang, Ayaan Malik, Kyungmin Lee, William Liang, Nadun Ranawaka, Jiasheng Gu, Yinzhen Xu, Guanzhi Wang, Fengyuan Hu, Avnish Narayan, Johan Bjorck, Jing Wang, Gwanghyun Kim, Dantong Niu, Ruijie Zheng, Yuqi Xie, Jimmy Wu, Qi Wang, Ryan Julian, Danfei Xu, Yilun Du, Yevgen Chebotar, Scott Reed, Jan Kautz, Yuke Zhu, Linxi "Jim" Fan, Joel Jang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; State-of-the-art Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models excel at semantic generalization but struggle to generalize to unseen physical motions in novel environments. We introduce DreamZero, a World Action Model (WAM) built upon a pretrained video diffusion backbone. Unlike VLAs, WAMs learn physical dynamics by predicting future world states and actions, using video as a dense representation of how the world evolves. By jointly modeling video and action, DreamZero learns diverse skills effectively from heterogeneous robot data without relying on repetitive demonstrations. This results in over 2x improvement in generalization to new tasks and environments compared to state-of-the-art VLAs in real robot experiments. Crucially, through model and system optimizations, we enable a 14B autoregressive video diffusion model to perform real-time closed-loop control at 7Hz. Finally, we demonstrate two forms of cross-embodiment transfer: video-only demonstrations from other robots or humans yield a relative improvement of over 42% on unseen task performance with just 10-20 minutes of data. More surprisingly, DreamZero enables few-shot embodiment adaptation, transferring to a new embodiment with only 30 minutes of play data while retaining zero-shot generalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15922</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 15:04:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GLM-5: from Vibe Coding to Agentic Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15763</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15763.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; GLM-5 Team, Aohan Zeng, Xin Lv, Zhenyu Hou, Zhengxiao Du, Qinkai Zheng, Bin Chen, Da Yin, Chendi Ge, Chengxing Xie, Cunxiang Wang, Gengzheng Pan, Hao Zeng, Haoke Zhang, Haoran Wang, Huilong Chen, Jiajie Zhang, Jian Jiao, Jiaqi Guo, Jingsen Wang, Jingzhao Du, Jinzhu Wu, Kedong Wang, Lei Li, Lin Fan, Lucen Zhong, Mingdao Liu, Mingming Zhao, Pengfan Du, Qian Dong, Rui Lu, Shuang-Li, Shulin Cao, Song Liu, Ting Jiang, Xiaodong Chen, Xiaohan Zhang, Xuancheng Huang, Xuezhen Dong, Yabo Xu, Yao Wei, Yifan An, Yilin Niu, Yitong Zhu, Yuanhao Wen, Yukuo Cen, Yushi Bai, Zhongpei Qiao, Zihan Wang, Zikang Wang, Zilin Zhu, Ziqiang Liu, Zixuan Li, Bojie Wang, Bosi Wen, Can Huang, Changpeng Cai, Chao Yu, Chen Li, Chen Li, Chenghua Huang, Chengwei Hu, Chenhui Zhang, Chenzheng Zhu, Congfeng Yin, Daoyan Lin, Dayong Yang, Di Wang, Ding Ai, Erle Zhu, Fangzhou Yi, Feiyu Chen, Guohong Wen, Hailong Sun, Haisha Zhao, Haiyi Hu, Hanchen Zhang, Hanrui Liu, Hanyu Zhang, Hao Peng, Hao Tai, Haobo Zhang, He Liu, Hongwei Wang, Hongxi Yan, Hongyu Ge, Huan Liu, Huan Liu, Huanpeng Chu, Jia'ni Zhao, Jiachen Wang, Jiajing Zhao, Jiamin Ren, Jiapeng Wang, Jiaxin Zhang, Jiayi Gui, Jiayue Zhao, Jijie Li, Jing An, Jing Li, Jingwei Yuan, Jinhua Du, Jinxin Liu, Junkai Zhi, Junwen Duan, Kaiyue Zhou, Kangjian Wei, Ke Wang, Keyun Luo, Laiqiang Zhang, Leigang Sha, Liang Xu, Lindong Wu, Lintao Ding, Lu Chen, Minghao Li, Nianyi Lin, Pan Ta, Qiang Zou, Rongjun Song, Ruiqi Yang, Shangqing Tu, Shangtong Yang, Shaoxiang Wu, Shengyan Zhang, Shijie Li, Shuang Li, Shuyi Fan, Wei Qin, Wei Tian, Weining Zhang, Wenbo Yu, Wenjie Liang, Xiang Kuang, Xiangmeng Cheng, Xiangyang Li, Xiaoquan Yan, Xiaowei Hu, Xiaoying Ling, Xing Fan, Xingye Xia, Xinyuan Zhang, Xinze Zhang, Xirui Pan, Xunkai Zhang, Yandong Wu, Yanfu Li, Yidong Wang, Yifan Zhu, Yijun Tan, Yilin Zhou, Yiming Pan, Ying Zhang, Yinpei Su, Yipeng Geng, Yipeng Geng, Yong Yan, Yonglin Tan, Yuean Bi, Yuhan Shen, Yuhao Yang, Yujiang Li, Yunan Liu, Yunqing Wang, Yuntao Li, Yurong Wu, Yutao Zhang, Yuxi Duan, Yuxuan Zhang, Zezhen Liu, Zhengtao Jiang, Zhenhe Yan, Zheyu Zhang, Zhixiang Wei, Zhuo Chen, Zhuoer Feng, Zijun Yao, Ziwei Chai, Ziyuan Wang, Zuzhou Zhang, Bin Xu, Minlie Huang, Hongning Wang, Juanzi Li, Yuxiao Dong, Jie Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present GLM-5, a next-generation foundation model designed to transition the paradigm of vibe coding to agentic engineering. Building upon the agentic, reasoning, and coding (ARC) capabilities of its predecessor, GLM-5 adopts DSA to significantly reduce training and inference costs while maintaining long-context fidelity. To advance model alignment and autonomy, we implement a new asynchronous reinforcement learning infrastructure that drastically improves post-training efficiency by decoupling generation from training. Furthermore, we propose novel asynchronous agent RL algorithms that further improve RL quality, enabling the model to learn from complex, long-horizon interactions more effectively. Through these innovations, GLM-5 achieves state-of-the-art performance on major open benchmarks. Most critically, GLM-5 demonstrates unprecedented capability in real-world coding tasks, surpassing previous baselines in handling end-to-end software engineering challenges. Code, models, and more information are available at https://github.com/zai-org/GLM-5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15763</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:50:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding vs. Generation: Navigating Optimization Dilemma in Multimodal Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15772</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15772.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sen Ye, Mengde Xu, Shuyang Gu, Di He, Liwei Wang, Han Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current research in multimodal models faces a key challenge where enhancing generative capabilities often comes at the expense of understanding, and vice versa. We analyzed this trade-off and identify the primary cause might be the potential conflict between generation and understanding, which creates a competitive dynamic within the model. To address this, we propose the Reason-Reflect-Refine (R3) framework. This innovative algorithm re-frames the single-step generation task into a multi-step process of "generate-understand-regenerate". By explicitly leveraging the model's understanding capability during generation, we successfully mitigate the optimization dilemma, achieved stronger generation results and improved understanding ability which are related to the generation process. This offers valuable insights for designing next-generation unified multimodal models. Code is available at https://github.com/sen-ye/R3.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15772</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:04:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Memory Injection Attacks for Multi-Turn Conversations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15927</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15927.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Christian Schlarmann, Matthias Hein&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative large vision-language models (LVLMs) have recently achieved impressive performance gains, and their user base is growing rapidly. However, the security of LVLMs, in particular in a long-context multi-turn setting, is largely underexplored. In this paper, we consider the realistic scenario in which an attacker uploads a manipulated image to the web/social media. A benign user downloads this image and uses it as input to the LVLM. Our novel stealthy Visual Memory Injection (VMI) attack is designed such that on normal prompts the LVLM exhibits nominal behavior, but once the user gives a triggering prompt, the LVLM outputs a specific prescribed target message to manipulate the user, e.g. for adversarial marketing or political persuasion. Compared to previous work that focused on single-turn attacks, VMI is effective even after a long multi-turn conversation with the user. We demonstrate our attack on several recent open-weight LVLMs. This article thereby shows that large-scale manipulation of users is feasible with perturbed images in multi-turn conversation settings, calling for better robustness of LVLMs against these attacks. We release the source code at https://github.com/chs20/visual-memory-injection&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15927</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CrispEdit: Low-Curvature Projections for Scalable Non-Destructive LLM Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15823</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15823.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zarif Ikram, Arad Firouzkouhi, Stephen Tu, Mahdi Soltanolkotabi, Paria Rashidinejad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A central challenge in large language model (LLM) editing is capability preservation: methods that successfully change targeted behavior can quietly game the editing proxy and corrupt general capabilities, producing degenerate behaviors reminiscent of proxy/reward hacking. We present CrispEdit, a scalable and principled second-order editing algorithm that treats capability preservation as an explicit constraint, unifying and generalizing several existing editing approaches. CrispEdit formulates editing as constrained optimization and enforces the constraint by projecting edit updates onto the low-curvature subspace of the capability-loss landscape. At the crux of CrispEdit is expressing capability constraint via Bregman divergence, whose quadratic form yields the Gauss-Newton Hessian exactly and even when the base model is not trained to convergence. We make this second-order procedure efficient at the LLM scale using Kronecker-factored approximate curvature (K-FAC) and a novel matrix-free projector that exploits Kronecker structure to avoid constructing massive projection matrices. Across standard model-editing benchmarks, CrispEdit achieves high edit success while keeping capability degradation below 1% on average across datasets, significantly improving over prior editors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15823</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAM 3D Body: Robust Full-Body Human Mesh Recovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15989</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.15989.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xitong Yang, Devansh Kukreja, Don Pinkus, Anushka Sagar, Taosha Fan, Jinhyung Park, Soyong Shin, Jinkun Cao, Jiawei Liu, Nicolas Ugrinovic, Matt Feiszli, Jitendra Malik, Piotr Dollar, Kris Kitani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SAM 3D Body (3DB), a promptable model for single-image full-body 3D human mesh recovery (HMR) that demonstrates state-of-the-art performance, with strong generalization and consistent accuracy in diverse in-the-wild conditions. 3DB estimates the human pose of the body, feet, and hands. It is the first model to use a new parametric mesh representation, Momentum Human Rig (MHR), which decouples skeletal structure and surface shape. 3DB employs an encoder-decoder architecture and supports auxiliary prompts, including 2D keypoints and masks, enabling user-guided inference similar to the SAM family of models. We derive high-quality annotations from a multi-stage annotation pipeline that uses various combinations of manual keypoint annotation, differentiable optimization, multi-view geometry, and dense keypoint detection. Our data engine efficiently selects and processes data to ensure data diversity, collecting unusual poses and rare imaging conditions. We present a new evaluation dataset organized by pose and appearance categories, enabling nuanced analysis of model behavior. Our experiments demonstrate superior generalization and substantial improvements over prior methods in both qualitative user preference studies and traditional quantitative analysis. Both 3DB and MHR are open-source.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15989</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 20:26:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAEB: Massive Audio Embedding Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16008</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16008.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Adnan El Assadi, Isaac Chung, Chenghao Xiao, Roman Solomatin, Animesh Jha, Rahul Chand, Silky Singh, Kaitlyn Wang, Ali Sartaz Khan, Marc Moussa Nasser, Sufen Fong, Pengfei He, Alan Xiao, Ayush Sunil Munot, Aditya Shrivastava, Artem Gazizov, Niklas Muennighoff, Kenneth Enevoldsen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce the Massive Audio Embedding Benchmark (MAEB), a large-scale benchmark covering 30 tasks across speech, music, environmental sounds, and cross-modal audio-text reasoning in 100+ languages. We evaluate 50+ models and find that no single model dominates across all tasks: contrastive audio-text models excel at environmental sound classification (e.g., ESC50) but score near random on multilingual speech tasks (e.g., SIB-FLEURS), while speech-pretrained models show the opposite pattern. Clustering remains challenging for all models, with even the best-performing model achieving only modest results. We observe that models excelling on acoustic understanding often perform poorly on linguistic tasks, and vice versa. We also show that the performance of audio encoders on MAEB correlates highly with their performance when used in audio large language models. MAEB is derived from MAEB+, a collection of 98 tasks. MAEB is designed to maintain task diversity while reducing evaluation cost, and it integrates into the MTEB ecosystem for unified evaluation across text, image, and audio modalities. We release MAEB and all 98 tasks along with code and a leaderboard at https://github.com/embeddings-benchmark/mteb.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16008</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 21:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Personalized Agents from Human Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16173</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16173.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaiqu Liang, Julia Kruk, Shengyi Qian, Xianjun Yang, Shengjie Bi, Yuanshun Yao, Shaoliang Nie, Mingyang Zhang, Lijuan Liu, Jaime Fernández Fisac, Shuyan Zhou, Saghar Hosseini&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern AI agents are powerful but often fail to align with the idiosyncratic, evolving preferences of individual users. Prior approaches typically rely on static datasets, either training implicit preference models on interaction history or encoding user profiles in external memory. However, these approaches struggle with new users and with preferences that change over time. We introduce Personalized Agents from Human Feedback (PAHF), a framework for continual personalization in which agents learn online from live interaction using explicit per-user memory. PAHF operationalizes a three-step loop: (1) seeking pre-action clarification to resolve ambiguity, (2) grounding actions in preferences retrieved from memory, and (3) integrating post-action feedback to update memory when preferences drift. To evaluate this capability, we develop a four-phase protocol and two benchmarks in embodied manipulation and online shopping. These benchmarks quantify an agent's ability to learn initial preferences from scratch and subsequently adapt to persona shifts. Our theoretical analysis and empirical results show that integrating explicit memory with dual feedback channels is critical: PAHF learns substantially faster and consistently outperforms both no-memory and single-channel baselines, reducing initial personalization error and enabling rapid adaptation to preference shifts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16173</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 04:18:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-agent cooperation through in-context co-player inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16301</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16301.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marissa A. Weis, Maciej Wołczyk, Rajai Nasser, Rif A. Saurous, Blaise Agüera y Arcas, João Sacramento, Alexander Meulemans&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Achieving cooperation among self-interested agents remains a fundamental challenge in multi-agent reinforcement learning. Recent work showed that mutual cooperation can be induced between "learning-aware" agents that account for and shape the learning dynamics of their co-players. However, existing approaches typically rely on hardcoded, often inconsistent, assumptions about co-player learning rules or enforce a strict separation between "naive learners" updating on fast timescales and "meta-learners" observing these updates. Here, we demonstrate that the in-context learning capabilities of sequence models allow for co-player learning awareness without requiring hardcoded assumptions or explicit timescale separation. We show that training sequence model agents against a diverse distribution of co-players naturally induces in-context best-response strategies, effectively functioning as learning algorithms on the fast intra-episode timescale. We find that the cooperative mechanism identified in prior work-where vulnerability to extortion drives mutual shaping-emerges naturally in this setting: in-context adaptation renders agents vulnerable to extortion, and the resulting mutual pressure to shape the opponent's in-context learning dynamics resolves into the learning of cooperative behavior. Our results suggest that standard decentralized reinforcement learning on sequence models combined with co-player diversity provides a scalable path to learning cooperative behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16301</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 09:31:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NESSiE: The Necessary Safety Benchmark -- Identifying Errors that should not Exist</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16756</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16756.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Johannes Bertram, Jonas Geiping&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce NESSiE, the NEceSsary SafEty benchmark for large language models (LLMs). With minimal test cases of information and access security, NESSiE reveals safety-relevant failures that should not exist, given the low complexity of the tasks. NESSiE is intended as a lightweight, easy-to-use sanity check for language model safety and, as such, is not sufficient for guaranteeing safety in general -- but we argue that passing this test is necessary for any deployment. However, even state-of-the-art LLMs do not reach 100% on NESSiE and thus fail our necessary condition of language model safety, even in the absence of adversarial attacks. Our Safe &amp; Helpful (SH) metric allows for direct comparison of the two requirements, showing models are biased toward being helpful rather than safe. We further find that disabled reasoning for some models, but especially a benign distraction context degrade model performance. Overall, our results underscore the critical risks of deploying such models as autonomous agents in the wild. We make the dataset, package and plotting code publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16756</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 09:41:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CADEvolve: Creating Realistic CAD via Program Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Maksim Elistratov, Marina Barannikov, Gregory Ivanov, Valentin Khrulkov, Anton Konushin, Andrey Kuznetsov, Dmitrii Zhemchuzhnikov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Computer-Aided Design (CAD) delivers rapid, editable modeling for engineering and manufacturing. Recent AI progress now makes full automation feasible for various CAD tasks. However, progress is bottlenecked by data: public corpora mostly contain sketch-extrude sequences, lack complex operations, multi-operation composition and design intent, and thus hinder effective fine-tuning. Attempts to bypass this with frozen VLMs often yield simple or invalid programs due to limited 3D grounding in current foundation models. We present CADEvolve, an evolution-based pipeline and dataset that starts from simple primitives and, via VLM-guided edits and validations, incrementally grows CAD programs toward industrial-grade complexity. The result is 8k complex parts expressed as executable CadQuery parametric generators. After multi-stage post-processing and augmentation, we obtain a unified dataset of 1.3m scripts paired with rendered geometry and exercising the full CadQuery operation set. A VLM fine-tuned on CADEvolve achieves state-of-the-art results on the Image2CAD task across the DeepCAD, Fusion 360, and MCB benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16317</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 09:54:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMA: Multimodal Memory Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16493</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16493.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yihao Lu, Wanru Cheng, Zeyu Zhang, Hao Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-horizon multimodal agents depend on external memory; however, similarity-based retrieval often surfaces stale, low-credibility, or conflicting items, which can trigger overconfident errors. We propose Multimodal Memory Agent (MMA), which assigns each retrieved memory item a dynamic reliability score by combining source credibility, temporal decay, and conflict-aware network consensus, and uses this signal to reweight evidence and abstain when support is insufficient. We also introduce MMA-Bench, a programmatically generated benchmark for belief dynamics with controlled speaker reliability and structured text-vision contradictions. Using this framework, we uncover the "Visual Placebo Effect", revealing how RAG-based agents inherit latent visual biases from foundation models. On FEVER, MMA matches baseline accuracy while reducing variance by 35.2% and improving selective utility; on LoCoMo, a safety-oriented configuration improves actionable accuracy and reduces wrong answers; on MMA-Bench, MMA reaches 41.18% Type-B accuracy in Vision mode, while the baseline collapses to 0.0% under the same protocol. Code: https://github.com/AIGeeksGroup/MMA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16493</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:30:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Science of AI Agent Reliability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16666</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16666.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Stephan Rabanser, Sayash Kapoor, Peter Kirgis, Kangheng Liu, Saiteja Utpala, Arvind Narayanan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI agents are increasingly deployed to execute important tasks. While rising accuracy scores on standard benchmarks suggest rapid progress, many agents still continue to fail in practice. This discrepancy highlights a fundamental limitation of current evaluations: compressing agent behavior into a single success metric obscures critical operational flaws. Notably, it ignores whether agents behave consistently across runs, withstand perturbations, fail predictably, or have bounded error severity. Grounded in safety-critical engineering, we provide a holistic performance profile by proposing twelve concrete metrics that decompose agent reliability along four key dimensions: consistency, robustness, predictability, and safety. Evaluating 14 agentic models across two complementary benchmarks, we find that recent capability gains have only yielded small improvements in reliability. By exposing these persistent limitations, our metrics complement traditional evaluations while offering tools for reasoning about how agents perform, degrade, and fail.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16666</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:05:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Situated Awareness in the Real World</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16682</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16682.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chuhan Li, Ruilin Han, Joy Hsu, Yongyuan Liang, Rajiv Dhawan, Jiajun Wu, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Xin Eric Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A core aspect of human perception is situated awareness, the ability to relate ourselves to the surrounding physical environment and reason over possible actions in context. However, most existing benchmarks for multimodal foundation models (MFMs) emphasize environment-centric spatial relations (relations among objects in a scene), while largely overlooking observer-centric relationships that require reasoning relative to agent's viewpoint, pose, and motion. To bridge this gap, we introduce SAW-Bench (Situated Awareness in the Real World), a novel benchmark for evaluating egocentric situated awareness using real-world videos. SAW-Bench comprises 786 self-recorded videos captured with Ray-Ban Meta (Gen 2) smart glasses spanning diverse indoor and outdoor environments, and over 2,071 human-annotated question-answer pairs. It probes a model's observer-centric understanding with six different awareness tasks. Our comprehensive evaluation reveals a human-model performance gap of 37.66%, even with the best-performing MFM, Gemini 3 Flash. Beyond this gap, our in-depth analysis uncovers several notable findings; for example, while models can exploit partial geometric cues in egocentric videos, they often fail to infer a coherent camera geometry, leading to systematic spatial reasoning errors. We position SAW-Bench as a benchmark for situated spatial intelligence, moving beyond passive observation to understanding physically grounded, observer-centric dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16682</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:22:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calibrate-Then-Act: Cost-Aware Exploration in LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16699</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16699.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenxuan Ding, Nicholas Tomlin, Greg Durrett&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLMs are increasingly being used for complex problems which are not necessarily resolved in a single response, but require interacting with an environment to acquire information. In these scenarios, LLMs must reason about inherent cost-uncertainty tradeoffs in when to stop exploring and commit to an answer. For instance, on a programming task, an LLM should test a generated code snippet if it is uncertain about the correctness of that code; the cost of writing a test is nonzero, but typically lower than the cost of making a mistake. In this work, we show that we can induce LLMs to explicitly reason about balancing these cost-uncertainty tradeoffs, then perform more optimal environment exploration. We formalize multiple tasks, including information retrieval and coding, as sequential decision-making problems under uncertainty. Each problem has latent environment state that can be reasoned about via a prior which is passed to the LLM agent. We introduce a framework called Calibrate-Then-Act (CTA), where we feed the LLM this additional context to enable it to act more optimally. This improvement is preserved even under RL training of both the baseline and CTA. Our results on information-seeking QA and on a simplified coding task show that making cost-benefit tradeoffs explicit with CTA can help agents discover more optimal decision-making strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16699</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:46:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforced Fast Weights with Next-Sequence Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16704</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16704.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hee Seung Hwang, Xindi Wu, Sanghyuk Chun, Olga Russakovsky&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fast weight architectures offer a promising alternative to attention-based transformers for long-context modeling by maintaining constant memory overhead regardless of context length. However, their potential is limited by the next-token prediction (NTP) training paradigm. NTP optimizes single-token predictions and ignores semantic coherence across multiple tokens following a prefix. Consequently, fast weight models, which dynamically update their parameters to store contextual information, learn suboptimal representations that fail to capture long-range dependencies. We introduce REFINE (Reinforced Fast weIghts with Next sEquence prediction), a reinforcement learning framework that trains fast weight models under the next-sequence prediction (NSP) objective. REFINE selects informative token positions based on prediction entropy, generates multi-token rollouts, assigns self-supervised sequence-level rewards, and optimizes the model with group relative policy optimization (GRPO). REFINE is applicable throughout the training lifecycle of pre-trained language models: mid-training, post-training, and test-time training. Our experiments on LaCT-760M and DeltaNet-1.3B demonstrate that REFINE consistently outperforms supervised fine-tuning with NTP across needle-in-a-haystack retrieval, long-context question answering, and diverse tasks in LongBench. REFINE provides an effective and versatile framework for improving long-context modeling in fast weight architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16704</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:53:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Humanoid End-Effector Control for Open-Vocabulary Visual Loco-Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16705</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16705.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runpei Dong, Ziyan Li, Xialin He, Saurabh Gupta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual loco-manipulation of arbitrary objects in the wild with humanoid robots requires accurate end-effector (EE) control and a generalizable understanding of the scene via visual inputs (e.g., RGB-D images). Existing approaches are based on real-world imitation learning and exhibit limited generalization due to the difficulty in collecting large-scale training datasets. This paper presents a new paradigm, HERO, for object loco-manipulation with humanoid robots that combines the strong generalization and open-vocabulary understanding of large vision models with strong control performance from simulated training. We achieve this by designing an accurate residual-aware EE tracking policy. This EE tracking policy combines classical robotics with machine learning. It uses a) inverse kinematics to convert residual end-effector targets into reference trajectories, b) a learned neural forward model for accurate forward kinematics, c) goal adjustment, and d) replanning. Together, these innovations help us cut down the end-effector tracking error by 3.2x. We use this accurate end-effector tracker to build a modular system for loco-manipulation, where we use open-vocabulary large vision models for strong visual generalization. Our system is able to operate in diverse real-world environments, from offices to coffee shops, where the robot is able to reliably manipulate various everyday objects (e.g., mugs, apples, toys) on surfaces ranging from 43cm to 92cm in height. Systematic modular and end-to-end tests in simulation and the real world demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed design. We believe the advances in this paper can open up new ways of training humanoid robots to interact with daily objects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16705</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 18:55:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Mechanism and Dynamics of Modular Addition: Fourier Features, Lottery Ticket, and Grokking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16849</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16849.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianliang He, Leda Wang, Siyu Chen, Zhuoran Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present a comprehensive analysis of how two-layer neural networks learn features to solve the modular addition task. Our work provides a full mechanistic interpretation of the learned model and a theoretical explanation of its training dynamics. While prior work has identified that individual neurons learn single-frequency Fourier features and phase alignment, it does not fully explain how these features combine into a global solution. We bridge this gap by formalizing a diversification condition that emerges during training when overparametrized, consisting of two parts: phase symmetry and frequency diversification. We prove that these properties allow the network to collectively approximate a flawed indicator function on the correct logic for the modular addition task. While individual neurons produce noisy signals, the phase symmetry enables a majority-voting scheme that cancels out noise, allowing the network to robustly identify the correct sum. Furthermore, we explain the emergence of these features under random initialization via a lottery ticket mechanism. Our gradient flow analysis proves that frequencies compete within each neuron, with the "winner" determined by its initial spectral magnitude and phase alignment. From a technical standpoint, we provide a rigorous characterization of the layer-wise phase coupling dynamics and formalize the competitive landscape using the ODE comparison lemma. Finally, we use these insights to demystify grokking, characterizing it as a three-stage process involving memorization followed by two generalization phases, driven by the competition between loss minimization and weight decay.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16849</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 20:25:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovering Multiagent Learning Algorithms with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16928</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16928.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zun Li, John Schultz, Daniel Hennes, Marc Lanctot&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Much of the advancement of Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning (MARL) in imperfect-information games has historically depended on manual iterative refinement of baselines. While foundational families like Counterfactual Regret Minimization (CFR) and Policy Space Response Oracles (PSRO) rest on solid theoretical ground, the design of their most effective variants often relies on human intuition to navigate a vast algorithmic design space. In this work, we propose the use of AlphaEvolve, an evolutionary coding agent powered by large language models, to automatically discover new multiagent learning algorithms. We demonstrate the generality of this framework by evolving novel variants for two distinct paradigms of game-theoretic learning. First, in the domain of iterative regret minimization, we evolve the logic governing regret accumulation and policy derivation, discovering a new algorithm, Volatility-Adaptive Discounted (VAD-)CFR. VAD-CFR employs novel, non-intuitive mechanisms-including volatility-sensitive discounting, consistency-enforced optimism, and a hard warm-start policy accumulation schedule-to outperform state-of-the-art baselines like Discounted Predictive CFR+. Second, in the regime of population based training algorithms, we evolve training-time and evaluation-time meta strategy solvers for PSRO, discovering a new variant, Smoothed Hybrid Optimistic Regret (SHOR-)PSRO. SHOR-PSRO introduces a hybrid meta-solver that linearly blends Optimistic Regret Matching with a smoothed, temperature-controlled distribution over best pure strategies. By dynamically annealing this blending factor and diversity bonuses during training, the algorithm automates the transition from population diversity to rigorous equilibrium finding, yielding superior empirical convergence compared to standard static meta-solvers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16928</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 22:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DDiT: Dynamic Patch Scheduling for Efficient Diffusion Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16968</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.16968.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dahye Kim, Deepti Ghadiyaram, Raghudeep Gadde&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Transformers (DiTs) have achieved state-of-the-art performance in image and video generation, but their success comes at the cost of heavy computation. This inefficiency is largely due to the fixed tokenization process, which uses constant-sized patches throughout the entire denoising phase, regardless of the content's complexity. We propose dynamic tokenization, an efficient test-time strategy that varies patch sizes based on content complexity and the denoising timestep. Our key insight is that early timesteps only require coarser patches to model global structure, while later iterations demand finer (smaller-sized) patches to refine local details. During inference, our method dynamically reallocates patch sizes across denoising steps for image and video generation and substantially reduces cost while preserving perceptual generation quality. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach: it achieves up to 3.52times and 3.2times speedup on FLUX-1.Dev and Wan 2.1, respectively, without compromising the generation quality and prompt adherence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16968</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arcee Trinity Large Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17004</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.17004.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Varun Singh, Lucas Krauss, Sami Jaghouar, Matej Sirovatka, Charles Goddard, Fares Obied, Jack Min Ong, Jannik Straube, Fern, Aria Harley, Conner Stewart, Colin Kealty, Maziyar Panahi, Simon Kirsten, Anushka Deshpande, Anneketh Vij, Arthur Bresnu, Pranav Veldurthi, Raghav Ravishankar, Hardik Bishnoi, DatologyAI Team, Arcee AI Team, Prime Intellect Team, Mark McQuade, Johannes Hagemann, Lucas Atkins&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present the technical report for Arcee Trinity Large, a sparse Mixture-of-Experts model with 400B total parameters and 13B activated per token. Additionally, we report on Trinity Nano and Trinity Mini, with Trinity Nano having 6B total parameters with 1B activated per token, Trinity Mini having 26B total parameters with 3B activated per token. The models' modern architecture includes interleaved local and global attention, gated attention, depth-scaled sandwich norm, and sigmoid routing for Mixture-of-Experts. For Trinity Large, we also introduce a new MoE load balancing strategy titled Soft-clamped Momentum Expert Bias Updates (SMEBU). We train the models using the Muon optimizer. All three models completed training with zero loss spikes. Trinity Nano and Trinity Mini were pre-trained on 10 trillion tokens, and Trinity Large was pre-trained on 17 trillion tokens. The model checkpoints are available at https://huggingface.co/arcee-ai.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17004</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 01:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FRAPPE: Infusing World Modeling into Generalist Policies via Multiple Future Representation Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17259</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.17259.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Han Zhao, Jingbo Wang, Wenxuan Song, Shuai Chen, Yang Liu, Yan Wang, Haoang Li, Donglin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Enabling VLA models to predict environmental dynamics, known as world modeling, has been recognized as essential for improving robotic reasoning and generalization. However, current approaches face two main issues: 1. The training objective forces models to over-emphasize pixel-level reconstruction, which constrains semantic learning and generalization 2. Reliance on predicted future observations during inference often leads to error accumulation. To address these challenges, we introduce Future Representation Alignment via Parallel Progressive Expansion (FRAPPE). Our method adopts a two-stage fine-tuning strategy: In the mid-training phase, the model learns to predict the latent representations of future observations; In the post-training phase, we expand the computational workload in parallel and align the representation simultaneously with multiple different visual foundation models. By significantly improving fine-tuning efficiency and reducing dependence on action-annotated data, FRAPPE provides a scalable and data-efficient pathway to enhance world-awareness in generalist robotic policies. Experiments on the RoboTwin benchmark and real-world tasks demonstrate that FRAPPE outperforms state-of-the-art approaches and shows strong generalization in long-horizon and unseen scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17259</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 11:00:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Latents (UL): How to train your latents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17270</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.17270.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jonathan Heek, Emiel Hoogeboom, Thomas Mensink, Tim Salimans&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Unified Latents (UL), a framework for learning latent representations that are jointly regularized by a diffusion prior and decoded by a diffusion model. By linking the encoder's output noise to the prior's minimum noise level, we obtain a simple training objective that provides a tight upper bound on the latent bitrate. On ImageNet-512, our approach achieves competitive FID of 1.4, with high reconstruction quality (PSNR) while requiring fewer training FLOPs than models trained on Stable Diffusion latents. On Kinetics-600, we set a new state-of-the-art FVD of 1.3.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17270</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 11:18:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ArXiv-to-Model: A Practical Study of Scientific LM Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17288</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.17288.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anuj Gupta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While frontier large language models demonstrate strong reasoning and mathematical capabilities, the practical process of training domain-specialized scientific language models from raw sources remains under-documented. In this work, we present a detailed case study of training a 1.36B-parameter scientific language model directly from raw arXiv LaTeX sources spanning mathematics, computer science, and theoretical physics. We describe an end-to-end pipeline covering metadata filtering, archive validation, LaTeX extraction, text normalization, domain-aware tokenization, and dense transformer training under constrained compute (2xA100 GPUs). Through 24 experimental runs, we analyze training stability, scaling behavior, data yield losses, and infrastructure bottlenecks. Our findings highlight how preprocessing decisions significantly affect usable token volume, how tokenization impacts symbolic stability, and how storage and I/O constraints can rival compute as limiting factors. We further analyze convergence dynamics and show stable training behavior in a data-rich regime (52B pretraining tokens). Rather than proposing a novel architecture, this work provides an engineering-grounded, transparent account of training a small scientific language model from scratch. We hope these insights support researchers operating under moderate compute budgets who seek to build domain-specialized models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17288</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 11:47:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2Mamba2Furious: Linear in Complexity, Competitive in Accuracy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17363</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.17363.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gabriel Mongaras, Eric C. Larson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Linear attention transformers have become a strong alternative to softmax attention due to their efficiency. However, linear attention tends to be less expressive and results in reduced accuracy compared to softmax attention. To bridge the accuracy gap between softmax attention and linear attention, we manipulate Mamba-2, a very strong linear attention variant. We first simplify Mamba-2 down to its most fundamental and important components, evaluating which specific choices make it most accurate. From this simplified Mamba variant (Mamba-2S), we improve the A-mask and increase the order of the hidden state, resulting in a method, which we call 2Mamba, that is nearly as accurate as softmax attention, yet much more memory efficient for long context lengths. We also investigate elements to Mamba-2 that help surpass softmax attention accuracy. Code is provided for all our experiments&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17363</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:45:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computer-Using World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17365</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.17365.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiming Guan, Rui Yu, John Zhang, Lu Wang, Chaoyun Zhang, Liqun Li, Bo Qiao, Si Qin, He Huang, Fangkai Yang, Pu Zhao, Lukas Wutschitz, Samuel Kessler, Huseyin A Inan, Robert Sim, Saravan Rajmohan, Qingwei Lin, Dongmei Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agents operating in complex software environments benefit from reasoning about the consequences of their actions, as even a single incorrect user interface (UI) operation can derail long, artifact-preserving workflows. This challenge is particularly acute for computer-using scenarios, where real execution does not support counterfactual exploration, making large-scale trial-and-error learning and planning impractical despite the environment being fully digital and deterministic. We introduce the Computer-Using World Model (CUWM), a world model for desktop software that predicts the next UI state given the current state and a candidate action. CUWM adopts a two-stage factorization of UI dynamics: it first predicts a textual description of agent-relevant state changes, and then realizes these changes visually to synthesize the next screenshot. CUWM is trained on offline UI transitions collected from agents interacting with real Microsoft Office applications, and further refined with a lightweight reinforcement learning stage that aligns textual transition predictions with the structural requirements of computer-using environments. We evaluate CUWM via test-time action search, where a frozen agent uses the world model to simulate and compare candidate actions before execution. Across a range of Office tasks, world-model-guided test-time scaling improves decision quality and execution robustness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17365</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Distinct Human Interaction in Web Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17588</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.17588.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Faria Huq, Zora Zhiruo Wang, Zhanqiu Guo, Venu Arvind Arangarajan, Tianyue Ou, Frank Xu, Shuyan Zhou, Graham Neubig, Jeffrey P. Bigham&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite rapid progress in autonomous web agents, human involvement remains essential for shaping preferences and correcting agent behavior as tasks unfold. However, current agentic systems lack a principled understanding of when and why humans intervene, often proceeding autonomously past critical decision points or requesting unnecessary confirmation. In this work, we introduce the task of modeling human intervention to support collaborative web task execution. We collect CowCorpus, a dataset of 400 real-user web navigation trajectories containing over 4,200 interleaved human and agent actions. We identify four distinct patterns of user interaction with agents -- hands-off supervision, hands-on oversight, collaborative task-solving, and full user takeover. Leveraging these insights, we train language models (LMs) to anticipate when users are likely to intervene based on their interaction styles, yielding a 61.4-63.4% improvement in intervention prediction accuracy over base LMs. Finally, we deploy these intervention-aware models in live web navigation agents and evaluate them in a user study, finding a 26.5% increase in user-rated agent usefulness. Together, our results show structured modeling of human intervention leads to more adaptive, collaborative agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.17588</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 18:11:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
