<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:13:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>TokenHSI: Unified Synthesis of Physical Human-Scene Interactions through   Task Tokenization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19901</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.19901.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liang Pan, Zeshi Yang, Zhiyang Dou, Wenjia Wang, Buzhen Huang, Bo Dai, Taku Komura, Jingbo Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Synthesizing diverse and physically plausible Human-Scene Interactions (HSI) is pivotal for both computer animation and embodied AI. Despite encouraging progress, current methods mainly focus on developing separate controllers, each specialized for a specific interaction task. This significantly hinders the ability to tackle a wide variety of challenging HSI tasks that require the integration of multiple skills, e.g., sitting down while carrying an object. To address this issue, we present TokenHSI, a single, unified transformer-based policy capable of multi-skill unification and flexible adaptation. The key insight is to model the humanoid proprioception as a separate shared token and combine it with distinct task tokens via a masking mechanism. Such a unified policy enables effective knowledge sharing across skills, thereby facilitating the multi-task training. Moreover, our policy architecture supports variable length inputs, enabling flexible adaptation of learned skills to new scenarios. By training additional task tokenizers, we can not only modify the geometries of interaction targets but also coordinate multiple skills to address complex tasks. The experiments demonstrate that our approach can significantly improve versatility, adaptability, and extensibility in various HSI tasks. Website: https://liangpan99.github.io/TokenHSI/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19901</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 17:57:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding R1-Zero-Like Training: A Critical Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20783</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.20783.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zichen Liu, Changyu Chen, Wenjun Li, Penghui Qi, Tianyu Pang, Chao Du, Wee Sun Lee, Min Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; DeepSeek-R1-Zero has shown that reinforcement learning (RL) at scale can directly enhance the reasoning capabilities of LLMs without supervised fine-tuning. In this work, we critically examine R1-Zero-like training by analyzing its two core components: base models and RL. We investigate a wide range of base models, including DeepSeek-V3-Base, to understand how pretraining characteristics influence RL performance. Our analysis reveals that DeepSeek-V3-Base already exhibit ''Aha moment'', while Qwen2.5 base models demonstrate strong reasoning capabilities even without prompt templates, suggesting potential pretraining biases. Additionally, we identify an optimization bias in Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), which artificially increases response length (especially for incorrect outputs) during training. To address this, we introduce Dr. GRPO, an unbiased optimization method that improves token efficiency while maintaining reasoning performance. Leveraging these insights, we present a minimalist R1-Zero recipe that achieves 43.3% accuracy on AIME 2024 with a 7B base model, establishing a new state-of-the-art. Our code is available at https://github.com/sail-sg/understand-r1-zero.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20783</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 17:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unicorn: Text-Only Data Synthesis for Vision Language Model Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22655</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.22655.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaomin Yu, Pengxiang Ding, Wenjie Zhang, Siteng Huang, Songyang Gao, Chengwei Qin, Kejian Wu, Zhaoxin Fan, Ziyue Qiao, Donglin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training vision-language models (VLMs) typically requires large-scale, high-quality image-text pairs, but collecting or synthesizing such data is costly. In contrast, text data is abundant and inexpensive, prompting the question: can high-quality multimodal training data be synthesized purely from text? To tackle this, we propose a cross-integrated three-stage multimodal data synthesis framework, which generates two datasets: Unicorn-1.2M and Unicorn-471K-Instruction. In Stage 1: Diverse Caption Data Synthesis, we construct 1.2M semantically diverse high-quality captions by expanding sparse caption seeds using large language models (LLMs). In Stage 2: Instruction-Tuning Data Generation, we further process 471K captions into multi-turn instruction-tuning tasks to support complex reasoning. Finally, in Stage 3: Modality Representation Transfer, these textual captions representations are transformed into visual representations, resulting in diverse synthetic image representations. This three-stage process enables us to construct Unicorn-1.2M for pretraining and Unicorn-471K-Instruction for instruction-tuning, without relying on real images. By eliminating the dependency on real images while maintaining data quality and diversity, our framework offers a cost-effective and scalable solution for VLMs training. Code is available at https://github.com/Yu-xm/Unicorn.git.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22655</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 17:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Inference for Large Reasoning Models: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23077</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.23077.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yue Liu, Jiaying Wu, Yufei He, Hongcheng Gao, Hongyu Chen, Baolong Bi, Jiaheng Zhang, Zhiqi Huang, Bryan Hooi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) significantly improve the reasoning ability of Large Language Models (LLMs) by learning to reason, exhibiting promising performance in complex task-solving. However, their deliberative reasoning process leads to inefficiencies in token usage, memory consumption, and inference time. Thus, this survey provides a review of efficient inference methods designed specifically for LRMs, focusing on mitigating token inefficiency while preserving the reasoning quality. First, we introduce a taxonomy to group the recent methods into two main categories: (a) explicit compact Chain-of-Thought (CoT), which reduces tokens while keeping the explicit reasoning structure, and (b) implicit latent CoT, which encodes reasoning steps within hidden representations instead of explicit tokens. Meanwhile, we discuss their strengths and weaknesses. Then, we conduct empirical analyses on existing methods from performance and efficiency aspects. Besides, we present open challenges in this field, including human-centric controllable reasoning, trade-off between interpretability and efficiency of reasoning, ensuring safety of efficient reasoning, and broader applications of efficient reasoning. In addition, we highlight key insights for enhancing LRMs' inference efficiency via techniques such as model merging, new architectures, and agent routers. We hope this work serves as a valuable guide, helping researchers overcome challenges in this vibrant fieldhttps://github.com/yueliu1999/Awesome-Efficient-Inference-for-LRMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23077</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 13:27:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CodeARC: Benchmarking Reasoning Capabilities of LLM Agents for Inductive   Program Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23145</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.23145.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anjiang Wei, Tarun Suresh, Jiannan Cao, Naveen Kannan, Yuheng Wu, Kai Yan, Thiago S. F. X. Teixeira, Ke Wang, Alex Aiken&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Inductive program synthesis, or programming by example, requires synthesizing functions from input-output examples that generalize to unseen inputs. While large language model agents have shown promise in programming tasks guided by natural language, their ability to perform inductive program synthesis is underexplored. Existing evaluation protocols rely on static sets of examples and held-out tests, offering no feedback when synthesized functions are incorrect and failing to reflect real-world scenarios such as reverse engineering. We propose CodeARC, the Code Abstraction and Reasoning Challenge, a new evaluation framework where agents interact with a hidden target function by querying it with new inputs, synthesizing candidate functions, and iteratively refining their solutions using a differential testing oracle. This interactive setting encourages agents to perform function calls and self-correction based on feedback. We construct the first large-scale benchmark for general-purpose inductive program synthesis, featuring 1114 functions. Among 18 models evaluated, o3-mini performs best with a success rate of 52.7%, highlighting the difficulty of this task. Fine-tuning LLaMA-3.1-8B-Instruct on curated synthesis traces yields up to a 31% relative performance gain. CodeARC provides a more realistic and challenging testbed for evaluating LLM-based program synthesis and inductive reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23145</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 16:50:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MoCha: Towards Movie-Grade Talking Character Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23307</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.23307.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cong Wei, Bo Sun, Haoyu Ma, Ji Hou, Felix Juefei-Xu, Zecheng He, Xiaoliang Dai, Luxin Zhang, Kunpeng Li, Tingbo Hou, Animesh Sinha, Peter Vajda, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 131&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in video generation have achieved impressive motion realism, yet they often overlook character-driven storytelling, a crucial task for automated film, animation generation. We introduce Talking Characters, a more realistic task to generate talking character animations directly from speech and text. Unlike talking head, Talking Characters aims at generating the full portrait of one or more characters beyond the facial region. In this paper, we propose MoCha, the first of its kind to generate talking characters. To ensure precise synchronization between video and speech, we propose a speech-video window attention mechanism that effectively aligns speech and video tokens. To address the scarcity of large-scale speech-labeled video datasets, we introduce a joint training strategy that leverages both speech-labeled and text-labeled video data, significantly improving generalization across diverse character actions. We also design structured prompt templates with character tags, enabling, for the first time, multi-character conversation with turn-based dialogue-allowing AI-generated characters to engage in context-aware conversations with cinematic coherence. Extensive qualitative and quantitative evaluations, including human preference studies and benchmark comparisons, demonstrate that MoCha sets a new standard for AI-generated cinematic storytelling, achieving superior realism, expressiveness, controllability and generalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23307</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 04:22:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Physically Plausible Video Generation via VLM Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23368</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.23368.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xindi Yang, Baolu Li, Yiming Zhang, Zhenfei Yin, Lei Bai, Liqian Ma, Zhiyong Wang, Jianfei Cai, Tien-Tsin Wong, Huchuan Lu, Xu Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video diffusion models (VDMs) have advanced significantly in recent years, enabling the generation of highly realistic videos and drawing the attention of the community in their potential as world simulators. However, despite their capabilities, VDMs often fail to produce physically plausible videos due to an inherent lack of understanding of physics, resulting in incorrect dynamics and event sequences. To address this limitation, we propose a novel two-stage image-to-video generation framework that explicitly incorporates physics. In the first stage, we employ a Vision Language Model (VLM) as a coarse-grained motion planner, integrating chain-of-thought and physics-aware reasoning to predict a rough motion trajectories/changes that approximate real-world physical dynamics while ensuring the inter-frame consistency. In the second stage, we use the predicted motion trajectories/changes to guide the video generation of a VDM. As the predicted motion trajectories/changes are rough, noise is added during inference to provide freedom to the VDM in generating motion with more fine details. Extensive experimental results demonstrate that our framework can produce physically plausible motion, and comparative evaluations highlight the notable superiority of our approach over existing methods. More video results are available on our Project Page: https://madaoer.github.io/projects/physically_plausible_video_generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23368</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 09:03:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JavisDiT: Joint Audio-Video Diffusion Transformer with Hierarchical   Spatio-Temporal Prior Synchronization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23377</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.23377.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kai Liu, Wei Li, Lai Chen, Shengqiong Wu, Yanhao Zheng, Jiayi Ji, Fan Zhou, Rongxin Jiang, Jiebo Luo, Hao Fei, Tat-Seng Chua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces JavisDiT, a novel Joint Audio-Video Diffusion Transformer designed for synchronized audio-video generation (JAVG). Built upon the powerful Diffusion Transformer (DiT) architecture, JavisDiT is able to generate high-quality audio and video content simultaneously from open-ended user prompts. To ensure optimal synchronization, we introduce a fine-grained spatio-temporal alignment mechanism through a Hierarchical Spatial-Temporal Synchronized Prior (HiST-Sypo) Estimator. This module extracts both global and fine-grained spatio-temporal priors, guiding the synchronization between the visual and auditory components. Furthermore, we propose a new benchmark, JavisBench, consisting of 10,140 high-quality text-captioned sounding videos spanning diverse scenes and complex real-world scenarios. Further, we specifically devise a robust metric for evaluating the synchronization between generated audio-video pairs in real-world complex content. Experimental results demonstrate that JavisDiT significantly outperforms existing methods by ensuring both high-quality generation and precise synchronization, setting a new standard for JAVG tasks. Our code, model, and dataset will be made publicly available at https://javisdit.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23377</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 09:40:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TextCrafter: Accurately Rendering Multiple Texts in Complex Visual   Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23461</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.23461.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nikai Du, Zhennan Chen, Zhizhou Chen, Shan Gao, Xi Chen, Zhengkai Jiang, Jian Yang, Ying Tai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 95&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper explores the task of Complex Visual Text Generation (CVTG), which centers on generating intricate textual content distributed across diverse regions within visual images. In CVTG, image generation models often rendering distorted and blurred visual text or missing some visual text. To tackle these challenges, we propose TextCrafter, a novel multi-visual text rendering method. TextCrafter employs a progressive strategy to decompose complex visual text into distinct components while ensuring robust alignment between textual content and its visual carrier. Additionally, it incorporates a token focus enhancement mechanism to amplify the prominence of visual text during the generation process. TextCrafter effectively addresses key challenges in CVTG tasks, such as text confusion, omissions, and blurriness. Moreover, we present a new benchmark dataset, CVTG-2K, tailored to rigorously evaluate the performance of generative models on CVTG tasks. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method surpasses state-of-the-art approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23461</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 14:36:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JudgeLRM: Large Reasoning Models as a Judge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00050</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.00050.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nuo Chen, Zhiyuan Hu, Qingyun Zou, Jiaying Wu, Qian Wang, Bryan Hooi, Bingsheng He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rise of Large Language Models (LLMs) as evaluators offers a scalable alternative to human annotation, yet existing Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) for judges approaches often fall short in domains requiring complex reasoning. In this work, we investigate whether LLM judges truly benefit from enhanced reasoning capabilities. Through a detailed analysis of reasoning requirements across evaluation tasks, we reveal a negative correlation between SFT performance gains and the proportion of reasoning-demanding samples - highlighting the limitations of SFT in such scenarios. To address this, we introduce JudgeLRM, a family of judgment-oriented LLMs trained using reinforcement learning (RL) with judge-wise, outcome-driven rewards. JudgeLRM models consistently outperform both SFT-tuned and state-of-the-art reasoning models. Notably, JudgeLRM-3B surpasses GPT-4, and JudgeLRM-7B outperforms DeepSeek-R1 by 2.79% in F1 score, particularly excelling in judge tasks requiring deep reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00050</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 02:18:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What, How, Where, and How Well? A Survey on Test-Time Scaling in Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24235</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.24235.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qiyuan Zhang, Fuyuan Lyu, Zexu Sun, Lei Wang, Weixu Zhang, Zhihan Guo, Yufei Wang, Irwin King, Xue Liu, Chen Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As enthusiasm for scaling computation (data and parameters) in the pretraining era gradually diminished, test-time scaling (TTS), also referred to as ``test-time computing'' has emerged as a prominent research focus. Recent studies demonstrate that TTS can further elicit the problem-solving capabilities of large language models (LLMs), enabling significant breakthroughs not only in specialized reasoning tasks, such as mathematics and coding, but also in general tasks like open-ended Q&amp;A. However, despite the explosion of recent efforts in this area, there remains an urgent need for a comprehensive survey offering a systemic understanding. To fill this gap, we propose a unified, multidimensional framework structured along four core dimensions of TTS research: what to scale, how to scale, where to scale, and how well to scale. Building upon this taxonomy, we conduct an extensive review of methods, application scenarios, and assessment aspects, and present an organized decomposition that highlights the unique functional roles of individual techniques within the broader TTS landscape. From this analysis, we distill the major developmental trajectories of TTS to date and offer hands-on guidelines for practical deployment. Furthermore, we identify several open challenges and offer insights into promising future directions, including further scaling, clarifying the functional essence of techniques, generalizing to more tasks, and more attributions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24235</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 15:46:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open-Reasoner-Zero: An Open Source Approach to Scaling Up Reinforcement   Learning on the Base Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24290</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.24290.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingcheng Hu, Yinmin Zhang, Qi Han, Daxin Jiang, Xiangyu Zhang, Heung-Yeung Shum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Open-Reasoner-Zero, the first open source implementation of large-scale reasoning-oriented RL training focusing on scalability, simplicity and accessibility. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate that a minimalist approach, vanilla PPO with GAE (lambda=1, gamma=1) and straightforward rule-based rewards, without any KL regularization, is sufficient to scale up both response length and benchmark performance, similar to the phenomenon observed in DeepSeek-R1-Zero. Using the same base model as DeepSeek-R1-Zero-Qwen-32B, our implementation achieves superior performance on AIME2024, MATH500, and the GPQA Diamond benchmark while demonstrating remarkable efficiency -- requiring only a tenth of the training steps, compared to DeepSeek-R1-Zero pipeline. In the spirit of open source, we release our source code, parameter settings, training data, and model weights across various sizes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24290</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 16:36:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Effect of Reinforcement Learning on Video Understanding:   Insights from SEED-Bench-R1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24376</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.24376.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Chen, Yuying Ge, Rui Wang, Yixiao Ge, Lu Qiu, Ying Shan, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in Chain of Thought (COT) generation have significantly improved the reasoning capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs), with reinforcement learning (RL) emerging as an effective post-training approach. Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) inherit this reasoning potential but remain underexplored in tasks requiring both perception and logical reasoning. To address this, we introduce SEED-Bench-R1, a benchmark designed to systematically evaluate post-training methods for MLLMs in video understanding. It includes intricate real-world videos and complex everyday planning tasks in the format of multiple-choice questions, requiring sophisticated perception and reasoning. SEED-Bench-R1 assesses generalization through a three-level hierarchy: in-distribution, cross-environment, and cross-environment-task scenarios, equipped with a large-scale training dataset with easily verifiable ground-truth answers. Using Qwen2-VL-Instruct-7B as a base model, we compare RL with supervised fine-tuning (SFT), demonstrating RL's data efficiency and superior performance on both in-distribution and out-of-distribution tasks, even outperforming SFT on general video understanding benchmarks like LongVideoBench. Our detailed analysis reveals that RL enhances visual perception but often produces less logically coherent reasoning chains. We identify key limitations such as inconsistent reasoning and overlooked visual cues, and suggest future improvements in base model reasoning, reward modeling, and RL robustness against noisy signals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24376</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 17:55:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Any2Caption:Interpreting Any Condition to Caption for Controllable Video   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24379</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2503.24379.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengqiong Wu, Weicai Ye, Jiahao Wang, Quande Liu, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Kun Gai, Shuicheng Yan, Hao Fei, Tat-Seng Chua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 76&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; To address the bottleneck of accurate user intent interpretation within the current video generation community, we present Any2Caption, a novel framework for controllable video generation under any condition. The key idea is to decouple various condition interpretation steps from the video synthesis step. By leveraging modern multimodal large language models (MLLMs), Any2Caption interprets diverse inputs--text, images, videos, and specialized cues such as region, motion, and camera poses--into dense, structured captions that offer backbone video generators with better guidance. We also introduce Any2CapIns, a large-scale dataset with 337K instances and 407K conditions for any-condition-to-caption instruction tuning. Comprehensive evaluations demonstrate significant improvements of our system in controllability and video quality across various aspects of existing video generation models. Project Page: https://sqwu.top/Any2Cap/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24379</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 17:59:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advances and Challenges in Foundation Agents: From Brain-Inspired   Intelligence to Evolutionary, Collaborative, and Safe Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01990</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.01990.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bang Liu, Xinfeng Li, Jiayi Zhang, Jinlin Wang, Tanjin He, Sirui Hong, Hongzhang Liu, Shaokun Zhang, Kaitao Song, Kunlun Zhu, Yuheng Cheng, Suyuchen Wang, Xiaoqiang Wang, Yuyu Luo, Haibo Jin, Peiyan Zhang, Ollie Liu, Jiaqi Chen, Huan Zhang, Zhaoyang Yu, Haochen Shi, Boyan Li, Dekun Wu, Fengwei Teng, Xiaojun Jia, Jiawei Xu, Jinyu Xiang, Yizhang Lin, Tianming Liu, Tongliang Liu, Yu Su, Huan Sun, Glen Berseth, Jianyun Nie, Ian Foster, Logan Ward, Qingyun Wu, Yu Gu, Mingchen Zhuge, Xiangru Tang, Haohan Wang, Jiaxuan You, Chi Wang, Jian Pei, Qiang Yang, Xiaoliang Qi, Chenglin Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 271&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The advent of large language models (LLMs) has catalyzed a transformative shift in artificial intelligence, paving the way for advanced intelligent agents capable of sophisticated reasoning, robust perception, and versatile action across diverse domains. As these agents increasingly drive AI research and practical applications, their design, evaluation, and continuous improvement present intricate, multifaceted challenges. This survey provides a comprehensive overview, framing intelligent agents within a modular, brain-inspired architecture that integrates principles from cognitive science, neuroscience, and computational research. We structure our exploration into four interconnected parts. First, we delve into the modular foundation of intelligent agents, systematically mapping their cognitive, perceptual, and operational modules onto analogous human brain functionalities, and elucidating core components such as memory, world modeling, reward processing, and emotion-like systems. Second, we discuss self-enhancement and adaptive evolution mechanisms, exploring how agents autonomously refine their capabilities, adapt to dynamic environments, and achieve continual learning through automated optimization paradigms, including emerging AutoML and LLM-driven optimization strategies. Third, we examine collaborative and evolutionary multi-agent systems, investigating the collective intelligence emerging from agent interactions, cooperation, and societal structures, highlighting parallels to human social dynamics. Finally, we address the critical imperative of building safe, secure, and beneficial AI systems, emphasizing intrinsic and extrinsic security threats, ethical alignment, robustness, and practical mitigation strategies necessary for trustworthy real-world deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01990</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 18:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open-Qwen2VL: Compute-Efficient Pre-Training of Fully-Open Multimodal   LLMs on Academic Resources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00595</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.00595.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weizhi Wang, Yu Tian, Linjie Yang, Heng Wang, Xifeng Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The reproduction of state-of-the-art multimodal LLM pre-training faces barriers at every stage of the pipeline, including high-quality data filtering, multimodal data mixture strategies, sequence packing techniques, and training frameworks. We introduce Open-Qwen2VL, a fully open-source 2B-parameter Multimodal Large Language Model pre-trained efficiently on 29M image-text pairs using only 442 A100-40G GPU hours. Our approach employs low-to-high dynamic image resolution and multimodal sequence packing to significantly enhance pre-training efficiency. The training dataset was carefully curated using both MLLM-based filtering techniques (e.g., MLM-Filter) and conventional CLIP-based filtering methods, substantially improving data quality and training efficiency. The Open-Qwen2VL pre-training is conducted on academic level 8xA100-40G GPUs at UCSB on 5B packed multimodal tokens, which is 0.36\% of 1.4T multimodal pre-training tokens of Qwen2-VL. The final instruction-tuned Open-Qwen2VL outperforms partially-open state-of-the-art MLLM Qwen2-VL-2B on various multimodal benchmarks of MMBench, SEEDBench, MMstar, and MathVista, indicating the remarkable training efficiency of Open-Qwen2VL. We open-source all aspects of our work, including compute-efficient and data-efficient training details, data filtering methods, sequence packing scripts, pre-training data in WebDataset format, FSDP-based training codebase, and both base and instruction-tuned model checkpoints. We redefine "fully open" for multimodal LLMs as the complete release of: 1) the training codebase, 2) detailed data filtering techniques, and 3) all pre-training and supervised fine-tuning data used to develop the model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00595</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 09:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ScholarCopilot: Training Large Language Models for Academic Writing with   Accurate Citations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00824</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.00824.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yubo Wang, Xueguang Ma, Ping Nie, Huaye Zeng, Zhiheng Lyu, Yuxuan Zhang, Benjamin Schneider, Yi Lu, Xiang Yue, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Academic writing requires both coherent text generation and precise citation of relevant literature. Although recent Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) systems have significantly improved factual accuracy in general-purpose text generation, their capacity to adequately support professional academic writing remains limited. In this work, we introduce ScholarCopilot, a unified framework designed to enhance existing large language models for generating professional academic articles with accurate and contextually relevant citations. ScholarCopilot dynamically determines when to retrieve scholarly references by generating a retrieval token [RET], and then utilizes its representation to look up relevant citations from a database. The retrieved references are fed into the model to augment the generation process. We jointly optimize both the generation and citation tasks within a single framework to increase efficiency. Trained on 500K papers from arXiv, our model achieves a top-1 retrieval accuracy of 40.1% on our evaluation dataset, outperforming baselines such as E5-Mistral-7B-Instruct (15.0%) and BM25 (9.8%). On a dataset of 1,000 academic writing samples, ScholarCopilot scores 16.2/25 in generation quality (measured across relevance, coherence, academic rigor, completeness, and innovation), surpassing models with 10x more parameters such as Qwen-2.5-72B-Instruct (15.8/25). Human studies also confirm ScholarCopilot's superior performance in citation recall, writing efficiency, and overall user experience, confirming the effectiveness of our approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00824</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 14:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Visual-Spatial Reasoning via R1-Zero-Like Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00883</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.00883.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenyi Liao, Qingsong Xie, Yanhao Zhang, Zijian Kong, Haonan Lu, Zhenyu Yang, Zhijie Deng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Increasing attention has been placed on improving the reasoning capacities of multi-modal large language models (MLLMs). As the cornerstone for AI agents that function in the physical realm, video-based visual-spatial intelligence (VSI) emerges as one of the most pivotal reasoning capabilities of MLLMs. This work conducts a first, in-depth study on improving the visual-spatial reasoning of MLLMs via R1-Zero-like training. Technically, we first identify that the visual-spatial reasoning capacities of small- to medium-sized Qwen2-VL models cannot be activated via Chain of Thought (CoT) prompts. We then incorporate GRPO training for improved visual-spatial reasoning, using the carefully curated VSI-100k dataset, following DeepSeek-R1-Zero. During the investigation, we identify the necessity to keep the KL penalty (even with a small value) in GRPO. With just 120 GPU hours, our vsGRPO-2B model, fine-tuned from Qwen2-VL-2B, can outperform the base model by 12.1% and surpass GPT-4o. Moreover, our vsGRPO-7B model, fine-tuned from Qwen2-VL-7B, achieves performance comparable to that of the best open-source model LLaVA-NeXT-Video-72B. Additionally, we compare vsGRPO to supervised fine-tuning and direct preference optimization baselines and observe strong performance superiority. The code and dataset will be available soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00883</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 15:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Token Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00927</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.00927.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Olga Golovneva, Tianlu Wang, Jason Weston, Sainbayar Sukhbaatar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Soft attention is a critical mechanism powering LLMs to locate relevant parts within a given context. However, individual attention weights are determined by the similarity of only a single query and key token vector. This "single token attention" bottlenecks the amount of information used in distinguishing a relevant part from the rest of the context. To address this issue, we propose a new attention method, Multi-Token Attention (MTA), which allows LLMs to condition their attention weights on multiple query and key vectors simultaneously. This is achieved by applying convolution operations over queries, keys and heads, allowing nearby queries and keys to affect each other's attention weights for more precise attention. As a result, our method can locate relevant context using richer, more nuanced information that can exceed a single vector's capacity. Through extensive evaluations, we demonstrate that MTA achieves enhanced performance on a range of popular benchmarks. Notably, it outperforms Transformer baseline models on standard language modeling tasks, and on tasks that require searching for information within long contexts, where our method's ability to leverage richer information proves particularly beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00927</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 15:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WikiVideo: Article Generation from Multiple Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00939</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.00939.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Martin, Reno Kriz, William Gantt Walden, Kate Sanders, Hannah Recknor, Eugene Yang, Francis Ferraro, Benjamin Van Durme&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present the challenging task of automatically creating a high-level Wikipedia-style article that aggregates information from multiple diverse videos about real-world events, such as natural disasters or political elections. Videos are intuitive sources for retrieval-augmented generation (RAG), but most contemporary RAG workflows focus heavily on text and existing methods for video-based summarization focus on low-level scene understanding rather than high-level event semantics. To close this gap, we introduce WikiVideo, a benchmark consisting of expert-written articles and densely annotated videos that provide evidence for articles' claims, facilitating the integration of video into RAG pipelines and enabling the creation of in-depth content that is grounded in multimodal sources. We further propose Collaborative Article Generation (CAG), a novel interactive method for article creation from multiple videos. CAG leverages an iterative interaction between an r1-style reasoning model and a VideoLLM to draw higher level inferences about the target event than is possible with VideoLLMs alone, which fixate on low-level visual features. We benchmark state-of-the-art VideoLLMs and CAG in both oracle retrieval and RAG settings and find that CAG consistently outperforms alternative methods, while suggesting intriguing avenues for future work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00939</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 16:22:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MergeVQ: A Unified Framework for Visual Generation and Representation   with Disentangled Token Merging and Quantization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00999</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.00999.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyuan Li, Luyuan Zhang, Zedong Wang, Juanxi Tian, Cheng Tan, Zicheng Liu, Chang Yu, Qingsong Xie, Haonan Lu, Haoqian Wang, Zhen Lei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 87&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Masked Image Modeling (MIM) with Vector Quantization (VQ) has achieved great success in both self-supervised pre-training and image generation. However, most existing methods struggle to address the trade-off in shared latent space for generation quality vs. representation learning and efficiency. To push the limits of this paradigm, we propose MergeVQ, which incorporates token merging techniques into VQ-based generative models to bridge the gap between image generation and visual representation learning in a unified architecture. During pre-training, MergeVQ decouples top-k semantics from latent space with the token merge module after self-attention blocks in the encoder for subsequent Look-up Free Quantization (LFQ) and global alignment and recovers their fine-grained details through cross-attention in the decoder for reconstruction. As for the second-stage generation, we introduce MergeAR, which performs KV Cache compression for efficient raster-order prediction. Extensive experiments on ImageNet verify that MergeVQ as an AR generative model achieves competitive performance in both visual representation learning and image generation tasks while maintaining favorable token efficiency and inference speed. The code and model will be available at https://apexgen-x.github.io/MergeVQ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00999</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 17:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AnimeGamer: Infinite Anime Life Simulation with Next Game State   Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01014</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.01014.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junhao Cheng, Yuying Ge, Yixiao Ge, Jing Liao, Ying Shan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 66&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in image and video synthesis have opened up new promise in generative games. One particularly intriguing application is transforming characters from anime films into interactive, playable entities. This allows players to immerse themselves in the dynamic anime world as their favorite characters for life simulation through language instructions. Such games are defined as infinite game since they eliminate predetermined boundaries and fixed gameplay rules, where players can interact with the game world through open-ended language and experience ever-evolving storylines and environments. Recently, a pioneering approach for infinite anime life simulation employs large language models (LLMs) to translate multi-turn text dialogues into language instructions for image generation. However, it neglects historical visual context, leading to inconsistent gameplay. Furthermore, it only generates static images, failing to incorporate the dynamics necessary for an engaging gaming experience. In this work, we propose AnimeGamer, which is built upon Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) to generate each game state, including dynamic animation shots that depict character movements and updates to character states, as illustrated in Figure 1. We introduce novel action-aware multimodal representations to represent animation shots, which can be decoded into high-quality video clips using a video diffusion model. By taking historical animation shot representations as context and predicting subsequent representations, AnimeGamer can generate games with contextual consistency and satisfactory dynamics. Extensive evaluations using both automated metrics and human evaluations demonstrate that AnimeGamer outperforms existing methods in various aspects of the gaming experience. Codes and checkpoints are available at https://github.com/TencentARC/AnimeGamer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01014</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 17:57:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSeek-R1 Thoughtology: Let's &lt;think&gt; about LLM Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07128</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.07128.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sara Vera Marjanović, Arkil Patel, Vaibhav Adlakha, Milad Aghajohari, Parishad BehnamGhader, Mehar Bhatia, Aditi Khandelwal, Austin Kraft, Benno Krojer, Xing Han Lù, Nicholas Meade, Dongchan Shin, Amirhossein Kazemnejad, Gaurav Kamath, Marius Mosbach, Karolina Stańczak, Siva Reddy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 83&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models like DeepSeek-R1 mark a fundamental shift in how LLMs approach complex problems. Instead of directly producing an answer for a given input, DeepSeek-R1 creates detailed multi-step reasoning chains, seemingly "thinking" about a problem before providing an answer. This reasoning process is publicly available to the user, creating endless opportunities for studying the reasoning behaviour of the model and opening up the field of Thoughtology. Starting from a taxonomy of DeepSeek-R1's basic building blocks of reasoning, our analyses on DeepSeek-R1 investigate the impact and controllability of thought length, management of long or confusing contexts, cultural and safety concerns, and the status of DeepSeek-R1 vis-\`a-vis cognitive phenomena, such as human-like language processing and world modelling. Our findings paint a nuanced picture. Notably, we show DeepSeek-R1 has a 'sweet spot' of reasoning, where extra inference time can impair model performance. Furthermore, we find a tendency for DeepSeek-R1 to persistently ruminate on previously explored problem formulations, obstructing further exploration. We also note strong safety vulnerabilities of DeepSeek-R1 compared to its non-reasoning counterpart, which can also compromise safety-aligned LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07128</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:36:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamActor-M1: Holistic, Expressive and Robust Human Image Animation   with Hybrid Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01724</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.01724.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxuan Luo, Zhengkun Rong, Lizhen Wang, Longhao Zhang, Tianshu Hu, Yongming Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 65&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While recent image-based human animation methods achieve realistic body and facial motion synthesis, critical gaps remain in fine-grained holistic controllability, multi-scale adaptability, and long-term temporal coherence, which leads to their lower expressiveness and robustness. We propose a diffusion transformer (DiT) based framework, DreamActor-M1, with hybrid guidance to overcome these limitations. For motion guidance, our hybrid control signals that integrate implicit facial representations, 3D head spheres, and 3D body skeletons achieve robust control of facial expressions and body movements, while producing expressive and identity-preserving animations. For scale adaptation, to handle various body poses and image scales ranging from portraits to full-body views, we employ a progressive training strategy using data with varying resolutions and scales. For appearance guidance, we integrate motion patterns from sequential frames with complementary visual references, ensuring long-term temporal coherence for unseen regions during complex movements. Experiments demonstrate that our method outperforms the state-of-the-art works, delivering expressive results for portraits, upper-body, and full-body generation with robust long-term consistency. Project Page: https://grisoon.github.io/DreamActor-M1/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01724</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 13:30:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PaperBench: Evaluating AI's Ability to Replicate AI Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01848</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.01848.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Giulio Starace, Oliver Jaffe, Dane Sherburn, James Aung, Jun Shern Chan, Leon Maksin, Rachel Dias, Evan Mays, Benjamin Kinsella, Wyatt Thompson, Johannes Heidecke, Amelia Glaese, Tejal Patwardhan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce PaperBench, a benchmark evaluating the ability of AI agents to replicate state-of-the-art AI research. Agents must replicate 20 ICML 2024 Spotlight and Oral papers from scratch, including understanding paper contributions, developing a codebase, and successfully executing experiments. For objective evaluation, we develop rubrics that hierarchically decompose each replication task into smaller sub-tasks with clear grading criteria. In total, PaperBench contains 8,316 individually gradable tasks. Rubrics are co-developed with the author(s) of each ICML paper for accuracy and realism. To enable scalable evaluation, we also develop an LLM-based judge to automatically grade replication attempts against rubrics, and assess our judge's performance by creating a separate benchmark for judges. We evaluate several frontier models on PaperBench, finding that the best-performing tested agent, Claude 3.5 Sonnet (New) with open-source scaffolding, achieves an average replication score of 21.0\%. Finally, we recruit top ML PhDs to attempt a subset of PaperBench, finding that models do not yet outperform the human baseline. We https://github.com/openai/preparedness{open-source our code} to facilitate future research in understanding the AI engineering capabilities of AI agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01848</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 15:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoScene: Distilling Video Diffusion Model to Generate 3D Scenes in   One Step</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01956</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.01956.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hanyang Wang, Fangfu Liu, Jiawei Chi, Yueqi Duan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recovering 3D scenes from sparse views is a challenging task due to its inherent ill-posed problem. Conventional methods have developed specialized solutions (e.g., geometry regularization or feed-forward deterministic model) to mitigate the issue. However, they still suffer from performance degradation by minimal overlap across input views with insufficient visual information. Fortunately, recent video generative models show promise in addressing this challenge as they are capable of generating video clips with plausible 3D structures. Powered by large pretrained video diffusion models, some pioneering research start to explore the potential of video generative prior and create 3D scenes from sparse views. Despite impressive improvements, they are limited by slow inference time and the lack of 3D constraint, leading to inefficiencies and reconstruction artifacts that do not align with real-world geometry structure. In this paper, we propose VideoScene to distill the video diffusion model to generate 3D scenes in one step, aiming to build an efficient and effective tool to bridge the gap from video to 3D. Specifically, we design a 3D-aware leap flow distillation strategy to leap over time-consuming redundant information and train a dynamic denoising policy network to adaptively determine the optimal leap timestep during inference. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our VideoScene achieves faster and superior 3D scene generation results than previous video diffusion models, highlighting its potential as an efficient tool for future video to 3D applications. Project Page: https://hanyang-21.github.io/VideoScene&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01956</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 17:59:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Less-to-More Generalization: Unlocking More Controllability by   In-Context Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02160</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.02160.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaojin Wu, Mengqi Huang, Wenxu Wu, Yufeng Cheng, Fei Ding, Qian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although subject-driven generation has been extensively explored in image generation due to its wide applications, it still has challenges in data scalability and subject expansibility. For the first challenge, moving from curating single-subject datasets to multiple-subject ones and scaling them is particularly difficult. For the second, most recent methods center on single-subject generation, making it hard to apply when dealing with multi-subject scenarios. In this study, we propose a highly-consistent data synthesis pipeline to tackle this challenge. This pipeline harnesses the intrinsic in-context generation capabilities of diffusion transformers and generates high-consistency multi-subject paired data. Additionally, we introduce UNO, which consists of progressive cross-modal alignment and universal rotary position embedding. It is a multi-image conditioned subject-to-image model iteratively trained from a text-to-image model. Extensive experiments show that our method can achieve high consistency while ensuring controllability in both single-subject and multi-subject driven generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02160</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 22:20:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SkyReels-A2: Compose Anything in Video Diffusion Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02436</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.02436.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengcong Fei, Debang Li, Di Qiu, Jiahua Wang, Yikun Dou, Rui Wang, Jingtao Xu, Mingyuan Fan, Guibin Chen, Yang Li, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents SkyReels-A2, a controllable video generation framework capable of assembling arbitrary visual elements (e.g., characters, objects, backgrounds) into synthesized videos based on textual prompts while maintaining strict consistency with reference images for each element. We term this task elements-to-video (E2V), whose primary challenges lie in preserving the fidelity of each reference element, ensuring coherent composition of the scene, and achieving natural outputs. To address these, we first design a comprehensive data pipeline to construct prompt-reference-video triplets for model training. Next, we propose a novel image-text joint embedding model to inject multi-element representations into the generative process, balancing element-specific consistency with global coherence and text alignment. We also optimize the inference pipeline for both speed and output stability. Moreover, we introduce a carefully curated benchmark for systematic evaluation, i.e, A2 Bench. Experiments demonstrate that our framework can generate diverse, high-quality videos with precise element control. SkyReels-A2 is the first open-source commercial grade model for the generation of E2V, performing favorably against advanced closed-source commercial models. We anticipate SkyReels-A2 will advance creative applications such as drama and virtual e-commerce, pushing the boundaries of controllable video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02436</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 09:50:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inference-Time Scaling for Generalist Reward Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02495</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.02495.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijun Liu, Peiyi Wang, Runxin Xu, Shirong Ma, Chong Ruan, Peng Li, Yang Liu, Yu Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) has been widely adopted in post-training for large language models (LLMs) at scale. Recently, the incentivization of reasoning capabilities in LLMs from RL indicates that proper learning methods could enable effective inference-time scalability. A key challenge of RL is to obtain accurate reward signals for LLMs in various domains beyond verifiable questions or artificial rules. In this work, we investigate how to improve reward modeling (RM) with more inference compute for general queries, i.e. the inference-time scalability of generalist RM, and further, how to improve the effectiveness of performance-compute scaling with proper learning methods. For the RM approach, we adopt pointwise generative reward modeling (GRM) to enable flexibility for different input types and potential for inference-time scaling. For the learning method, we propose Self-Principled Critique Tuning (SPCT) to foster scalable reward generation behaviors in GRMs through online RL, to generate principles adaptively and critiques accurately, resulting in DeepSeek-GRM models. Furthermore, for effective inference-time scaling, we use parallel sampling to expand compute usage, and introduce a meta RM to guide voting process for better scaling performance. Empirically, we show that SPCT significantly improves the quality and scalability of GRMs, outperforming existing methods and models in various RM benchmarks without severe biases, and could achieve better performance compared to training-time scaling. DeepSeek-GRM still meets challenges in some tasks, which we believe can be addressed by future efforts in generalist reward systems. The models will be released and open-sourced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02495</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 11:19:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZClip: Adaptive Spike Mitigation for LLM Pre-Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02507</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.02507.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abhay Kumar, Louis Owen, Nilabhra Roy Chowdhury, Fabian Güra&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 77&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training large language models (LLMs) presents numerous challenges, including gradient instability and loss spikes. These phenomena can lead to catastrophic divergence, requiring costly checkpoint restoration and data batch skipping. Traditional gradient clipping techniques, such as constant or norm-based methods, fail to address these issues effectively due to their reliance on fixed thresholds or heuristics, leading to inefficient learning and requiring frequent manual intervention. In this work, we propose ZClip, an adaptive gradient clipping algorithm that dynamically adjusts the clipping threshold based on statistical properties of gradient norms over time. Unlike prior reactive strategies, ZClip proactively adapts to training dynamics without making any prior assumptions on the scale and the temporal evolution of gradient norms. At its core, it leverages z-score-based anomaly detection to identify and mitigate large gradient spikes, preventing malignant loss spikes while not interfering with convergence otherwise. Our code is available at: https://github.com/bluorion-com/ZClip.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02507</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 11:41:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Audio-visual Controlled Video Diffusion with Masked Selective State   Spaces Modeling for Natural Talking Head Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02542</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.02542.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fa-Ting Hong, Zunnan Xu, Zixiang Zhou, Jun Zhou, Xiu Li, Qin Lin, Qinglin Lu, Dan Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Talking head synthesis is vital for virtual avatars and human-computer interaction. However, most existing methods are typically limited to accepting control from a single primary modality, restricting their practical utility. To this end, we introduce ACTalker, an end-to-end video diffusion framework that supports both multi-signals control and single-signal control for talking head video generation. For multiple control, we design a parallel mamba structure with multiple branches, each utilizing a separate driving signal to control specific facial regions. A gate mechanism is applied across all branches, providing flexible control over video generation. To ensure natural coordination of the controlled video both temporally and spatially, we employ the mamba structure, which enables driving signals to manipulate feature tokens across both dimensions in each branch. Additionally, we introduce a mask-drop strategy that allows each driving signal to independently control its corresponding facial region within the mamba structure, preventing control conflicts. Experimental results demonstrate that our method produces natural-looking facial videos driven by diverse signals and that the mamba layer seamlessly integrates multiple driving modalities without conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02542</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 12:44:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-SWE-bench: A Multilingual Benchmark for Issue Resolving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02605</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.02605.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daoguang Zan, Zhirong Huang, Wei Liu, Hanwu Chen, Linhao Zhang, Shulin Xin, Lu Chen, Qi Liu, Xiaojian Zhong, Aoyan Li, Siyao Liu, Yongsheng Xiao, Liangqiang Chen, Yuyu Zhang, Jing Su, Tianyu Liu, Rui Long, Kai Shen, Liang Xiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The task of issue resolving is to modify a codebase to generate a patch that addresses a given issue. However, existing benchmarks, such as SWE-bench, focus almost exclusively on Python, making them insufficient for evaluating Large Language Models (LLMs) across diverse software ecosystems. To address this, we introduce a multilingual issue-resolving benchmark, called Multi-SWE-bench, covering Java, TypeScript, JavaScript, Go, Rust, C, and C++. It includes a total of 1,632 high-quality instances, which were carefully annotated from 2,456 candidates by 68 expert annotators, ensuring that the benchmark can provide an accurate and reliable evaluation. Based on Multi-SWE-bench, we evaluate a series of state-of-the-art models using three representative methods (Agentless, SWE-agent, and OpenHands) and present a comprehensive analysis with key empirical insights. In addition, we launch a Multi-SWE-RL open-source community, aimed at building large-scale reinforcement learning (RL) training datasets for issue-resolving tasks. As an initial contribution, we release a set of 4,723 well-structured instances spanning seven programming languages, laying a solid foundation for RL research in this domain. More importantly, we open-source our entire data production pipeline, along with detailed tutorials, encouraging the open-source community to continuously contribute and expand the dataset. We envision our Multi-SWE-bench and the ever-growing Multi-SWE-RL community as catalysts for advancing RL toward its full potential, bringing us one step closer to the dawn of AGI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02605</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 14:06:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPT-ImgEval: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Diagnosing GPT4o in Image   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02782</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.02782.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Yan, Junyan Ye, Weijia Li, Zilong Huang, Shenghai Yuan, Xiangyang He, Kaiqing Lin, Jun He, Conghui He, Li Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The recent breakthroughs in OpenAI's GPT4o model have demonstrated surprisingly good capabilities in image generation and editing, resulting in significant excitement in the community. This technical report presents the first-look evaluation benchmark (named GPT-ImgEval), quantitatively and qualitatively diagnosing GPT-4o's performance across three critical dimensions: (1) generation quality, (2) editing proficiency, and (3) world knowledge-informed semantic synthesis. Across all three tasks, GPT-4o demonstrates strong performance, significantly surpassing existing methods in both image generation control and output quality, while also showcasing exceptional knowledge reasoning capabilities. Furthermore, based on the GPT-4o's generated data, we propose a classification-model-based approach to investigate the underlying architecture of GPT-4o, where our empirical results suggest the model consists of an auto-regressive (AR) combined with a diffusion-based head for image decoding, rather than the VAR-like architectures. We also provide a complete speculation on GPT-4o's overall architecture. In addition, we conduct a series of analyses to identify and visualize GPT-4o's specific limitations and the synthetic artifacts commonly observed in its image generation. We also present a comparative study of multi-round image editing between GPT-4o and Gemini 2.0 Flash, and discuss the safety implications of GPT-4o's outputs, particularly their detectability by existing image forensic models. We hope that our work can offer valuable insight and provide a reliable benchmark to guide future research, foster reproducibility, and accelerate innovation in the field of image generation and beyond. The codes and datasets used for evaluating GPT-4o can be found at https://github.com/PicoTrex/GPT-ImgEval.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02782</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 17:23:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Envisioning Beyond the Pixels: Benchmarking Reasoning-Informed Visual   Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02826</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.02826.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangyu Zhao, Peiyuan Zhang, Kexian Tang, Hao Li, Zicheng Zhang, Guangtao Zhai, Junchi Yan, Hua Yang, Xue Yang, Haodong Duan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 67&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Multi-modality Models (LMMs) have made significant progress in visual understanding and generation, but they still face challenges in General Visual Editing, particularly in following complex instructions, preserving appearance consistency, and supporting flexible input formats. To address this gap, we introduce RISEBench, the first benchmark for evaluating Reasoning-Informed viSual Editing (RISE). RISEBench focuses on four key reasoning types: Temporal, Causal, Spatial, and Logical Reasoning. We curate high-quality test cases for each category and propose an evaluation framework that assesses Instruction Reasoning, Appearance Consistency, and Visual Plausibility with both human judges and an LMM-as-a-judge approach. Our experiments reveal that while GPT-4o-Native significantly outperforms other open-source and proprietary models, even this state-of-the-art system struggles with logical reasoning tasks, highlighting an area that remains underexplored. As an initial effort, RISEBench aims to provide foundational insights into reasoning-aware visual editing and to catalyze future research. Though still in its early stages, we are committed to continuously expanding and refining the benchmark to support more comprehensive, reliable, and scalable evaluations of next-generation multimodal systems. Our code and data will be released at https://github.com/PhoenixZ810/RISEBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02826</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Reflection in Pre-Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04022</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.04022.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Essential AI, Darsh J Shah, Peter Rushton, Somanshu Singla, Mohit Parmar, Kurt Smith, Yash Vanjani, Ashish Vaswani, Adarsh Chaluvaraju, Andrew Hojel, Andrew Ma, Anil Thomas, Anthony Polloreno, Ashish Tanwer, Burhan Drak Sibai, Divya S Mansingka, Divya Shivaprasad, Ishaan Shah, Karl Stratos, Khoi Nguyen, Michael Callahan, Michael Pust, Mrinal Iyer, Philip Monk, Platon Mazarakis, Ritvik Kapila, Saurabh Srivastava, Tim Romanski&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 77&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A language model's ability to reflect on its own reasoning provides a key advantage for solving complex problems. While most recent research has focused on how this ability develops during reinforcement learning, we show that it actually begins to emerge much earlier - during the model's pre-training. To study this, we introduce deliberate errors into chains-of-thought and test whether the model can still arrive at the correct answer by recognizing and correcting these mistakes. By tracking performance across different stages of pre-training, we observe that this self-correcting ability appears early and improves steadily over time. For instance, an OLMo2-7B model pre-trained on 4 trillion tokens displays self-correction on our six self-reflection tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04022</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 02:24:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T1: Tool-integrated Self-verification for Test-time Compute Scaling in   Small Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04718</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.04718.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minki Kang, Jongwon Jeong, Jaewoong Cho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have demonstrated that test-time compute scaling effectively improves the performance of small language models (sLMs). However, prior research has mainly examined test-time compute scaling with an additional larger model as a verifier, leaving self-verification by sLMs underexplored. In this work, we investigate whether sLMs can reliably self-verify their outputs under test-time scaling. We find that even with knowledge distillation from larger verifiers, sLMs struggle with verification tasks requiring memorization, such as numerical calculations and fact-checking. To address this limitation, we propose Tool-integrated self-verification (T1), which delegates memorization-heavy verification steps to external tools, such as a code interpreter. Our theoretical analysis shows that tool integration reduces memorization demands and improves test-time scaling performance. Experiments on the MATH benchmark demonstrate that, with T1, a Llama-3.2 1B model under test-time scaling outperforms the significantly larger Llama-3.1 8B model. Moreover, T1 generalizes effectively to both mathematical (MATH500) and multi-domain knowledge-intensive tasks (MMLU-Pro). Our findings highlight the potential of tool integration to substantially improve the self-verification abilities of sLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04718</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 04:01:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FantasyTalking: Realistic Talking Portrait Generation via Coherent   Motion Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04842</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.04842.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengchao Wang, Qiang Wang, Fan Jiang, Yaqi Fan, Yunpeng Zhang, Yonggang Qi, Kun Zhao, Mu Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Creating a realistic animatable avatar from a single static portrait remains challenging. Existing approaches often struggle to capture subtle facial expressions, the associated global body movements, and the dynamic background. To address these limitations, we propose a novel framework that leverages a pretrained video diffusion transformer model to generate high-fidelity, coherent talking portraits with controllable motion dynamics. At the core of our work is a dual-stage audio-visual alignment strategy. In the first stage, we employ a clip-level training scheme to establish coherent global motion by aligning audio-driven dynamics across the entire scene, including the reference portrait, contextual objects, and background. In the second stage, we refine lip movements at the frame level using a lip-tracing mask, ensuring precise synchronization with audio signals. To preserve identity without compromising motion flexibility, we replace the commonly used reference network with a facial-focused cross-attention module that effectively maintains facial consistency throughout the video. Furthermore, we integrate a motion intensity modulation module that explicitly controls expression and body motion intensity, enabling controllable manipulation of portrait movements beyond mere lip motion. Extensive experimental results show that our proposed approach achieves higher quality with better realism, coherence, motion intensity, and identity preservation. Ours project page: https://fantasy-amap.github.io/fantasy-talking/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04842</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 08:56:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRIMA.CPP: Speeding Up 70B-Scale LLM Inference on Low-Resource Everyday   Home Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08791</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.08791.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zonghang Li, Tao Li, Wenjiao Feng, Mohsen Guizani, Hongfang Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 127&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Emergency of DeepSeek R1 and QwQ 32B have broken through performance barriers for running frontier large language models (LLMs) on home devices. While consumer hardware is getting stronger and model quantization is improving, existing end-side solutions still demand GPU clusters, large RAM/VRAM, and high bandwidth, far beyond what a common home cluster can handle. This paper introduces prima.cpp, a distributed inference system that runs 70B-scale models on everyday home devices using a mix of CPU/GPU, low RAM/VRAM, Wi-Fi, and cross-platform support. It uses mmap to manage model weights and introduces piped-ring parallelism with prefetching to hide disk loading. By modeling heterogeneity in computation, communication, disk, memory (and its management behavior), and OS, it optimally assigns model layers to each device's CPU and GPU, further reducing token latency. An elegant algorithm named Halda is proposed to solve this NP-hard assignment problem. We evaluate prima.cpp on a common four-node home cluster. It outperforms llama.cpp, exo, and dllama on 30B+ models while keeping memory pressure below 6%. This brings frontier 30B-70B models, such as Llama 3, DeepSeek R1, Qwen 2.5, and QwQ to home assistants, making advanced AI truly accessible to individuals. The code is open source and available at https://github.com/Lizonghang/prima.cpp.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08791</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 13:46:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-Minute Video Generation with Test-Time Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05298</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.05298.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Karan Dalal, Daniel Koceja, Gashon Hussein, Jiarui Xu, Yue Zhao, Youjin Song, Shihao Han, Ka Chun Cheung, Jan Kautz, Carlos Guestrin, Tatsunori Hashimoto, Sanmi Koyejo, Yejin Choi, Yu Sun, Xiaolong Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Transformers today still struggle to generate one-minute videos because self-attention layers are inefficient for long context. Alternatives such as Mamba layers struggle with complex multi-scene stories because their hidden states are less expressive. We experiment with Test-Time Training (TTT) layers, whose hidden states themselves can be neural networks, therefore more expressive. Adding TTT layers into a pre-trained Transformer enables it to generate one-minute videos from text storyboards. For proof of concept, we curate a dataset based on Tom and Jerry cartoons. Compared to baselines such as Mamba~2, Gated DeltaNet, and sliding-window attention layers, TTT layers generate much more coherent videos that tell complex stories, leading by 34 Elo points in a human evaluation of 100 videos per method. Although promising, results still contain artifacts, likely due to the limited capability of the pre-trained 5B model. The efficiency of our implementation can also be improved. We have only experimented with one-minute videos due to resource constraints, but the approach can be extended to longer videos and more complex stories. Sample videos, code and annotations are available at: https://test-time-training.github.io/video-dit&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05298</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 17:56:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SmolVLM: Redefining small and efficient multimodal models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05299</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.05299.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Andrés Marafioti, Orr Zohar, Miquel Farré, Merve Noyan, Elie Bakouch, Pedro Cuenca, Cyril Zakka, Loubna Ben Allal, Anton Lozhkov, Nouamane Tazi, Vaibhav Srivastav, Joshua Lochner, Hugo Larcher, Mathieu Morlon, Lewis Tunstall, Leandro von Werra, Thomas Wolf&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 177&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Vision-Language Models (VLMs) deliver exceptional performance but require significant computational resources, limiting their deployment on mobile and edge devices. Smaller VLMs typically mirror design choices of larger models, such as extensive image tokenization, leading to inefficient GPU memory usage and constrained practicality for on-device applications.   We introduce SmolVLM, a series of compact multimodal models specifically engineered for resource-efficient inference. We systematically explore architectural configurations, tokenization strategies, and data curation optimized for low computational overhead. Through this, we identify key design choices that yield substantial performance gains on image and video tasks with minimal memory footprints.   Our smallest model, SmolVLM-256M, uses less than 1GB GPU memory during inference and outperforms the 300-times larger Idefics-80B model, despite an 18-month development gap. Our largest model, at 2.2B parameters, rivals state-of-the-art VLMs consuming twice the GPU memory. SmolVLM models extend beyond static images, demonstrating robust video comprehension capabilities.   Our results emphasize that strategic architectural optimizations, aggressive yet efficient tokenization, and carefully curated training data significantly enhance multimodal performance, facilitating practical, energy-efficient deployments at significantly smaller scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05299</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 17:58:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>URECA: Unique Region Caption Anything</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05305</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.05305.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sangbeom Lim, Junwan Kim, Heeji Yoon, Jaewoo Jung, Seungryong Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Region-level captioning aims to generate natural language descriptions for specific image regions while highlighting their distinguishing features. However, existing methods struggle to produce unique captions across multi-granularity, limiting their real-world applicability. To address the need for detailed region-level understanding, we introduce URECA dataset, a large-scale dataset tailored for multi-granularity region captioning. Unlike prior datasets that focus primarily on salient objects, URECA dataset ensures a unique and consistent mapping between regions and captions by incorporating a diverse set of objects, parts, and background elements. Central to this is a stage-wise data curation pipeline, where each stage incrementally refines region selection and caption generation. By leveraging Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) at each stage, our pipeline produces distinctive and contextually grounded captions with improved accuracy and semantic diversity. Building upon this dataset, we present URECA, a novel captioning model designed to effectively encode multi-granularity regions. URECA maintains essential spatial properties such as position and shape through simple yet impactful modifications to existing MLLMs, enabling fine-grained and semantically rich region descriptions. Our approach introduces dynamic mask modeling and a high-resolution mask encoder to enhance caption uniqueness. Experiments show that URECA achieves state-of-the-art performance on URECA dataset and generalizes well to existing region-level captioning benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05305</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 17:59:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>COIG-P: A High-Quality and Large-Scale Chinese Preference Dataset for   Alignment with Human Values</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05535</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.05535.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; M-A-P Team, Siwei Wu, Jincheng Ren, Xinrun Du, Shuyue Guo, Xingwei Qu, Yiming Liang, Jie Liu, Yunwen Li, Tianyu Zheng, Boyu Feng, Huaqing Yuan, Zenith Wang, Jiaheng Liu, Wenhao Huang, Chenglin Cai, Haoran Que, Jian Yang, Yuelin Bai, Zekun Moore Wang, Zhouliang Yu, Qunshu Lin, Ding Pan, Yuchen Jiang, Tiannan Wang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Shenzhi Wang, Xingyuan Bu, Minghao Liu, Guoyin Wang, Ge Zhang, Chenghua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Aligning large language models (LLMs) with human preferences has achieved remarkable success. However, existing Chinese preference datasets are limited by small scale, narrow domain coverage, and lack of rigorous data validation. Additionally, the reliance on human annotators for instruction and response labeling significantly constrains the scalability of human preference datasets. To address these challenges, we design an LLM-based Chinese preference dataset annotation pipeline with no human intervention. Specifically, we crawled and carefully filtered 92k high-quality Chinese queries and employed 15 mainstream LLMs to generate and score chosen-rejected response pairs. Based on it, we introduce COIG-P (Chinese Open Instruction Generalist - Preference), a high-quality, large-scale Chinese preference dataset, comprises 1,009k Chinese preference pairs spanning 6 diverse domains: Chat, Code, Math, Logic, Novel, and Role. Building upon COIG-P, to reduce the overhead of using LLMs for scoring, we trained a 8B-sized Chinese Reward Model (CRM) and meticulously constructed a Chinese Reward Benchmark (CRBench). Evaluation results based on AlignBench liu2024alignbenchbenchmarkingchinesealignment show that that COIG-P significantly outperforms other Chinese preference datasets, and it brings significant performance improvements ranging from 2% to 12% for the Qwen2/2.5 and Infinity-Instruct-3M-0625 model series, respectively. The results on CRBench demonstrate that our CRM has a strong and robust scoring ability. We apply it to filter chosen-rejected response pairs in a test split of COIG-P, and our experiments show that it is comparable to GPT-4o in identifying low-quality samples while maintaining efficiency and cost-effectiveness. Our codes and data are released in https://github.com/multimodal-art-projection/COIG-P.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05535</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 22:15:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork R1V: Pioneering Multimodal Reasoning with Chain-of-Thought</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05599</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.05599.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Peng, Chris, Xiaokun Wang, Yichen Wei, Jiangbo Pei, Weijie Qiu, Ai Jian, Yunzhuo Hao, Jiachun Pan, Tianyidan Xie, Li Ge, Rongxian Zhuang, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 81&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Skywork R1V, a multimodal reasoning model extending the an R1-series Large language models (LLM) to visual modalities via an efficient multimodal transfer method. Leveraging a lightweight visual projector, Skywork R1V facilitates seamless multimodal adaptation without necessitating retraining of either the foundational language model or the vision encoder. To strengthen visual-text alignment, we propose a hybrid optimization strategy that combines Iterative Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) with Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), significantly enhancing cross-modal integration efficiency. Additionally, we introduce an adaptive-length Chain-of-Thought distillation approach for reasoning data generation. This approach dynamically optimizes reasoning chain lengths, thereby enhancing inference efficiency and preventing excessive reasoning overthinking. Empirical evaluations demonstrate that Skywork R1V, with only 38B parameters, delivers competitive performance, achieving a score of 69.0 on the MMMU benchmark and 67.5 on MathVista. Meanwhile, it maintains robust textual reasoning performance, evidenced by impressive scores of 72.0 on AIME and 94.0 on MATH500. The Skywork R1V model weights have been publicly released to promote openness and reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05599</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 01:19:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DDT: Decoupled Diffusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05741</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.05741.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuai Wang, Zhi Tian, Weilin Huang, Limin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion transformers have demonstrated remarkable generation quality, albeit requiring longer training iterations and numerous inference steps. In each denoising step, diffusion transformers encode the noisy inputs to extract the lower-frequency semantic component and then decode the higher frequency with identical modules. This scheme creates an inherent optimization dilemma: encoding low-frequency semantics necessitates reducing high-frequency components, creating tension between semantic encoding and high-frequency decoding. To resolve this challenge, we propose a new \color{ddtD}ecoupled \color{ddtD}iffusion \color{ddtT}ransformer~(\color{ddtDDT}), with a decoupled design of a dedicated condition encoder for semantic extraction alongside a specialized velocity decoder. Our experiments reveal that a more substantial encoder yields performance improvements as model size increases. For ImageNet 256times256, Our DDT-XL/2 achieves a new state-of-the-art performance of {1.31 FID}~(nearly 4times faster training convergence compared to previous diffusion transformers). For ImageNet 512times512, Our DDT-XL/2 achieves a new state-of-the-art FID of 1.28. Additionally, as a beneficial by-product, our decoupled architecture enhances inference speed by enabling the sharing self-condition between adjacent denoising steps. To minimize performance degradation, we propose a novel statistical dynamic programming approach to identify optimal sharing strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05741</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 07:17:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Empirical Study of GPT-4o Image Generation Capabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05979</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.05979.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sixiang Chen, Jinbin Bai, Zhuoran Zhao, Tian Ye, Qingyu Shi, Donghao Zhou, Wenhao Chai, Xin Lin, Jianzong Wu, Chao Tang, Shilin Xu, Tao Zhang, Haobo Yuan, Yikang Zhou, Wei Chow, Linfeng Li, Xiangtai Li, Lei Zhu, Lu Qi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The landscape of image generation has rapidly evolved, from early GAN-based approaches to diffusion models and, most recently, to unified generative architectures that seek to bridge understanding and generation tasks. Recent advances, especially the GPT-4o, have demonstrated the feasibility of high-fidelity multimodal generation, their architectural design remains mysterious and unpublished. This prompts the question of whether image and text generation have already been successfully integrated into a unified framework for those methods. In this work, we conduct an empirical study of GPT-4o's image generation capabilities, benchmarking it against leading open-source and commercial models. Our evaluation covers four main categories, including text-to-image, image-to-image, image-to-3D, and image-to-X generation, with more than 20 tasks. Our analysis highlights the strengths and limitations of GPT-4o under various settings, and situates it within the broader evolution of generative modeling. Through this investigation, we identify promising directions for future unified generative models, emphasizing the role of architectural design and data scaling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05979</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 12:34:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hogwild! Inference: Parallel LLM Generation via Concurrent Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06261</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.06261.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gleb Rodionov, Roman Garipov, Alina Shutova, George Yakushev, Vage Egiazarian, Anton Sinitsin, Denis Kuznedelev, Dan Alistarh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 107&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated the ability to tackle increasingly complex tasks through advanced reasoning, long-form content generation, and tool use. Solving these tasks often involves long inference-time computations. In human problem solving, a common strategy to expedite work is collaboration: by dividing the problem into sub-tasks, exploring different strategies concurrently, etc. Recent research has shown that LLMs can also operate in parallel by implementing explicit cooperation frameworks, such as voting mechanisms or the explicit creation of independent sub-tasks that can be executed in parallel. However, each of these frameworks may not be suitable for all types of tasks, which can hinder their applicability. In this work, we propose a different design approach: we run LLM "workers" in parallel , allowing them to synchronize via a concurrently-updated attention cache and prompt these workers to decide how best to collaborate. Our approach allows the instances to come up with their own collaboration strategy for the problem at hand, all the while "seeing" each other's partial progress in the concurrent cache. We implement this approach via Hogwild! Inference: a parallel LLM inference engine where multiple instances of the same LLM run in parallel with the same attention cache, with "instant" access to each other's generated tokens. Hogwild! inference takes advantage of Rotary Position Embeddings (RoPE) to avoid recomputation while improving parallel hardware utilization. We find that modern reasoning-capable LLMs can perform inference with shared Key-Value cache out of the box, without additional fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06261</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 17:59:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniSVG: A Unified Scalable Vector Graphics Generation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06263</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.06263.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiying Yang, Wei Cheng, Sijin Chen, Xianfang Zeng, Jiaxu Zhang, Liao Wang, Gang Yu, Xingjun Ma, Yu-Gang Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 156&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) is an important image format widely adopted in graphic design because of their resolution independence and editability. The study of generating high-quality SVG has continuously drawn attention from both designers and researchers in the AIGC community. However, existing methods either produces unstructured outputs with huge computational cost or is limited to generating monochrome icons of over-simplified structures. To produce high-quality and complex SVG, we propose OmniSVG, a unified framework that leverages pre-trained Vision-Language Models (VLMs) for end-to-end multimodal SVG generation. By parameterizing SVG commands and coordinates into discrete tokens, OmniSVG decouples structural logic from low-level geometry for efficient training while maintaining the expressiveness of complex SVG structure. To further advance the development of SVG synthesis, we introduce MMSVG-2M, a multimodal dataset with two million richly annotated SVG assets, along with a standardized evaluation protocol for conditional SVG generation tasks. Extensive experiments show that OmniSVG outperforms existing methods and demonstrates its potential for integration into professional SVG design workflows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06263</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 17:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Missing Premise exacerbates Overthinking: Are Reasoning Models losing   Critical Thinking Skill?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06514</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.06514.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenrui Fan, Ming Li, Lichao Sun, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We find that the response length of reasoning LLMs, whether trained by reinforcement learning or supervised learning, drastically increases for ill-posed questions with missing premises (MiP), ending up with redundant and ineffective thinking. This newly introduced scenario exacerbates the general overthinking issue to a large extent, which we name as the MiP-Overthinking. Such failures are against the ``test-time scaling law'' but have been widely observed on multiple datasets we curated with MiP, indicating the harm of cheap overthinking and a lack of critical thinking. Surprisingly, LLMs not specifically trained for reasoning exhibit much better performance on the MiP scenario, producing much shorter responses that quickly identify ill-posed queries. This implies a critical flaw of the current training recipe for reasoning LLMs, which does not encourage efficient thinking adequately, leading to the abuse of thinking patterns. To further investigate the reasons behind such failures, we conduct fine-grained analyses of the reasoning length, overthinking patterns, and location of critical thinking on different types of LLMs. Moreover, our extended ablation study reveals that the overthinking is contagious through the distillation of reasoning models' responses. These results improve the understanding of overthinking and shed novel insights into mitigating the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.06514</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 01:25:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Have we unified image generation and understanding yet? An empirical   study of GPT-4o's image generation ability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08003</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.08003.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ning Li, Jingran Zhang, Justin Cui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; OpenAI's multimodal GPT-4o has demonstrated remarkable capabilities in image generation and editing, yet its ability to achieve world knowledge-informed semantic synthesis--seamlessly integrating domain knowledge, contextual reasoning, and instruction adherence--remains unproven. In this study, we systematically evaluate these capabilities across three critical dimensions: (1) Global Instruction Adherence, (2) Fine-Grained Editing Precision, and (3) Post-Generation Reasoning. While existing benchmarks highlight GPT-4o's strong capabilities in image generation and editing, our evaluation reveals GPT-4o's persistent limitations: the model frequently defaults to literal interpretations of instructions, inconsistently applies knowledge constraints, and struggles with conditional reasoning tasks. These findings challenge prevailing assumptions about GPT-4o's unified understanding and generation capabilities, exposing significant gaps in its dynamic knowledge integration. Our study calls for the development of more robust benchmarks and training strategies that go beyond surface-level alignment, emphasizing context-aware and reasoning-grounded multimodal generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08003</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 16:10:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OLMoTrace: Tracing Language Model Outputs Back to Trillions of Training   Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07096</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.07096.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiacheng Liu, Taylor Blanton, Yanai Elazar, Sewon Min, YenSung Chen, Arnavi Chheda-Kothary, Huy Tran, Byron Bischoff, Eric Marsh, Michael Schmitz, Cassidy Trier, Aaron Sarnat, Jenna James, Jon Borchardt, Bailey Kuehl, Evie Cheng, Karen Farley, Sruthi Sreeram, Taira Anderson, David Albright, Carissa Schoenick, Luca Soldaini, Dirk Groeneveld, Rock Yuren Pang, Pang Wei Koh, Noah A. Smith, Sophie Lebrecht, Yejin Choi, Hannaneh Hajishirzi, Ali Farhadi, Jesse Dodge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present OLMoTrace, the first system that traces the outputs of language models back to their full, multi-trillion-token training data in real time. OLMoTrace finds and shows verbatim matches between segments of language model output and documents in the training text corpora. Powered by an extended version of infini-gram (Liu et al., 2024), our system returns tracing results within a few seconds. OLMoTrace can help users understand the behavior of language models through the lens of their training data. We showcase how it can be used to explore fact checking, hallucination, and the creativity of language models. OLMoTrace is publicly available and fully open-source.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07096</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 17:59:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kimi-VL Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07491</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.07491.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kimi Team, Angang Du, Bohong Yin, Bowei Xing, Bowen Qu, Bowen Wang, Cheng Chen, Chenlin Zhang, Chenzhuang Du, Chu Wei, Congcong Wang, Dehao Zhang, Dikang Du, Dongliang Wang, Enming Yuan, Enzhe Lu, Fang Li, Flood Sung, Guangda Wei, Guokun Lai, Han Zhu, Hao Ding, Hao Hu, Hao Yang, Hao Zhang, Haoning Wu, Haotian Yao, Haoyu Lu, Heng Wang, Hongcheng Gao, Huabin Zheng, Jiaming Li, Jianlin Su, Jianzhou Wang, Jiaqi Deng, Jiezhong Qiu, Jin Xie, Jinhong Wang, Jingyuan Liu, Junjie Yan, Kun Ouyang, Liang Chen, Lin Sui, Longhui Yu, Mengfan Dong, Mengnan Dong, Nuo Xu, Pengyu Cheng, Qizheng Gu, Runjie Zhou, Shaowei Liu, Sihan Cao, Tao Yu, Tianhui Song, Tongtong Bai, Wei Song, Weiran He, Weixiao Huang, Weixin Xu, Xiaokun Yuan, Xingcheng Yao, Xingzhe Wu, Xinxing Zu, Xinyu Zhou, Xinyuan Wang, Y. Charles, Yan Zhong, Yang Li, Yangyang Hu, Yanru Chen, Yejie Wang, Yibo Liu, Yibo Miao, Yidao Qin, Yimin Chen, Yiping Bao, Yiqin Wang, Yongsheng Kang, Yuanxin Liu, Yulun Du, Yuxin Wu, Yuzhi Wang, Yuzi Yan, Zaida Zhou, Zhaowei Li, Zhejun Jiang, Zheng Zhang, Zhilin Yang, Zhiqi Huang, Zihao Huang, Zijia Zhao, Ziwei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 122&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Kimi-VL, an efficient open-source Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) vision-language model (VLM) that offers advanced multimodal reasoning, long-context understanding, and strong agent capabilities - all while activating only 2.8B parameters in its language decoder (Kimi-VL-A3B). Kimi-VL demonstrates strong performance across challenging domains: as a general-purpose VLM, Kimi-VL excels in multi-turn agent tasks (e.g., OSWorld), matching flagship models. Furthermore, it exhibits remarkable capabilities across diverse challenging vision language tasks, including college-level image and video comprehension, OCR, mathematical reasoning, and multi-image understanding. In comparative evaluations, it effectively competes with cutting-edge efficient VLMs such as GPT-4o-mini, Qwen2.5-VL-7B, and Gemma-3-12B-IT, while surpassing GPT-4o in several key domains. Kimi-VL also advances in processing long contexts and perceiving clearly. With a 128K extended context window, Kimi-VL can process diverse long inputs, achieving impressive scores of 64.5 on LongVideoBench and 35.1 on MMLongBench-Doc. Its native-resolution vision encoder, MoonViT, further allows it to see and understand ultra-high-resolution visual inputs, achieving 83.2 on InfoVQA and 34.5 on ScreenSpot-Pro, while maintaining lower computational cost for common tasks. Building upon Kimi-VL, we introduce an advanced long-thinking variant: Kimi-VL-Thinking. Developed through long chain-of-thought (CoT) supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and reinforcement learning (RL), this model exhibits strong long-horizon reasoning capabilities. It achieves scores of 61.7 on MMMU, 36.8 on MathVision, and 71.3 on MathVista while maintaining the compact 2.8B activated LLM parameters, setting a new standard for efficient multimodal thinking models. Code and models are publicly accessible at https://github.com/MoonshotAI/Kimi-VL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07491</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 06:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ColorBench: Can VLMs See and Understand the Colorful World? A   Comprehensive Benchmark for Color Perception, Reasoning, and Robustness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10514</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.10514.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yijun Liang, Ming Li, Chenrui Fan, Ziyue Li, Dang Nguyen, Kwesi Cobbina, Shweta Bhardwaj, Jiuhai Chen, Fuxiao Liu, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Color plays an important role in human perception and usually provides critical clues in visual reasoning. However, it is unclear whether and how vision-language models (VLMs) can perceive, understand, and leverage color as humans. This paper introduces ColorBench, an innovative benchmark meticulously crafted to assess the capabilities of VLMs in color understanding, including color perception, reasoning, and robustness. By curating a suite of diverse test scenarios, with grounding in real applications, ColorBench evaluates how these models perceive colors, infer meanings from color-based cues, and maintain consistent performance under varying color transformations. Through an extensive evaluation of 32 VLMs with varying language models and vision encoders, our paper reveals some undiscovered findings: (i) The scaling law (larger models are better) still holds on ColorBench, while the language model plays a more important role than the vision encoder. (ii) However, the performance gaps across models are relatively small, indicating that color understanding has been largely neglected by existing VLMs. (iii) CoT reasoning improves color understanding accuracies and robustness, though they are vision-centric tasks. (iv) Color clues are indeed leveraged by VLMs on ColorBench but they can also mislead models in some tasks. These findings highlight the critical limitations of current VLMs and underscore the need to enhance color comprehension. Our ColorBenchcan serve as a foundational tool for advancing the study of human-level color understanding of multimodal AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10514</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 16:36:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VL-Rethinker: Incentivizing Self-Reflection of Vision-Language Models   with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08837</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.08837.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haozhe Wang, Chao Qu, Zuming Huang, Wei Chu, Fangzhen Lin, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, slow-thinking systems like GPT-o1 and DeepSeek-R1 have demonstrated great potential in solving challenging problems through explicit reflection. They significantly outperform the best fast-thinking models, such as GPT-4o, on various math and science benchmarks. However, their multimodal reasoning capabilities remain on par with fast-thinking models. For instance, GPT-o1's performance on benchmarks like MathVista, MathVerse, and MathVision is similar to fast-thinking models. In this paper, we aim to enhance the slow-thinking capabilities of vision-language models using reinforcement learning (without relying on distillation) to advance the state of the art. First, we adapt the GRPO algorithm with a novel technique called Selective Sample Replay (SSR) to address the vanishing advantages problem. While this approach yields strong performance, the resulting RL-trained models exhibit limited self-reflection or self-verification. To further encourage slow-thinking, we introduce Forced Rethinking, which appends a textual rethinking trigger to the end of initial rollouts in RL training, explicitly enforcing a self-reflection reasoning step. By combining these two techniques, our model, VL-Rethinker, advances state-of-the-art scores on MathVista, MathVerse, and MathVision to achieve 80.3%, 61.8%, and 43.9% respectively. VL-Rethinker also achieves open-source SoTA on multi-disciplinary benchmarks such as MMMU-Pro, EMMA, and MEGA-Bench, narrowing the gap with GPT-o1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08837</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 17:41:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VCR-Bench: A Comprehensive Evaluation Framework for Video   Chain-of-Thought Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07956</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.07956.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yukun Qi, Yiming Zhao, Yu Zeng, Xikun Bao, Wenxuan Huang, Lin Chen, Zehui Chen, Jie Zhao, Zhongang Qi, Feng Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The advancement of Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning has significantly enhanced the capabilities of large language models (LLMs) and large vision-language models (LVLMs). However, a rigorous evaluation framework for video CoT reasoning remains absent. Current video benchmarks fail to adequately assess the reasoning process and expose whether failures stem from deficiencies in perception or reasoning capabilities. Therefore, we introduce VCR-Bench, a novel benchmark designed to comprehensively evaluate LVLMs' Video Chain-of-Thought Reasoning capabilities. VCR-Bench comprises 859 videos spanning a variety of video content and durations, along with 1,034 high-quality question-answer pairs. Each pair is manually annotated with a stepwise CoT rationale, where every step is tagged to indicate its association with the perception or reasoning capabilities. Furthermore, we design seven distinct task dimensions and propose the CoT score to assess the entire CoT process based on the stepwise tagged CoT rationals. Extensive experiments on VCR-Bench highlight substantial limitations in current LVLMs. Even the top-performing model, o1, only achieves a 62.8% CoT score and an 56.7% accuracy, while most models score below 40%. Experiments show most models score lower on perception than reasoning steps, revealing LVLMs' key bottleneck in temporal-spatial information processing for complex video reasoning. A robust positive correlation between the CoT score and accuracy confirms the validity of our evaluation framework and underscores the critical role of CoT reasoning in solving complex video reasoning tasks. We hope VCR-Bench to serve as a standardized evaluation framework and expose the actual drawbacks in complex video reasoning task.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07956</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 17:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MM-IFEngine: Towards Multimodal Instruction Following</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07957</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.07957.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengyuan Ding, Shenxi Wu, Xiangyu Zhao, Yuhang Zang, Haodong Duan, Xiaoyi Dong, Pan Zhang, Yuhang Cao, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Instruction Following (IF) ability measures how well Multi-modal Large Language Models (MLLMs) understand exactly what users are telling them and whether they are doing it right. Existing multimodal instruction following training data is scarce, the benchmarks are simple with atomic instructions, and the evaluation strategies are imprecise for tasks demanding exact output constraints. To address this, we present MM-IFEngine, an effective pipeline to generate high-quality image-instruction pairs. Our MM-IFEngine pipeline yields large-scale, diverse, and high-quality training data MM-IFInstruct-23k, which is suitable for Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) and extended as MM-IFDPO-23k for Direct Preference Optimization (DPO). We further introduce MM-IFEval, a challenging and diverse multi-modal instruction-following benchmark that includes (1) both compose-level constraints for output responses and perception-level constraints tied to the input images, and (2) a comprehensive evaluation pipeline incorporating both rule-based assessment and judge model. We conduct SFT and DPO experiments and demonstrate that fine-tuning MLLMs on MM-IFInstruct-23k and MM-IFDPO-23k achieves notable gains on various IF benchmarks, such as MM-IFEval (+10.2%), MIA (+7.6%), and IFEval (+12.3%). The full data and evaluation code will be released on https://github.com/SYuan03/MM-IFEngine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07957</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 17:59:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VisualCloze: A Universal Image Generation Framework via Visual   In-Context Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07960</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.07960.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhong-Yu Li, Ruoyi Du, Juncheng Yan, Le Zhuo, Zhen Li, Peng Gao, Zhanyu Ma, Ming-Ming Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in diffusion models significantly advances various image generation tasks. However, the current mainstream approach remains focused on building task-specific models, which have limited efficiency when supporting a wide range of different needs. While universal models attempt to address this limitation, they face critical challenges, including generalizable task instruction, appropriate task distributions, and unified architectural design. To tackle these challenges, we propose VisualCloze, a universal image generation framework, which supports a wide range of in-domain tasks, generalization to unseen ones, unseen unification of multiple tasks, and reverse generation. Unlike existing methods that rely on language-based task instruction, leading to task ambiguity and weak generalization, we integrate visual in-context learning, allowing models to identify tasks from visual demonstrations. Meanwhile, the inherent sparsity of visual task distributions hampers the learning of transferable knowledge across tasks. To this end, we introduce Graph200K, a graph-structured dataset that establishes various interrelated tasks, enhancing task density and transferable knowledge. Furthermore, we uncover that our unified image generation formulation shared a consistent objective with image infilling, enabling us to leverage the strong generative priors of pre-trained infilling models without modifying the architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07960</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 17:59:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C3PO: Critical-Layer, Core-Expert, Collaborative Pathway Optimization   for Test-Time Expert Re-Mixing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07964</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.07964.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongyang Li, Ziyue Li, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) Large Language Models (LLMs) suffer from severely sub-optimal expert pathways-our study reveals that naive expert selection learned from pretraining leaves a surprising 10-20% accuracy gap for improvement. Motivated by this observation, we develop a novel class of test-time optimization methods to re-weight or "re-mixing" the experts in different layers jointly for each test sample. Since the test sample's ground truth is unknown, we propose to optimize a surrogate objective defined by the sample's "successful neighbors" from a reference set of samples. We introduce three surrogates and algorithms based on mode-finding, kernel regression, and the average loss of similar reference samples/tasks. To reduce the cost of optimizing whole pathways, we apply our algorithms merely to the core experts' mixing weights in critical layers, which enjoy similar performance but save significant computation. This leads to "Critical-Layer, Core-Expert, Collaborative Pathway Optimization (C3PO)". We apply C3PO to two recent MoE LLMs and examine it on six widely-used benchmarks. It consistently improves the base model by 7-15% in accuracy and outperforms widely used test-time learning baselines, e.g., in-context learning and prompt/prefix tuning, by a large margin. Moreover, C3PO enables MoE LLMs with 1-3B active parameters to outperform LLMs of 7-9B parameters, hence improving MoE's advantages on efficiency. Our thorough ablation study further sheds novel insights on achieving test-time improvement on MoE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07964</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MineWorld: a Real-Time and Open-Source Interactive World Model on   Minecraft</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08388</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.08388.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junliang Guo, Yang Ye, Tianyu He, Haoyu Wu, Yushu Jiang, Tim Pearce, Jiang Bian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; World modeling is a crucial task for enabling intelligent agents to effectively interact with humans and operate in dynamic environments. In this work, we propose MineWorld, a real-time interactive world model on Minecraft, an open-ended sandbox game which has been utilized as a common testbed for world modeling. MineWorld is driven by a visual-action autoregressive Transformer, which takes paired game scenes and corresponding actions as input, and generates consequent new scenes following the actions. Specifically, by transforming visual game scenes and actions into discrete token ids with an image tokenizer and an action tokenizer correspondingly, we consist the model input with the concatenation of the two kinds of ids interleaved. The model is then trained with next token prediction to learn rich representations of game states as well as the conditions between states and actions simultaneously. In inference, we develop a novel parallel decoding algorithm that predicts the spatial redundant tokens in each frame at the same time, letting models in different scales generate 4 to 7 frames per second and enabling real-time interactions with game players. In evaluation, we propose new metrics to assess not only visual quality but also the action following capacity when generating new scenes, which is crucial for a world model. Our comprehensive evaluation shows the efficacy of MineWorld, outperforming SoTA open-sourced diffusion based world models significantly. The code and model have been released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08388</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 09:41:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genius: A Generalizable and Purely Unsupervised Self-Training Framework   For Advanced Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08672</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.08672.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fangzhi Xu, Hang Yan, Chang Ma, Haiteng Zhao, Qiushi Sun, Kanzhi Cheng, Junxian He, Jun Liu, Zhiyong Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Advancing LLM reasoning skills has captivated wide interest. However, current post-training techniques rely heavily on supervisory signals, such as outcome supervision or auxiliary reward models, which face the problem of scalability and high annotation costs. This motivates us to enhance LLM reasoning without the need for external supervision. We introduce a generalizable and purely unsupervised self-training framework, named Genius. Without external auxiliary, Genius requires to seek the optimal response sequence in a stepwise manner and optimize the LLM. To explore the potential steps and exploit the optimal ones, Genius introduces a stepwise foresight re-sampling strategy to sample and estimate the step value by simulating future outcomes. Further, we recognize that the unsupervised setting inevitably induces the intrinsic noise and uncertainty. To provide a robust optimization, we propose an advantage-calibrated optimization (ACO) loss function to mitigate estimation inconsistencies. Combining these techniques together, Genius provides an advanced initial step towards self-improve LLM reasoning with general queries and without supervision, revolutionizing reasoning scaling laws given the vast availability of general queries. The code will be released at https://github.com/xufangzhi/Genius.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08672</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 16:26:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seaweed-7B: Cost-Effective Training of Video Generation Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08685</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.08685.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Team Seawead, Ceyuan Yang, Zhijie Lin, Yang Zhao, Shanchuan Lin, Zhibei Ma, Haoyuan Guo, Hao Chen, Lu Qi, Sen Wang, Feng Cheng, Feilong Zuo Xuejiao Zeng, Ziyan Yang, Fangyuan Kong, Zhiwu Qing, Fei Xiao, Meng Wei, Tuyen Hoang, Siyu Zhang, Peihao Zhu, Qi Zhao, Jiangqiao Yan, Liangke Gui, Sheng Bi, Jiashi Li, Yuxi Ren, Rui Wang, Huixia Li, Xuefeng Xiao, Shu Liu, Feng Ling, Heng Zhang, Houmin Wei, Huafeng Kuang, Jerry Duncan, Junda Zhang, Junru Zheng, Li Sun, Manlin Zhang, Renfei Sun, Xiaobin Zhuang, Xiaojie Li, Xin Xia, Xuyan Chi, Yanghua Peng, Yuping Wang, Yuxuan Wang, Zhongkai Zhao, Zhuo Chen, Zuquan Song, Zhenheng Yang, Jiashi Feng, Jianchao Yang, Lu Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 122&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This technical report presents a cost-efficient strategy for training a video generation foundation model. We present a mid-sized research model with approximately 7 billion parameters (7B) called Seaweed-7B trained from scratch using 665,000 H100 GPU hours. Despite being trained with moderate computational resources, Seaweed-7B demonstrates highly competitive performance compared to contemporary video generation models of much larger size. Design choices are especially crucial in a resource-constrained setting. This technical report highlights the key design decisions that enhance the performance of the medium-sized diffusion model. Empirically, we make two observations: (1) Seaweed-7B achieves performance comparable to, or even surpasses, larger models trained on substantially greater GPU resources, and (2) our model, which exhibits strong generalization ability, can be effectively adapted across a wide range of downstream applications either by lightweight fine-tuning or continue training. See the project page at https://seaweed.video/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08685</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 16:46:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GigaTok: Scaling Visual Tokenizers to 3 Billion Parameters for   Autoregressive Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08736</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.08736.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianwei Xiong, Jun Hao Liew, Zilong Huang, Jiashi Feng, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In autoregressive (AR) image generation, visual tokenizers compress images into compact discrete latent tokens, enabling efficient training of downstream autoregressive models for visual generation via next-token prediction. While scaling visual tokenizers improves image reconstruction quality, it often degrades downstream generation quality -- a challenge not adequately addressed in existing literature. To address this, we introduce GigaTok, the first approach to simultaneously improve image reconstruction, generation, and representation learning when scaling visual tokenizers. We identify the growing complexity of latent space as the key factor behind the reconstruction vs. generation dilemma. To mitigate this, we propose semantic regularization, which aligns tokenizer features with semantically consistent features from a pre-trained visual encoder. This constraint prevents excessive latent space complexity during scaling, yielding consistent improvements in both reconstruction and downstream autoregressive generation. Building on semantic regularization, we explore three key practices for scaling tokenizers:(1) using 1D tokenizers for better scalability, (2) prioritizing decoder scaling when expanding both encoder and decoder, and (3) employing entropy loss to stabilize training for billion-scale tokenizers. By scaling to 3 space billion parameters, GigaTok achieves state-of-the-art performance in reconstruction, downstream AR generation, and downstream AR representation quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08736</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterative Self-Training for Code Generation via Reinforced Re-Ranking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09643</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.09643.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nikita Sorokin, Ivan Sedykh, Valentin Malykh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating high-quality code that solves complex programming tasks is challenging, especially with current decoder-based models that produce highly stochastic outputs. In code generation, even minor errors can easily break the entire solution. Leveraging multiple sampled solutions can significantly improve the overall output quality.   One effective way to enhance code generation is by pairing a code generation model with a reranker model, which selects the best solution from the generated samples. We propose a novel iterative self-training approach for self-training reranker models using Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO), aimed at improving both reranking accuracy and the overall code generation process. Unlike traditional PPO approaches, where the focus is on optimizing a generative model with a reward model, our approach emphasizes the development of a robust reward/reranking model. This model improves the quality of generated code through reranking and addresses problems and errors that the reward model might overlook during PPO alignment with the reranker. Our method iteratively refines the training dataset by re-evaluating outputs, identifying high-scoring negative examples, and incorporating them into the training loop, that boosting model performance.   Our evaluation on the MultiPL-E dataset demonstrates that our 13.4B parameter model outperforms a 33B model in code generation quality while being three times faster. Moreover, it achieves performance comparable to GPT-4 and surpasses it in one programming language.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09643</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2025 16:34:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FUSION: Fully Integration of Vision-Language Representations for Deep   Cross-Modal Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09925</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.09925.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zheng Liu, Mengjie Liu, Jingzhou Chen, Jingwei Xu, Bin Cui, Conghui He, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce FUSION, a family of multimodal large language models (MLLMs) with a fully vision-language alignment and integration paradigm. Unlike existing methods that primarily rely on late-stage modality interaction during LLM decoding, our approach achieves deep, dynamic integration throughout the entire processing pipeline. To this end, we propose Text-Guided Unified Vision Encoding, incorporating textual information in vision encoding to achieve pixel-level integration. We further design Context-Aware Recursive Alignment Decoding that recursively aggregates visual features conditioned on textual context during decoding, enabling fine-grained, question-level semantic integration. To guide feature mapping and mitigate modality discrepancies, we develop Dual-Supervised Semantic Mapping Loss. Additionally, we construct a Synthesized Language-Driven Question-Answer (QA) dataset through a new data synthesis method, prioritizing high-quality QA pairs to optimize text-guided feature integration. Building on these foundations, we train FUSION at two scales-3B, 8B-and demonstrate that our full-modality integration approach significantly outperforms existing methods with only 630 vision tokens. Notably, FUSION 3B surpasses Cambrian-1 8B and Florence-VL 8B on most benchmarks. FUSION 3B continues to outperform Cambrian-1 8B even when limited to 300 vision tokens. Our ablation studies show that FUSION outperforms LLaVA-NeXT on over half of the benchmarks under same configuration without dynamic resolution, highlighting the effectiveness of our approach. We release our code, model weights, and dataset. https://github.com/starriver030515/FUSION&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09925</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 06:33:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heimdall: test-time scaling on the generative verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10337</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.10337.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenlei Shi, Xing Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; An AI system can create and maintain knowledge only to the extent that it can verify that knowledge itself. Recent work on long Chain-of-Thought reasoning has demonstrated great potential of LLMs on solving competitive problems, but their verification ability remains to be weak and not sufficiently investigated. In this paper, we propose Heimdall, the long CoT verification LLM that can accurately judge the correctness of solutions. With pure reinforcement learning, we boost the verification accuracy from 62.5% to 94.5% on competitive math problems. By scaling with repeated sampling, the accuracy further increases to 97.5%. Through human evaluation, Heimdall demonstrates impressive generalization capabilities, successfully detecting most issues in challenging math proofs, the type of which is not included during training. Furthermore, we propose Pessimistic Verification to extend the functionality of Heimdall to scaling up the problem solving. It calls Heimdall to judge the solutions from a solver model and based on the pessimistic principle, selects the most likely correct solution with the least uncertainty. Taking DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-32B as the solver model, Pessimistic Verification improves the solution accuracy on AIME2025 from 54.2% to 70.0% with 16x compute budget and to 83.3% with more compute budget. With the stronger solver Gemini 2.5 Pro, the score reaches 93.0%. Finally, we prototype an automatic knowledge discovery system, a ternary system where one poses questions, another provides solutions, and the third verifies the solutions. Using the data synthesis work NuminaMath for the first two components, Heimdall effectively identifies problematic records within the dataset and reveals that nearly half of the data is flawed, which interestingly aligns with the recent ablation studies from NuminaMath.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10337</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 15:46:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InternVL3: Exploring Advanced Training and Test-Time Recipes for   Open-Source Multimodal Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10479</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.10479.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinguo Zhu, Weiyun Wang, Zhe Chen, Zhaoyang Liu, Shenglong Ye, Lixin Gu, Yuchen Duan, Hao Tian, Weijie Su, Jie Shao, Zhangwei Gao, Erfei Cui, Yue Cao, Yangzhou Liu, Weiye Xu, Hao Li, Jiahao Wang, Han Lv, Dengnian Chen, Songze Li, Yinan He, Tan Jiang, Jiapeng Luo, Yi Wang, Conghui He, Botian Shi, Xingcheng Zhang, Wenqi Shao, Junjun He, Yingtong Xiong, Wenwen Qu, Peng Sun, Penglong Jiao, Lijun Wu, Kaipeng Zhang, Huipeng Deng, Jiaye Ge, Kai Chen, Limin Wang, Min Dou, Lewei Lu, Xizhou Zhu, Tong Lu, Dahua Lin, Yu Qiao, Jifeng Dai, Wenhai Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 250&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce InternVL3, a significant advancement in the InternVL series featuring a native multimodal pre-training paradigm. Rather than adapting a text-only large language model (LLM) into a multimodal large language model (MLLM) that supports visual inputs, InternVL3 jointly acquires multimodal and linguistic capabilities from both diverse multimodal data and pure-text corpora during a single pre-training stage. This unified training paradigm effectively addresses the complexities and alignment challenges commonly encountered in conventional post-hoc training pipelines for MLLMs. To further improve performance and scalability, InternVL3 incorporates variable visual position encoding (V2PE) to support extended multimodal contexts, employs advanced post-training techniques such as supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and mixed preference optimization (MPO), and adopts test-time scaling strategies alongside an optimized training infrastructure. Extensive empirical evaluations demonstrate that InternVL3 delivers superior performance across a wide range of multi-modal tasks. In particular, InternVL3-78B achieves a score of 72.2 on the MMMU benchmark, setting a new state-of-the-art among open-source MLLMs. Its capabilities remain highly competitive with leading proprietary models, including ChatGPT-4o, Claude 3.5 Sonnet, and Gemini 2.5 Pro, while also maintaining strong pure-language proficiency. In pursuit of open-science principles, we will publicly release both the training data and model weights to foster further research and development in next-generation MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10479</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 17:59:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>xVerify: Efficient Answer Verifier for Reasoning Model Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10481</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.10481.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ding Chen, Qingchen Yu, Pengyuan Wang, Wentao Zhang, Bo Tang, Feiyu Xiong, Xinchi Li, Minchuan Yang, Zhiyu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 84&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the release of the o1 model by OpenAI, reasoning models adopting slow thinking strategies have gradually emerged. As the responses generated by such models often include complex reasoning, intermediate steps, and self-reflection, existing evaluation methods are often inadequate. They struggle to determine whether the LLM output is truly equivalent to the reference answer, and also have difficulty identifying and extracting the final answer from long, complex responses. To address this issue, we propose xVerify, an efficient answer verifier for reasoning model evaluations. xVerify demonstrates strong capability in equivalence judgment, enabling it to effectively determine whether the answers produced by reasoning models are equivalent to reference answers across various types of objective questions. To train and evaluate xVerify, we construct the VAR dataset by collecting question-answer pairs generated by multiple LLMs across various datasets, leveraging multiple reasoning models and challenging evaluation sets designed specifically for reasoning model assessment. A multi-round annotation process is employed to ensure label accuracy. Based on the VAR dataset, we train multiple xVerify models of different scales. In evaluation experiments conducted on both the test set and generalization set, all xVerify models achieve overall F1 scores and accuracy exceeding 95\%. Notably, the smallest variant, xVerify-0.5B-I, outperforms all evaluation methods except GPT-4o, while xVerify-3B-Ib surpasses GPT-4o in overall performance. These results validate the effectiveness and generalizability of xVerify.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10481</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 17:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Instruction and Reasoning Data shape Post-Training: Data Quality   through the Lens of Layer-wise Gradients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10766</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.10766.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Li, Yanhong Li, Ziyue Li, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As the post-training of large language models (LLMs) advances from instruction-following to complex reasoning tasks, understanding how different data affect finetuning dynamics remains largely unexplored. In this paper, we present a spectral analysis of layer-wise gradients induced by low/high-quality instruction and reasoning data for LLM post-training. Our analysis reveals that widely-studied metrics for data evaluation, e.g., IFD, InsTag, Difficulty, and Reward, can be explained and unified by spectral properties computed from gradients' singular value decomposition (SVD). Specifically, higher-quality data are usually associated with lower nuclear norms and higher effective ranks. Notably, effective rank exhibits better robustness and resolution than nuclear norm in capturing subtle quality differences. For example, reasoning data achieves substantially higher effective ranks than instruction data, implying richer gradient structures on more complex tasks. Our experiments also highlight that models within the same family share similar gradient patterns regardless of their sizes, whereas different model families diverge significantly. Providing a unified view on the effects of data quality across instruction and reasoning data, this work illuminates the interplay between data quality and training stability, shedding novel insights into developing better data exploration strategies for post-training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10766</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 23:53:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-Teaming: Multi-Turn Jailbreaks and Defenses with Adaptive Multi-Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13203</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.13203.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Salman Rahman, Liwei Jiang, James Shiffer, Genglin Liu, Sheriff Issaka, Md Rizwan Parvez, Hamid Palangi, Kai-Wei Chang, Yejin Choi, Saadia Gabriel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-turn interactions with language models (LMs) pose critical safety risks, as harmful intent can be strategically spread across exchanges. Yet, the vast majority of prior work has focused on single-turn safety, while adaptability and diversity remain among the key challenges of multi-turn red-teaming. To address these challenges, we present X-Teaming, a scalable framework that systematically explores how seemingly harmless interactions escalate into harmful outcomes and generates corresponding attack scenarios. X-Teaming employs collaborative agents for planning, attack optimization, and verification, achieving state-of-the-art multi-turn jailbreak effectiveness and diversity with success rates up to 98.1% across representative leading open-weight and closed-source models. In particular, X-Teaming achieves a 96.2% attack success rate against the latest Claude 3.7 Sonnet model, which has been considered nearly immune to single-turn attacks. Building on X-Teaming, we introduce XGuard-Train, an open-source multi-turn safety training dataset that is 20x larger than the previous best resource, comprising 30K interactive jailbreaks, designed to enable robust multi-turn safety alignment for LMs. Our work offers essential tools and insights for mitigating sophisticated conversational attacks, advancing the multi-turn safety of LMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13203</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 16:11:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seedream 3.0 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11346</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.11346.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Gao, Lixue Gong, Qiushan Guo, Xiaoxia Hou, Zhichao Lai, Fanshi Li, Liang Li, Xiaochen Lian, Chao Liao, Liyang Liu, Wei Liu, Yichun Shi, Shiqi Sun, Yu Tian, Zhi Tian, Peng Wang, Rui Wang, Xuanda Wang, Xun Wang, Ye Wang, Guofeng Wu, Jie Wu, Xin Xia, Xuefeng Xiao, Zhonghua Zhai, Xinyu Zhang, Qi Zhang, Yuwei Zhang, Shijia Zhao, Jianchao Yang, Weilin Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Seedream 3.0, a high-performance Chinese-English bilingual image generation foundation model. We develop several technical improvements to address existing challenges in Seedream 2.0, including alignment with complicated prompts, fine-grained typography generation, suboptimal visual aesthetics and fidelity, and limited image resolutions. Specifically, the advancements of Seedream 3.0 stem from improvements across the entire pipeline, from data construction to model deployment. At the data stratum, we double the dataset using a defect-aware training paradigm and a dual-axis collaborative data-sampling framework. Furthermore, we adopt several effective techniques such as mixed-resolution training, cross-modality RoPE, representation alignment loss, and resolution-aware timestep sampling in the pre-training phase. During the post-training stage, we utilize diversified aesthetic captions in SFT, and a VLM-based reward model with scaling, thereby achieving outputs that well align with human preferences. Furthermore, Seedream 3.0 pioneers a novel acceleration paradigm. By employing consistent noise expectation and importance-aware timestep sampling, we achieve a 4 to 8 times speedup while maintaining image quality. Seedream 3.0 demonstrates significant improvements over Seedream 2.0: it enhances overall capabilities, in particular for text-rendering in complicated Chinese characters which is important to professional typography generation. In addition, it provides native high-resolution output (up to 2K), allowing it to generate images with high visual quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11346</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 16:19:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReTool: Reinforcement Learning for Strategic Tool Use in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11536</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.11536.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiazhan Feng, Shijue Huang, Xingwei Qu, Ge Zhang, Yujia Qin, Baoquan Zhong, Chengquan Jiang, Jinxin Chi, Wanjun Zhong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While reasoning models (e.g., DeepSeek R1) trained with reinforcement learning (RL), excel in textual reasoning, they struggle in scenarios requiring structured problem-solving, such as geometric reasoning, concise computation, or complex equation solving-areas where computational tools like code interpreters (CI) demonstrate distinct advantages. To bridge this gap, we propose ReTool, which enhances long-form reasoning with tool-integrated learning, including two key features: (1) dynamic interleaving of real-time code execution within natural language reasoning processes, and (2) an automated RL paradigm that allows policy rollouts with multi-turn real-time code execution and teaches the model in learning when and how to invoke tools based on outcome feedback. ReTool employs a systematic training framework, beginning with synthetic cold-start data generation to produce code-augmented long-form reasoning traces for fine-tuning base models. Subsequent RL training leverages task outcomes as rewards to iteratively refine the model's tool use strategy, enabling autonomous discovery of optimal tool invocation patterns without human priors. Experiments on the challenging MATH Olympiad benchmark AIME demonstrate ReTool's superiority: Our 32B model achieves 67% accuracy with 400 training steps, outperforming text-based RL baseline (40% accuracy, 1080 steps) in efficiency and performance. Remarkably, ReTool-32B attains 72.5% accuracy in extended settings, surpassing OpenAI's o1-preview by 27.9%. Further analysis reveals emergent behaviors such as code self-correction, signaling an ''aha moment'' in which the model autonomously masters adaptive tool use. These findings highlight the promise of outcome-driven tool integration for advancing complex mathematical reasoning and offer new insights into hybrid neuro-symbolic systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11536</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 18:10:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NodeRAG: Structuring Graph-based RAG with Heterogeneous Nodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11544</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.11544.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyang Xu, Haojie Zheng, Chengze Li, Haoxiang Chen, Yixin Liu, Ruoxi Chen, Lichao Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) empowers large language models to access external and private corpus, enabling factually consistent responses in specific domains. By exploiting the inherent structure of the corpus, graph-based RAG methods further enrich this process by building a knowledge graph index and leveraging the structural nature of graphs. However, current graph-based RAG approaches seldom prioritize the design of graph structures. Inadequately designed graph not only impede the seamless integration of diverse graph algorithms but also result in workflow inconsistencies and degraded performance. To further unleash the potential of graph for RAG, we propose NodeRAG, a graph-centric framework introducing heterogeneous graph structures that enable the seamless and holistic integration of graph-based methodologies into the RAG workflow. By aligning closely with the capabilities of LLMs, this framework ensures a fully cohesive and efficient end-to-end process. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate that NodeRAG exhibits performance advantages over previous methods, including GraphRAG and LightRAG, not only in indexing time, query time, and storage efficiency but also in delivering superior question-answering performance on multi-hop benchmarks and open-ended head-to-head evaluations with minimal retrieval tokens. Our GitHub repository could be seen at https://github.com/Terry-Xu-666/NodeRAG.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11544</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 18:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BitNet b1.58 2B4T Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12285</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.12285.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuming Ma, Hongyu Wang, Shaohan Huang, Xingxing Zhang, Ying Hu, Ting Song, Yan Xia, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce BitNet b1.58 2B4T, the first open-source, native 1-bit Large Language Model (LLM) at the 2-billion parameter scale. Trained on a corpus of 4 trillion tokens, the model has been rigorously evaluated across benchmarks covering language understanding, mathematical reasoning, coding proficiency, and conversational ability. Our results demonstrate that BitNet b1.58 2B4T achieves performance on par with leading open-weight, full-precision LLMs of similar size, while offering significant advantages in computational efficiency, including substantially reduced memory footprint, energy consumption, and decoding latency. To facilitate further research and adoption, the model weights are released via Hugging Face along with open-source inference implementations for both GPU and CPU architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12285</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 17:51:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WORLDMEM: Long-term Consistent World Simulation with Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12369</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.12369.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeqi Xiao, Yushi Lan, Yifan Zhou, Wenqi Ouyang, Shuai Yang, Yanhong Zeng, Xingang Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; World simulation has gained increasing popularity due to its ability to model virtual environments and predict the consequences of actions. However, the limited temporal context window often leads to failures in maintaining long-term consistency, particularly in preserving 3D spatial consistency. In this work, we present WorldMem, a framework that enhances scene generation with a memory bank consisting of memory units that store memory frames and states (e.g., poses and timestamps). By employing a memory attention mechanism that effectively extracts relevant information from these memory frames based on their states, our method is capable of accurately reconstructing previously observed scenes, even under significant viewpoint or temporal gaps. Furthermore, by incorporating timestamps into the states, our framework not only models a static world but also captures its dynamic evolution over time, enabling both perception and interaction within the simulated world. Extensive experiments in both virtual and real scenarios validate the effectiveness of our approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12369</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 17:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ToolRL: Reward is All Tool Learning Needs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13958</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.13958.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng Qian, Emre Can Acikgoz, Qi He, Hongru Wang, Xiusi Chen, Dilek Hakkani-Tür, Gokhan Tur, Heng Ji&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current Large Language Models (LLMs) often undergo supervised fine-tuning (SFT) to acquire tool use capabilities. However, SFT struggles to generalize to unfamiliar or complex tool use scenarios. Recent advancements in reinforcement learning (RL), particularly with R1-like models, have demonstrated promising reasoning and generalization abilities. Yet, reward design for tool use presents unique challenges: multiple tools may be invoked with diverse parameters, and coarse-grained reward signals, such as answer matching, fail to offer the finegrained feedback required for effective learning. In this work, we present the first comprehensive study on reward design for tool selection and application tasks within the RL paradigm. We systematically explore a wide range of reward strategies, analyzing their types, scales, granularity, and temporal dynamics. Building on these insights, we propose a principled reward design tailored for tool use tasks and apply it to train LLMs using Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO). Empirical evaluations across diverse benchmarks demonstrate that our approach yields robust, scalable, and stable training, achieving a 17% improvement over base models and a 15% gain over SFT models. These results highlight the critical role of thoughtful reward design in enhancing the tool use capabilities and generalization performance of LLMs. All the codes are released to facilitate future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13958</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 21:45:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Packing Input Frame Context in Next-Frame Prediction Models for Video   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12626</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.12626.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lvmin Zhang, Maneesh Agrawala&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present a neural network structure, FramePack, to train next-frame (or next-frame-section) prediction models for video generation. The FramePack compresses input frames to make the transformer context length a fixed number regardless of the video length. As a result, we are able to process a large number of frames using video diffusion with computation bottleneck similar to image diffusion. This also makes the training video batch sizes significantly higher (batch sizes become comparable to image diffusion training). We also propose an anti-drifting sampling method that generates frames in inverted temporal order with early-established endpoints to avoid exposure bias (error accumulation over iterations). Finally, we show that existing video diffusion models can be finetuned with FramePack, and their visual quality may be improved because the next-frame prediction supports more balanced diffusion schedulers with less extreme flow shift timesteps.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12626</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 04:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antidistillation Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13146</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.13146.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yash Savani, Asher Trockman, Zhili Feng, Avi Schwarzschild, Alexander Robey, Marc Finzi, J. Zico Kolter&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Frontier models that generate extended reasoning traces inadvertently produce rich token sequences that can facilitate model distillation. Recognizing this vulnerability, model owners may seek sampling strategies that limit the effectiveness of distillation without compromising model performance. Antidistillation sampling provides exactly this capability. By strategically modifying a model's next-token probability distribution, antidistillation sampling poisons reasoning traces, rendering them significantly less effective for distillation while preserving the model's practical utility. For further details, see https://antidistillation.com.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13146</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 17:54:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLIMB: CLustering-based Iterative Data Mixture Bootstrapping for   Language Model Pre-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13161</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.13161.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shizhe Diao, Yu Yang, Yonggan Fu, Xin Dong, Dan Su, Markus Kliegl, Zijia Chen, Peter Belcak, Yoshi Suhara, Hongxu Yin, Mostofa Patwary, Yingyan, Lin, Jan Kautz, Pavlo Molchanov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 87&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Pre-training datasets are typically collected from web content and lack inherent domain divisions. For instance, widely used datasets like Common Crawl do not include explicit domain labels, while manually curating labeled datasets such as The Pile is labor-intensive. Consequently, identifying an optimal pre-training data mixture remains a challenging problem, despite its significant benefits for pre-training performance. To address these challenges, we propose CLustering-based Iterative Data Mixture Bootstrapping (CLIMB), an automated framework that discovers, evaluates, and refines data mixtures in a pre-training setting. Specifically, CLIMB embeds and clusters large-scale datasets in a semantic space and then iteratively searches for optimal mixtures using a smaller proxy model and a predictor. When continuously trained on 400B tokens with this mixture, our 1B model exceeds the state-of-the-art Llama-3.2-1B by 2.0%. Moreover, we observe that optimizing for a specific domain (e.g., Social Sciences) yields a 5% improvement over random sampling. Finally, we introduce ClimbLab, a filtered 1.2-trillion-token corpus with 20 clusters as a research playground, and ClimbMix, a compact yet powerful 400-billion-token dataset designed for efficient pre-training that delivers superior performance under an equal token budget. We analyze the final data mixture, elucidating the characteristics of an optimal data mixture. Our data is available at: https://research.nvidia.com/labs/lpr/climb/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13161</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 17:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generate, but Verify: Reducing Hallucination in Vision-Language Models   with Retrospective Resampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13169</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.13169.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tsung-Han Wu, Heekyung Lee, Jiaxin Ge, Joseph E. Gonzalez, Trevor Darrell, David M. Chan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language Models (VLMs) excel at visual understanding but often suffer from visual hallucinations, where they generate descriptions of nonexistent objects, actions, or concepts, posing significant risks in safety-critical applications. Existing hallucination mitigation methods typically follow one of two paradigms: generation adjustment, which modifies decoding behavior to align text with visual inputs, and post-hoc verification, where external models assess and correct outputs. While effective, generation adjustment methods often rely on heuristics and lack correction mechanisms, while post-hoc verification is complicated, typically requiring multiple models and tending to reject outputs rather than refine them. In this work, we introduce REVERSE, a unified framework that integrates hallucination-aware training with on-the-fly self-verification. By leveraging a new hallucination-verification dataset containing over 1.3M semi-synthetic samples, along with a novel inference-time retrospective resampling technique, our approach enables VLMs to both detect hallucinations during generation and dynamically revise those hallucinations. Our evaluations show that REVERSE achieves state-of-the-art hallucination reduction, outperforming the best existing methods by up to 12% on CHAIR-MSCOCO and 28% on HaloQuest. Our dataset, model, and code are available at: https://reverse-vlm.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13169</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 17:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perception Encoder: The best visual embeddings are not at the output of   the network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13181</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.13181.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daniel Bolya, Po-Yao Huang, Peize Sun, Jang Hyun Cho, Andrea Madotto, Chen Wei, Tengyu Ma, Jiale Zhi, Jathushan Rajasegaran, Hanoona Rasheed, Junke Wang, Marco Monteiro, Hu Xu, Shiyu Dong, Nikhila Ravi, Daniel Li, Piotr Dollár, Christoph Feichtenhofer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Perception Encoder (PE), a state-of-the-art encoder for image and video understanding trained via simple vision-language learning. Traditionally, vision encoders have relied on a variety of pretraining objectives, each tailored to specific downstream tasks such as classification, captioning, or localization. Surprisingly, after scaling our carefully tuned image pretraining recipe and refining with our robust video data engine, we find that contrastive vision-language training alone can produce strong, general embeddings for all of these downstream tasks. There is only one caveat: these embeddings are hidden within the intermediate layers of the network. To draw them out, we introduce two alignment methods, language alignment for multimodal language modeling, and spatial alignment for dense prediction. Together with the core contrastive checkpoint, our PE family of models achieves state-of-the-art performance on a wide variety of tasks, including zero-shot image and video classification and retrieval; document, image, and video Q&amp;A; and spatial tasks such as detection, depth estimation, and tracking. To foster further research, we are releasing our models, code, and a novel dataset of synthetically and human-annotated videos.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13181</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MIG: Automatic Data Selection for Instruction Tuning by Maximizing   Information Gain in Semantic Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13835</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.13835.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yicheng Chen, Yining Li, Kai Hu, Zerun Ma, Haochen Ye, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data quality and diversity are key to the construction of effective instruction-tuning datasets. % With the increasing availability of open-source instruction-tuning datasets, it is advantageous to automatically select high-quality and diverse subsets from a vast amount of data. % Existing methods typically prioritize instance quality and use heuristic rules to maintain diversity. % However, this absence of a comprehensive view of the entire collection often leads to suboptimal results. % Moreover, heuristic rules generally focus on distance or clustering within the embedding space, which fails to accurately capture the intent of complex instructions in the semantic space. % To bridge this gap, we propose a unified method for quantifying the information content of datasets. This method models the semantic space by constructing a label graph and quantifies diversity based on the distribution of information within the graph. % Based on such a measurement, we further introduce an efficient sampling method that selects data samples iteratively to Maximize the Information Gain (MIG) in semantic space. % Experiments on various datasets and base models demonstrate that MIG consistently outperforms state-of-the-art methods. % Notably, the model fine-tuned with 5\% Tulu3 data sampled by MIG achieves comparable performance to the official SFT model trained on the full dataset, with improvements of +5.73\% on AlpacaEval and +6.89\% on Wildbench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13835</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 17:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Reinforcement Learning Really Incentivize Reasoning Capacity in   LLMs Beyond the Base Model?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13837</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.13837.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Yue, Zhiqi Chen, Rui Lu, Andrew Zhao, Zhaokai Wang, Yang Yue, Shiji Song, Gao Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 116&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has recently demonstrated notable success in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of LLMs, particularly in mathematics and programming tasks. It is widely believed that RLVR enables LLMs to continuously self-improve, thus acquiring novel reasoning abilities that exceed corresponding base models' capacity. In this study, however, we critically re-examines this assumption by measuring the pass@k metric with large values of k to explore the reasoning capability boundary of the models across a wide range of model families and benchmarks. Surprisingly, the RL does not, in fact, elicit fundamentally new reasoning patterns. While RL-trained models outperform their base models at smaller values of k (\eg, k=1), base models can achieve a comparable or even higher pass@k score compared to their RL counterparts at large k values. The reasoning paths generated by RL-trained models are already included in the base models' sampling distribution, suggesting that most reasoning abilities manifested in RL-trained models are already obtained by base models. Further analysis shows that RL training boosts the performance by biasing the model's output distribution toward paths that are more likely to yield rewards, therefore sampling correct responses more efficiently. But this also results in a narrower reasoning capability boundary compared to base models. Similar results are observed in visual reasoning tasks trained with RLVR. Moreover, we find that distillation can genuinely introduce new knowledge into the model, different from RLVR. These findings underscore a critical limitation of RLVR in advancing LLM reasoning abilities which requires us to fundamentally rethink the impact of RL training in reasoning LLMs and the need of a better paradigm. Project Page: https://limit-of-RLVR.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13837</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamID: High-Fidelity and Fast diffusion-based Face Swapping via   Triplet ID Group Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14509</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.14509.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fulong Ye, Miao Hua, Pengze Zhang, Xinghui Li, Qichao Sun, Songtao Zhao, Qian He, Xinglong Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce DreamID, a diffusion-based face swapping model that achieves high levels of ID similarity, attribute preservation, image fidelity, and fast inference speed. Unlike the typical face swapping training process, which often relies on implicit supervision and struggles to achieve satisfactory results. DreamID establishes explicit supervision for face swapping by constructing Triplet ID Group data, significantly enhancing identity similarity and attribute preservation. The iterative nature of diffusion models poses challenges for utilizing efficient image-space loss functions, as performing time-consuming multi-step sampling to obtain the generated image during training is impractical. To address this issue, we leverage the accelerated diffusion model SD Turbo, reducing the inference steps to a single iteration, enabling efficient pixel-level end-to-end training with explicit Triplet ID Group supervision. Additionally, we propose an improved diffusion-based model architecture comprising SwapNet, FaceNet, and ID Adapter. This robust architecture fully unlocks the power of the Triplet ID Group explicit supervision. Finally, to further extend our method, we explicitly modify the Triplet ID Group data during training to fine-tune and preserve specific attributes, such as glasses and face shape. Extensive experiments demonstrate that DreamID outperforms state-of-the-art methods in terms of identity similarity, pose and expression preservation, and image fidelity. Overall, DreamID achieves high-quality face swapping results at 512*512 resolution in just 0.6 seconds and performs exceptionally well in challenging scenarios such as complex lighting, large angles, and occlusions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14509</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 06:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Reason under Off-Policy Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14945</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.14945.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianhao Yan, Yafu Li, Zican Hu, Zhi Wang, Ganqu Cui, Xiaoye Qu, Yu Cheng, Yue Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 77&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large reasoning models (LRMs) demonstrate that sophisticated behaviors such as multi-step reasoning and self-reflection can emerge via reinforcement learning (RL) with simple rule-based rewards. However, existing zero-RL approaches are inherently ``on-policy'', limiting learning to a model's own outputs and failing to acquire reasoning abilities beyond its initial capabilities. We introduce LUFFY (Learning to reason Under oFF-policY guidance), a framework that augments zero-RL with off-policy reasoning traces. LUFFY dynamically balances imitation and exploration by combining off-policy demonstrations with on-policy rollouts during training. Notably, we propose policy shaping via regularized importance sampling to avoid superficial and rigid imitation during mixed-policy training. Remarkably, LUFFY achieves an over +7.0 average gain across six math benchmarks and an advantage of over +6.2 points in out-of-distribution tasks. It also substantially surpasses imitation-based supervised fine-tuning (SFT), particularly in generalization. Analysis shows LUFFY not only imitates effectively but also explores beyond demonstrations, offering a scalable path to train generalizable reasoning models with off-policy guidance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14945</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 08:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kuwain 1.5B: An Arabic SLM via Language Injection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15120</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15120.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Khalil Hennara, Sara Chrouf, Mohamed Motaism Hamed, Zeina Aldallal, Omar Hadid, Safwan AlModhayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 113&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Enhancing existing models with new knowledge is a crucial aspect of AI development. This paper introduces a novel method for integrating a new language into a large language model (LLM). Our approach successfully incorporates a previously unseen target language into an existing LLM without compromising its prior knowledge. We trained a tiny model with 1.5 billion parameters named Kuwain by injecting the Arabic language into a small open-source model mainly trained in English. Our method demonstrates significant improvements in Arabic language performance, with an average 8% improvement across various benchmarks, while retaining the model's existing knowledge with a minimum amount of the original model's data. This offers a cost-effective alternative to training a comprehensive model in both English and Arabic. The results highlight the potential for efficient, targeted language model expansion without extensive retraining or resource-intensive processes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15120</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 14:17:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlowReasoner: Reinforcing Query-Level Meta-Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15257</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15257.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongcheng Gao, Yue Liu, Yufei He, Longxu Dou, Chao Du, Zhijie Deng, Bryan Hooi, Min Lin, Tianyu Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper proposes a query-level meta-agent named FlowReasoner to automate the design of query-level multi-agent systems, i.e., one system per user query. Our core idea is to incentivize a reasoning-based meta-agent via external execution feedback. Concretely, by distilling DeepSeek R1, we first endow the basic reasoning ability regarding the generation of multi-agent systems to FlowReasoner. Then, we further enhance it via reinforcement learning (RL) with external execution feedback. A multi-purpose reward is designed to guide the RL training from aspects of performance, complexity, and efficiency. In this manner, FlowReasoner is enabled to generate a personalized multi-agent system for each user query via deliberative reasoning. Experiments on both engineering and competition code benchmarks demonstrate the superiority of FlowReasoner. Remarkably, it surpasses o1-mini by 10.52% accuracy across three benchmarks. The code is available at https://github.com/sail-sg/FlowReasoner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15257</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 17:35:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eagle 2.5: Boosting Long-Context Post-Training for Frontier   Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15271</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15271.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guo Chen, Zhiqi Li, Shihao Wang, Jindong Jiang, Yicheng Liu, Lidong Lu, De-An Huang, Wonmin Byeon, Matthieu Le, Tuomas Rintamaki, Tyler Poon, Max Ehrlich, Tuomas Rintamaki, Tyler Poon, Tong Lu, Limin Wang, Bryan Catanzaro, Jan Kautz, Andrew Tao, Zhiding Yu, Guilin Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 65&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Eagle 2.5, a family of frontier vision-language models (VLMs) for long-context multimodal learning. Our work addresses the challenges in long video comprehension and high-resolution image understanding, introducing a generalist framework for both tasks. The proposed training framework incorporates Automatic Degrade Sampling and Image Area Preservation, two techniques that preserve contextual integrity and visual details. The framework also includes numerous efficiency optimizations in the pipeline for long-context data training. Finally, we propose Eagle-Video-110K, a novel dataset that integrates both story-level and clip-level annotations, facilitating long-video understanding. Eagle 2.5 demonstrates substantial improvements on long-context multimodal benchmarks, providing a robust solution to the limitations of existing VLMs. Notably, our best model Eagle 2.5-8B achieves 72.4% on Video-MME with 512 input frames, matching the results of top-tier commercial model such as GPT-4o and large-scale open-source models like Qwen2.5-VL-72B and InternVL2.5-78B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15271</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 17:57:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VisuLogic: A Benchmark for Evaluating Visual Reasoning in Multi-modal   Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15279</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15279.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weiye Xu, Jiahao Wang, Weiyun Wang, Zhe Chen, Wengang Zhou, Aijun Yang, Lewei Lu, Houqiang Li, Xiaohua Wang, Xizhou Zhu, Wenhai Wang, Jifeng Dai, Jinguo Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 71&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual reasoning is a core component of human intelligence and a critical capability for advanced multimodal models. Yet current reasoning evaluations of multimodal large language models (MLLMs) often rely on text descriptions and allow language-based reasoning shortcuts, failing to measure genuine vision-centric reasoning. To address this, we introduce VisuLogic: a benchmark of 1,000 human-verified problems across six categories (e.g., quantitative shifts, spatial relations, attribute comparisons). These various types of questions can be evaluated to assess the visual reasoning capabilities of MLLMs from multiple perspectives. We evaluate leading MLLMs on this benchmark and analyze their results to identify common failure modes. Most models score below 30% accuracy-only slightly above the 25% random baseline and far below the 51.4% achieved by humans-revealing significant gaps in visual reasoning. Furthermore, we provide a supplementary training dataset and a reinforcement-learning baseline to support further progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15279</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 17:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Understanding Camera Motions in Any Video</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15376</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15376.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiqiu Lin, Siyuan Cen, Daniel Jiang, Jay Karhade, Hewei Wang, Chancharik Mitra, Tiffany Ling, Yuhan Huang, Sifan Liu, Mingyu Chen, Rushikesh Zawar, Xue Bai, Yilun Du, Chuang Gan, Deva Ramanan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 145&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce CameraBench, a large-scale dataset and benchmark designed to assess and improve camera motion understanding. CameraBench consists of ~3,000 diverse internet videos, annotated by experts through a rigorous multi-stage quality control process. One of our contributions is a taxonomy of camera motion primitives, designed in collaboration with cinematographers. We find, for example, that some motions like "follow" (or tracking) require understanding scene content like moving subjects. We conduct a large-scale human study to quantify human annotation performance, revealing that domain expertise and tutorial-based training can significantly enhance accuracy. For example, a novice may confuse zoom-in (a change of intrinsics) with translating forward (a change of extrinsics), but can be trained to differentiate the two. Using CameraBench, we evaluate Structure-from-Motion (SfM) and Video-Language Models (VLMs), finding that SfM models struggle to capture semantic primitives that depend on scene content, while VLMs struggle to capture geometric primitives that require precise estimation of trajectories. We then fine-tune a generative VLM on CameraBench to achieve the best of both worlds and showcase its applications, including motion-augmented captioning, video question answering, and video-text retrieval. We hope our taxonomy, benchmark, and tutorials will drive future efforts towards the ultimate goal of understanding camera motions in any video.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15376</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 18:34:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Adaptive Parallel Reasoning with Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15466</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15466.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiayi Pan, Xiuyu Li, Long Lian, Charlie Snell, Yifei Zhou, Adam Yala, Trevor Darrell, Kurt Keutzer, Alane Suhr&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling inference-time computation has substantially improved the reasoning capabilities of language models. However, existing methods have significant limitations: serialized chain-of-thought approaches generate overly long outputs, leading to increased latency and exhausted context windows, while parallel methods such as self-consistency suffer from insufficient coordination, resulting in redundant computations and limited performance gains. To address these shortcomings, we propose Adaptive Parallel Reasoning (APR), a novel reasoning framework that enables language models to orchestrate both serialized and parallel computations end-to-end. APR generalizes existing reasoning methods by enabling adaptive multi-threaded inference using spawn() and join() operations. A key innovation is our end-to-end reinforcement learning strategy, optimizing both parent and child inference threads to enhance task success rate without requiring predefined reasoning structures. Experiments on the Countdown reasoning task demonstrate significant benefits of APR: (1) higher performance within the same context window (83.4% vs. 60.0% at 4k context); (2) superior scalability with increased computation (80.1% vs. 66.6% at 20k total tokens); (3) improved accuracy at equivalent latency (75.2% vs. 57.3% at approximately 5,000ms). APR represents a step towards enabling language models to autonomously optimize their reasoning processes through adaptive allocation of computation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15466</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 22:29:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bitter Lesson Learned from 2,000+ Multilingual Benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15521</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15521.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minghao Wu, Weixuan Wang, Sinuo Liu, Huifeng Yin, Xintong Wang, Yu Zhao, Chenyang Lyu, Longyue Wang, Weihua Luo, Kaifu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language models (LLMs) continue to advance in linguistic capabilities, robust multilingual evaluation has become essential for promoting equitable technological progress. This position paper examines over 2,000 multilingual (non-English) benchmarks from 148 countries, published between 2021 and 2024, to evaluate past, present, and future practices in multilingual benchmarking. Our findings reveal that, despite significant investments amounting to tens of millions of dollars, English remains significantly overrepresented in these benchmarks. Additionally, most benchmarks rely on original language content rather than translations, with the majority sourced from high-resource countries such as China, India, Germany, the UK, and the USA. Furthermore, a comparison of benchmark performance with human judgments highlights notable disparities. STEM-related tasks exhibit strong correlations with human evaluations (0.70 to 0.85), while traditional NLP tasks like question answering (e.g., XQuAD) show much weaker correlations (0.11 to 0.30). Moreover, translating English benchmarks into other languages proves insufficient, as localized benchmarks demonstrate significantly higher alignment with local human judgments (0.68) than their translated counterparts (0.47). This underscores the importance of creating culturally and linguistically tailored benchmarks rather than relying solely on translations. Through this comprehensive analysis, we highlight six key limitations in current multilingual evaluation practices, propose the guiding principles accordingly for effective multilingual benchmarking, and outline five critical research directions to drive progress in the field. Finally, we call for a global collaborative effort to develop human-aligned benchmarks that prioritize real-world applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15521</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 01:47:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tina: Tiny Reasoning Models via LoRA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15777</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.15777.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shangshang Wang, Julian Asilis, Ömer Faruk Akgül, Enes Burak Bilgin, Ollie Liu, Willie Neiswanger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; How cost-effectively can strong reasoning abilities be achieved in language models? Driven by this fundamental question, we present Tina, a family of tiny reasoning models achieved with high cost-efficiency. Notably, Tina demonstrates that substantial reasoning performance can be developed using only minimal resources, by applying parameter-efficient updates during reinforcement learning (RL), using low-rank adaptation (LoRA), to an already tiny 1.5B parameter base model. This minimalist approach produces models that achieve reasoning performance which is competitive with, and sometimes surpasses, SOTA RL reasoning models built upon the same base model. Crucially, this is achieved at a tiny fraction of the computational post-training cost employed by existing SOTA models. In fact, the best Tina model achieves a &gt;20\% reasoning performance increase and 43.33\% Pass@1 accuracy on AIME24, at only \$9 USD post-training and evaluation cost (i.e., an estimated 260x cost reduction). Our work reveals the surprising effectiveness of efficient RL reasoning via LoRA. We validate this across multiple open-source reasoning datasets and various ablation settings starting with a single, fixed set of hyperparameters. Furthermore, we hypothesize that this effectiveness and efficiency stem from LoRA rapidly adapting the model to the structural format of reasoning rewarded by RL, while largely preserving the base model's underlying knowledge. In service of accessibility and open research, we fully open-source all code, training logs, and model weights \&amp; checkpoints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15777</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 10:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiveCC: Learning Video LLM with Streaming Speech Transcription at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16030</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.16030.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Joya Chen, Ziyun Zeng, Yiqi Lin, Wei Li, Zejun Ma, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent video large language models (Video LLMs) often depend on costly human annotations or proprietary model APIs (e.g., GPT-4o) to produce training data, which limits their training at scale. In this paper, we explore large-scale training for Video LLM with cheap automatic speech recognition (ASR) transcripts. Specifically, we propose a novel streaming training approach that densely interleaves the ASR words and video frames according to their timestamps. Compared to previous studies in vision-language representation with ASR, our method naturally fits the streaming characteristics of ASR, thus enabling the model to learn temporally-aligned, fine-grained vision-language modeling. To support the training algorithm, we introduce a data production pipeline to process YouTube videos and their closed captions (CC, same as ASR), resulting in Live-CC-5M dataset for pre-training and Live-WhisperX-526K dataset for high-quality supervised fine-tuning (SFT). Remarkably, even without SFT, the ASR-only pre-trained LiveCC-7B-Base model demonstrates competitive general video QA performance and exhibits a new capability in real-time video commentary. To evaluate this, we carefully design a new LiveSports-3K benchmark, using LLM-as-a-judge to measure the free-form commentary. Experiments show our final LiveCC-7B-Instruct model can surpass advanced 72B models (Qwen2.5-VL-72B-Instruct, LLaVA-Video-72B) in commentary quality even working in a real-time mode. Meanwhile, it achieves state-of-the-art results at the 7B/8B scale on popular video QA benchmarks such as VideoMME and OVOBench, demonstrating the broad generalizability of our approach. All resources of this paper have been released at https://showlab.github.io/livecc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16030</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 16:52:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Describe Anything: Detailed Localized Image and Video Captioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16072</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.16072.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Long Lian, Yifan Ding, Yunhao Ge, Sifei Liu, Hanzi Mao, Boyi Li, Marco Pavone, Ming-Yu Liu, Trevor Darrell, Adam Yala, Yin Cui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating detailed and accurate descriptions for specific regions in images and videos remains a fundamental challenge for vision-language models. We introduce the Describe Anything Model (DAM), a model designed for detailed localized captioning (DLC). DAM preserves both local details and global context through two key innovations: a focal prompt, which ensures high-resolution encoding of targeted regions, and a localized vision backbone, which integrates precise localization with its broader context. To tackle the scarcity of high-quality DLC data, we propose a Semi-supervised learning (SSL)-based Data Pipeline (DLC-SDP). DLC-SDP starts with existing segmentation datasets and expands to unlabeled web images using SSL. We introduce DLC-Bench, a benchmark designed to evaluate DLC without relying on reference captions. DAM sets new state-of-the-art on 7 benchmarks spanning keyword-level, phrase-level, and detailed multi-sentence localized image and video captioning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16072</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 17:51:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PHYBench: Holistic Evaluation of Physical Perception and Reasoning in   Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16074</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.16074.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shi Qiu, Shaoyang Guo, Zhuo-Yang Song, Yunbo Sun, Zeyu Cai, Jiashen Wei, Tianyu Luo, Yixuan Yin, Haoxu Zhang, Yi Hu, Chenyang Wang, Chencheng Tang, Haoling Chang, Qi Liu, Ziheng Zhou, Tianyu Zhang, Jingtian Zhang, Zhangyi Liu, Minghao Li, Yuku Zhang, Boxuan Jing, Xianqi Yin, Yutong Ren, Zizhuo Fu, Weike Wang, Xudong Tian, Anqi Lv, Laifu Man, Jianxiang Li, Feiyu Tao, Qihua Sun, Zhou Liang, Yushu Mu, Zhongxuan Li, Jing-Jun Zhang, Shutao Zhang, Xiaotian Li, Xingqi Xia, Jiawei Lin, Zheyu Shen, Jiahang Chen, Qiuhao Xiong, Binran Wang, Fengyuan Wang, Ziyang Ni, Bohan Zhang, Fan Cui, Changkun Shao, Qing-Hong Cao, Ming-xing Luo, Muhan Zhang, Hua Xing Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce PHYBench, a novel, high-quality benchmark designed for evaluating reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs) in physical contexts. PHYBench consists of 500 meticulously curated physics problems based on real-world physical scenarios, designed to assess the ability of models to understand and reason about realistic physical processes. Covering mechanics, electromagnetism, thermodynamics, optics, modern physics, and advanced physics, the benchmark spans difficulty levels from high school exercises to undergraduate problems and Physics Olympiad challenges. Additionally, we propose the Expression Edit Distance (EED) Score, a novel evaluation metric based on the edit distance between mathematical expressions, which effectively captures differences in model reasoning processes and results beyond traditional binary scoring methods. We evaluate various LLMs on PHYBench and compare their performance with human experts. Our results reveal that even state-of-the-art reasoning models significantly lag behind human experts, highlighting their limitations and the need for improvement in complex physical reasoning scenarios. Our benchmark results and dataset are publicly available at https://phybench-official.github.io/phybench-demo/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16074</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 17:53:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TTRL: Test-Time Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16084</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.16084.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxin Zuo, Kaiyan Zhang, Shang Qu, Li Sheng, Xuekai Zhu, Biqing Qi, Youbang Sun, Ganqu Cui, Ning Ding, Bowen Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 96&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper investigates Reinforcement Learning (RL) on data without explicit labels for reasoning tasks in Large Language Models (LLMs). The core challenge of the problem is reward estimation during inference while not having access to ground-truth information. While this setting appears elusive, we find that common practices in Test-Time Scaling (TTS), such as majority voting, yield surprisingly effective rewards suitable for driving RL training. In this work, we introduce Test-Time Reinforcement Learning (TTRL), a novel method for training LLMs using RL on unlabeled data. TTRL enables self-evolution of LLMs by utilizing the priors in the pre-trained models. Our experiments demonstrate that TTRL consistently improves performance across a variety of tasks and models. Notably, TTRL boosts the pass@1 performance of Qwen-2.5-Math-7B by approximately 159% on the AIME 2024 with only unlabeled test data. Furthermore, although TTRL is only supervised by the Maj@N metric, TTRL has demonstrated performance to consistently surpass the upper limit of the initial model, and approach the performance of models trained directly on test data with ground-truth labels. Our experimental findings validate the general effectiveness of TTRL across various tasks, and highlight TTRL's potential for broader tasks and domains. GitHub: https://github.com/PRIME-RL/TTRL&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16084</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork R1V2: Multimodal Hybrid Reinforcement Learning for Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16656</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.16656.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chris, Yichen Wei, Yi Peng, Xiaokun Wang, Weijie Qiu, Wei Shen, Tianyidan Xie, Jiangbo Pei, Jianhao Zhang, Yunzhuo Hao, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Skywork R1V2, a next-generation multimodal reasoning model and a major leap forward from its predecessor, Skywork R1V. At its core, R1V2 introduces a hybrid reinforcement learning paradigm that harmonizes reward-model guidance with rule-based strategies, thereby addressing the long-standing challenge of balancing sophisticated reasoning capabilities with broad generalization. To further enhance training efficiency, we propose the Selective Sample Buffer (SSB) mechanism, which effectively counters the ``Vanishing Advantages'' dilemma inherent in Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) by prioritizing high-value samples throughout the optimization process. Notably, we observe that excessive reinforcement signals can induce visual hallucinations--a phenomenon we systematically monitor and mitigate through calibrated reward thresholds throughout the training process. Empirical results affirm the exceptional capability of R1V2, with benchmark-leading performances such as 62.6 on OlympiadBench, 79.0 on AIME2024, 63.6 on LiveCodeBench, and 74.0 on MMMU. These results underscore R1V2's superiority over existing open-source models and demonstrate significant progress in closing the performance gap with premier proprietary systems, including Gemini 2.5 and OpenAI o4-mini. The Skywork R1V2 model weights have been publicly released to promote openness and reproducibility https://huggingface.co/Skywork/Skywork-R1V2-38B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16656</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 12:24:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paper2Code: Automating Code Generation from Scientific Papers in Machine   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17192</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17192.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minju Seo, Jinheon Baek, Seongyun Lee, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 95&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the rapid growth of machine learning research, corresponding code implementations are often unavailable, making it slow and labor-intensive for researchers to reproduce results and build upon prior work. In the meantime, recent Large Language Models (LLMs) excel at understanding scientific documents and generating high-quality code. Inspired by this, we introduce PaperCoder, a multi-agent LLM framework that transforms machine learning papers into functional code repositories. PaperCoder operates in three stages: planning, where it constructs a high-level roadmap, designs the system architecture with diagrams, identifies file dependencies, and generates configuration files; analysis, which focuses on interpreting implementation-specific details; and generation, where modular, dependency-aware code is produced. Moreover, each phase is instantiated through a set of specialized agents designed to collaborate effectively across the pipeline. We then evaluate PaperCoder on generating code implementations from machine learning papers based on both model-based and human evaluations, specifically from the original paper authors, with author-released repositories as ground truth if available. Our results demonstrate the effectiveness of PaperCoder in creating high-quality, faithful implementations. Furthermore, it consistently shows strengths in the recently released PaperBench benchmark, surpassing strong baselines by substantial margins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17192</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 01:57:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking the Modality Barrier: Universal Embedding Learning with   Multimodal LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17432</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17432.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tiancheng Gu, Kaicheng Yang, Ziyong Feng, Xingjun Wang, Yanzhao Zhang, Dingkun Long, Yingda Chen, Weidong Cai, Jiankang Deng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Contrastive Language-Image Pre-training (CLIP) framework has become a widely used approach for multimodal representation learning, particularly in image-text retrieval and clustering. However, its efficacy is constrained by three key limitations: (1) text token truncation, (2) isolated image-text encoding, and (3) deficient compositionality due to bag-of-words behavior. While recent Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have demonstrated significant advances in generalized vision-language understanding, their potential for learning transferable multimodal representations remains underexplored.In this work, we present UniME (Universal Multimodal Embedding), a novel two-stage framework that leverages MLLMs to learn discriminative representations for diverse downstream tasks. In the first stage, we perform textual discriminative knowledge distillation from a powerful LLM-based teacher model to enhance the embedding capability of the MLLM\'s language component. In the second stage, we introduce hard negative enhanced instruction tuning to further advance discriminative representation learning. Specifically, we initially mitigate false negative contamination and then sample multiple hard negatives per instance within each batch, forcing the model to focus on challenging samples. This approach not only improves discriminative power but also enhances instruction-following ability in downstream tasks. We conduct extensive experiments on the MMEB benchmark and multiple retrieval tasks, including short and long caption retrieval and compositional retrieval. Results demonstrate that UniME achieves consistent performance improvement across all tasks, exhibiting superior discriminative and compositional capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17432</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 10:51:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RefVNLI: Towards Scalable Evaluation of Subject-driven Text-to-image   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17502</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17502.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aviv Slobodkin, Hagai Taitelbaum, Yonatan Bitton, Brian Gordon, Michal Sokolik, Nitzan Bitton Guetta, Almog Gueta, Royi Rassin, Itay Laish, Dani Lischinski, Idan Szpektor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Subject-driven text-to-image (T2I) generation aims to produce images that align with a given textual description, while preserving the visual identity from a referenced subject image. Despite its broad downstream applicability -- ranging from enhanced personalization in image generation to consistent character representation in video rendering -- progress in this field is limited by the lack of reliable automatic evaluation. Existing methods either assess only one aspect of the task (i.e., textual alignment or subject preservation), misalign with human judgments, or rely on costly API-based evaluation. To address this, we introduce RefVNLI, a cost-effective metric that evaluates both textual alignment and subject preservation in a single prediction. Trained on a large-scale dataset derived from video-reasoning benchmarks and image perturbations, RefVNLI outperforms or matches existing baselines across multiple benchmarks and subject categories (e.g., Animal, Object), achieving up to 6.4-point gains in textual alignment and 8.5-point gains in subject consistency. It also excels with lesser-known concepts, aligning with human preferences at over 87\% accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17502</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 12:44:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step1X-Edit: A Practical Framework for General Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17761</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.17761.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiyu Liu, Yucheng Han, Peng Xing, Fukun Yin, Rui Wang, Wei Cheng, Jiaqi Liao, Yingming Wang, Honghao Fu, Chunrui Han, Guopeng Li, Yuang Peng, Quan Sun, Jingwei Wu, Yan Cai, Zheng Ge, Ranchen Ming, Lei Xia, Xianfang Zeng, Yibo Zhu, Binxing Jiao, Xiangyu Zhang, Gang Yu, Daxin Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 83&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In recent years, image editing models have witnessed remarkable and rapid development. The recent unveiling of cutting-edge multimodal models such as GPT-4o and Gemini2 Flash has introduced highly promising image editing capabilities. These models demonstrate an impressive aptitude for fulfilling a vast majority of user-driven editing requirements, marking a significant advancement in the field of image manipulation. However, there is still a large gap between the open-source algorithm with these closed-source models. Thus, in this paper, we aim to release a state-of-the-art image editing model, called Step1X-Edit, which can provide comparable performance against the closed-source models like GPT-4o and Gemini2 Flash. More specifically, we adopt the Multimodal LLM to process the reference image and the user's editing instruction. A latent embedding has been extracted and integrated with a diffusion image decoder to obtain the target image. To train the model, we build a data generation pipeline to produce a high-quality dataset. For evaluation, we develop the GEdit-Bench, a novel benchmark rooted in real-world user instructions. Experimental results on GEdit-Bench demonstrate that Step1X-Edit outperforms existing open-source baselines by a substantial margin and approaches the performance of leading proprietary models, thereby making significant contributions to the field of image editing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17761</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 17:25:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BitNet v2: Native 4-bit Activations with Hadamard Transformation for   1-bit LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18415</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.18415.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongyu Wang, Shuming Ma, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Efficient deployment of 1-bit Large Language Models (LLMs) is hindered by activation outliers, which complicate quantization to low bit-widths. We introduce BitNet v2, a novel framework enabling native 4-bit activation quantization for 1-bit LLMs. To tackle outliers in attention and feed-forward network activations, we propose H-BitLinear, a module applying an online Hadamard transformation prior to activation quantization. This transformation smooths sharp activation distributions into more Gaussian-like forms, suitable for low-bit representation. Experiments show BitNet v2 trained from scratch with 8-bit activations matches BitNet b1.58 performance. Crucially, BitNet v2 achieves minimal performance degradation when trained with native 4-bit activations, significantly reducing memory footprint and computational cost for batched inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18415</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 15:17:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning for Reasoning in Large Language Models with One   Training Example</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20571</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20571.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiping Wang, Qing Yang, Zhiyuan Zeng, Liliang Ren, Lucas Liu, Baolin Peng, Hao Cheng, Xuehai He, Kuan Wang, Jianfeng Gao, Weizhu Chen, Shuohang Wang, Simon Shaolei Du, Yelong Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We show that reinforcement learning with verifiable reward using one training example (1-shot RLVR) is effective in incentivizing the math reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). Applying RLVR to the base model Qwen2.5-Math-1.5B, we identify a single example that elevates model performance on MATH500 from 36.0% to 73.6%, and improves the average performance across six common mathematical reasoning benchmarks from 17.6% to 35.7%. This result matches the performance obtained using the 1.2k DeepScaleR subset (MATH500: 73.6%, average: 35.9%), which includes the aforementioned example. Similar substantial improvements are observed across various models (Qwen2.5-Math-7B, Llama3.2-3B-Instruct, DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-1.5B), RL algorithms (GRPO and PPO), and different math examples (many of which yield approximately 30% or greater improvement on MATH500 when employed as a single training example). In addition, we identify some interesting phenomena during 1-shot RLVR, including cross-domain generalization, increased frequency of self-reflection, and sustained test performance improvement even after the training accuracy has saturated, a phenomenon we term post-saturation generalization. Moreover, we verify that the effectiveness of 1-shot RLVR primarily arises from the policy gradient loss, distinguishing it from the "grokking" phenomenon. We also show the critical role of promoting exploration (e.g., by adding entropy loss with an appropriate coefficient) in 1-shot RLVR training. As a bonus, we observe that applying entropy loss alone, without any outcome reward, significantly enhances Qwen2.5-Math-1.5B's performance on MATH500 by 27.4%. These findings can inspire future work on RLVR data efficiency and encourage a re-examination of both recent progress and the underlying mechanisms in RLVR. Our code, model, and data are open source at https://github.com/ypwang61/One-Shot-RLVR&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20571</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 09:24:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReasonIR: Training Retrievers for Reasoning Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20595</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20595.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rulin Shao, Rui Qiao, Varsha Kishore, Niklas Muennighoff, Xi Victoria Lin, Daniela Rus, Bryan Kian Hsiang Low, Sewon Min, Wen-tau Yih, Pang Wei Koh, Luke Zettlemoyer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present ReasonIR-8B, the first retriever specifically trained for general reasoning tasks. Existing retrievers have shown limited gains on reasoning tasks, in part because existing training datasets focus on short factual queries tied to documents that straightforwardly answer them. We develop a synthetic data generation pipeline that, for each document, our pipeline creates a challenging and relevant query, along with a plausibly related but ultimately unhelpful hard negative. By training on a mixture of our synthetic data and existing public data, ReasonIR-8B achieves a new state-of-the-art of 29.9 nDCG@10 without reranker and 36.9 nDCG@10 with reranker on BRIGHT, a widely-used reasoning-intensive information retrieval (IR) benchmark. When applied to RAG tasks, ReasonIR-8B improves MMLU and GPQA performance by 6.4% and 22.6% respectively, relative to the closed-book baseline, outperforming other retrievers and search engines. In addition, ReasonIR-8B uses test-time compute more effectively: on BRIGHT, its performance consistently increases with longer and more information-rich rewritten queries; it continues to outperform other retrievers when combined with an LLM reranker. Our training recipe is general and can be easily extended to future LLMs; to this end, we open-source our code, data, and model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20595</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 09:49:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniversalRAG: Retrieval-Augmented Generation over Multiple Corpora with   Diverse Modalities and Granularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20734</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20734.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Woongyeong Yeo, Kangsan Kim, Soyeong Jeong, Jinheon Baek, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) has shown substantial promise in improving factual accuracy by grounding model responses with external knowledge relevant to queries. However, most existing RAG approaches are limited to a text-only corpus, and while recent efforts have extended RAG to other modalities such as images and videos, they typically operate over a single modality-specific corpus. In contrast, real-world queries vary widely in the type of knowledge they require, which a single type of knowledge source cannot address. To address this, we introduce UniversalRAG, a novel RAG framework designed to retrieve and integrate knowledge from heterogeneous sources with diverse modalities and granularities. Specifically, motivated by the observation that forcing all modalities into a unified representation space derived from a single combined corpus causes a modality gap, where the retrieval tends to favor items from the same modality as the query, we propose a modality-aware routing mechanism that dynamically identifies the most appropriate modality-specific corpus and performs targeted retrieval within it. Also, beyond modality, we organize each modality into multiple granularity levels, enabling fine-tuned retrieval tailored to the complexity and scope of the query. We validate UniversalRAG on 8 benchmarks spanning multiple modalities, showing its superiority over modality-specific and unified baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20734</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 13:18:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Leaderboard Illusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20879</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20879.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shivalika Singh, Yiyang Nan, Alex Wang, Daniel D'Souza, Sayash Kapoor, Ahmet Üstün, Sanmi Koyejo, Yuntian Deng, Shayne Longpre, Noah Smith, Beyza Ermis, Marzieh Fadaee, Sara Hooker&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Measuring progress is fundamental to the advancement of any scientific field. As benchmarks play an increasingly central role, they also grow more susceptible to distortion. Chatbot Arena has emerged as the go-to leaderboard for ranking the most capable AI systems. Yet, in this work we identify systematic issues that have resulted in a distorted playing field. We find that undisclosed private testing practices benefit a handful of providers who are able to test multiple variants before public release and retract scores if desired. We establish that the ability of these providers to choose the best score leads to biased Arena scores due to selective disclosure of performance results. At an extreme, we identify 27 private LLM variants tested by Meta in the lead-up to the Llama-4 release. We also establish that proprietary closed models are sampled at higher rates (number of battles) and have fewer models removed from the arena than open-weight and open-source alternatives. Both these policies lead to large data access asymmetries over time. Providers like Google and OpenAI have received an estimated 19.2% and 20.4% of all data on the arena, respectively. In contrast, a combined 83 open-weight models have only received an estimated 29.7% of the total data. We show that access to Chatbot Arena data yields substantial benefits; even limited additional data can result in relative performance gains of up to 112% on the arena distribution, based on our conservative estimates. Together, these dynamics result in overfitting to Arena-specific dynamics rather than general model quality. The Arena builds on the substantial efforts of both the organizers and an open community that maintains this valuable evaluation platform. We offer actionable recommendations to reform the Chatbot Arena's evaluation framework and promote fairer, more transparent benchmarking for the field&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20879</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 15:48:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
