<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:02:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>On the Use of Agentic Coding: An Empirical Study of Pull Requests on   GitHub</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14745</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14745.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Miku Watanabe, Hao Li, Yutaro Kashiwa, Brittany Reid, Hajimu Iida, Ahmed E. Hassan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly being integrated into software development processes. The ability to generate code and submit pull requests with minimal human intervention, through the use of autonomous AI agents, is poised to become a standard practice. However, little is known about the practical usefulness of these pull requests and the extent to which their contributions are accepted in real-world projects. In this paper, we empirically study 567 GitHub pull requests (PRs) generated using Claude Code, an agentic coding tool, across 157 diverse open-source projects. Our analysis reveals that developers tend to rely on agents for tasks such as refactoring, documentation, and testing. The results indicate that 83.8% of these agent-assisted PRs are eventually accepted and merged by project maintainers, with 54.9% of the merged PRs are integrated without further modification. The remaining 45.1% require additional changes benefit from human revisions, especially for bug fixes, documentation, and adherence to project-specific standards. These findings suggest that while agent-assisted PRs are largely acceptable, they still benefit from human oversight and refinement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14745</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 08:48:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>kh2d-solver: A Python Library for Idealized Two-Dimensional   Incompressible Kelvin-Helmholtz Instability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16080</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16080.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sandy H. S. Herho, Nurjanna J. Trilaksono, Faiz R. Fajary, Gandhi Napitupulu, Iwan P. Anwar, Faruq Khadami, Dasapta E. Irawan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present an open-source Python library for simulating two-dimensional incompressible Kelvin-Helmholtz instabilities in stratified shear flows. The solver employs a fractional-step projection method with spectral Poisson solution via Fast Sine Transform, achieving second-order spatial accuracy. Implementation leverages NumPy, SciPy, and Numba JIT compilation for efficient computation. Four canonical test cases explore Reynolds numbers 1000--5000 and Richardson numbers 0.1--0.3: classical shear layer, double shear configuration, rotating flow, and forced turbulence. Statistical analysis using Shannon entropy and complexity indices reveals that double shear layers achieve 2.8times higher mixing rates than forced turbulence despite lower Reynolds numbers. The solver runs efficiently on standard desktop hardware, with 384times192 grid simulations completing in approximately 31 minutes. Results demonstrate that mixing efficiency depends on instability generation pathways rather than intensity measures alone, challenging Richardson number-based parameterizations and suggesting refinements for subgrid-scale representation in climate models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16080</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 15:26:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Speech Understanding in Speech-Aware Language Models with GRPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16990</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16990.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Avishai Elmakies, Hagai Aronowitz, Nimrod Shabtay, Eli Schwartz, Ron Hoory, Avihu Dekel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce a Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO)-based method for training Speech-Aware Large Language Models (SALLMs) on open-format speech understanding tasks, such as Spoken Question Answering and Automatic Speech Translation. SALLMs have proven highly effective for speech understanding tasks. GRPO has recently gained traction for its efficiency in training LLMs, and prior work has explored its application to SALLMs, primarily in multiple-choice tasks. Building on this, we focus on open-format tasks that better reflect the generative abilities of the models. Our approach leverages GRPO with BLEU as the reward signal to optimize SALLMs, and we demonstrate empirically that it surpasses standard SFT across several key metrics. Finally, we explore the potential of incorporating off-policy samples within GRPO for these tasks, highlighting avenues for further improvement and further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16990</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 09:09:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ATLAS: Benchmarking and Adapting LLMs for Global Trade via Harmonized   Tariff Code Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18400</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18400.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pritish Yuvraj, Siva Devarakonda&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Accurate classification of products under the Harmonized Tariff Schedule (HTS) is a critical bottleneck in global trade, yet it has received little attention from the machine learning community. Misclassification can halt shipments entirely, with major postal operators suspending deliveries to the U.S. due to incomplete customs documentation. We introduce the first benchmark for HTS code classification, derived from the U.S. Customs Rulings Online Search System (CROSS). Evaluating leading LLMs, we find that our fine-tuned Atlas model (LLaMA-3.3-70B) achieves 40 percent fully correct 10-digit classifications and 57.5 percent correct 6-digit classifications, improvements of 15 points over GPT-5-Thinking and 27.5 points over Gemini-2.5-Pro-Thinking. Beyond accuracy, Atlas is roughly five times cheaper than GPT-5-Thinking and eight times cheaper than Gemini-2.5-Pro-Thinking, and can be self-hosted to guarantee data privacy in high-stakes trade and compliance workflows. While Atlas sets a strong baseline, the benchmark remains highly challenging, with only 40 percent 10-digit accuracy. By releasing both dataset and model, we aim to position HTS classification as a new community benchmark task and invite future work in retrieval, reasoning, and alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18400</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 20:32:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SimpleFold: Folding Proteins is Simpler than You Think</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18480</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18480.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuyang Wang, Jiarui Lu, Navdeep Jaitly, Josh Susskind, Miguel Angel Bautista&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Protein folding models have achieved groundbreaking results typically via a combination of integrating domain knowledge into the architectural blocks and training pipelines. Nonetheless, given the success of generative models across different but related problems, it is natural to question whether these architectural designs are a necessary condition to build performant models. In this paper, we introduce SimpleFold, the first flow-matching based protein folding model that solely uses general purpose transformer blocks. Protein folding models typically employ computationally expensive modules involving triangular updates, explicit pair representations or multiple training objectives curated for this specific domain. Instead, SimpleFold employs standard transformer blocks with adaptive layers and is trained via a generative flow-matching objective with an additional structural term. We scale SimpleFold to 3B parameters and train it on approximately 9M distilled protein structures together with experimental PDB data. On standard folding benchmarks, SimpleFold-3B achieves competitive performance compared to state-of-the-art baselines, in addition SimpleFold demonstrates strong performance in ensemble prediction which is typically difficult for models trained via deterministic reconstruction objectives. Due to its general-purpose architecture, SimpleFold shows efficiency in deployment and inference on consumer-level hardware. SimpleFold challenges the reliance on complex domain-specific architectures designs in protein folding, opening up an alternative design space for future progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18480</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lavida-O: Elastic Large Masked Diffusion Models for Unified Multimodal   Understanding and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19244</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19244.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shufan Li, Jiuxiang Gu, Kangning Liu, Zhe Lin, Zijun Wei, Aditya Grover, Jason Kuen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose Lavida-O, a unified Masked Diffusion Model (MDM) for multimodal understanding and generation. Unlike existing multimodal MDMs such as MMaDa and Muddit which only support simple image-level understanding tasks and low-resolution image generation, Lavida-O presents a single framework that enables image-level understanding, object grounding, image editing, and high-resolution (1024px) text-to-image synthesis. Lavida-O incorporates a novel Elastic Mixture-of-Transformers (Elastic-MoT) architecture that couples a lightweight generation branch with a larger understanding branch, supported by token compression, universal text conditioning and stratified sampling for efficient and high-quality generation. Lavida-O further incorporates planning and iterative self-reflection in image generation and editing tasks, seamlessly boosting generation quality with its understanding capabilities. Lavida-O achieves state-of-the-art performance on a wide range of benchmarks including RefCOCO object grounding, GenEval text-to-image generation, and ImgEdit image editing, outperforming existing autoregressive models and continuous diffusion models such as Qwen2.5-VL and FluxKontext-dev, while offering considerable speedup at inference. These advances establish Lavida-O as a new paradigm for scalable multimodal reasoning and generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19244</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:05:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLMs4All: A Review on Large Language Models for Research and   Applications in Academic Disciplines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19580</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19580.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanfang, Ye, Zheyuan Zhang, Tianyi Ma, Zehong Wang, Yiyang Li, Shifu Hou, Weixiang Sun, Kaiwen Shi, Yijun Ma, Wei Song, Ahmed Abbasi, Ying Cheng, Jane Cleland-Huang, Steven Corcelli, Patricia Culligan, Robert Goulding, Ming Hu, Ting Hua, John Lalor, Fang Liu, Tengfei Luo, Ed Maginn, Nuno Moniz, Jason Rohr, Brett Savoie, Daniel Slate, Tom Stapleford, Matthew Webber, Olaf Wiest, Johnny Zhang, Nitesh Chawla&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Cutting-edge Artificial Intelligence (AI) techniques keep reshaping our view of the world. For example, Large Language Models (LLMs) based applications such as ChatGPT have shown the capability of generating human-like conversation on extensive topics. Due to the impressive performance on a variety of language-related tasks (e.g., open-domain question answering, translation, and document summarization), one can envision the far-reaching impacts that can be brought by the LLMs with broader real-world applications (e.g., customer service, education and accessibility, and scientific discovery). Inspired by their success, this paper will offer an overview of state-of-the-art LLMs and their integration into a wide range of academic disciplines, including: (1) arts, letters, and law (e.g., history, philosophy, political science, arts and architecture, law), (2) economics and business (e.g., finance, economics, accounting, marketing), and (3) science and engineering (e.g., mathematics, physics and mechanical engineering, chemistry and chemical engineering, life sciences and bioengineering, earth sciences and civil engineering, computer science and electrical engineering). Integrating humanity and technology, in this paper, we will explore how LLMs are shaping research and practice in these fields, while also discussing key limitations, open challenges, and future directions in the era of generative AI. The review of how LLMs are engaged across disciplines-along with key observations and insights-can help researchers and practitioners interested in exploiting LLMs to advance their works in diverse real-world applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19580</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 21:09:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logics-Parsing Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19760</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19760.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangyang Chen, Shuzhao Li, Xiuwen Zhu, Yongfan Chen, Fan Yang, Cheng Fang, Lin Qu, Xiaoxiao Xu, Hu Wei, Minggang Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Vision-Language models (LVLM) have spurred significant progress in document parsing task. Compared to traditional pipeline-based methods, end-to-end paradigms have shown their excellence in converting PDF images into structured outputs through integrated Optical Character Recognition (OCR), table recognition, mathematical formula recognition and so on. However, the absence of explicit analytical stages for document layouts and reading orders limits the LVLM's capability in handling complex document types such as multi-column newspapers or posters. To address this limitation, we propose in this report Logics-Parsing: an end-to-end LVLM-based model augmented with reinforcement learning. Our model incorporates meticulously designed reward mechanisms to optimize complex layout analysis and reading order inference. In addition, we expand the model's versatility by incorporating diverse data types such as chemical formulas and handwritten Chinese characters into supervised fine-tuning. Finally, to enable rigorous evaluation of our approach, we introduce LogicsParsingBench, a curated set of 1,078 page-level PDF images spanning nine major categories and over twenty sub-categories, which will be released later. Comprehensive experiments conducted on LogicsParsingBench have validated the efficacy and State-of-the-art (SOTA) performance of our proposed model across diverse document analysis scenarios. Project Page: https://github.com/alibaba/Logics-Parsing&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19760</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 04:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SIM-CoT: Supervised Implicit Chain-of-Thought</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xilin Wei, Xiaoran Liu, Yuhang Zang, Xiaoyi Dong, Yuhang Cao, Jiaqi Wang, Xipeng Qiu, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Implicit Chain-of-Thought (CoT) methods present a promising, token-efficient alternative to explicit CoT reasoning in Large Language Models (LLMs), but a persistent performance gap has limited the application of implicit CoT. We identify a core latent instability issue by scaling the computational budget of implicit CoT approaches: as we increase the number of implicit reasoning tokens to enhance performance, the training process often becomes unstable and collapses. Our analysis reveals that this instability arises from the latent representations becoming homogeneous and losing their semantic diversity, a failure caused by insufficient step-level supervision in existing implicit CoT approaches. To address this issue, we propose SIM-CoT, a plug-and-play training module that introduces step-level supervision to stabilize and enrich the latent reasoning space. Specifically, SIM-CoT employs an auxiliary decoder during training to align each implicit token with its corresponding explicit reasoning step, ensuring that latent states capture distinct and meaningful information. The proposed auxiliary decoder is removed during inference, preserving the computational efficiency of implicit CoT methods with no added overhead. In addition, the auxiliary decoder affords interpretability of implicit reasoning by projecting each latent token onto an explicit reasoning vocabulary, enabling per-step visualization of semantic roles and diagnosis. SIM-CoT significantly enhances both the in-domain accuracy and out-of-domain stability of various implicit CoT methods, boosting baselines like Coconut by +8.2% on GPT-2 and CODI by +3.0% on LLaMA-3.1 8B. Demonstrating strong scalability, SIM-CoT also surpasses the explicit CoT baseline on GPT-2 by 2.1% with 2.3\times greater token efficiency, while substantially closing the performance gap on larger models like LLaMA-3.1 8B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20317</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:01:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video models are zero-shot learners and reasoners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20328</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20328.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Thaddäus Wiedemer, Yuxuan Li, Paul Vicol, Shixiang Shane Gu, Nick Matarese, Kevin Swersky, Been Kim, Priyank Jaini, Robert Geirhos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The remarkable zero-shot capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs) have propelled natural language processing from task-specific models to unified, generalist foundation models. This transformation emerged from simple primitives: large, generative models trained on web-scale data. Curiously, the same primitives apply to today's generative video models. Could video models be on a trajectory towards general-purpose vision understanding, much like LLMs developed general-purpose language understanding? We demonstrate that Veo 3 can solve a broad variety of tasks it wasn't explicitly trained for: segmenting objects, detecting edges, editing images, understanding physical properties, recognizing object affordances, simulating tool use, and more. These abilities to perceive, model, and manipulate the visual world enable early forms of visual reasoning like maze and symmetry solving. Veo's emergent zero-shot capabilities indicate that video models are on a path to becoming unified, generalist vision foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20328</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:17:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EmbeddingGemma: Powerful and Lightweight Text Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20354</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20354.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Henrique Schechter Vera, Sahil Dua, Biao Zhang, Daniel Salz, Ryan Mullins, Sindhu Raghuram Panyam, Sara Smoot, Iftekhar Naim, Joe Zou, Feiyang Chen, Daniel Cer, Alice Lisak, Min Choi, Lucas Gonzalez, Omar Sanseviero, Glenn Cameron, Ian Ballantyne, Kat Black, Kaifeng Chen, Weiyi Wang, Zhe Li, Gus Martins, Jinhyuk Lee, Mark Sherwood, Juyeong Ji, Renjie Wu, Jingxiao Zheng, Jyotinder Singh, Abheesht Sharma, Divya Sreepat, Aashi Jain, Adham Elarabawy, AJ Co, Andreas Doumanoglou, Babak Samari, Ben Hora, Brian Potetz, Dahun Kim, Enrique Alfonseca, Fedor Moiseev, Feng Han, Frank Palma Gomez, Gustavo Hernández Ábrego, Hesen Zhang, Hui Hui, Jay Han, Karan Gill, Ke Chen, Koert Chen, Madhuri Shanbhogue, Michael Boratko, Paul Suganthan, Sai Meher Karthik Duddu, Sandeep Mariserla, Setareh Ariafar, Shanfeng Zhang, Shijie Zhang, Simon Baumgartner, Sonam Goenka, Steve Qiu, Tanmaya Dabral, Trevor Walker, Vikram Rao, Waleed Khawaja, Wenlei Zhou, Xiaoqi Ren, Ye Xia, Yichang Chen, Yi-Ting Chen, Zhe Dong, Zhongli Ding, Francesco Visin, Gaël Liu, Jiageng Zhang, Kathleen Kenealy, Michelle Casbon, Ravin Kumar, Thomas Mesnard, Zach Gleicher, Cormac Brick, Olivier Lacombe, Adam Roberts, Yunhsuan Sung, Raphael Hoffmann, Tris Warkentin, Armand Joulin, Tom Duerig, Mojtaba Seyedhosseini&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce EmbeddingGemma, a new lightweight, open text embedding model based on the Gemma 3 language model family. Our innovative training recipe strategically captures knowledge from larger models via encoder-decoder initialization and geometric embedding distillation. We improve model robustness and expressiveness with a spread-out regularizer, and ensure generalizability by merging checkpoints from varied, optimized mixtures. Evaluated on the Massive Text Embedding Benchmark (MTEB) across multilingual, English, and code domains, EmbeddingGemma (300M) achieves state-of-the-art results. Notably, it outperforms prior top models, both proprietary and open, with fewer than 500M parameters, and provides performance comparable to models double its size, offering an exceptional performance-to-cost ratio. Remarkably, this lead persists when quantizing model weights or truncating embedding outputs. This makes EmbeddingGemma particularly well-suited for low-latency and high-throughput use cases such as on-device applications. We provide ablation studies exploring our key design choices. We release EmbeddingGemma to the community to promote further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20354</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:56:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhysCtrl: Generative Physics for Controllable and Physics-Grounded Video   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20358</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20358.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chen Wang, Chuhao Chen, Yiming Huang, Zhiyang Dou, Yuan Liu, Jiatao Gu, Lingjie Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing video generation models excel at producing photo-realistic videos from text or images, but often lack physical plausibility and 3D controllability. To overcome these limitations, we introduce PhysCtrl, a novel framework for physics-grounded image-to-video generation with physical parameters and force control. At its core is a generative physics network that learns the distribution of physical dynamics across four materials (elastic, sand, plasticine, and rigid) via a diffusion model conditioned on physics parameters and applied forces. We represent physical dynamics as 3D point trajectories and train on a large-scale synthetic dataset of 550K animations generated by physics simulators. We enhance the diffusion model with a novel spatiotemporal attention block that emulates particle interactions and incorporates physics-based constraints during training to enforce physical plausibility. Experiments show that PhysCtrl generates realistic, physics-grounded motion trajectories which, when used to drive image-to-video models, yield high-fidelity, controllable videos that outperform existing methods in both visual quality and physical plausibility. Project Page: https://cwchenwang.github.io/physctrl&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20358</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EditVerse: Unifying Image and Video Editing and Generation with   In-Context Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20360</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20360.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuan Ju, Tianyu Wang, Yuqian Zhou, He Zhang, Qing Liu, Nanxuan Zhao, Zhifei Zhang, Yijun Li, Yuanhao Cai, Shaoteng Liu, Daniil Pakhomov, Zhe Lin, Soo Ye Kim, Qiang Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in foundation models highlight a clear trend toward unification and scaling, showing emergent capabilities across diverse domains. While image generation and editing have rapidly transitioned from task-specific to unified frameworks, video generation and editing remain fragmented due to architectural limitations and data scarcity. In this work, we introduce EditVerse, a unified framework for image and video generation and editing within a single model. By representing all modalities, i.e., text, image, and video, as a unified token sequence, EditVerse leverages self-attention to achieve robust in-context learning, natural cross-modal knowledge transfer, and flexible handling of inputs and outputs with arbitrary resolutions and durations. To address the lack of video editing training data, we design a scalable data pipeline that curates 232K video editing samples and combines them with large-scale image and video datasets for joint training. Furthermore, we present EditVerseBench, the first benchmark for instruction-based video editing covering diverse tasks and resolutions. Extensive experiments and user studies demonstrate that EditVerse achieves state-of-the-art performance, surpassing existing open-source and commercial models, while exhibiting emergent editing and generation abilities across modalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20360</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
