<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:02:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Lost in the Mix: Evaluating LLM Understanding of Code-Switched Text</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14012</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.14012.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amr Mohamed, Yang Zhang, Michalis Vazirgiannis, Guokan Shang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Code-switching (CSW) is the act of alternating between two or more languages within a single discourse. This phenomenon is widespread in multilingual communities, and increasingly prevalent in online content, where users naturally mix languages in everyday communication. As a result, Large Language Models (LLMs), now central to content processing and generation, are frequently exposed to code-switched inputs. Given their widespread use, it is crucial to understand how LLMs process and reason about such mixed-language text. This paper presents a systematic evaluation of LLM comprehension under code-switching by generating CSW variants of established reasoning and comprehension benchmarks. While degradation is evident when foreign tokens disrupt English textx2013even under linguistic constraintsx2013embedding English into other languages often improves comprehension. Though prompting yields mixed results, fine-tuning offers a more stable path to degradation mitigation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14012</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 21:19:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent Operation and Maintenance and Prediction Model Optimization   for Improving Wind Power Generation Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16095</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16095.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xun Liu, Xiaobin Wu, Jiaqi He, Rajan Das Gupta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This study explores the effectiveness of predictive maintenance models and the optimization of intelligent Operation and Maintenance (O&amp;M) systems in improving wind power generation efficiency. Through qualitative research, structured interviews were conducted with five wind farm engineers and maintenance managers, each with extensive experience in turbine operations. Using thematic analysis, the study revealed that while predictive maintenance models effectively reduce downtime by identifying major faults, they often struggle with detecting smaller, gradual failures. Key challenges identified include false positives, sensor malfunctions, and difficulties in integrating new models with older turbine systems. Advanced technologies such as digital twins, SCADA systems, and condition monitoring have significantly enhanced turbine maintenance practices. However, these technologies still require improvements, particularly in AI refinement and real-time data integration. The findings emphasize the need for continuous development to fully optimize wind turbine performance and support the broader adoption of renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16095</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 07:31:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRPO-CARE: Consistency-Aware Reinforcement Learning for Multimodal   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16141</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16141.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Chen, Yuying Ge, Rui Wang, Yixiao Ge, Junhao Cheng, Ying Shan, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reinforcement learning approaches, such as outcome-supervised GRPO, have advanced Chain-of-Thought reasoning in large language models (LLMs), yet their adaptation to multimodal LLMs (MLLMs) is unexplored. To address the lack of rigorous evaluation for MLLM post-training methods, we introduce SEED-Bench-R1, a benchmark with complex real-world videos requiring balanced perception and reasoning. It offers a large training set and evaluates generalization across three escalating challenges: in-distribution, cross-environment, and cross-environment-task scenarios. Using SEED-Bench-R1, we find that standard GRPO, while improving answer accuracy, often reduces logical coherence between reasoning steps and answers, with only a 57.9% consistency rate. This stems from reward signals focusing solely on final answers, encouraging shortcuts, and strict KL penalties limiting exploration.To address this, we propose GRPO-CARE, a consistency-aware RL framework optimizing both answer correctness and reasoning coherence without explicit supervision. GRPO-CARE introduces a two-tiered reward: (1) a base reward for answer correctness, and (2) an adaptive consistency bonus, computed by comparing the model's reasoning-to-answer likelihood (via a slowly-evolving reference model) against group peers.This dual mechanism amplifies rewards for reasoning paths that are both correct and logically consistent. Replacing KL penalties with this adaptive bonus, GRPO-CARE outperforms standard GRPO on SEED-Bench-R1, achieving a 6.7% performance gain on the hardest evaluation level and a 24.5% improvement in consistency. It also shows strong transferability, improving model performance across diverse video understanding benchmarks. Our work contributes a systematically designed benchmark and a generalizable post-training framework, advancing the development of more interpretable and robust MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16141</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 08:49:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JarvisArt: Liberating Human Artistic Creativity via an Intelligent Photo   Retouching Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17612</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17612.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunlong Lin, Zixu Lin, Kunjie Lin, Jinbin Bai, Panwang Pan, Chenxin Li, Haoyu Chen, Zhongdao Wang, Xinghao Ding, Wenbo Li, Shuicheng Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Photo retouching has become integral to contemporary visual storytelling, enabling users to capture aesthetics and express creativity. While professional tools such as Adobe Lightroom offer powerful capabilities, they demand substantial expertise and manual effort. In contrast, existing AI-based solutions provide automation but often suffer from limited adjustability and poor generalization, failing to meet diverse and personalized editing needs. To bridge this gap, we introduce JarvisArt, a multi-modal large language model (MLLM)-driven agent that understands user intent, mimics the reasoning process of professional artists, and intelligently coordinates over 200 retouching tools within Lightroom. JarvisArt undergoes a two-stage training process: an initial Chain-of-Thought supervised fine-tuning to establish basic reasoning and tool-use skills, followed by Group Relative Policy Optimization for Retouching (GRPO-R) to further enhance its decision-making and tool proficiency. We also propose the Agent-to-Lightroom Protocol to facilitate seamless integration with Lightroom. To evaluate performance, we develop MMArt-Bench, a novel benchmark constructed from real-world user edits. JarvisArt demonstrates user-friendly interaction, superior generalization, and fine-grained control over both global and local adjustments, paving a new avenue for intelligent photo retouching. Notably, it outperforms GPT-4o with a 60% improvement in average pixel-level metrics on MMArt-Bench for content fidelity, while maintaining comparable instruction-following capabilities. Project Page: https://jarvisart.vercel.app/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17612</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 06:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain-of-Experts: Unlocking the Communication Power of   Mixture-of-Experts Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18945</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18945.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihan Wang, Rui Pan, Jiarui Yao, Robert Csordas, Linjie Li, Lu Yin, Jiajun Wu, Tong Zhang, Manling Li, Shiwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose Chain-of-Experts (CoE), a new Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture that introduces sequential expert communication within each layer. Unlike traditional MoE models, where experts operate independently in parallel, CoE processes tokens iteratively across a chain of experts inside a layer. To support dynamic expert selection across iterations, CoE employs a dedicated router at each iteration step within a layer. This design allows tokens to re-evaluate and select different experts during each iteration, rather than being statically assigned. As a result, CoE introduces a flexible routing mechanism that increases the diversity of expert combinations and enriches the model's representational capacity. CoE demonstrates improved performance under fixed compute: on math reasoning tasks, it reduces validation loss from 1.20 to 1.12 compared to a standard MoE. Beyond performance, CoE offers a new scaling axis: depth through expert iteration, which complements conventional width/depth scaling. For example, using 2x iterations matches the performance of 3x expert selections (in width), while reducing memory usage by 17.6-42% relative to other scaling strategies. Our analysis reveals that CoE's benefits stem from its iterative residual structure and enhanced expert specialization empowered by iterative routing, which together unlock more expressive representations. Code is available at https://github.com/ZihanWang314/coe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18945</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 02:15:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-SQL: Illuminating LLM Pathways to Solve User SQL Issues in   Real-World Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18951</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18951.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinyang Li, Xiaolong Li, Ge Qu, Per Jacobsson, Bowen Qin, Binyuan Hui, Shuzheng Si, Nan Huo, Xiaohan Xu, Yue Zhang, Ziwei Tang, Yuanshuai Li, Florensia Widjaja, Xintong Zhu, Feige Zhou, Yongfeng Huang, Yannis Papakonstantinou, Fatma Ozcan, Chenhao Ma, Reynold Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Resolution of complex SQL issues persists as a significant bottleneck in real-world database applications. Current Large Language Models (LLMs), while adept at text-to-SQL translation, have not been rigorously evaluated on the more challenging task of debugging SQL issues. To address this gap, we introduce BIRD-CRITIC, a new SQL issue debugging benchmark comprising 530 PostgreSQL tasks (BIRD-CRITIC-PG) and 570 multi-dialect tasks (BIRD-CRITIC-Multi), distilled from authentic user issues and replayed within new environments to facilitate rigorous evaluation. Baseline evaluations underscore the task's complexity, with the leading reasoning model O3-Mini achieving only 38.87% success rate on BIRD-CRITIC-PG and 33.33% on BIRD-CRITIC-Multi. Meanwhile, advancing open-source models for database tasks is crucial for empowering local development while safeguarding data privacy. Therefore, we present Six-Gym (Sql-fIX-Gym), a training environment for elevating open-source model capabilities for SQL issue debugging. This environment leverages SQL-Rewind strategy, which automatically generates executable issue-solution datasets by reverse-engineering issues from verified SQLs. However, popular trajectory-based fine-tuning methods do not explore substantial supervisory signals. We further propose f-Plan Boosting, which extracts high-level debugging plans from SQL solutions, enabling teacher LLMs to produce 73.7% more successful trajectories for training. We integrate these components into an open-source agent, Bird-Fixer. Based on Qwen-2.5-Coder-14B, Bird-Fixer achieves 38.11% success rate on BIRD-CRITIC-PG and 29.65% on BIRD-CRITIC-Multi, surpassing leading proprietary models such as Claude-3.7-Sonnet and GPT-4.1, marking a significant step toward democratizing sophisticated SQL-debugging capabilities. The leaderboard and source code are available: https://bird-critic.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18951</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 09:41:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix-Game: Interactive World Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18701</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18701.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Zhang, Chunli Peng, Boyang Wang, Puyi Wang, Qingcheng Zhu, Fei Kang, Biao Jiang, Zedong Gao, Eric Li, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Matrix-Game, an interactive world foundation model for controllable game world generation. Matrix-Game is trained using a two-stage pipeline that first performs large-scale unlabeled pretraining for environment understanding, followed by action-labeled training for interactive video generation. To support this, we curate Matrix-Game-MC, a comprehensive Minecraft dataset comprising over 2,700 hours of unlabeled gameplay video clips and over 1,000 hours of high-quality labeled clips with fine-grained keyboard and mouse action annotations. Our model adopts a controllable image-to-world generation paradigm, conditioned on a reference image, motion context, and user actions. With over 17 billion parameters, Matrix-Game enables precise control over character actions and camera movements, while maintaining high visual quality and temporal coherence. To evaluate performance, we develop GameWorld Score, a unified benchmark measuring visual quality, temporal quality, action controllability, and physical rule understanding for Minecraft world generation. Extensive experiments show that Matrix-Game consistently outperforms prior open-source Minecraft world models (including Oasis and MineWorld) across all metrics, with particularly strong gains in controllability and physical consistency. Double-blind human evaluations further confirm the superiority of Matrix-Game, highlighting its ability to generate perceptually realistic and precisely controllable videos across diverse game scenarios. To facilitate future research on interactive image-to-world generation, we will open-source the Matrix-Game model weights and the GameWorld Score benchmark at https://github.com/SkyworkAI/Matrix-Game.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18701</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 14:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>USAD: Universal Speech and Audio Representation via Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18843</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18843.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Heng-Jui Chang, Saurabhchand Bhati, James Glass, Alexander H. Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-supervised learning (SSL) has revolutionized audio representations, yet models often remain domain-specific, focusing on either speech or non-speech tasks. In this work, we present Universal Speech and Audio Distillation (USAD), a unified approach to audio representation learning that integrates diverse audio types - speech, sound, and music - into a single model. USAD employs efficient layer-to-layer distillation from domain-specific SSL models to train a student on a comprehensive audio dataset. USAD offers competitive performance across various benchmarks and datasets, including frame and instance-level speech processing tasks, audio tagging, and sound classification, achieving near state-of-the-art results with a single encoder on SUPERB and HEAR benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18843</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork-SWE: Unveiling Data Scaling Laws for Software Engineering in   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19290</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19290.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liang Zeng, Yongcong Li, Yuzhen Xiao, Changshi Li, Chris Yuhao Liu, Rui Yan, Tianwen Wei, Jujie He, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Software engineering (SWE) has recently emerged as a crucial testbed for next-generation LLM agents, demanding inherent capabilities in two critical dimensions: sustained iterative problem-solving (e.g., &gt;50 interaction rounds) and long-context dependency resolution (e.g., &gt;32k tokens). However, the data curation process in SWE remains notoriously time-consuming, as it heavily relies on manual annotation for code file filtering and the setup of dedicated runtime environments to execute and validate unit tests. Consequently, most existing datasets are limited to only a few thousand GitHub-sourced instances. To this end, we propose an incremental, automated data-curation pipeline that systematically scales both the volume and diversity of SWE datasets. Our dataset comprises 10,169 real-world Python task instances from 2,531 distinct GitHub repositories, each accompanied by a task specified in natural language and a dedicated runtime-environment image for automated unit-test validation. We have carefully curated over 8,000 successfully runtime-validated training trajectories from our proposed SWE dataset. When fine-tuning the Skywork-SWE model on these trajectories, we uncover a striking data scaling phenomenon: the trained model's performance for software engineering capabilities in LLMs continues to improve as the data size increases, showing no signs of saturation. Notably, our Skywork-SWE model achieves 38.0% pass@1 accuracy on the SWE-bench Verified benchmark without using verifiers or multiple rollouts, establishing a new state-of-the-art (SOTA) among the Qwen2.5-Coder-32B-based LLMs built on the OpenHands agent framework. Furthermore, with the incorporation of test-time scaling techniques, the performance further improves to 47.0% accuracy, surpassing the previous SOTA results for sub-32B parameter models. We release the Skywork-SWE-32B model checkpoint to accelerate future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19290</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 03:53:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mem4Nav: Boosting Vision-and-Language Navigation in Urban Environments   with a Hierarchical Spatial-Cognition Long-Short Memory System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19433</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19433.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lixuan He, Haoyu Dong, Zhenxing Chen, Yangcheng Yu, Jie Feng, Yong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-and-Language Navigation (VLN) in large-scale urban environments requires embodied agents to ground linguistic instructions in complex scenes and recall relevant experiences over extended time horizons. Prior modular pipelines offer interpretability but lack unified memory, while end-to-end (M)LLM agents excel at fusing vision and language yet remain constrained by fixed context windows and implicit spatial reasoning. We introduce Mem4Nav, a hierarchical spatial-cognition long-short memory system that can augment any VLN backbone. Mem4Nav fuses a sparse octree for fine-grained voxel indexing with a semantic topology graph for high-level landmark connectivity, storing both in trainable memory tokens embedded via a reversible Transformer. Long-term memory (LTM) compresses and retains historical observations at both octree and graph nodes, while short-term memory (STM) caches recent multimodal entries in relative coordinates for real-time obstacle avoidance and local planning. At each step, STM retrieval sharply prunes dynamic context, and, when deeper history is needed, LTM tokens are decoded losslessly to reconstruct past embeddings. Evaluated on Touchdown and Map2Seq across three backbones (modular, state-of-the-art VLN with prompt-based LLM, and state-of-the-art VLN with strided-attention MLLM), Mem4Nav yields 7-13 pp gains in Task Completion, sufficient SPD reduction, and &gt;10 pp nDTW improvement. Ablations confirm the indispensability of both the hierarchical map and dual memory modules. Our codes are open-sourced via https://github.com/tsinghua-fib-lab/Mem4Nav.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19433</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 09:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Large Language Models Capture Human Annotator Disagreements?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19467</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19467.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingwei Ni, Yu Fan, Vilém Zouhar, Donya Rooein, Alexander Hoyle, Mrinmaya Sachan, Markus Leippold, Dirk Hovy, Elliott Ash&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human annotation variation (i.e., annotation disagreements) is common in NLP and often reflects important information such as task subjectivity and sample ambiguity. While Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly used for automatic annotation to reduce human effort, their evaluation often focuses on predicting the majority-voted "ground truth" labels. It is still unclear, however, whether these models also capture informative human annotation variation. Our work addresses this gap by extensively evaluating LLMs' ability to predict annotation disagreements without access to repeated human labels. Our results show that LLMs struggle with modeling disagreements, which can be overlooked by majority label-based evaluations. Notably, while RLVR-style (Reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards) reasoning generally boosts LLM performance, it degrades performance in disagreement prediction. Our findings highlight the critical need for evaluating and improving LLM annotators in disagreement modeling. Code and data at https://github.com/EdisonNi-hku/Disagreement_Prediction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19467</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 09:49:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guidance in the Frequency Domain Enables High-Fidelity Sampling at Low   CFG Scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19713</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19713.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seyedmorteza Sadat, Tobias Vontobel, Farnood Salehi, Romann M. Weber&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Classifier-free guidance (CFG) has become an essential component of modern conditional diffusion models. Although highly effective in practice, the underlying mechanisms by which CFG enhances quality, detail, and prompt alignment are not fully understood. We present a novel perspective on CFG by analyzing its effects in the frequency domain, showing that low and high frequencies have distinct impacts on generation quality. Specifically, low-frequency guidance governs global structure and condition alignment, while high-frequency guidance mainly enhances visual fidelity. However, applying a uniform scale across all frequencies -- as is done in standard CFG -- leads to oversaturation and reduced diversity at high scales and degraded visual quality at low scales. Based on these insights, we propose frequency-decoupled guidance (FDG), an effective approach that decomposes CFG into low- and high-frequency components and applies separate guidance strengths to each component. FDG improves image quality at low guidance scales and avoids the drawbacks of high CFG scales by design. Through extensive experiments across multiple datasets and models, we demonstrate that FDG consistently enhances sample fidelity while preserving diversity, leading to improved FID and recall compared to CFG, establishing our method as a plug-and-play alternative to standard classifier-free guidance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19713</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 15:19:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SRFT: A Single-Stage Method with Supervised and Reinforcement   Fine-Tuning for Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19767</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19767.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqian Fu, Tinghong Chen, Jiajun Chai, Xihuai Wang, Songjun Tu, Guojun Yin, Wei Lin, Qichao Zhang, Yuanheng Zhu, Dongbin Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have achieved remarkable progress in reasoning tasks, yet the optimal integration of Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) and Reinforcement Learning (RL) remains a fundamental challenge. Through comprehensive analysis of token distributions, learning dynamics, and integration mechanisms from entropy-based perspectives, we reveal key differences between these paradigms: SFT induces coarse-grained global changes to LLM policy distributions, while RL performs fine-grained selective optimizations, with entropy serving as a critical indicator of training effectiveness. Building on these observations, we propose Supervised Reinforcement Fine-Tuning (SRFT), a single-stage method that unifies both fine-tuning paradigms through entropy-aware weighting mechanisms. Our approach simultaneously applies SFT and RL to directly optimize the LLM using demonstrations and self-exploration rollouts rather than through two-stage sequential methods. Extensive experiments show that SRFT achieves 59.1% average accuracy, outperforming zero-RL methods by 9.0% on five mathematical reasoning benchmarks and 10.9% on three out-of-distribution benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19767</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 16:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Do Open-Source LLMs Struggle with Data Analysis? A Systematic   Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19794</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19794.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqi Zhu, Yi Zhong, Jintian Zhang, Ziheng Zhang, Shuofei Qiao, Yujie Luo, Lun Du, Da Zheng, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) hold promise in automating data analysis tasks, yet open-source models face significant limitations in these kinds of reasoning-intensive scenarios. In this work, we investigate strategies to enhance the data analysis capabilities of open-source LLMs. By curating a seed dataset of diverse, realistic scenarios, we evaluate models across three dimensions: data understanding, code generation, and strategic planning. Our analysis reveals three key findings: (1) Strategic planning quality serves as the primary determinant of model performance; (2) Interaction design and task complexity significantly influence reasoning capabilities; (3) Data quality demonstrates a greater impact than diversity in achieving optimal performance. We leverage these insights to develop a data synthesis methodology, demonstrating significant improvements in open-source LLMs' analytical reasoning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19794</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:04:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KnowRL: Exploring Knowledgeable Reinforcement Learning for Factuality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19807</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19807.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baochang Ren, Shuofei Qiao, Wenhao Yu, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs), particularly slow-thinking models, often exhibit severe hallucination, outputting incorrect content due to an inability to accurately recognize knowledge boundaries during reasoning. While Reinforcement Learning (RL) can enhance complex reasoning abilities, its outcome-oriented reward mechanism often lacks factual supervision over the thinking process, further exacerbating the hallucination problem. To address the high hallucination in slow-thinking models, we propose Knowledge-enhanced RL, KnowRL. KnowRL guides models to perform fact-based slow thinking by integrating a factuality reward, based on knowledge verification, into the RL training process, helping them recognize their knowledge boundaries. KnowRL guides models to perform fact-based slow thinking by integrating a factuality reward, based on knowledge verification, into the RL training process, helping them recognize their knowledge boundaries. This targeted factual input during RL training enables the model to learn and internalize fact-based reasoning strategies. By directly rewarding adherence to facts within the reasoning steps, KnowRL fosters a more reliable thinking process. Experimental results on three hallucination evaluation datasets and two reasoning evaluation datasets demonstrate that KnowRL effectively mitigates hallucinations in slow-thinking models while maintaining their original strong reasoning capabilities. Our code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/KnowRL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19807</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:17:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Speculative Decoding with Lookahead Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19830</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19830.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yichao Fu, Rui Ge, Zelei Shao, Zhijie Deng, Hao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning models excel by generating long chain-of-thoughts, but decoding the resulting thousands of tokens is slow. Token-level speculative decoding (SD) helps, but its benefit is capped, because the chance that an entire gamma-token guess is correct falls exponentially as gamma grows. This means allocating more compute for longer token drafts faces an algorithmic ceiling -- making the speedup modest and hardware-agnostic. We raise this ceiling with Lookahead Reasoning, which exploits a second, step-level layer of parallelism. Our key insight is that reasoning models generate step-by-step, and each step needs only to be semantically correct, not exact token matching. In Lookahead Reasoning, a lightweight draft model proposes several future steps; the target model expands each proposal in one batched pass, and a verifier keeps semantically correct steps while letting the target regenerate any that fail. Token-level SD still operates within each reasoning step, so the two layers of parallelism multiply. We show Lookahead Reasoning lifts the peak speedup of SD both theoretically and empirically. Across GSM8K, AIME, and other benchmarks, Lookahead Reasoning improves the speedup of SD from 1.4x to 2.1x while preserving answer quality, and its speedup scales better with additional GPU throughput. Our code is available at https://github.com/hao-ai-lab/LookaheadReasoning&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19830</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:48:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SimpleGVR: A Simple Baseline for Latent-Cascaded Video Super-Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19838</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19838.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liangbin Xie, Yu Li, Shian Du, Menghan Xia, Xintao Wang, Fanghua Yu, Ziyan Chen, Pengfei Wan, Jiantao Zhou, Chao Dong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Latent diffusion models have emerged as a leading paradigm for efficient video generation. However, as user expectations shift toward higher-resolution outputs, relying solely on latent computation becomes inadequate. A promising approach involves decoupling the process into two stages: semantic content generation and detail synthesis. The former employs a computationally intensive base model at lower resolutions, while the latter leverages a lightweight cascaded video super-resolution (VSR) model to achieve high-resolution output. In this work, we focus on studying key design principles for latter cascaded VSR models, which are underexplored currently. First, we propose two degradation strategies to generate training pairs that better mimic the output characteristics of the base model, ensuring alignment between the VSR model and its upstream generator. Second, we provide critical insights into VSR model behavior through systematic analysis of (1) timestep sampling strategies, (2) noise augmentation effects on low-resolution (LR) inputs. These findings directly inform our architectural and training innovations. Finally, we introduce interleaving temporal unit and sparse local attention to achieve efficient training and inference, drastically reducing computational overhead. Extensive experiments demonstrate the superiority of our framework over existing methods, with ablation studies confirming the efficacy of each design choice. Our work establishes a simple yet effective baseline for cascaded video super-resolution generation, offering practical insights to guide future advancements in efficient cascaded synthesis systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19838</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:57:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Progressive Generation with Decomposable Flow Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19839</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19839.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Moayed Haji-Ali, Willi Menapace, Ivan Skorokhodov, Arpit Sahni, Sergey Tulyakov, Vicente Ordonez, Aliaksandr Siarohin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating high-dimensional visual modalities is a computationally intensive task. A common solution is progressive generation, where the outputs are synthesized in a coarse-to-fine spectral autoregressive manner. While diffusion models benefit from the coarse-to-fine nature of denoising, explicit multi-stage architectures are rarely adopted. These architectures have increased the complexity of the overall approach, introducing the need for a custom diffusion formulation, decomposition-dependent stage transitions, add-hoc samplers, or a model cascade. Our contribution, Decomposable Flow Matching (DFM), is a simple and effective framework for the progressive generation of visual media. DFM applies Flow Matching independently at each level of a user-defined multi-scale representation (such as Laplacian pyramid). As shown by our experiments, our approach improves visual quality for both images and videos, featuring superior results compared to prior multistage frameworks. On Imagenet-1k 512px, DFM achieves 35.2% improvements in FDD scores over the base architecture and 26.4% over the best-performing baseline, under the same training compute. When applied to finetuning of large models, such as FLUX, DFM shows faster convergence speed to the training distribution. Crucially, all these advantages are achieved with a single model, architectural simplicity, and minimal modifications to existing training pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19839</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:58:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal Finetuning Made Scalable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19847</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19847.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeju Qiu, Weiyang Liu, Adrian Weller, Bernhard Schölkopf&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Orthogonal finetuning (OFT) offers highly parameter-efficient adaptation while preventing catastrophic forgetting, but its high runtime and memory demands limit practical deployment. We identify the core computational bottleneck in OFT as its weight-centric implementation, which relies on costly matrix-matrix multiplications with cubic complexity. To overcome this, we propose OFTv2, an input-centric reformulation that instead uses matrix-vector multiplications (i.e., matrix-free computation), reducing the computational cost to quadratic. We further introduce the Cayley-Neumann parameterization, an efficient orthogonal parameterization that approximates the matrix inversion in Cayley transform via a truncated Neumann series. These modifications allow OFTv2 to achieve up to 10x faster training and 3x lower GPU memory usage without compromising performance. In addition, we extend OFTv2 to support finetuning quantized foundation models and show that it outperforms the popular QLoRA in training stability, efficiency, and memory usage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19847</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ScaleCap: Inference-Time Scalable Image Captioning via Dual-Modality   Debiasing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19848</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19848.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Long Xing, Qidong Huang, Xiaoyi Dong, Pan Zhang, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Jinsong Li, Shuangrui Ding, Weiming Zhang, Nenghai Yu, Jiaqi Wang, Feng Wu, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents ScaleCap, an inference-time scalable image captioning strategy that generates comprehensive and detailed image captions. The key challenges of high-quality image captioning lie in the inherent biases of LVLMs: multimodal bias resulting in imbalanced descriptive granularity, offering detailed accounts of some elements while merely skimming over others; linguistic bias leading to hallucinated descriptions of non-existent objects. To address these issues, we propose a scalable debiased captioning strategy, which continuously enriches and calibrates the caption with increased inference budget. Specifically, we propose two novel components: heuristic question answering and contrastive sentence rating. The former generates content-specific questions based on the image and answers them to progressively inject relevant information into the caption. The latter employs sentence-level offline contrastive decoding to effectively identify and eliminate hallucinations caused by linguistic biases. With increased inference cost, more heuristic questions are raised by ScaleCap to progressively capture additional visual details, generating captions that are more accurate, balanced, and informative. Extensive modality alignment experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of ScaleCap. Annotating 450K images with ScaleCap and using them for LVLM pretraining leads to consistent performance gains across 11 widely used benchmarks. Furthermore, ScaleCap showcases superb richness and fidelity of generated captions with two additional tasks: replacing images with captions in VQA task, and reconstructing images from captions to assess semantic coverage. Code is available at https://github.com/Cooperx521/ScaleCap.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19848</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Vision-Language-Action Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19850</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19850.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqi Wang, Xinghang Li, Wenxuan Wang, Junbo Zhang, Yingyan Li, Yuntao Chen, Xinlong Wang, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language-action models (VLAs) have garnered significant attention for their potential in advancing robotic manipulation. However, previous approaches predominantly rely on the general comprehension capabilities of vision-language models (VLMs) to generate action signals, often overlooking the rich temporal and causal structure embedded in visual observations. In this paper, we present UniVLA, a unified and native multimodal VLA model that autoregressively models vision, language, and action signals as discrete token sequences. This formulation enables flexible multimodal tasks learning, particularly from large-scale video data. By incorporating world modeling during post-training, UniVLA captures causal dynamics from videos, facilitating effective transfer to downstream policy learning--especially for long-horizon tasks. Our approach sets new state-of-the-art results across several widely used simulation benchmarks, including CALVIN, LIBERO, and Simplenv-Bridge, significantly surpassing previous methods. For example, UniVLA achieves 95.5% average success rate on LIBERO benchmark, surpassing pi0-FAST's 85.5%. We further demonstrate its broad applicability on real-world ALOHA manipulation and autonomous driving.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19850</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AnimaX: Animating the Inanimate in 3D with Joint Video-Pose Diffusion   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19851</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19851.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zehuan Huang, Haoran Feng, Yangtian Sun, Yuanchen Guo, Yanpei Cao, Lu Sheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present AnimaX, a feed-forward 3D animation framework that bridges the motion priors of video diffusion models with the controllable structure of skeleton-based animation. Traditional motion synthesis methods are either restricted to fixed skeletal topologies or require costly optimization in high-dimensional deformation spaces. In contrast, AnimaX effectively transfers video-based motion knowledge to the 3D domain, supporting diverse articulated meshes with arbitrary skeletons. Our method represents 3D motion as multi-view, multi-frame 2D pose maps, and enables joint video-pose diffusion conditioned on template renderings and a textual motion prompt. We introduce shared positional encodings and modality-aware embeddings to ensure spatial-temporal alignment between video and pose sequences, effectively transferring video priors to motion generation task. The resulting multi-view pose sequences are triangulated into 3D joint positions and converted into mesh animation via inverse kinematics. Trained on a newly curated dataset of 160,000 rigged sequences, AnimaX achieves state-of-the-art results on VBench in generalization, motion fidelity, and efficiency, offering a scalable solution for category-agnostic 3D animation. Project page: https://anima-x.github.io/{https://anima-x.github.io/}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19851</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
