<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 00:12:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>TalkVid: A Large-Scale Diversified Dataset for Audio-Driven Talking Head   Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shunian Chen, Hejin Huang, Yexin Liu, Zihan Ye, Pengcheng Chen, Chenghao Zhu, Michael Guan, Rongsheng Wang, Junying Chen, Guanbin Li, Ser-Nam Lim, Harry Yang, Benyou Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Audio-driven talking head synthesis has achieved remarkable photorealism, yet state-of-the-art (SOTA) models exhibit a critical failure: they lack generalization to the full spectrum of human diversity in ethnicity, language, and age groups. We argue that this generalization gap is a direct symptom of limitations in existing training data, which lack the necessary scale, quality, and diversity. To address this challenge, we introduce TalkVid, a new large-scale, high-quality, and diverse dataset containing 1244 hours of video from 7729 unique speakers. TalkVid is curated through a principled, multi-stage automated pipeline that rigorously filters for motion stability, aesthetic quality, and facial detail, and is validated against human judgments to ensure its reliability. Furthermore, we construct and release TalkVid-Bench, a stratified evaluation set of 500 clips meticulously balanced across key demographic and linguistic axes. Our experiments demonstrate that a model trained on TalkVid outperforms counterparts trained on previous datasets, exhibiting superior cross-dataset generalization. Crucially, our analysis on TalkVid-Bench reveals performance disparities across subgroups that are obscured by traditional aggregate metrics, underscoring its necessity for future research. Code and data can be found in https://github.com/FreedomIntelligence/TalkVid&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13618</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 08:31:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLIPSym: Delving into Symmetry Detection with CLIP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14197</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14197.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tinghan Yang, Md Ashiqur Rahman, Raymond A. Yeh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Symmetry is one of the most fundamental geometric cues in computer vision, and detecting it has been an ongoing challenge. With the recent advances in vision-language models,~i.e., CLIP, we investigate whether a pre-trained CLIP model can aid symmetry detection by leveraging the additional symmetry cues found in the natural image descriptions. We propose CLIPSym, which leverages CLIP's image and language encoders and a rotation-equivariant decoder based on a hybrid of Transformer and G-Convolution to detect rotation and reflection symmetries. To fully utilize CLIP's language encoder, we have developed a novel prompting technique called Semantic-Aware Prompt Grouping (SAPG), which aggregates a diverse set of frequent object-based prompts to better integrate the semantic cues for symmetry detection. Empirically, we show that CLIPSym outperforms the current state-of-the-art on three standard symmetry detection datasets (DENDI, SDRW, and LDRS). Finally, we conduct detailed ablations verifying the benefits of CLIP's pre-training, the proposed equivariant decoder, and the SAPG technique. The code is available at https://github.com/timyoung2333/CLIPSym.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14197</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 18:43:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EduRABSA: An Education Review Dataset for Aspect-based Sentiment   Analysis Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17008</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.17008.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yan Cathy Hua, Paul Denny, Jörg Wicker, Katerina Taskova&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Every year, most educational institutions seek and receive an enormous volume of text feedback from students on courses, teaching, and overall experience. Yet, turning this raw feedback into useful insights is far from straightforward. It has been a long-standing challenge to adopt automatic opinion mining solutions for such education review text data due to the content complexity and low-granularity reporting requirements. Aspect-based Sentiment Analysis (ABSA) offers a promising solution with its rich, sub-sentence-level opinion mining capabilities. However, existing ABSA research and resources are very heavily focused on the commercial domain. In education, they are scarce and hard to develop due to limited public datasets and strict data protection. A high-quality, annotated dataset is urgently needed to advance research in this under-resourced area. In this work, we present EduRABSA (Education Review ABSA), the first public, annotated ABSA education review dataset that covers three review subject types (course, teaching staff, university) in the English language and all main ABSA tasks, including the under-explored implicit aspect and implicit opinion extraction. We also share ASQE-DPT (Data Processing Tool), an offline, lightweight, installation-free manual data annotation tool that generates labelled datasets for comprehensive ABSA tasks from a single-task annotation. Together, these resources contribute to the ABSA community and education domain by removing the dataset barrier, supporting research transparency and reproducibility, and enabling the creation and sharing of further resources. The dataset, annotation tool, and scripts and statistics for dataset processing and sampling are available at https://github.com/yhua219/edurabsa_dataset_and_annotation_tool.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17008</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 12:38:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From reactive to cognitive: brain-inspired spatial intelligence for   embodied agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17198</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.17198.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shouwei Ruan, Liyuan Wang, Caixin Kang, Qihui Zhu, Songming Liu, Xingxing Wei, Hang Su&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatial cognition enables adaptive goal-directed behavior by constructing internal models of space. Robust biological systems consolidate spatial knowledge into three interconnected forms: landmarks for salient cues, route knowledge for movement trajectories, and survey knowledge for map-like representations. While recent advances in multi-modal large language models (MLLMs) have enabled visual-language reasoning in embodied agents, these efforts lack structured spatial memory and instead operate reactively, limiting their generalization and adaptability in complex real-world environments. Here we present Brain-inspired Spatial Cognition for Navigation (BSC-Nav), a unified framework for constructing and leveraging structured spatial memory in embodied agents. BSC-Nav builds allocentric cognitive maps from egocentric trajectories and contextual cues, and dynamically retrieves spatial knowledge aligned with semantic goals. Integrated with powerful MLLMs, BSC-Nav achieves state-of-the-art efficacy and efficiency across diverse navigation tasks, demonstrates strong zero-shot generalization, and supports versatile embodied behaviors in the real physical world, offering a scalable and biologically grounded path toward general-purpose spatial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17198</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 03:20:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI-Level Evaluation of ALLaM 34B: Measuring an Arabic-Centric LLM via   HUMAIN Chat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17378</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.17378.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Omer Nacar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) trained primarily on English corpora often struggle to capture the linguistic and cultural nuances of Arabic. To address this gap, the Saudi Data and AI Authority (SDAIA) introduced the ALLaM family of Arabic-focused models. The most capable of these available to the public, ALLaM-34B, was subsequently adopted by HUMAIN, who developed and deployed HUMAIN Chat, a closed conversational web service built on this model. This paper presents an expanded and refined UI-level evaluation of ALLaM-34B. Using a prompt pack spanning modern standard Arabic, five regional dialects, code-switching, factual knowledge, arithmetic and temporal reasoning, creative generation, and adversarial safety, we collected 115 outputs (23 prompts times 5 runs) and scored each with three frontier LLM judges (GPT-5, Gemini 2.5 Pro, Claude Sonnet-4). We compute category-level means with 95\% confidence intervals, analyze score distributions, and visualize dialect-wise metric heat maps. The updated analysis reveals consistently high performance on generation and code-switching tasks (both averaging 4.92/5), alongside strong results in MSA handling (4.74/5), solid reasoning ability (4.64/5), and improved dialect fidelity (4.21/5). Safety-related prompts show stable, reliable performance of (4.54/5). Taken together, these results position ALLaM-34B as a robust and culturally grounded Arabic LLM, demonstrating both technical strength and practical readiness for real-world deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17378</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 14:32:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mimicking the Physicist's Eye:A VLM-centric Approach for Physics Formula   Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17380</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.17380.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Liu, Songning Lai, Pengze Li, Di Yu, Wenjie Zhou, Yiyang Zhou, Peng Xia, Zijun Wang, Xi Chen, Shixiang Tang, Lei Bai, Wanli Ouyang, Mingyu Ding, Huaxiu Yao, Aoran Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Automated discovery of physical laws from observational data in the real world is a grand challenge in AI. Current methods, relying on symbolic regression or LLMs, are limited to uni-modal data and overlook the rich, visual phenomenological representations of motion that are indispensable to physicists. This "sensory deprivation" severely weakens their ability to interpret the inherent spatio-temporal patterns within dynamic phenomena. To address this gap, we propose VIPER-R1, a multimodal model that performs Visual Induction for Physics-based Equation Reasoning to discover fundamental symbolic formulas. It integrates visual perception, trajectory data, and symbolic reasoning to emulate the scientific discovery process. The model is trained via a curriculum of Motion Structure Induction (MSI), using supervised fine-tuning to interpret kinematic phase portraits and to construct hypotheses guided by a Causal Chain of Thought (C-CoT), followed by Reward-Guided Symbolic Calibration (RGSC) to refine the formula structure with reinforcement learning. During inference, the trained VIPER-R1 acts as an agent: it first posits a high-confidence symbolic ansatz, then proactively invokes an external symbolic regression tool to perform Symbolic Residual Realignment (SR^2). This final step, analogous to a physicist's perturbation analysis, reconciles the theoretical model with empirical data. To support this research, we introduce PhysSymbol, a new 5,000-instance multimodal corpus. Experiments show that VIPER-R1 consistently outperforms state-of-the-art VLM baselines in accuracy and interpretability, enabling more precise discovery of physical laws. Project page: https://jiaaqiliu.github.io/VIPER-R1/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17380</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 14:34:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TiKMiX: Take Data Influence into Dynamic Mixture for Language Model   Pre-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17677</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.17677.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Wang, Binbin Liu, Fengze Liu, Yuanfan Guo, Jiyao Deng, Xuecheng Wu, Weidong Zhou, Xiaohuan Zhou, Taifeng Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The data mixture used in the pre-training of a language model is a cornerstone of its final performance. However, a static mixing strategy is suboptimal, as the model's learning preferences for various data domains shift dynamically throughout training. Crucially, observing these evolving preferences in a computationally efficient manner remains a significant challenge. To address this, we propose TiKMiX, a method that dynamically adjusts the data mixture according to the model's evolving preferences. TiKMiX introduces Group Influence, an efficient metric for evaluating the impact of data domains on the model. This metric enables the formulation of the data mixing problem as a search for an optimal, influence-maximizing distribution. We solve this via two approaches: TiKMiX-D for direct optimization, and TiKMiX-M, which uses a regression model to predict a superior mixture. We trained models with different numbers of parameters, on up to 1 trillion tokens. TiKMiX-D exceeds the performance of state-of-the-art methods like REGMIX while using just 20% of the computational resources. TiKMiX-M leads to an average performance gain of 2% across 9 downstream benchmarks. Our experiments reveal that a model's data preferences evolve with training progress and scale, and we demonstrate that dynamically adjusting the data mixture based on Group Influence, a direct measure of these preferences, significantly improves performance by mitigating the underdigestion of data seen with static ratios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17677</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 05:18:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A.S.E: A Repository-Level Benchmark for Evaluating Security in   AI-Generated Code</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.18106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Keke Lian, Bin Wang, Lei Zhang, Libo Chen, Junjie Wang, Ziming Zhao, Yujiu Yang, Haotong Duan, Haoran Zhao, Shuang Liao, Mingda Guo, Jiazheng Quan, Yilu Zhong, Chenhao He, Zichuan Chen, Jie Wu, Haoling Li, Zhaoxuan Li, Jiongchi Yu, Hui Li, Dong Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 197&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The increasing adoption of large language models (LLMs) in software engineering necessitates rigorous security evaluation of their generated code. However, existing benchmarks are inadequate, as they focus on isolated code snippets, employ unstable evaluation methods that lack reproducibility, and fail to connect the quality of input context with the security of the output. To address these gaps, we introduce A.S.E (AI Code Generation Security Evaluation), a benchmark for repository-level secure code generation. A.S.E constructs tasks from real-world repositories with documented CVEs, preserving full repository context like build systems and cross-file dependencies. Its reproducible, containerized evaluation framework uses expert-defined rules to provide stable, auditable assessments of security, build quality, and generation stability. Our evaluation of leading LLMs on A.S.E reveals three key findings: (1) Claude-3.7-Sonnet achieves the best overall performance. (2) The security gap between proprietary and open-source models is narrow; Qwen3-235B-A22B-Instruct attains the top security score. (3) Concise, ``fast-thinking'' decoding strategies consistently outperform complex, ``slow-thinking'' reasoning for security patching.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18106</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 15:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drawing2CAD: Sequence-to-Sequence Learning for CAD Generation from   Vector Drawings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18733</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.18733.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Feiwei Qin, Shichao Lu, Junhao Hou, Changmiao Wang, Meie Fang, Ligang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Computer-Aided Design (CAD) generative modeling is driving significant innovations across industrial applications. Recent works have shown remarkable progress in creating solid models from various inputs such as point clouds, meshes, and text descriptions. However, these methods fundamentally diverge from traditional industrial workflows that begin with 2D engineering drawings. The automatic generation of parametric CAD models from these 2D vector drawings remains underexplored despite being a critical step in engineering design. To address this gap, our key insight is to reframe CAD generation as a sequence-to-sequence learning problem where vector drawing primitives directly inform the generation of parametric CAD operations, preserving geometric precision and design intent throughout the transformation process. We propose Drawing2CAD, a framework with three key technical components: a network-friendly vector primitive representation that preserves precise geometric information, a dual-decoder transformer architecture that decouples command type and parameter generation while maintaining precise correspondence, and a soft target distribution loss function accommodating inherent flexibility in CAD parameters. To train and evaluate Drawing2CAD, we create CAD-VGDrawing, a dataset of paired engineering drawings and parametric CAD models, and conduct thorough experiments to demonstrate the effectiveness of our method. Code and dataset are available at https://github.com/lllssc/Drawing2CAD.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18733</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 07:01:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No Label Left Behind: A Unified Surface Defect Detection Model for all   Supervision Regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19060</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.19060.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Blaž Rolih, Matic Fučka, Danijel Skočaj&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Surface defect detection is a critical task across numerous industries, aimed at efficiently identifying and localising imperfections or irregularities on manufactured components. While numerous methods have been proposed, many fail to meet industrial demands for high performance, efficiency, and adaptability. Existing approaches are often constrained to specific supervision scenarios and struggle to adapt to the diverse data annotations encountered in real-world manufacturing processes, such as unsupervised, weakly supervised, mixed supervision, and fully supervised settings. To address these challenges, we propose SuperSimpleNet, a highly efficient and adaptable discriminative model built on the foundation of SimpleNet. SuperSimpleNet incorporates a novel synthetic anomaly generation process, an enhanced classification head, and an improved learning procedure, enabling efficient training in all four supervision scenarios, making it the first model capable of fully leveraging all available data annotations. SuperSimpleNet sets a new standard for performance across all scenarios, as demonstrated by its results on four challenging benchmark datasets. Beyond accuracy, it is very fast, achieving an inference time below 10 ms. With its ability to unify diverse supervision paradigms while maintaining outstanding speed and reliability, SuperSimpleNet represents a promising step forward in addressing real-world manufacturing challenges and bridging the gap between academic research and industrial applications. Code: https://github.com/blaz-r/SuperSimpleNet&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19060</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 14:20:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democracy-in-Silico: Institutional Design as Alignment in AI-Governed   Polities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19562</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.19562.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Trisanth Srinivasan, Santosh Patapati&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces Democracy-in-Silico, an agent-based simulation where societies of advanced AI agents, imbued with complex psychological personas, govern themselves under different institutional frameworks. We explore what it means to be human in an age of AI by tasking Large Language Models (LLMs) to embody agents with traumatic memories, hidden agendas, and psychological triggers. These agents engage in deliberation, legislation, and elections under various stressors, such as budget crises and resource scarcity. We present a novel metric, the Power-Preservation Index (PPI), to quantify misaligned behavior where agents prioritize their own power over public welfare. Our findings demonstrate that institutional design, specifically the combination of a Constitutional AI (CAI) charter and a mediated deliberation protocol, serves as a potent alignment mechanism. These structures significantly reduce corrupt power-seeking behavior, improve policy stability, and enhance citizen welfare compared to less constrained democratic models. The simulation reveals that an institutional design may offer a framework for aligning the complex, emergent behaviors of future artificial agent societies, forcing us to reconsider what human rituals and responsibilities are essential in an age of shared authorship with non-human entities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19562</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 04:44:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantization Robustness to Input Degradations for Object Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19600</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.19600.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Toghrul Karimov, Hassan Imani, Allan Kazakov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Post-training quantization (PTQ) is crucial for deploying efficient object detection models, like YOLO, on resource-constrained devices. However, the impact of reduced precision on model robustness to real-world input degradations such as noise, blur, and compression artifacts is a significant concern. This paper presents a comprehensive empirical study evaluating the robustness of YOLO models (nano to extra-large scales) across multiple precision formats: FP32, FP16 (TensorRT), Dynamic UINT8 (ONNX), and Static INT8 (TensorRT). We introduce and evaluate a degradation-aware calibration strategy for Static INT8 PTQ, where the TensorRT calibration process is exposed to a mix of clean and synthetically degraded images. Models were benchmarked on the COCO dataset under seven distinct degradation conditions (including various types and levels of noise, blur, low contrast, and JPEG compression) and a mixed-degradation scenario. Results indicate that while Static INT8 TensorRT engines offer substantial speedups (~1.5-3.3x) with a moderate accuracy drop (~3-7% mAP50-95) on clean data, the proposed degradation-aware calibration did not yield consistent, broad improvements in robustness over standard clean-data calibration across most models and degradations. A notable exception was observed for larger model scales under specific noise conditions, suggesting model capacity may influence the efficacy of this calibration approach. These findings highlight the challenges in enhancing PTQ robustness and provide insights for deploying quantized detectors in uncontrolled environments. All code and evaluation tables are available at https://github.com/AllanK24/QRID.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19600</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 06:20:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T2R-bench: A Benchmark for Generating Article-Level Reports from Real   World Industrial Tables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19813</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.19813.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jie Zhang, Changzai Pan, Kaiwen Wei, Sishi Xiong, Yu Zhao, Xiangyu Li, Jiaxin Peng, Xiaoyan Gu, Jian Yang, Wenhan Chang, Zhenhe Wu, Jiang Zhong, Shuangyong Song, Yongxiang Li, Xuelong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Extensive research has been conducted to explore the capabilities of large language models (LLMs) in table reasoning. However, the essential task of transforming tables information into reports remains a significant challenge for industrial applications. This task is plagued by two critical issues: 1) the complexity and diversity of tables lead to suboptimal reasoning outcomes; and 2) existing table benchmarks lack the capacity to adequately assess the practical application of this task. To fill this gap, we propose the table-to-report task and construct a bilingual benchmark named T2R-bench, where the key information flow from the tables to the reports for this task. The benchmark comprises 457 industrial tables, all derived from real-world scenarios and encompassing 19 industry domains as well as 4 types of industrial tables. Furthermore, we propose an evaluation criteria to fairly measure the quality of report generation. The experiments on 25 widely-used LLMs reveal that even state-of-the-art models like Deepseek-R1 only achieves performance with 62.71 overall score, indicating that LLMs still have room for improvement on T2R-bench. Source code and data will be available after acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19813</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 11:55:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HERMES: Human-to-Robot Embodied Learning from Multi-Source Motion Data   for Mobile Dexterous Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20085</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20085.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhecheng Yuan, Tianming Wei, Langzhe Gu, Pu Hua, Tianhai Liang, Yuanpei Chen, Huazhe Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Leveraging human motion data to impart robots with versatile manipulation skills has emerged as a promising paradigm in robotic manipulation. Nevertheless, translating multi-source human hand motions into feasible robot behaviors remains challenging, particularly for robots equipped with multi-fingered dexterous hands characterized by complex, high-dimensional action spaces. Moreover, existing approaches often struggle to produce policies capable of adapting to diverse environmental conditions. In this paper, we introduce HERMES, a human-to-robot learning framework for mobile bimanual dexterous manipulation. First, HERMES formulates a unified reinforcement learning approach capable of seamlessly transforming heterogeneous human hand motions from multiple sources into physically plausible robotic behaviors. Subsequently, to mitigate the sim2real gap, we devise an end-to-end, depth image-based sim2real transfer method for improved generalization to real-world scenarios. Furthermore, to enable autonomous operation in varied and unstructured environments, we augment the navigation foundation model with a closed-loop Perspective-n-Point (PnP) localization mechanism, ensuring precise alignment of visual goals and effectively bridging autonomous navigation and dexterous manipulation. Extensive experimental results demonstrate that HERMES consistently exhibits generalizable behaviors across diverse, in-the-wild scenarios, successfully performing numerous complex mobile bimanual dexterous manipulation tasks. Project Page:https://gemcollector.github.io/HERMES/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20085</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 17:53:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Droplet3D: Commonsense Priors from Videos Facilitate 3D Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20470</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20470.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaochuan Li, Guoguang Du, Runze Zhang, Liang Jin, Qi Jia, Lihua Lu, Zhenhua Guo, Yaqian Zhao, Haiyang Liu, Tianqi Wang, Changsheng Li, Xiaoli Gong, Rengang Li, Baoyu Fan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling laws have validated the success and promise of large-data-trained models in creative generation across text, image, and video domains. However, this paradigm faces data scarcity in the 3D domain, as there is far less of it available on the internet compared to the aforementioned modalities. Fortunately, there exist adequate videos that inherently contain commonsense priors, offering an alternative supervisory signal to mitigate the generalization bottleneck caused by limited native 3D data. On the one hand, videos capturing multiple views of an object or scene provide a spatial consistency prior for 3D generation. On the other hand, the rich semantic information contained within the videos enables the generated content to be more faithful to the text prompts and semantically plausible. This paper explores how to apply the video modality in 3D asset generation, spanning datasets to models. We introduce Droplet3D-4M, the first large-scale video dataset with multi-view level annotations, and train Droplet3D, a generative model supporting both image and dense text input. Extensive experiments validate the effectiveness of our approach, demonstrating its ability to produce spatially consistent and semantically plausible content. Moreover, in contrast to the prevailing 3D solutions, our approach exhibits the potential for extension to scene-level applications. This indicates that the commonsense priors from the videos significantly facilitate 3D creation. We have open-sourced all resources including the dataset, code, technical framework, and model weights: https://dropletx.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20470</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 06:39:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video-MTR: Reinforced Multi-Turn Reasoning for Long Video Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20478</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20478.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuan Xie, Tianshui Chen, Zheng Ge, Lionel Ni&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-form video understanding, characterized by long-range temporal dependencies and multiple events, remains a challenge. Existing methods often rely on static reasoning or external visual-language models (VLMs), which face issues like complexity and sub-optimal performance due to the lack of end-to-end training. In this paper, we propose Video-MTR, a reinforced multi-turn reasoning framework designed to enable iterative key video segment selection and question comprehension. Unlike traditional video reasoning pipeline, which generate predictions in a single turn, Video-MTR performs reasoning in multiple turns, selecting video segments progressively based on the evolving understanding of previously processed segments and the current question. This iterative process allows for a more refined and contextually aware analysis of the video. To ensure intermediate reasoning process, we introduce a novel gated bi-level reward system, combining trajectory-level rewards based on answer correctness and turn-level rewards emphasizing frame-query relevance. This system optimizes both video segment selection and question comprehension, eliminating the need for external VLMs and allowing end-to-end training. Extensive experiments on benchmarks like VideoMME, MLVU, and EgoSchema demonstrate that Video-MTR outperforms existing methods in both accuracy and efficiency, advancing the state-of-the-art in long video understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20478</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 06:55:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PVPO: Pre-Estimated Value-Based Policy Optimization for Agentic   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21104</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21104.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenfeng Feng, Penghong Zhao, Guochao Jiang, Chuzhan Hao, Yuewei Zhang, Hao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Critic-free reinforcement learning methods, particularly group policies, have attracted considerable attention for their efficiency in complex tasks. However, these methods rely heavily on multiple sampling and comparisons within the policy to estimate advantage, which may cause the policy to fall into local optimum and increase computational cost. To address these issues, we propose PVPO, an efficient reinforcement learning method enhanced by an advantage reference anchor and data pre-sampling. Specifically, we use the reference model to rollout in advance and employ the calculated reward score as a reference anchor. Our approach effectively corrects the cumulative bias introduced by intra-group comparisons and significantly reduces reliance on the number of rollouts. Meanwhile, the reference model can assess sample difficulty during data pre-sampling, enabling effective selection of high-gain data to improve training efficiency. Experiments conducted on nine datasets across two domains demonstrate that PVPO achieves State-Of-The-Art (SOTA) performance. Our approach not only demonstrates robust generalization across multiple tasks, but also exhibits scalable performance across models of varying scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21104</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 09:18:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FastFit: Accelerating Multi-Reference Virtual Try-On via Cacheable   Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20586</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20586.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zheng Chong, Yanwei Lei, Shiyue Zhang, Zhuandi He, Zhen Wang, Xujie Zhang, Xiao Dong, Yiling Wu, Dongmei Jiang, Xiaodan Liang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite its great potential, virtual try-on technology is hindered from real-world application by two major challenges: the inability of current methods to support multi-reference outfit compositions (including garments and accessories), and their significant inefficiency caused by the redundant re-computation of reference features in each denoising step. To address these challenges, we propose FastFit, a high-speed multi-reference virtual try-on framework based on a novel cacheable diffusion architecture. By employing a Semi-Attention mechanism and substituting traditional timestep embeddings with class embeddings for reference items, our model fully decouples reference feature encoding from the denoising process with negligible parameter overhead. This allows reference features to be computed only once and losslessly reused across all steps, fundamentally breaking the efficiency bottleneck and achieving an average 3.5x speedup over comparable methods. Furthermore, to facilitate research on complex, multi-reference virtual try-on, we introduce DressCode-MR, a new large-scale dataset. It comprises 28,179 sets of high-quality, paired images covering five key categories (tops, bottoms, dresses, shoes, and bags), constructed through a pipeline of expert models and human feedback refinement. Extensive experiments on the VITON-HD, DressCode, and our DressCode-MR datasets show that FastFit surpasses state-of-the-art methods on key fidelity metrics while offering its significant advantage in inference efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20586</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 09:25:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Can Input Reformulation Improve Tool Usage Accuracy in a Complex   Dynamic Environment? A Study on τ-bench</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20931</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20931.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Venkatesh Mishra, Amir Saeidi, Satyam Raj, Mutsumi Nakamura, Jayanth Srinivasa, Gaowen Liu, Ali Payani, Chitta Baral&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in reasoning and planning capabilities of large language models (LLMs) have enabled their potential as autonomous agents capable of tool use in dynamic environments. However, in multi-turn conversational environments like tau-bench, these agents often struggle with consistent reasoning, adherence to domain-specific policies, and extracting correct information over a long horizon of tool-calls and conversation. To capture and mitigate these failures, we conduct a comprehensive manual analysis of the common errors occurring in the conversation trajectories. We then experiment with reformulations of inputs to the tool-calling agent for improvement in agent decision making. Finally, we propose the Input-Reformulation Multi-Agent (IRMA) framework, which automatically reformulates user queries augmented with relevant domain rules and tool suggestions for the tool-calling agent to focus on. The results show that IRMA significantly outperforms ReAct, Function Calling, and Self-Reflection by 16.1%, 12.7%, and 19.1%, respectively, in overall pass^5 scores. These findings highlight the superior reliability and consistency of IRMA compared to other methods in dynamic environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20931</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 15:57:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EmbodiedOneVision: Interleaved Vision-Text-Action Pretraining for   General Robot Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21112</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21112.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Delin Qu, Haoming Song, Qizhi Chen, Zhaoqing Chen, Xianqiang Gao, Xinyi Ye, Qi Lv, Modi Shi, Guanghui Ren, Cheng Ruan, Maoqing Yao, Haoran Yang, Jiacheng Bao, Bin Zhao, Dong Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The human ability to seamlessly perform multimodal reasoning and physical interaction in the open world is a core goal for general-purpose embodied intelligent systems. Recent vision-language-action (VLA) models, which are co-trained on large-scale robot and visual-text data, have demonstrated notable progress in general robot control. However, they still fail to achieve human-level flexibility in interleaved reasoning and interaction. In this work, introduce EO-Robotics, consists of EO-1 model and EO-Data1.5M dataset. EO-1 is a unified embodied foundation model that achieves superior performance in multimodal embodied reasoning and robot control through interleaved vision-text-action pre-training. The development of EO-1 is based on two key pillars: (i) a unified architecture that processes multimodal inputs indiscriminately (image, text, video, and action), and (ii) a massive, high-quality multimodal embodied reasoning dataset, EO-Data1.5M, which contains over 1.5 million samples with emphasis on interleaved vision-text-action comprehension. EO-1 is trained through synergies between auto-regressive decoding and flow matching denoising on EO-Data1.5M, enabling seamless robot action generation and multimodal embodied reasoning. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of interleaved vision-text-action learning for open-world understanding and generalization, validated through a variety of long-horizon, dexterous manipulation tasks across multiple embodiments. This paper details the architecture of EO-1, the data construction strategy of EO-Data1.5M, and the training methodology, offering valuable insights for developing advanced embodied foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21112</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 17:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Theoretical Limitations of Embedding-Based Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21038</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21038.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Orion Weller, Michael Boratko, Iftekhar Naim, Jinhyuk Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vector embeddings have been tasked with an ever-increasing set of retrieval tasks over the years, with a nascent rise in using them for reasoning, instruction-following, coding, and more. These new benchmarks push embeddings to work for any query and any notion of relevance that could be given. While prior works have pointed out theoretical limitations of vector embeddings, there is a common assumption that these difficulties are exclusively due to unrealistic queries, and those that are not can be overcome with better training data and larger models. In this work, we demonstrate that we may encounter these theoretical limitations in realistic settings with extremely simple queries. We connect known results in learning theory, showing that the number of top-k subsets of documents capable of being returned as the result of some query is limited by the dimension of the embedding. We empirically show that this holds true even if we restrict to k=2, and directly optimize on the test set with free parameterized embeddings. We then create a realistic dataset called LIMIT that stress tests models based on these theoretical results, and observe that even state-of-the-art models fail on this dataset despite the simple nature of the task. Our work shows the limits of embedding models under the existing single vector paradigm and calls for future research to develop methods that can resolve this fundamental limitation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21038</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 17:43:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R-4B: Incentivizing General-Purpose Auto-Thinking Capability in MLLMs   via Bi-Mode Annealing and Reinforce Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21113</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21113.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jie Jiang, Qi Yang, Bolin Ni, Shiming Xiang, Han Hu, Houwen Peng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 104&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) equipped with step-by-step thinking capabilities have demonstrated remarkable performance on complex reasoning problems. However, this thinking process is redundant for simple problems solvable without complex reasoning. To address this inefficiency, we propose R-4B, an auto-thinking MLLM, which can adaptively decide when to think based on problem complexity. The central idea of R-4B is to empower the model with both thinking and non-thinking capabilities using bi-mode annealing, and apply Bi-mode Policy Optimization~(BPO) to improve the model's accuracy in determining whether to activate the thinking process. Specifically, we first train the model on a carefully curated dataset spanning various topics, which contains samples from both thinking and non-thinking modes. Then it undergoes a second phase of training under an improved GRPO framework, where the policy model is forced to generate responses from both modes for each input query. Experimental results show that R-4B achieves state-of-the-art performance across 25 challenging benchmarks. It outperforms Qwen2.5-VL-7B in most tasks and achieves performance comparable to larger models such as Kimi-VL-A3B-Thinking-2506 (16B) on reasoning-intensive benchmarks with lower computational cost.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21113</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 17:48:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Scientific Large Language Models: From Data Foundations to   Agent Frontiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21148</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21148.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Hu, Chenglong Ma, Wei Li, Wanghan Xu, Jiamin Wu, Jucheng Hu, Tianbin Li, Guohang Zhuang, Jiaqi Liu, Yingzhou Lu, Ying Chen, Chaoyang Zhang, Cheng Tan, Jie Ying, Guocheng Wu, Shujian Gao, Pengcheng Chen, Jiashi Lin, Haitao Wu, Lulu Chen, Fengxiang Wang, Yuanyuan Zhang, Xiangyu Zhao, Feilong Tang, Encheng Su, Junzhi Ning, Xinyao Liu, Ye Du, Changkai Ji, Cheng Tang, Huihui Xu, Ziyang Chen, Ziyan Huang, Jiyao Liu, Pengfei Jiang, Yizhou Wang, Chen Tang, Jianyu Wu, Yuchen Ren, Siyuan Yan, Zhonghua Wang, Zhongxing Xu, Shiyan Su, Shangquan Sun, Runkai Zhao, Zhisheng Zhang, Yu Liu, Fudi Wang, Yuanfeng Ji, Yanzhou Su, Hongming Shan, Chunmei Feng, Jiahao Xu, Jiangtao Yan, Wenhao Tang, Diping Song, Lihao Liu, Yanyan Huang, Lequan Yu, Bin Fu, Shujun Wang, Xiaomeng Li, Xiaowei Hu, Yun Gu, Ben Fei, Zhongying Deng, Benyou Wang, Yuewen Cao, Minjie Shen, Haodong Duan, Jie Xu, Yirong Chen, Fang Yan, Hongxia Hao, Jielan Li, Jiajun Du, Yanbo Wang, Imran Razzak, Chi Zhang, Lijun Wu, Conghui He, Zhaohui Lu, Jinhai Huang, Yihao Liu, Fenghua Ling, Yuqiang Li, Aoran Wang, Qihao Zheng, Nanqing Dong, Tianfan Fu, Dongzhan Zhou, Yan Lu, Wenlong Zhang, Jin Ye, Jianfei Cai, Wanli Ouyang, Yu Qiao, Zongyuan Ge, Shixiang Tang, Junjun He, Chunfeng Song, Lei Bai, Bowen Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 132&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scientific Large Language Models (Sci-LLMs) are transforming how knowledge is represented, integrated, and applied in scientific research, yet their progress is shaped by the complex nature of scientific data. This survey presents a comprehensive, data-centric synthesis that reframes the development of Sci-LLMs as a co-evolution between models and their underlying data substrate. We formulate a unified taxonomy of scientific data and a hierarchical model of scientific knowledge, emphasizing the multimodal, cross-scale, and domain-specific challenges that differentiate scientific corpora from general natural language processing datasets. We systematically review recent Sci-LLMs, from general-purpose foundations to specialized models across diverse scientific disciplines, alongside an extensive analysis of over 270 pre-/post-training datasets, showing why Sci-LLMs pose distinct demands -- heterogeneous, multi-scale, uncertainty-laden corpora that require representations preserving domain invariance and enabling cross-modal reasoning. On evaluation, we examine over 190 benchmark datasets and trace a shift from static exams toward process- and discovery-oriented assessments with advanced evaluation protocols. These data-centric analyses highlight persistent issues in scientific data development and discuss emerging solutions involving semi-automated annotation pipelines and expert validation. Finally, we outline a paradigm shift toward closed-loop systems where autonomous agents based on Sci-LLMs actively experiment, validate, and contribute to a living, evolving knowledge base. Collectively, this work provides a roadmap for building trustworthy, continually evolving artificial intelligence (AI) systems that function as a true partner in accelerating scientific discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21148</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 18:30:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Residual Echo State Networks: exploring residual orthogonal   connections in untrained Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21172</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21172.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Matteo Pinna, Andrea Ceni, Claudio Gallicchio&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Echo State Networks (ESNs) are a particular type of untrained Recurrent Neural Networks (RNNs) within the Reservoir Computing (RC) framework, popular for their fast and efficient learning. However, traditional ESNs often struggle with long-term information processing. In this paper, we introduce a novel class of deep untrained RNNs based on temporal residual connections, called Deep Residual Echo State Networks (DeepResESNs). We show that leveraging a hierarchy of untrained residual recurrent layers significantly boosts memory capacity and long-term temporal modeling. For the temporal residual connections, we consider different orthogonal configurations, including randomly generated and fixed-structure configurations, and we study their effect on network dynamics. A thorough mathematical analysis outlines necessary and sufficient conditions to ensure stable dynamics within DeepResESN. Our experiments on a variety of time series tasks showcase the advantages of the proposed approach over traditional shallow and deep RC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21172</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 19:22:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-Task Alignment Drives Distinct RL Outcomes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21188</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21188.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoze Wu, Cheng Wang, Wenshuo Zhao, Junxian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in applying reinforcement learning (RL) to large language models (LLMs) have led to substantial progress. In particular, a series of remarkable yet often counterintuitive phenomena have been reported in LLMs, exhibiting patterns not typically observed in traditional RL settings. For example, notable claims include that a single training example can match the performance achieved with an entire dataset, that the reward signal does not need to be very accurate, and that training solely with negative samples can match or even surpass sophisticated reward-based methods. However, the precise conditions under which these observations hold - and, critically, when they fail - remain unclear. In this work, we identify a key factor that differentiates RL observations: whether the pretrained model already exhibits strong Model-Task Alignment, as measured by pass@k accuracy on the evaluated task. Through a systematic and comprehensive examination of a series of counterintuitive claims, supported by rigorous experimental validation across different model architectures and task domains, our findings show that while standard RL training remains consistently robust across settings, many of these counterintuitive results arise only when the model and task already exhibit strong model-task alignment. In contrast, these techniques fail to drive substantial learning in more challenging regimes, where standard RL methods remain effective.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21188</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 20:02:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Code Embeddings from Code Generation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21290</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21290.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daria Kryvosheieva, Saba Sturua, Michael Günther, Scott Martens, Han Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; jina-code-embeddings is a novel code embedding model suite designed to retrieve code from natural language queries, perform technical question-answering, and identify semantically similar code snippets across programming languages. It makes innovative use of an autoregressive backbone pre-trained on both text and code, generating embeddings via last-token pooling. We outline the training recipe and demonstrate state-of-the-art performance despite the relatively small size of the models, validating this approach to code embedding model construction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21290</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 01:18:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stairway to Fairness: Connecting Group and Individual Fairness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21334</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21334.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Theresia Veronika Rampisela, Maria Maistro, Tuukka Ruotsalo, Falk Scholer, Christina Lioma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fairness in recommender systems (RSs) is commonly categorised into group fairness and individual fairness. However, there is no established scientific understanding of the relationship between the two fairness types, as prior work on both types has used different evaluation measures or evaluation objectives for each fairness type, thereby not allowing for a proper comparison of the two. As a result, it is currently not known how increasing one type of fairness may affect the other. To fill this gap, we study the relationship of group and individual fairness through a comprehensive comparison of evaluation measures that can be used for both fairness types. Our experiments with 8 runs across 3 datasets show that recommendations that are highly fair for groups can be very unfair for individuals. Our finding is novel and useful for RS practitioners aiming to improve the fairness of their systems. Our code is available at: https://github.com/theresiavr/stairway-to-fairness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21334</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 05:25:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Think in Games: Learning to Reason in Games via Reinforcement Learning   with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21365</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21365.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Liao, Yu Gu, Yuan Sui, Zining Zhu, Yifan Lu, Guohua Tang, Zhongqian Sun, Wei Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) excel at complex reasoning tasks such as mathematics and coding, yet they frequently struggle with simple interactive tasks that young children perform effortlessly. This discrepancy highlights a critical gap between declarative knowledge (knowing about something) and procedural knowledge (knowing how to do something). Although traditional reinforcement learning (RL) agents can acquire procedural knowledge through environmental interaction, they often operate as black boxes and require substantial training data. In contrast, LLMs possess extensive world knowledge and reasoning capabilities, but are unable to effectively convert this static knowledge into dynamic decision-making in interactive settings. To address this challenge, we propose Think in Games (TiG), a novel framework that empowers LLMs to develop procedural understanding through direct interaction with game environments, while retaining their inherent reasoning and explanatory abilities. Specifically, TiG reformulates RL-based decision-making as a language modeling task: LLMs generate language-guided policies, which are refined iteratively through online reinforcement learning based on environmental feedback. Our experimental results show that TiG successfully bridges the gap between declarative and procedural knowledge, achieving competitive performance with dramatically lower data and computational demands compared to conventional RL methods. Moreover, TiG provides step-by-step natural language explanations for its decisions, greatly improving transparency and interpretability in complex interactive tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21365</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 07:13:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AHELM: A Holistic Evaluation of Audio-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21376</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21376.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tony Lee, Haoqin Tu, Chi Heem Wong, Zijun Wang, Siwei Yang, Yifan Mai, Yuyin Zhou, Cihang Xie, Percy Liang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluations of audio-language models (ALMs) -- multimodal models that take interleaved audio and text as input and output text -- are hindered by the lack of standardized benchmarks; most benchmarks measure only one or two capabilities and omit evaluative aspects such as fairness or safety. Furthermore, comparison across models is difficult as separate evaluations test a limited number of models and use different prompting methods and inference parameters. To address these shortfalls, we introduce AHELM, a benchmark that aggregates various datasets -- including 2 new synthetic audio-text datasets called PARADE, which evaluates the ALMs on avoiding stereotypes, and CoRe-Bench, which measures reasoning over conversational audio through inferential multi-turn question answering -- to holistically measure the performance of ALMs across 10 aspects we have identified as important to the development and usage of ALMs: audio perception, knowledge, reasoning, emotion detection, bias, fairness, multilinguality, robustness, toxicity, and safety. We also standardize the prompts, inference parameters, and evaluation metrics to ensure equitable comparisons across models. We test 14 open-weight and closed-API ALMs from 3 developers and 3 additional simple baseline systems each consisting of an automatic speech recognizer and a language model. Our results show that while Gemini 2.5 Pro ranks top in 5 out of 10 aspects, it exhibits group unfairness (p=0.01) on ASR tasks whereas most of the other models do not. We also find that the baseline systems perform reasonably well on AHELM, with one ranking 5th overall despite having only speech-to-text capabilities. For transparency, all raw prompts, model generations, and outputs are available on our website at https://crfm.stanford.edu/helm/audio/v1.0.0. AHELM is intended to be a living benchmark and new datasets and models will be added over time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21376</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 07:40:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Morae: Proactively Pausing UI Agents for User Choices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21456</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21456.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi-Hao Peng, Dingzeyu Li, Jeffrey P. Bigham, Amy Pavel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; User interface (UI) agents promise to make inaccessible or complex UIs easier to access for blind and low-vision (BLV) users. However, current UI agents typically perform tasks end-to-end without involving users in critical choices or making them aware of important contextual information, thus reducing user agency. For example, in our field study, a BLV participant asked to buy the cheapest available sparkling water, and the agent automatically chose one from several equally priced options, without mentioning alternative products with different flavors or better ratings. To address this problem, we introduce Morae, a UI agent that automatically identifies decision points during task execution and pauses so that users can make choices. Morae uses large multimodal models to interpret user queries alongside UI code and screenshots, and prompt users for clarification when there is a choice to be made. In a study over real-world web tasks with BLV participants, Morae helped users complete more tasks and select options that better matched their preferences, as compared to baseline agents, including OpenAI Operator. More broadly, this work exemplifies a mixed-initiative approach in which users benefit from the automation of UI agents while being able to express their preferences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21456</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 09:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ELV-Halluc: Benchmarking Semantic Aggregation Hallucinations in Long   Video Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21496</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21496.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Lu, Jiahao Wang, Yaolun Zhang, Ruohui Wang, Xuanyu Zheng, Yepeng Tang, Dahua Lin, Lewei Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video multimodal large language models (Video-MLLMs) have achieved remarkable progress in video understanding. However, they remain vulnerable to hallucination-producing content inconsistent with or unrelated to video inputs. Previous video hallucination benchmarks primarily focus on short-videos. They attribute hallucinations to factors such as strong language priors, missing frames, or vision-language biases introduced by the visual encoder. While these causes indeed account for most hallucinations in short videos, they still oversimplify the cause of hallucinations. Sometimes, models generate incorrect outputs but with correct frame-level semantics. We refer to this type of hallucination as Semantic Aggregation Hallucination (SAH), which arises during the process of aggregating frame-level semantics into event-level semantic groups. Given that SAH becomes particularly critical in long videos due to increased semantic complexity across multiple events, it is essential to separate and thoroughly investigate the causes of this type of hallucination. To address the above issues, we introduce ELV-Halluc, the first benchmark dedicated to long-video hallucination, enabling a systematic investigation of SAH. Our experiments confirm the existence of SAH and show that it increases with semantic complexity. Additionally, we find that models are more prone to SAH on rapidly changing semantics. Moreover, we discuss potential approaches to mitigate SAH. We demonstrate that positional encoding strategy contributes to alleviating SAH, and further adopt DPO strategy to enhance the model's ability to distinguish semantics within and across events. To support this, we curate a dataset of 8K adversarial data pairs and achieve improvements on both ELV-Halluc and Video-MME, including a substantial 27.7% reduction in SAH ratio.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21496</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 10:25:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UItron: Foundational GUI Agent with Advanced Perception and Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21767</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.21767.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhixiong Zeng, Jing Huang, Liming Zheng, Wenkang Han, Yufeng Zhong, Lei Chen, Longrong Yang, Yingjie Chu, Yuzhi He, Lin Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; GUI agent aims to enable automated operations on Mobile/PC devices, which is an important task toward achieving artificial general intelligence. The rapid advancement of VLMs accelerates the development of GUI agents, owing to their powerful capabilities in visual understanding and task planning. However, building a GUI agent remains a challenging task due to the scarcity of operation trajectories, the availability of interactive infrastructure, and the limitation of initial capabilities in foundation models. In this work, we introduce UItron, an open-source foundational model for automatic GUI agents, featuring advanced GUI perception, grounding, and planning capabilities. UItron highlights the necessity of systemic data engineering and interactive infrastructure as foundational components for advancing GUI agent development. It not only systematically studies a series of data engineering strategies to enhance training effects, but also establishes an interactive environment connecting both Mobile and PC devices. In training, UItron adopts supervised finetuning over perception and planning tasks in various GUI scenarios, and then develop a curriculum reinforcement learning framework to enable complex reasoning and exploration for online environments. As a result, UItron achieves superior performance in benchmarks of GUI perception, grounding, and planning. In particular, UItron highlights the interaction proficiency with top-tier Chinese mobile APPs, as we identified a general lack of Chinese capabilities even in state-of-the-art solutions. To this end, we manually collect over one million steps of operation trajectories across the top 100 most popular apps, and build the offline and online agent evaluation environments. Experimental results demonstrate that UItron achieves significant progress in Chinese app scenarios, propelling GUI agents one step closer to real-world application.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21767</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 16:40:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Deep Research: Bring Your Own Model and Strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00244</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00244.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peter Belcak, Pavlo Molchanov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep research tools are among the most impactful and most commonly encountered agentic systems today. We observe, however, that each deep research agent introduced so far is hard-coded to carry out a particular research strategy using a fixed choice of tools. We introduce Universal Deep Research (UDR), a generalist agentic system that wraps around any language model and enables the user to create, edit, and refine their own entirely custom deep research strategies without any need for additional training or finetuning. To showcase the generality of our system, we equip UDR with example minimal, expansive, and intensive research strategies, and provide a user interface to facilitate experimentation with the system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00244</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 21:22:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open Data Synthesis For Deep Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00375</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00375.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyi Xia, Kun Luo, Hongjin Qian, Zheng Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly expected to go beyond simple factual queries toward Deep Research-tasks that require decomposing questions into sub-problems, coordinating multi-step reasoning, and synthesizing evidence from diverse sources. We formalize Deep Research tasks with verifiable answers as Hierarchical Constraint Satisfaction Problems (HCSPs), which are fundamentally different from single-constraint, multi-hop, or flat CSP formulations. However, existing benchmarks (e.g., Natural Questions, HotpotQA) fail to capture this complexity, while recent synthetic datasets often introduce shortcut reasoning, knowledge leakage, or lack sufficient structural depth. To address this gap, we introduce InfoSeek, a scalable framework for synthesizing complex Deep Research tasks. InfoSeek uses a dual-agent system to recursively build a Research Tree from large-scale webpages, blurring intermediate nodes into valid sub-problems, and converting these trees into natural language questions that require traversing the full hierarchy. It also enables rapid scaling, yielding over 50K training examples, a curated test set, and reasoning trajectories generated via reject sampling. Experiments show that models trained on InfoSeek consistently outperform strong baselines. On a challenging benchmark BrowseComp-Plus, 3B LLMs optimized with InfoSeek surpass much larger 32B models and lightweight commercial APIs (e.g., Gemini2.5-Flash), while achieving performance comparable to stronger APIs (e.g., Gemini2.5-Pro). By preserving meta-information such as intermediate steps and retrieval labels, InfoSeek further supports advanced optimization strategies, including compound reward design and trajectory-level exploration. We provide our codes and datasets in https://github.com/VectorSpaceLab/InfoSeek{this repository}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00375</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 06:02:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metis: Training Large Language Models with Advanced Low-Bit Quantization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00404</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00404.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hengjie Cao, Mengyi Chen, Yifeng Yang, Ruijun Huang, Fang Dong, Jixian Zhou, Anrui Chen, Mingzhi Dong, Yujiang Wang, Jinlong Hou, Yuan Cheng, Fan Wu, Fan Yang, Tun Lu, Ning Gu, Li Shang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This work identifies anisotropic parameter distributions as a fundamental barrier to training large language models (LLMs) with low-bit quantization: a few dominant singular values create wide numerical ranges that conflict with the inherent bias of block-wise quantization. This bias disproportionately preserves high-magnitude values while discarding smaller ones, causing training instability and low model performance. This work introduces Metis, a training framework that combines (i) spectral decomposition with random embedding to efficiently disentangle dominant from long-tail components, compressing broad distributions into quantization-friendly narrow ranges; (ii) adaptive learning rates in the spectral domain to amplify underrepresented directions and better capture diverse features critical for performance; and (iii) a dual-range regularizer that jointly constrains numerical precision and parameter range distribution, ensuring stable, unbiased low-bit training. With Metis, FP8 training surpasses FP32 baselines, and FP4 training achieves accuracy comparable to FP32, paving the way for robust and scalable LLM training under advanced low-bit quantization. The code implementation for Metis is available at: https://github.com/typename-yyf/Metis-quantization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00404</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 08:09:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gold Medals in an Empty Room: Diagnosing Metalinguistic Reasoning in   LLMs with Camlang</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00425</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00425.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fenghua Liu, Yulong Chen, Yixuan Liu, Zhujun Jin, Solomon Tsai, Ming Zhong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) achieve gold-medal performance across many benchmarks, yet it remains unclear whether such success reflects genuine reasoning or pattern matching. From a cognitive science perspective, an informative test is whether models can master an unfamiliar language through explicit metalinguistic deductive learning, a paradigm where human learners can reliably internalise grammatical systems through metalinguistic reasoning. We address this question with Camlang, a novel constructed language that exhibits naturalistic yet unattested feature combinations. Camlang consists of two explicit resources, a grammar book and a bilingual dictionary, which mirror adult second-language learning via explicit grammar rules and lexical lookup, and enable us to disentangle errors in morpho-syntax, lexical semantics, and sentence-level reasoning. Human experiments show that these resources are sufficient for participants to acquire Camlang and successfully solve Camlang tasks. To operationalise evaluation, we adapt CommonsenseQA into Camlang, creating Camlang-CSQA-v0, the first task in a broader suite where solving questions requires applying grammar rules and lexical mappings. Experimental results show that GPT-5 achieves 98\% EM accuracy in English but only 47\% in Camlang, far below human performance at 87\%, while other state-of-the-art reasoning LLMs perform even worse. Human verification further reveals that most model successes stem from shallow lexical alignment while GPT-5 shows emerging metalinguistic awareness to a limited extent but not systematic grammatical mastery as humans. Camlang establishes a cognitively grounded evaluation paradigm that exposes fundamental gaps between current models and human metalinguistic competence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00425</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 09:13:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixture of Global and Local Experts with Diffusion Transformer for   Controllable Face Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00428</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00428.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuechao Zou, Shun Zhang, Xing Fu, Yue Li, Kai Li, Yushe Cao, Congyan Lang, Pin Tao, Junliang Xing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Controllable face generation poses critical challenges in generative modeling due to the intricate balance required between semantic controllability and photorealism. While existing approaches struggle with disentangling semantic controls from generation pipelines, we revisit the architectural potential of Diffusion Transformers (DiTs) through the lens of expert specialization. This paper introduces Face-MoGLE, a novel framework featuring: (1) Semantic-decoupled latent modeling through mask-conditioned space factorization, enabling precise attribute manipulation; (2) A mixture of global and local experts that captures holistic structure and region-level semantics for fine-grained controllability; (3) A dynamic gating network producing time-dependent coefficients that evolve with diffusion steps and spatial locations. Face-MoGLE provides a powerful and flexible solution for high-quality, controllable face generation, with strong potential in generative modeling and security applications. Extensive experiments demonstrate its effectiveness in multimodal and monomodal face generation settings and its robust zero-shot generalization capability. Project page is available at https://github.com/XavierJiezou/Face-MoGLE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00428</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 09:21:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MobiAgent: A Systematic Framework for Customizable Mobile Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00531</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00531.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng Zhang, Erhu Feng, Xi Zhao, Yisheng Zhao, Wangbo Gong, Jiahui Sun, Dong Du, Zhichao Hua, Yubin Xia, Haibo Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the rapid advancement of Vision-Language Models (VLMs), GUI-based mobile agents have emerged as a key development direction for intelligent mobile systems. However, existing agent models continue to face significant challenges in real-world task execution, particularly in terms of accuracy and efficiency. To address these limitations, we propose MobiAgent, a comprehensive mobile agent system comprising three core components: the MobiMind-series agent models, the AgentRR acceleration framework, and the MobiFlow benchmarking suite. Furthermore, recognizing that the capabilities of current mobile agents are still limited by the availability of high-quality data, we have developed an AI-assisted agile data collection pipeline that significantly reduces the cost of manual annotation. Compared to both general-purpose LLMs and specialized GUI agent models, MobiAgent achieves state-of-the-art performance in real-world mobile scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00531</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 15:24:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C-DiffDet+: Fusing Global Scene Context with Generative Denoising for   High-Fidelity Object Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00578</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00578.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abdellah Zakaria Sellam, Ilyes Benaissa, Salah Eddine Bekhouche, Abdenour Hadid, Vito Renó, Cosimo Distante&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-grained object detection in challenging visual domains, such as vehicle damage assessment, presents a formidable challenge even for human experts to resolve reliably. While DiffusionDet has advanced the state-of-the-art through conditional denoising diffusion, its performance remains limited by local feature conditioning in context-dependent scenarios. We address this fundamental limitation by introducing Context-Aware Fusion (CAF), which leverages cross-attention mechanisms to integrate global scene context with local proposal features directly. The global context is generated using a separate dedicated encoder that captures comprehensive environmental information, enabling each object proposal to attend to scene-level understanding. Our framework significantly enhances the generative detection paradigm by enabling each object proposal to attend to comprehensive environmental information. Experimental results demonstrate an improvement over state-of-the-art models on the CarDD benchmark, establishing new performance benchmarks for context-aware object detection in fine-grained domains&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00578</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 18:06:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SQL-of-Thought: Multi-agentic Text-to-SQL with Guided Error Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00581</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00581.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Saumya Chaturvedi, Aman Chadha, Laurent Bindschaedler&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Converting natural language queries into SQL queries is a crucial challenge in both industry and academia, aiming to increase access to databases and large-scale applications. This work examines how in-context learning and chain-of-thought can be utilized to develop a robust solution for text-to-SQL systems. We propose SQL-of-Thought: a multi-agent framework that decomposes the Text2SQL task into schema linking, subproblem identification, query plan generation, SQL generation, and a guided correction loop. Unlike prior systems that rely only on execution-based static correction, we introduce taxonomy-guided dynamic error modification informed by in-context learning. SQL-of-Thought achieves state-of-the-art results on the Spider dataset and its variants, combining guided error taxonomy with reasoning-based query planning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00581</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 18:27:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gated Associative Memory: A Parallel O(N) Architecture for Efficient   Sequence Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00605</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00605.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rishiraj Acharya&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Transformer architecture, underpinned by the self-attention mechanism, has become the de facto standard for sequence modeling tasks. However, its core computational primitive scales quadratically with sequence length (O(N^2)), creating a significant bottleneck for processing long contexts. In this paper, we propose the Gated Associative Memory (GAM) network, a novel, fully parallel architecture for sequence modeling that exhibits linear complexity (O(N)) with respect to sequence length. The GAM block replaces the self-attention layer with two parallel pathways: a causal convolution to efficiently capture local, position-dependent context, and a parallel associative memory retrieval mechanism to model global, content-based patterns. These pathways are dynamically fused using a gating mechanism, allowing the model to flexibly combine local and global information for each token. We implement GAM from scratch and conduct a rigorous comparative analysis against a standard Transformer model and a modern linear-time baseline (Mamba) on the WikiText-2 benchmark, as well as against the Transformer on the TinyStories dataset. Our experiments demonstrate that GAM is consistently faster, outperforming both baselines on training speed, and achieves a superior or competitive final validation perplexity across all datasets, establishing it as a promising and efficient alternative for sequence modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00605</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 20:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLaVA-Critic-R1: Your Critic Model is Secretly a Strong Policy Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00676</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00676.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiyao Wang, Chunyuan Li, Jianwei Yang, Kai Zhang, Bo Liu, Tianyi Xiong, Furong Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In vision-language modeling, critic models are typically trained to evaluate outputs -- assigning scalar scores or pairwise preferences -- rather than to generate responses. This separation from policy models, which produce the responses, is so entrenched that critics are rarely considered for direct policy use. In this work, we challenge this convention. We propose to reorganize preference-labeled critic datasets into verifiable training signals and perform reinforcement learning directly on a base generative model, producing LLaVA-Critic-R1, a multimodal critic trained to optimize preference judgments while retaining full generation ability. Surprisingly, LLaVA-Critic-R1 emerges not only as a top-performing critic but also as a competitive policy model -- matching or surpassing specialized reasoning VLMs trained with in-domain data across 26 visual reasoning and understanding benchmarks, with an average gain of +5.7% over its base model (Qwen-2.5-VL-7B). Extending this approach to existing strong reasoning VLMs yields LLaVA-Critic-R1+, which further advances policy performance without sacrificing critic quality, achieving a SoTA performance of 71.9 on MMMU at the 7B scale. Finally, we show that the enhanced critic ability benefits inference: applying self-critique at test time yields an average +13.8% improvement on five representative reasoning tasks without additional training. Our results reveal that RL training on critic data can produce a unified model excelling at both evaluation and generation, offering a simple path toward scalable, self-improving multimodal systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00676</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 03:08:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SATQuest: A Verifier for Logical Reasoning Evaluation and Reinforcement   Fine-Tuning of LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00930</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.00930.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanxiao Zhao, Yaqian Li, Zihao Bo, Rinyoichi Takezoe, Haojia Hui, Mo Guang, Lei Ren, Xiaolin Qin, Kaiwen Long&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable general reasoning capabilities. However, systematically evaluating and enhancing these reasoning capabilities is challenging due to the lack of controllable and scalable tools for fine-grained analysis. Existing benchmarks and datasets often lack the necessary variable control for multi-dimensional, systematic analysis and training, or have narrow problem types and formats. To address these limitations, we introduce SATQuest, a systematic verifier designed to evaluate and enhance logical reasoning in LLMs by generating diverse, Satisfiability-based logical reasoning problems directly from Conjunctive Normal Form (CNF) instances. SATQuest structures these problems along three orthogonal dimensions: instance scale, problem type, and question format, employing randomized, SAT-based problem generation and objective answer verification via PySAT. This design mitigates memorization issues, allows for nuanced insights into reasoning performance, and enables effective reinforcement fine-tuning. Our extensive evaluation of various LLMs using SATQuest identified significant limitations in their logical reasoning, particularly in generalizing beyond familiar mathematical formats. Furthermore, we show that reinforcement fine-tuning with SATQuest rewards substantially improves targeted task performance and generalizes to more complex instances, while highlighting remaining challenges in cross-format adaptation. Through these demonstrations, we showcase SATQuest's potential as a foundational tool and a valuable starting point for advancing LLM logical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00930</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 16:56:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlashAdventure: A Benchmark for GUI Agents Solving Full Story Arcs in   Diverse Adventure Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01052</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01052.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaewoo Ahn, Junseo Kim, Heeseung Yun, Jaehyeon Son, Dongmin Park, Jaewoong Cho, Gunhee Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; GUI agents powered by LLMs show promise in interacting with diverse digital environments. Among these, video games offer a valuable testbed due to their varied interfaces, with adventure games posing additional challenges through complex, narrative-driven interactions. Existing game benchmarks, however, lack diversity and rarely evaluate agents on completing entire storylines. To address this, we introduce FlashAdventure, a benchmark of 34 Flash-based adventure games designed to test full story arc completion and tackle the observation-behavior gap: the challenge of remembering and acting on earlier gameplay information. We also propose CUA-as-a-Judge, an automated gameplay evaluator, and COAST, an agentic framework leveraging long-term clue memory to better plan and solve sequential tasks. Experiments show current GUI agents struggle with full story arcs, while COAST improves milestone completion by bridging the observation-behavior gap. Nonetheless, a marked discrepancy between humans and best-performing agents warrants continued research efforts to narrow this divide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01052</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 01:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VerlTool: Towards Holistic Agentic Reinforcement Learning with Tool Use</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01055</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01055.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dongfu Jiang, Yi Lu, Zhuofeng Li, Zhiheng Lyu, Ping Nie, Haozhe Wang, Alex Su, Hui Chen, Kai Zou, Chao Du, Tianyu Pang, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has demonstrated success in enhancing LLM reasoning capabilities, but remains limited to single-turn interactions without tool integration. While recent Agentic Reinforcement Learning with Tool use (ARLT) approaches have emerged to address multi-turn tool interactions, existing works develop task-specific codebases that suffer from fragmentation, synchronous execution bottlenecks, and limited extensibility across domains. These inefficiencies hinder broader community adoption and algorithmic innovation. We introduce VerlTool, a unified and modular framework that addresses these limitations through systematic design principles. VerlTool provides four key contributions: (1) upstream alignment with VeRL ensuring compatibility and simplified maintenance, (2) unified tool management via standardized APIs supporting diverse modalities including code execution, search, SQL databases, and vision processing, (3) asynchronous rollout execution achieving near 2times speedup by eliminating synchronization bottlenecks, and (4) comprehensive evaluation demonstrating competitive performance across 6 ARLT domains. Our framework formalizes ARLT as multi-turn trajectories with multi-modal observation tokens (text/image/video), extending beyond single-turn RLVR paradigms. We train and evaluate models on mathematical reasoning, knowledge QA, SQL generation, visual reasoning, web search, and software engineering tasks, achieving results comparable to specialized systems while providing unified training infrastructure. The modular plugin architecture enables rapid tool integration requiring only lightweight Python definitions, significantly reducing development overhead and providing a scalable foundation for tool-augmented RL research. Our code is open-sourced at https://github.com/TIGER-AI-Lab/verl-tool.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01055</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 01:45:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robix: A Unified Model for Robot Interaction, Reasoning and Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huang Fang, Mengxi Zhang, Heng Dong, Wei Li, Zixuan Wang, Qifeng Zhang, Xueyun Tian, Yucheng Hu, Hang Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Robix, a unified model that integrates robot reasoning, task planning, and natural language interaction within a single vision-language architecture. Acting as the high-level cognitive layer in a hierarchical robot system, Robix dynamically generates atomic commands for the low-level controller and verbal responses for human interaction, enabling robots to follow complex instructions, plan long-horizon tasks, and interact naturally with human within an end-to-end framework. Robix further introduces novel capabilities such as proactive dialogue, real-time interruption handling, and context-aware commonsense reasoning during task execution. At its core, Robix leverages chain-of-thought reasoning and adopts a three-stage training strategy: (1) continued pretraining to enhance foundational embodied reasoning abilities including 3D spatial understanding, visual grounding, and task-centric reasoning; (2) supervised finetuning to model human-robot interaction and task planning as a unified reasoning-action sequence; and (3) reinforcement learning to improve reasoning-action consistency and long-horizon task coherence. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Robix outperforms both open-source and commercial baselines (e.g., GPT-4o and Gemini 2.5 Pro) in interactive task execution, demonstrating strong generalization across diverse instruction types (e.g., open-ended, multi-stage, constrained, invalid, and interrupted) and various user-involved tasks such as table bussing, grocery shopping, and dietary filtering.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01106</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 03:53:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>POINTS-Reader: Distillation-Free Adaptation of Vision-Language Models   for Document Conversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01215</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01215.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuan Liu, Zhongyin Zhao, Le Tian, Haicheng Wang, Xubing Ye, Yangxiu You, Zilin Yu, Chuhan Wu, Xiao Zhou, Yang Yu, Jie Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; High-quality labeled data is essential for training accurate document conversion models, particularly in domains with complex formats such as tables, formulas, and multi-column text. However, manual annotation is both costly and time-consuming, while automatic labeling using existing models often lacks accuracy in handling such challenging scenarios. Consequently, training student models by distilling outputs from teacher models can significantly limit their performance in real-world applications. In this paper, we propose a fully automated, distillation-free framework comprising two stages for constructing high-quality document extraction datasets and models capable of handling diverse document formats and layouts. In the first stage, we introduce a method for generating large-scale, diverse synthetic data, which enables a model to extract key elements in a unified format with strong initial performance. In the second stage, we present a self-improvement approach that further adapts the model, initially trained on synthetic data, to real-world documents. Specifically, we first use the fine-tuned model to annotate real documents, then apply a suite of filtering strategies to verify annotation quality, and finally retrain the model on the verified dataset. By iteratively repeating this process, we progressively enhance both the model's conversion capabilities and the quality of the generated data. We train a public POINTS-1.5 model to obtain POINTS-Reader, which surpasses many existing public and proprietary models of comparable or larger size. Our model is available at https://github.com/Tencent/POINTS-Reader.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01215</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 07:54:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards More Diverse and Challenging Pre-training for Point Cloud   Learning: Self-Supervised Cross Reconstruction with Decoupled Views</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01250</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01250.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangdong Zhang, Shaofeng Zhang, Junchi Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Point cloud learning, especially in a self-supervised way without manual labels, has gained growing attention in both vision and learning communities due to its potential utility in a wide range of applications. Most existing generative approaches for point cloud self-supervised learning focus on recovering masked points from visible ones within a single view. Recognizing that a two-view pre-training paradigm inherently introduces greater diversity and variance, it may thus enable more challenging and informative pre-training. Inspired by this, we explore the potential of two-view learning in this domain. In this paper, we propose Point-PQAE, a cross-reconstruction generative paradigm that first generates two decoupled point clouds/views and then reconstructs one from the other. To achieve this goal, we develop a crop mechanism for point cloud view generation for the first time and further propose a novel positional encoding to represent the 3D relative position between the two decoupled views. The cross-reconstruction significantly increases the difficulty of pre-training compared to self-reconstruction, which enables our method to surpass previous single-modal self-reconstruction methods in 3D self-supervised learning. Specifically, it outperforms the self-reconstruction baseline (Point-MAE) by 6.5%, 7.0%, and 6.7% in three variants of ScanObjectNN with the Mlp-Linear evaluation protocol. The code is available at https://github.com/aHapBean/Point-PQAE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01250</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 08:42:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>M3Ret: Unleashing Zero-shot Multimodal Medical Image Retrieval via   Self-Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01360</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01360.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Che Liu, Zheng Jiang, Chengyu Fang, Heng Guo, Yan-Jie Zhou, Jiaqi Qu, Le Lu, Minfeng Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Medical image retrieval is essential for clinical decision-making and translational research, relying on discriminative visual representations. Yet, current methods remain fragmented, relying on separate architectures and training strategies for 2D, 3D, and video-based medical data. This modality-specific design hampers scalability and inhibits the development of unified representations. To enable unified learning, we curate a large-scale hybrid-modality dataset comprising 867,653 medical imaging samples, including 2D X-rays and ultrasounds, RGB endoscopy videos, and 3D CT scans. Leveraging this dataset, we train M3Ret, a unified visual encoder without any modality-specific customization. It successfully learns transferable representations using both generative (MAE) and contrastive (SimDINO) self-supervised learning (SSL) paradigms. Our approach sets a new state-of-the-art in zero-shot image-to-image retrieval across all individual modalities, surpassing strong baselines such as DINOv3 and the text-supervised BMC-CLIP. More remarkably, strong cross-modal alignment emerges without paired data, and the model generalizes to unseen MRI tasks, despite never observing MRI during pretraining, demonstrating the generalizability of purely visual self-supervision to unseen modalities. Comprehensive analyses further validate the scalability of our framework across model and data sizes. These findings deliver a promising signal to the medical imaging community, positioning M3Ret as a step toward foundation models for visual SSL in multimodal medical image understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01360</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 10:59:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Vectors: Transferring Chain-of-Thought Capabilities via Task   Arithmetic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01363</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01363.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohammad Zbeeb, Hasan Abed Al Kader Hammoud, Bernard Ghanem&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models often require costly optimization, such as reinforcement learning, to master complex reasoning tasks. This work demonstrates that reasoning ability, once learned, can be extracted and transferred between models as a compact task vector. We source two publicly available, identically initialized Qwen2.5 models, one fine-tuned with supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and the other with group relative policy optimization (GRPO) on the same dataset. From these, we extract a reasoning vector: v_{reason} = theta_{GRPO} - theta_{SFT}. We hypothesize that this vector captures the reasoning capability instilled by reinforcement learning while factoring out shared knowledge from the SFT process. When added to compatible instruction-tuned models through simple arithmetic, this vector consistently improves performance across diverse reasoning benchmarks: GSM8K (+4.9%), HumanEval (+4.3%), SciQ (+1.7%), and BigBenchHard (+12.3% for the 1.5B model). The performance improvements persist under adversarial conditions. Conversely, subtracting the vector causes significant performance degradation (-11.8% on GSM8K), demonstrating the vector's strong contribution to the model's reasoning abilities. This work shows how reasoning capabilities, typically developed through expensive training, can be extracted from existing open-source models and reused through simple tensor arithmetic, offering a practical way to enhance models by recycling prior computational investments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01363</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 11:04:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepResearch Arena: The First Exam of LLMs' Research Abilities via   Seminar-Grounded Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01396</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01396.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haiyuan Wan, Chen Yang, Junchi Yu, Meiqi Tu, Jiaxuan Lu, Di Yu, Jianbao Cao, Ben Gao, Jiaqing Xie, Aoran Wang, Wenlong Zhang, Philip Torr, Dongzhan Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep research agents have attracted growing attention for their potential to orchestrate multi-stage research workflows, spanning literature synthesis, methodological design, and empirical verification. Despite these strides, evaluating their research capability faithfully is rather challenging due to the difficulty of collecting frontier research questions that genuinely capture researchers' attention and intellectual curiosity. To address this gap, we introduce DeepResearch Arena, a benchmark grounded in academic seminars that capture rich expert discourse and interaction, better reflecting real-world research environments and reducing the risk of data leakage. To automatically construct DeepResearch Arena, we propose a Multi-Agent Hierarchical Task Generation (MAHTG) system that extracts research-worthy inspirations from seminar transcripts. The MAHTG system further translates research-worthy inspirations into high-quality research tasks, ensuring the traceability of research task formulation while filtering noise. With the MAHTG system, we curate DeepResearch Arena with over 10,000 high-quality research tasks from over 200 academic seminars, spanning 12 disciplines, such as literature, history, and science. Our extensive evaluation shows that DeepResearch Arena presents substantial challenges for current state-of-the-art agents, with clear performance gaps observed across different models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01396</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 11:42:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Optimizers for Large Language Model Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01440</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01440.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Andrei Semenov, Matteo Pagliardini, Martin Jaggi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The recent development of Large Language Models (LLMs) has been accompanied by an effervescence of novel ideas and methods to better optimize the loss of deep learning models. Claims from those methods are myriad: from faster convergence to removing reliance on certain hyperparameters. However, the diverse experimental protocols used to validate these claims make direct comparisons between methods challenging. This study presents a comprehensive evaluation of recent optimization techniques across standardized LLM pretraining scenarios, systematically varying model size, batch size, and training duration. Through careful tuning of each method, we provide guidance to practitioners on which optimizer is best suited for each scenario. For researchers, our work highlights promising directions for future optimization research. Finally, by releasing our code and making all experiments fully reproducible, we hope our efforts can help the development and rigorous benchmarking of future methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01440</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 12:50:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kwai Keye-VL 1.5 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01563</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01563.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Biao Yang, Bin Wen, Boyang Ding, Changyi Liu, Chenglong Chu, Chengru Song, Chongling Rao, Chuan Yi, Da Li, Dunju Zang, Fan Yang, Guorui Zhou, Guowang Zhang, Han Shen, Hao Peng, Haojie Ding, Hao Wang, Hengrui Ju, Jiaming Huang, Jiangxia Cao, Jiankang Chen, Jingyun Hua, Kaibing Chen, Kaiyu Jiang, Kaiyu Tang, Kun Gai, Muhao Wei, Qiang Wang, Ruitao Wang, Sen Na, Shengnan Zhang, Siyang Mao, Sui Huang, Tianke Zhang, Tingting Gao, Wei Chen, Wei Yuan, Xiangyu Wu, Xiao Hu, Xingyu Lu, Yi-Fan Zhang, Yiping Yang, Yulong Chen, Zeyi Lu, Zhenhua Wu, Zhixin Ling, Zhuoran Yang, Ziming Li, Di Xu, Haixuan Gao, Hang Li, Jing Wang, Lejian Ren, Qigen Hu, Qianqian Wang, Shiyao Wang, Xinchen Luo, Yan Li, Yuhang Hu, Zixing Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In recent years, the development of Large Language Models (LLMs) has significantly advanced, extending their capabilities to multimodal tasks through Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs). However, video understanding remains a challenging area due to the dynamic and information-dense nature of videos. Existing models struggle with the trade-off between spatial resolution and temporal coverage when processing video content. We present Keye-VL-1.5, which addresses fundamental challenges in video comprehension through three key innovations. First, we introduce a novel Slow-Fast video encoding strategy that dynamically allocates computational resources based on inter-frame similarity, processing key frames with significant visual changes at higher resolution (Slow pathway) while handling relatively static frames with increased temporal coverage at lower resolution (Fast pathway). Second, we implement a progressive four-stage pre-training methodology that systematically extends the model's context length from 8K to 128K tokens, enabling processing of longer videos and more complex visual content. Third, we develop a comprehensive post-training pipeline focusing on reasoning enhancement and human preference alignment, incorporating a 5-step chain-of-thought data construction process, iterative GSPO-based reinforcement learning with progressive prompt hinting for difficult cases, and alignment training. Through extensive evaluation on public benchmarks and rigorous internal human assessment, Keye-VL-1.5 demonstrates significant improvements over existing models, particularly excelling in video understanding tasks while maintaining competitive performance on general multimodal benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01563</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 15:46:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ViSTA-SLAM: Visual SLAM with Symmetric Two-view Association</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01584</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01584.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ganlin Zhang, Shenhan Qian, Xi Wang, Daniel Cremers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present ViSTA-SLAM as a real-time monocular visual SLAM system that operates without requiring camera intrinsics, making it broadly applicable across diverse camera setups. At its core, the system employs a lightweight symmetric two-view association (STA) model as the frontend, which simultaneously estimates relative camera poses and regresses local pointmaps from only two RGB images. This design reduces model complexity significantly, the size of our frontend is only 35\% that of comparable state-of-the-art methods, while enhancing the quality of two-view constraints used in the pipeline. In the backend, we construct a specially designed Sim(3) pose graph that incorporates loop closures to address accumulated drift. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach achieves superior performance in both camera tracking and dense 3D reconstruction quality compared to current methods. Github repository: https://github.com/zhangganlin/vista-slam&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01584</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 16:12:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Large Vision and Language Models by Learning from a Panel of   Peers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01610</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01610.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jefferson Hernandez, Jing Shi, Simon Jenni, Vicente Ordonez, Kushal Kafle&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional alignment methods for Large Vision and Language Models (LVLMs) primarily rely on human-curated preference data. Human-generated preference data is costly; machine-generated preference data is limited in quality; and self-supervised preference data often introduces hallucinations. To overcome these limitations, we propose a novel Panel-of-Peers learning framework inspired by collaborative learning among humans. This approach leverages a panel of LVLMs, each evaluating and learning from their collective outputs through an iterative self-improvement process. By simulating a peer review system, our models generate, assess, and refine outputs in response to a curated set of prompts, mimicking a classroom learning environment. We demonstrate that this methodology enhances model performance without requiring extensive human-labeled datasets. Our experiments show significant improvement across multiple benchmarks, demonstrating the potential of peer evaluations as a scalable alternative to self-supervised alignment. Notably, we show that Panel-of-Peers increases the average score on fifteen benchmarks from 48% to 57%&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01610</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 16:43:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenVision 2: A Family of Generative Pretrained Visual Encoders for   Multimodal Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01644</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01644.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanqing Liu, Xianhang Li, Letian Zhang, Zirui Wang, Zeyu Zheng, Yuyin Zhou, Cihang Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper provides a simplification on OpenVision's architecture and loss design for enhancing its training efficiency. Following the prior vision-language pretraining works CapPa and AIMv2, as well as modern multimodal designs like LLaVA, our changes are straightforward: we remove the text encoder (and therefore the contrastive loss), retaining only the captioning loss as a purely generative training signal. We name this new version OpenVision 2. The initial results are promising: despite this simplification, OpenVision 2 competitively matches the original model's performance on a broad set of multimodal benchmarks while substantially cutting both training time and memory consumption. For example, with ViT-L/14, it reduces training time by about 1.5x (from 83h to 57h), and memory usage by about 1.8x (from 24.5GB to 13.8GB, equivalently allowing the maximum batch size to grow from 2k to 8k). This superior training efficiency also allows us to scale far beyond the largest vision encoder used in OpenVision, reaching more than 1 billion parameters. We hold a strong belief that this lightweight, generative-only paradigm is compelling for future vision encoder development in multimodal foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01644</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 17:38:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flaw or Artifact? Rethinking Prompt Sensitivity in Evaluating LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01790</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01790.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Andong Hua, Kenan Tang, Chenhe Gu, Jindong Gu, Eric Wong, Yao Qin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Prompt sensitivity, referring to the phenomenon where paraphrasing (i.e., repeating something written or spoken using different words) leads to significant changes in large language model (LLM) performance, has been widely accepted as a core limitation of LLMs. In this work, we revisit this issue and ask: Is the widely reported high prompt sensitivity truly an inherent weakness of LLMs, or is it largely an artifact of evaluation processes? To answer this question, we systematically evaluate 7 LLMs (e.g., GPT and Gemini family) across 6 benchmarks, including both multiple-choice and open-ended tasks on 12 diverse prompt templates. We find that much of the prompt sensitivity stems from heuristic evaluation methods, including log-likelihood scoring and rigid answer matching, which often overlook semantically correct responses expressed through alternative phrasings, such as synonyms or paraphrases. When we adopt LLM-as-a-Judge evaluations, we observe a substantial reduction in performance variance and a consistently higher correlation in model rankings across prompts. Our findings suggest that modern LLMs are more robust to prompt templates than previously believed, and that prompt sensitivity may be more an artifact of evaluation than a flaw in the models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01790</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 21:38:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOSAIC: Multi-Subject Personalized Generation via Correspondence-Aware   Alignment and Disentanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01977</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01977.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dong She, Siming Fu, Mushui Liu, Qiaoqiao Jin, Hualiang Wang, Mu Liu, Jidong Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-subject personalized generation presents unique challenges in maintaining identity fidelity and semantic coherence when synthesizing images conditioned on multiple reference subjects. Existing methods often suffer from identity blending and attribute leakage due to inadequate modeling of how different subjects should interact within shared representation spaces. We present MOSAIC, a representation-centric framework that rethinks multi-subject generation through explicit semantic correspondence and orthogonal feature disentanglement. Our key insight is that multi-subject generation requires precise semantic alignment at the representation level - knowing exactly which regions in the generated image should attend to which parts of each reference. To enable this, we introduce SemAlign-MS, a meticulously annotated dataset providing fine-grained semantic correspondences between multiple reference subjects and target images, previously unavailable in this domain. Building on this foundation, we propose the semantic correspondence attention loss to enforce precise point-to-point semantic alignment, ensuring high consistency from each reference to its designated regions. Furthermore, we develop the multi-reference disentanglement loss to push different subjects into orthogonal attention subspaces, preventing feature interference while preserving individual identity characteristics. Extensive experiments demonstrate that MOSAIC achieves state-of-the-art performance on multiple benchmarks. Notably, while existing methods typically degrade beyond 3 subjects, MOSAIC maintains high fidelity with 4+ reference subjects, opening new possibilities for complex multi-subject synthesis applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01977</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 05:40:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Noise Inversion for Next-scale Autoregressive Text-based Image   Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01984</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01984.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Quan Dao, Xiaoxiao He, Ligong Han, Ngan Hoai Nguyen, Amin Heyrani Nobar, Faez Ahmed, Han Zhang, Viet Anh Nguyen, Dimitris Metaxas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual autoregressive models (VAR) have recently emerged as a promising class of generative models, achieving performance comparable to diffusion models in text-to-image generation tasks. While conditional generation has been widely explored, the ability to perform prompt-guided image editing without additional training is equally critical, as it supports numerous practical real-world applications. This paper investigates the text-to-image editing capabilities of VAR by introducing Visual AutoRegressive Inverse Noise (VARIN), the first noise inversion-based editing technique designed explicitly for VAR models. VARIN leverages a novel pseudo-inverse function for argmax sampling, named Location-aware Argmax Inversion (LAI), to generate inverse Gumbel noises. These inverse noises enable precise reconstruction of the source image and facilitate targeted, controllable edits aligned with textual prompts. Extensive experiments demonstrate that VARIN effectively modifies source images according to specified prompts while significantly preserving the original background and structural details, thus validating its efficacy as a practical editing approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01984</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 06:01:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attributes as Textual Genes: Leveraging LLMs as Genetic Algorithm   Simulators for Conditional Synthetic Data Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02040</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02040.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guangzeng Han, Weisi Liu, Xiaolei Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) excel at generating synthetic data, but ensuring its quality and diversity remains challenging. We propose Genetic Prompt, a novel framework that combines genetic algorithms with LLMs to augment synthetic data generation. Our approach treats semantic text attributes as gene sequences and leverages the LLM to simulate crossover and mutation operations. This genetic process enhances data quality and diversity by creating novel attribute combinations, yielding synthetic distributions closer to real-world data. To optimize parent selection, we also integrate an active learning scheme that expands the offspring search space. Our experiments on multiple NLP tasks reveal several key findings: Genetic Prompt not only significantly outperforms state-of-the-art baselines but also shows robust performance across various generator model sizes and scales. Moreover, we demonstrate that fusing our synthetic data with the original training set significantly boosts downstream model performance, particularly for class-imbalanced scenarios. Our findings validate that Genetic Prompt is an effective method for producing high-quality synthetic data for a wide range of NLP applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02040</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 07:35:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fantastic Pretraining Optimizers and Where to Find Them</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02046</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02046.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaiyue Wen, David Hall, Tengyu Ma, Percy Liang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AdamW has long been the dominant optimizer in language model pretraining, despite numerous claims that alternative optimizers offer 1.4 to 2x speedup. We posit that two methodological shortcomings have obscured fair comparisons and hindered practical adoption: (i) unequal hyperparameter tuning and (ii) limited or misleading evaluation setups. To address these two issues, we conduct a systematic study of ten deep learning optimizers across four model scales (0.1B-1.2B parameters) and data-to-model ratios (1-8x the Chinchilla optimum). We find that fair and informative comparisons require rigorous hyperparameter tuning and evaluations across a range of model scales and data-to-model ratios, performed at the end of training. First, optimal hyperparameters for one optimizer may be suboptimal for another, making blind hyperparameter transfer unfair. Second, the actual speedup of many proposed optimizers over well-tuned baselines is lower than claimed and decreases with model size to only 1.1x for 1.2B parameter models. Thirdly, comparing intermediate checkpoints before reaching the target training budgets can be misleading, as rankings between two optimizers can flip during training due to learning rate decay. Through our thorough investigation, we find that all the fastest optimizers such as Muon and Soap, use matrices as preconditioners -- multiplying gradients with matrices rather than entry-wise scalars. However, the speedup of matrix-based optimizers is inversely proportional to model scale, decreasing from 1.4x over AdamW for 0.1B parameter models to merely 1.1x for 1.2B parameter models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02046</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 07:43:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AMBEDKAR-A Multi-level Bias Elimination through a Decoding Approach with   Knowledge Augmentation for Robust Constitutional Alignment of Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02133</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02133.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Snehasis Mukhopadhyay, Aryan Kasat, Shivam Dubey, Rahul Karthikeyan, Dhruv Sood, Vinija Jain, Aman Chadha, Amitava Das&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) can inadvertently reflect societal biases present in their training data, leading to harmful or prejudiced outputs. In the Indian context, our empirical evaluations across a suite of models reveal that biases around caste and religion are particularly salient. Yet, most existing mitigation strategies are Western-centric and fail to address these local nuances. We propose AMBEDKAR, a framework inspired by the egalitarian vision of Dr B. R. Ambedkar, architect of the Indian Constitution, to guide LLM outputs toward fairness, neutrality, and inclusion in line with Articles 14 to 17. Our approach introduces a Constitution-Aware Decoding Layer, guided by the AI Constitution of India and applied only at inference time, without any parameter updates to the base model. We incorporate a speculative decoding algorithm that proactively reduces casteist and communal bias during generation. This mitigation layer operates directly within the decoding process, avoiding changes to model internals and lowering the computational and infrastructural costs associated with retraining. We reinterpret speculative decoding not merely as an efficiency tool but as a mechanism for fairness. In this framework, a Small Language Model (SLM) acts as a potentially biased generator, while a constitutionally guided Large Language Model (LLM) serves as the verifier. Rather than accelerating generation, the LLM enforces bias-robust trajectories in the SLM outputs. This inversion of roles gives rise to a fairness-by-speculation paradigm. Our approach yields an absolute reduction of bias up to 26.41 percent compared to baseline. Our source code, datasets, and results are available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/AMBEDKAR-983B/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02133</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 09:33:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baichuan-M2: Scaling Medical Capability with Large Verifier System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02208</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02208.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baichuan-M2 Team, Chengfeng Dou, Chong Liu, Fan Yang, Fei Li, Jiyuan Jia, Mingyang Chen, Qiang Ju, Shuai Wang, Shunya Dang, Tianpeng Li, Xiangrong Zeng, Yijie Zhou, Chenzheng Zhu, Da Pan, Fei Deng, Guangwei Ai, Guosheng Dong, Hongda Zhang, Jinyang Tai, Jixiang Hong, Kai Lu, Linzhuang Sun, Peidong Guo, Qian Ma, Rihui Xin, Shihui Yang, Shusen Zhang, Yichuan Mo, Zheng Liang, Zhishou Zhang, Hengfu Cui, Zuyi Zhu, Xiaochuan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language models (LLMs) advance in conversational and reasoning capabilities, their practical application in healthcare has become a critical research focus. However, there is a notable gap between the performance of medical LLMs on static benchmarks such as USMLE and their utility in real-world clinical decision-making. This discrepancy arises because traditional exams fail to capture the dynamic, interactive nature of medical consultations. To address this challenge, we introduce a novel dynamic verification framework that moves beyond static answer verifier, establishing a large-scale, high-fidelity interactive reinforcement learning system. Our framework comprises two key components: a Patient Simulator that creates realistic clinical environments using de-identified medical records, and a Clinical Rubrics Generator that dynamically produces multi-dimensional evaluation metrics. Building on this foundation, we develop Baichuan-M2, a 32B-parameter medical augmented reasoning model trained through a multi-stage reinforcement learning strategy with an improved Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) algorithm. Evaluated on HealthBench, Baichuan-M2 outperforms all other open-source models and most advanced closed-source counterparts, achieving a score above 32 on the challenging HealthBench Hard benchmark-previously exceeded only by GPT-5. Our work demonstrates that robust dynamic verifier system is essential for aligning LLM capabilities with practical clinical applications, establishing a new Pareto front in the performance-parameter trade-off for medical AI deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02208</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 11:23:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DCPO: Dynamic Clipping Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02333</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02333.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shihui Yang, Chengfeng Dou, Peidong Guo, Kai Lu, Qiang Ju, Fei Deng, Rihui Xin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning from Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as a promising framework for enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models. However, existing approaches such as GRPO often suffer from zero gradients. This problem arises primarily due to fixed clipping bounds for token-level probability ratios and the standardization of identical rewards, which can lead to ineffective gradient updates and underutilization of generated responses. In this work, we propose Dynamic Clipping Policy Optimization (DCPO), which introduces a dynamic clipping strategy that adaptively adjusts the clipping bounds based on token-specific prior probabilities to enhance token-level exploration, and a smooth advantage standardization technique that standardizes rewards across cumulative training steps to improve the response-level effective utilization of generated responses. DCPO achieved state-of-the-art performance on four benchmarks based on four different models. In particular, DCPO achieved an Avg@1 of 46.7 under greedy decoding and an Avg@32 of 38.8 under 32 times sampling on the AIME24 benchmark, surpassing both DAPO (36.7/31.6) and GRPO (36.7/32.1) on the Qwen2.5-Math-7B model. On the AIME25 benchmark based on Qwen2.5-14B, DCPO achieves a performance of (23.3/19.0), surpassing GRPO (13.3/10.5) and DAPO (20.0/15.3). Furthermore, DCPO achieved an average 28% improvement in the nonzero advantage over GRPO in four models, doubled the training efficiency over DAPO, and significantly reduced the token clipping ratio by an order of magnitude compared to both GRPO and DAPO, while achieving superior performance. These results highlight DCPO's effectiveness in leveraging generated data more efficiently for reinforcement learning in large language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02333</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 14:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedDINOv3: How to adapt vision foundation models for medical image   segmentation?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02379</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02379.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuheng Li, Yizhou Wu, Yuxiang Lai, Mingzhe Hu, Xiaofeng Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Accurate segmentation of organs and tumors in CT and MRI scans is essential for diagnosis, treatment planning, and disease monitoring. While deep learning has advanced automated segmentation, most models remain task-specific, lacking generalizability across modalities and institutions. Vision foundation models (FMs) pretrained on billion-scale natural images offer powerful and transferable representations. However, adapting them to medical imaging faces two key challenges: (1) the ViT backbone of most foundation models still underperform specialized CNNs on medical image segmentation, and (2) the large domain gap between natural and medical images limits transferability. We introduce MedDINOv3, a simple and effective framework for adapting DINOv3 to medical segmentation. We first revisit plain ViTs and design a simple and effective architecture with multi-scale token aggregation. Then, we perform domain-adaptive pretraining on CT-3M, a curated collection of 3.87M axial CT slices, using a multi-stage DINOv3 recipe to learn robust dense features. MedDINOv3 matches or exceeds state-of-the-art performance across four segmentation benchmarks, demonstrating the potential of vision foundation models as unified backbones for medical image segmentation. The code is available at https://github.com/ricklisz/MedDINOv3.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02379</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 14:44:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GenCompositor: Generative Video Compositing with Diffusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02460</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02460.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuzhou Yang, Xiaoyu Li, Xiaodong Cun, Guangzhi Wang, Lingen Li, Ying Shan, Jian Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video compositing combines live-action footage to create video production, serving as a crucial technique in video creation and film production. Traditional pipelines require intensive labor efforts and expert collaboration, resulting in lengthy production cycles and high manpower costs. To address this issue, we automate this process with generative models, called generative video compositing. This new task strives to adaptively inject identity and motion information of foreground video to the target video in an interactive manner, allowing users to customize the size, motion trajectory, and other attributes of the dynamic elements added in final video. Specifically, we designed a novel Diffusion Transformer (DiT) pipeline based on its intrinsic properties. To maintain consistency of the target video before and after editing, we revised a light-weight DiT-based background preservation branch with masked token injection. As to inherit dynamic elements from other sources, a DiT fusion block is proposed using full self-attention, along with a simple yet effective foreground augmentation for training. Besides, for fusing background and foreground videos with different layouts based on user control, we developed a novel position embedding, named Extended Rotary Position Embedding (ERoPE). Finally, we curated a dataset comprising 61K sets of videos for our new task, called VideoComp. This data includes complete dynamic elements and high-quality target videos. Experiments demonstrate that our method effectively realizes generative video compositing, outperforming existing possible solutions in fidelity and consistency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02460</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 16:10:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SimpleTIR: End-to-End Reinforcement Learning for Multi-Turn   Tool-Integrated Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02479</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02479.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenghai Xue, Longtao Zheng, Qian Liu, Yingru Li, Xiaosen Zheng, Zejun Ma, Bo An&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 76&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) can significantly improve their reasoning capabilities by interacting with external tools, a paradigm known as Tool-Integrated Reasoning (TIR). However, extending TIR to multi-turn scenarios using Reinforcement Learning (RL) is often hindered by training instability and performance collapse. We identify that such instability is primarily caused by a distributional drift from external tool feedback, leading to the generation of low-probability tokens. This issue compounds over successive turns, causing catastrophic gradient norm explosions that derail the training process. To address this challenge, we introduce SimpleTIR , a plug-and-play algorithm that stabilizes multi-turn TIR training. Its core strategy is to identify and filter out trajectories containing void turns, i.e., turns that yield neither a code block nor a final answer. By removing these problematic trajectories from the policy update, SimpleTIR effectively blocks the harmful, high-magnitude gradients, thus stabilizing the learning dynamics. Extensive experiments show that SimpleTIR achieves state-of-the-art performance on challenging math reasoning benchmarks, notably elevating the AIME24 score from a text-only baseline of 22.1 to 50.5 when starting from the Qwen2.5-7B base model. Furthermore, by avoiding the constraints of supervised fine-tuning, SimpleTIR encourages the model to discover diverse and sophisticated reasoning patterns, such as self-correction and cross-validation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02479</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 16:30:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implicit Actor Critic Coupling via a Supervised Learning Framework for   RLVR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02522</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02522.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaming Li, Longze Chen, Ze Gong, Yukun Chen, Lu Wang, Wanwei He, Run Luo, Min Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) have empowered large language models (LLMs) to tackle challenging reasoning tasks such as mathematics and programming. RLVR leverages verifiable outcome rewards to guide policy optimization, enabling LLMs to progressively improve output quality in a grounded and reliable manner. Despite its promise, the RLVR paradigm poses significant challenges, as existing methods often suffer from sparse reward signals and unstable policy gradient updates, particularly in RL-based approaches. To address the challenges, we propose PACS, a novel RLVR framework that achieves imPlicit Actor Critic coupling via a Supervised learning framework. By treating the outcome reward as a predictable label, we reformulate the RLVR problem into a supervised learning task over a score function parameterized by the policy model and optimized using cross-entropy loss. A detailed gradient analysis shows that this supervised formulation inherently recovers the classical policy gradient update while implicitly coupling actor and critic roles, yielding more stable and efficient training. Benchmarking on challenging mathematical reasoning tasks, PACS outperforms strong RLVR baselines, such as PPO and GRPO, achieving superior reasoning performance. For instance, PACS achieves 59.78\% at pass@256 on AIME 2025, representing improvements of 13.32 and 14.36 points over PPO and GRPO. This simple yet powerful framework offers a promising avenue for LLMs post-training with verifiable rewards. Our code and data are available as open source at https://github.com/ritzz-ai/PACS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02522</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:22:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavors of Moonshine: Tiny Specialized ASR Models for Edge Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02523</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02523.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Evan King, Adam Sabra, Manjunath Kudlur, James Wang, Pete Warden&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present the Flavors of Moonshine, a suite of tiny automatic speech recognition (ASR) models specialized for a range of underrepresented languages. Prevailing wisdom suggests that multilingual ASR models outperform monolingual counterparts by exploiting cross-lingual phonetic similarities. We challenge this assumption, showing that for sufficiently small models (27M parameters), training monolingual systems on a carefully balanced mix of high-quality human-labeled, pseudo-labeled, and synthetic data yields substantially superior performance. On average, our models achieve error rates 48% lower than the comparably sized Whisper Tiny model, outperform the 9x larger Whisper Small model, and in most cases match or outperform the 28x larger Whisper Medium model. These results advance the state of the art for models of this size, enabling accurate on-device ASR for languages that previously had limited support. We release Arabic, Chinese, Japanese, Korean, Ukrainian, and Vietnamese Moonshine models under a permissive open-source license.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02523</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:22:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manipulation as in Simulation: Enabling Accurate Geometry Perception in   Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02530</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02530.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minghuan Liu, Zhengbang Zhu, Xiaoshen Han, Peng Hu, Haotong Lin, Xinyao Li, Jingxiao Chen, Jiafeng Xu, Yichu Yang, Yunfeng Lin, Xinghang Li, Yong Yu, Weinan Zhang, Tao Kong, Bingyi Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern robotic manipulation primarily relies on visual observations in a 2D color space for skill learning but suffers from poor generalization. In contrast, humans, living in a 3D world, depend more on physical properties-such as distance, size, and shape-than on texture when interacting with objects. Since such 3D geometric information can be acquired from widely available depth cameras, it appears feasible to endow robots with similar perceptual capabilities. Our pilot study found that using depth cameras for manipulation is challenging, primarily due to their limited accuracy and susceptibility to various types of noise. In this work, we propose Camera Depth Models (CDMs) as a simple plugin on daily-use depth cameras, which take RGB images and raw depth signals as input and output denoised, accurate metric depth. To achieve this, we develop a neural data engine that generates high-quality paired data from simulation by modeling a depth camera's noise pattern. Our results show that CDMs achieve nearly simulation-level accuracy in depth prediction, effectively bridging the sim-to-real gap for manipulation tasks. Notably, our experiments demonstrate, for the first time, that a policy trained on raw simulated depth, without the need for adding noise or real-world fine-tuning, generalizes seamlessly to real-world robots on two challenging long-horizon tasks involving articulated, reflective, and slender objects, with little to no performance degradation. We hope our findings will inspire future research in utilizing simulation data and 3D information in general robot policies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02530</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:29:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jointly Reinforcing Diversity and Quality in Language Model Generations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02534</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02534.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianjian Li, Yiming Zhang, Ping Yu, Swarnadeep Saha, Daniel Khashabi, Jason Weston, Jack Lanchantin, Tianlu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Post-training of Large Language Models (LMs) often prioritizes accuracy and helpfulness at the expense of diversity. This creates a tension: while post-training improves response quality, it also sharpens output distributions and reduces the range of ideas, limiting the usefulness of LMs in creative and exploratory tasks such as brainstorming, storytelling, or problem solving. We address this challenge with Diversity-Aware Reinforcement Learning (DARLING), a framework that jointly optimizes for response quality and semantic diversity. At its core, DARLING introduces a learned partition function to measure diversity beyond surface-level lexical variations. This diversity signal is then combined with a quality reward during online reinforcement learning, encouraging models to generate outputs that are both high-quality and distinct. Experiments across multiple model families and sizes show that DARLING generalizes to two regimes: non-verifiable tasks (instruction following and creative writing) and verifiable tasks (competition math). On five benchmarks in the first setting, DARLING consistently outperforms quality-only RL baselines, producing outputs that are simultaneously of higher quality and novelty. In the second setting, DARLING achieves higher pass@1 (solution quality) and pass@k (solution variety). Most strikingly, explicitly optimizing for diversity catalyzes exploration in online RL, which manifests itself as higher-quality responses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02534</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:38:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI-TARS-2 Technical Report: Advancing GUI Agent with Multi-Turn   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02544</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02544.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoming Wang, Haoyang Zou, Huatong Song, Jiazhan Feng, Junjie Fang, Junting Lu, Longxiang Liu, Qinyu Luo, Shihao Liang, Shijue Huang, Wanjun Zhong, Yining Ye, Yujia Qin, Yuwen Xiong, Yuxin Song, Zhiyong Wu, Bo Li, Chen Dun, Chong Liu, Fuxing Leng, Hanbin Wang, Hao Yu, Haobin Chen, Hongyi Guo, Jing Su, Jingjia Huang, Kai Shen, Kaiyu Shi, Lin Yan, Peiyao Zhao, Pengfei Liu, Qinghao Ye, Renjie Zheng, Wayne Xin Zhao, Wen Heng, Wenhao Huang, Wenqian Wang, Xiaobo Qin, Yi Lin, Youbin Wu, Zehui Chen, Zihao Wang, Baoquan Zhong, Xinchun Zhang, Xujing Li, Yuanfan Li, Zhongkai Zhao, Chengquan Jiang, Faming Wu, Haotian Zhou, Jinlin Pang, Li Han, Qianli Ma, Siyao Liu, Songhua Cai, Wenqi Fu, Xin Liu, Zhi Zhang, Bo Zhou, Guoliang Li, Jiajun Shi, Jiale Yang, Jie Tang, Li Li, Taoran Lu, Woyu Lin, Xiaokang Tong, Xinyao Li, Yichi Zhang, Yu Miao, Zhengxuan Jiang, Zili Li, Ziyuan Zhao, Chenxin Li, Dehua Ma, Feng Lin, Ge Zhang, Haihua Yang, Hangyu Guo, Hongda Zhu, Jiaheng Liu, Junda Du, Kai Cai, Kuanye Li, Lichen Yuan, Meilan Han, Minchao Wang, Shuyue Guo, Tianhao Cheng, Xiaobo Ma, Xiaojun Xiao, Xiaolong Huang, Xinjie Chen, Yidi Du, Yilin Chen, Yiwen Wang, Zhaojian Li, Zhenzhu Yang, Zhiyuan Zeng, Chaolin Jin, Chen Li, Hao Chen, Haoli Chen, Jian Chen, Qinghao Zhao, Guang Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 105&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The development of autonomous agents for graphical user interfaces (GUIs) presents major challenges in artificial intelligence. While recent advances in native agent models have shown promise by unifying perception, reasoning, action, and memory through end-to-end learning, open problems remain in data scalability, multi-turn reinforcement learning (RL), the limitations of GUI-only operation, and environment stability. In this technical report, we present UI-TARS-2, a native GUI-centered agent model that addresses these challenges through a systematic training methodology: a data flywheel for scalable data generation, a stabilized multi-turn RL framework, a hybrid GUI environment that integrates file systems and terminals, and a unified sandbox platform for large-scale rollouts. Empirical evaluation demonstrates that UI-TARS-2 achieves significant improvements over its predecessor UI-TARS-1.5. On GUI benchmarks, it reaches 88.2 on Online-Mind2Web, 47.5 on OSWorld, 50.6 on WindowsAgentArena, and 73.3 on AndroidWorld, outperforming strong baselines such as Claude and OpenAI agents. In game environments, it attains a mean normalized score of 59.8 across a 15-game suite-roughly 60% of human-level performance-and remains competitive with frontier proprietary models (e.g., OpenAI o3) on LMGame-Bench. Additionally, the model can generalize to long-horizon information-seeking tasks and software engineering benchmarks, highlighting its robustness across diverse agent tasks. Detailed analyses of training dynamics further provide insights into achieving stability and efficiency in large-scale agent RL. These results underscore UI-TARS-2's potential to advance the state of GUI agents and exhibit strong generalization to real-world interactive scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02544</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:44:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Landscape of Agentic Reinforcement Learning for LLMs: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02547</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02547.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guibin Zhang, Hejia Geng, Xiaohang Yu, Zhenfei Yin, Zaibin Zhang, Zelin Tan, Heng Zhou, Zhongzhi Li, Xiangyuan Xue, Yijiang Li, Yifan Zhou, Yang Chen, Chen Zhang, Yutao Fan, Zihu Wang, Songtao Huang, Yue Liao, Hongru Wang, Mengyue Yang, Heng Ji, Michael Littman, Jun Wang, Shuicheng Yan, Philip Torr, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 156&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The emergence of agentic reinforcement learning (Agentic RL) marks a paradigm shift from conventional reinforcement learning applied to large language models (LLM RL), reframing LLMs from passive sequence generators into autonomous, decision-making agents embedded in complex, dynamic worlds. This survey formalizes this conceptual shift by contrasting the degenerate single-step Markov Decision Processes (MDPs) of LLM-RL with the temporally extended, partially observable Markov decision processes (POMDPs) that define Agentic RL. Building on this foundation, we propose a comprehensive twofold taxonomy: one organized around core agentic capabilities, including planning, tool use, memory, reasoning, self-improvement, and perception, and the other around their applications across diverse task domains. Central to our thesis is that reinforcement learning serves as the critical mechanism for transforming these capabilities from static, heuristic modules into adaptive, robust agentic behavior. To support and accelerate future research, we consolidate the landscape of open-source environments, benchmarks, and frameworks into a practical compendium. By synthesizing over five hundred recent works, this survey charts the contours of this rapidly evolving field and highlights the opportunities and challenges that will shape the development of scalable, general-purpose AI agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02547</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:46:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DynaGuard: A Dynamic Guardrail Model With User-Defined Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02563</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02563.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Monte Hoover, Vatsal Baherwani, Neel Jain, Khalid Saifullah, Joseph Vincent, Chirag Jain, Melissa Kazemi Rad, C. Bayan Bruss, Ashwinee Panda, Tom Goldstein&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Guardian models are used to supervise and moderate the outputs of user-facing chatbots, enforcing guardrails and detecting bad behaviors. Standard guardian models like LlamaGuard detect predefined, static categories of harms. We propose dynamic guardian models that evaluate text based on user-defined policies, making them useful for different application domains that are not addressed by standard guardian models. Our dynamic guardian models can be used for fast detection of policy violations or with chain-of-thought reasoning that articulates and justifies the model outputs. Our dynamic guardian models match static models in detection accuracy for static harm categories while identifying violations of free-form policies with accuracy comparable to frontier reasoning models in a fraction of the time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02563</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:57:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planning with Reasoning using Vision Language World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02722</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.02722.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Delong Chen, Theo Moutakanni, Willy Chung, Yejin Bang, Ziwei Ji, Allen Bolourchi, Pascale Fung&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Effective planning requires strong world models, but high-level world models that can understand and reason about actions with semantic and temporal abstraction remain largely underdeveloped. We introduce the Vision Language World Model (VLWM), a foundation model trained for language-based world modeling on natural videos. Given visual observations, the VLWM first infers the overall goal achievements then predicts a trajectory composed of interleaved actions and world state changes. Those targets are extracted by iterative LLM Self-Refine conditioned on compressed future observations represented by Tree of Captions. The VLWM learns both an action policy and a dynamics model, which respectively facilitates reactive system-1 plan decoding and reflective system-2 planning via cost minimization. The cost evaluates the semantic distance between the hypothetical future states given by VLWM roll-outs and the expected goal state, and is measured by a critic model that we trained in a self-supervised manner. The VLWM achieves state-of-the-art Visual Planning for Assistance (VPA) performance on both benchmark evaluations and our proposed PlannerArena human evaluations, where system-2 improves the Elo score by +27% upon system-1. The VLWM models also outperforms strong VLM baselines on RoboVQA and WorldPrediction benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02722</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:18:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loong: Synthesize Long Chain-of-Thoughts at Scale through Verifiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03059</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.03059.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xingyue Huang, Rishabh, Gregor Franke, Ziyi Yang, Jiamu Bai, Weijie Bai, Jinhe Bi, Zifeng Ding, Yiqun Duan, Chengyu Fan, Wendong Fan, Xin Gao, Ruohao Guo, Yuan He, Zhuangzhuang He, Xianglong Hu, Neil Johnson, Bowen Li, Fangru Lin, Siyu Lin, Tong Liu, Yunpu Ma, Hao Shen, Hao Sun, Beibei Wang, Fangyijie Wang, Hao Wang, Haoran Wang, Yang Wang, Yifeng Wang, Zhaowei Wang, Ziyang Wang, Yifan Wu, Zikai Xiao, Chengxing Xie, Fan Yang, Junxiao Yang, Qianshuo Ye, Ziyu Ye, Guangtao Zeng, Yuwen Ebony Zhang, Zeyu Zhang, Zihao Zhu, Bernard Ghanem, Philip Torr, Guohao Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown that their reasoning capabilities can be significantly improved through Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Reward (RLVR), particularly in domains like mathematics and programming, where ground-truth correctness can be automatically evaluated. However, extending this success to other reasoning-intensive domains remains challenging due to the scarcity of high-quality, verifiable datasets and the high cost of human supervision. In this work, we introduce the Loong Project: an open-source framework for scalable synthetic data generation and verification across a diverse range of reasoning-intensive domains. The framework consists of two key components: (1) LoongBench, a curated seed dataset containing 8,729 human-vetted examples across 12 domains (e.g., Advanced Mathematics, Chemistry, Logic), each paired with executable code and rich metadata; and (2) LoongEnv, a modular synthetic data generation environment that supports multiple prompting strategies to produce new question-answer-code triples. Together, these components form an agent-environment loop that enables reinforcement learning, where an LLM-based agent is rewarded for generating Chain-of-Thought (CoT) solutions that align with code-executed answers. Empirically, we benchmark LoongBench on a broad suite of both open-source and proprietary LLMs to evaluate domain coverage and reveal performance bottlenecks. In addition, we conduct a comprehensive analysis of synthetic data generated by LoongEnv, examining correctness, difficulty, and diversity. Code and documentation are available at https://github.com/camel-ai/loong.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03059</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 06:42:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Correctness: Harmonizing Process and Outcome Rewards through RL   Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03403</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.03403.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenlu Ye, Zhou Yu, Ziji Zhang, Hao Chen, Narayanan Sadagopan, Jing Huang, Tong Zhang, Anurag Beniwal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) has emerged to be a predominant paradigm for mathematical reasoning tasks, offering stable improvements in reasoning ability. However, Outcome Reward Models (ORMs) in RLVR are too coarse-grained to distinguish flawed reasoning within correct answers or valid reasoning within incorrect answers. This lack of granularity introduces noisy and misleading gradients significantly and hinders further progress in reasoning process quality. While Process Reward Models (PRMs) offer fine-grained guidance for intermediate steps, they frequently suffer from inaccuracies and are susceptible to reward hacking.   To resolve this dilemma, we introduce PRocess cOnsistency Filter (PROF), an effective data process curation method that harmonizes noisy, fine-grained process rewards with accurate, coarse-grained outcome rewards. Rather than naively blending PRM and ORM in the objective function (arXiv:archive/2506.18896), PROF leverages their complementary strengths through consistency-driven sample selection. Our approach retains correct responses with higher averaged process values and incorrect responses with lower averaged process values, while maintaining positive/negative training sample balance. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method not only consistently improves the final accuracy over 4% compared to the blending approaches, but also strengthens the quality of intermediate reasoning steps. Codes and training recipes are available at https://github.com/Chenluye99/PROF.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03403</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 15:28:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LMEnt: A Suite for Analyzing Knowledge in Language Models from   Pretraining Data to Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03405</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.03405.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daniela Gottesman, Alon Gilae-Dotan, Ido Cohen, Yoav Gur-Arieh, Marius Mosbach, Ori Yoran, Mor Geva&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language models (LMs) increasingly drive real-world applications that require world knowledge. However, the internal processes through which models turn data into representations of knowledge and beliefs about the world, are poorly understood. Insights into these processes could pave the way for developing LMs with knowledge representations that are more consistent, robust, and complete. To facilitate studying these questions, we present LMEnt, a suite for analyzing knowledge acquisition in LMs during pretraining. LMEnt introduces: (1) a knowledge-rich pretraining corpus, fully annotated with entity mentions, based on Wikipedia, (2) an entity-based retrieval method over pretraining data that outperforms previous approaches by as much as 80.4%, and (3) 12 pretrained models with up to 1B parameters and 4K intermediate checkpoints, with comparable performance to popular open-sourced models on knowledge benchmarks. Together, these resources provide a controlled environment for analyzing connections between entity mentions in pretraining and downstream performance, and the effects of causal interventions in pretraining data. We show the utility of LMEnt by studying knowledge acquisition across checkpoints, finding that fact frequency is key, but does not fully explain learning trends. We release LMEnt to support studies of knowledge in LMs, including knowledge representations, plasticity, editing, attribution, and learning dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03405</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 15:31:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drivel-ology: Challenging LLMs with Interpreting Nonsense with Depth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03867</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.03867.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Wang, Chenghao Xiao, Chia-Yi Hsiao, Zi Yan Chang, Chi-Li Chen, Tyler Loakman, Chenghua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 177&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Drivelology, a unique linguistic phenomenon characterised as "nonsense with depth", utterances that are syntactically coherent yet pragmatically paradoxical, emotionally loaded, or rhetorically subversive. While such expressions may resemble surface-level nonsense, they encode implicit meaning requiring contextual inference, moral reasoning, or emotional interpretation. We find that current large language models (LLMs), despite excelling at many natural language processing (NLP) tasks, consistently fail to grasp the layered semantics of Drivelological text. To investigate this, we construct a small but diverse benchmark dataset of over 1,200 meticulously curated examples, with select instances in English, Mandarin, Spanish, French, Japanese, and Korean. Annotation was especially challenging: each of the examples required careful expert review to verify that it truly reflected Drivelological characteristics. The process involved multiple rounds of discussion and adjudication to address disagreements, highlighting the subtle and subjective nature of the Drivelology. We evaluate a range of LLMs on classification, generation, and reasoning tasks. Our results reveal clear limitations of LLMs: models often confuse Drivelology with shallow nonsense, produce incoherent justifications, or miss the implied rhetorical function altogether. These findings highlight a deeper representational gap in LLMs' pragmatic understanding and challenge the assumption that statistical fluency implies cognitive comprehension. We release our dataset and code to facilitate further research in modelling linguistic depth beyond surface-level coherence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03867</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 03:58:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>False Sense of Security: Why Probing-based Malicious Input Detection   Fails to Generalize</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03888</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.03888.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng Wang, Zeming Wei, Qin Liu, Muhao Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) can comply with harmful instructions, raising serious safety concerns despite their impressive capabilities. Recent work has leveraged probing-based approaches to study the separability of malicious and benign inputs in LLMs' internal representations, and researchers have proposed using such probing methods for safety detection. We systematically re-examine this paradigm. Motivated by poor out-of-distribution performance, we hypothesize that probes learn superficial patterns rather than semantic harmfulness. Through controlled experiments, we confirm this hypothesis and identify the specific patterns learned: instructional patterns and trigger words. Our investigation follows a systematic approach, progressing from demonstrating comparable performance of simple n-gram methods, to controlled experiments with semantically cleaned datasets, to detailed analysis of pattern dependencies. These results reveal a false sense of security around current probing-based approaches and highlight the need to redesign both models and evaluation protocols, for which we provide further discussions in the hope of suggesting responsible further research in this direction. We have open-sourced the project at https://github.com/WangCheng0116/Why-Probe-Fails.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03888</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 05:15:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NER Retriever: Zero-Shot Named Entity Retrieval with Type-Aware   Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04011</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04011.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Or Shachar, Uri Katz, Yoav Goldberg, Oren Glickman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present NER Retriever, a zero-shot retrieval framework for ad-hoc Named Entity Retrieval, a variant of Named Entity Recognition (NER), where the types of interest are not provided in advance, and a user-defined type description is used to retrieve documents mentioning entities of that type. Instead of relying on fixed schemas or fine-tuned models, our method builds on internal representations of large language models (LLMs) to embed both entity mentions and user-provided open-ended type descriptions into a shared semantic space. We show that internal representations, specifically the value vectors from mid-layer transformer blocks, encode fine-grained type information more effectively than commonly used top-layer embeddings. To refine these representations, we train a lightweight contrastive projection network that aligns type-compatible entities while separating unrelated types. The resulting entity embeddings are compact, type-aware, and well-suited for nearest-neighbor search. Evaluated on three benchmarks, NER Retriever significantly outperforms both lexical and dense sentence-level retrieval baselines. Our findings provide empirical support for representation selection within LLMs and demonstrate a practical solution for scalable, schema-free entity retrieval. The NER Retriever Codebase is publicly available at https://github.com/ShacharOr100/ner_retriever&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04011</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 08:42:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse IFEval: Can LLMs Unlearn Stubborn Training Conventions to Follow   Real Instructions?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04292</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04292.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qinyan Zhang, Xinping Lei, Ruijie Miao, Yu Fu, Haojie Fan, Le Chang, Jiafan Hou, Dingling Zhang, Zhongfei Hou, Ziqiang Yang, Changxin Pu, Fei Hu, Jingkai Liu, Mengyun Liu, Yang Liu, Xiang Gao, Jiaheng Liu, Tong Yang, Zaiyuan Wang, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) achieve strong performance on diverse tasks but often exhibit cognitive inertia, struggling to follow instructions that conflict with the standardized patterns learned during supervised fine-tuning (SFT). To evaluate this limitation, we propose Inverse IFEval, a benchmark that measures models Counter-intuitive Abilitytheir capacity to override training-induced biases and comply with adversarial instructions. Inverse IFEval introduces eight types of such challenges, including Question Correction, Intentional Textual Flaws, Code without Comments, and Counterfactual Answering. Using a human-in-the-loop pipeline, we construct a dataset of 1012 high-quality Chinese and English questions across 23 domains, evaluated under an optimized LLM-as-a-Judge framework. Experiments on existing leading LLMs demonstrate the necessity of our proposed Inverse IFEval benchmark. Our findings emphasize that future alignment efforts should not only pursue fluency and factual correctness but also account for adaptability under unconventional contexts. We hope that Inverse IFEval serves as both a diagnostic tool and a foundation for developing methods that mitigate cognitive inertia, reduce overfitting to narrow patterns, and ultimately enhance the instruction-following reliability of LLMs in diverse and unpredictable real-world scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04292</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 15:03:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Editor to Dense Geometry Estimator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04338</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04338.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; JiYuan Wang, Chunyu Lin, Lei Sun, Rongying Liu, Lang Nie, Mingxing Li, Kang Liao, Xiangxiang Chu, Yao Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Leveraging visual priors from pre-trained text-to-image (T2I) generative models has shown success in dense prediction. However, dense prediction is inherently an image-to-image task, suggesting that image editing models, rather than T2I generative models, may be a more suitable foundation for fine-tuning.   Motivated by this, we conduct a systematic analysis of the fine-tuning behaviors of both editors and generators for dense geometry estimation. Our findings show that editing models possess inherent structural priors, which enable them to converge more stably by ``refining" their innate features, and ultimately achieve higher performance than their generative counterparts.   Based on these findings, we introduce FE2E, a framework that pioneeringly adapts an advanced editing model based on Diffusion Transformer (DiT) architecture for dense geometry prediction. Specifically, to tailor the editor for this deterministic task, we reformulate the editor's original flow matching loss into the ``consistent velocity" training objective. And we use logarithmic quantization to resolve the precision conflict between the editor's native BFloat16 format and the high precision demand of our tasks. Additionally, we leverage the DiT's global attention for a cost-free joint estimation of depth and normals in a single forward pass, enabling their supervisory signals to mutually enhance each other.   Without scaling up the training data, FE2E achieves impressive performance improvements in zero-shot monocular depth and normal estimation across multiple datasets. Notably, it achieves over 35\% performance gains on the ETH3D dataset and outperforms the DepthAnything series, which is trained on 100times data. The project page can be accessed https://amap-ml.github.io/FE2E/{here}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04338</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 15:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition Models: Rethinking the Generative Learning Objective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04394</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04394.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zidong Wang, Yiyuan Zhang, Xiaoyu Yue, Xiangyu Yue, Yangguang Li, Wanli Ouyang, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A fundamental dilemma in generative modeling persists: iterative diffusion models achieve outstanding fidelity, but at a significant computational cost, while efficient few-step alternatives are constrained by a hard quality ceiling. This conflict between generation steps and output quality arises from restrictive training objectives that focus exclusively on either infinitesimal dynamics (PF-ODEs) or direct endpoint prediction. We address this challenge by introducing an exact, continuous-time dynamics equation that analytically defines state transitions across any finite time interval. This leads to a novel generative paradigm, Transition Models (TiM), which adapt to arbitrary-step transitions, seamlessly traversing the generative trajectory from single leaps to fine-grained refinement with more steps. Despite having only 865M parameters, TiM achieves state-of-the-art performance, surpassing leading models such as SD3.5 (8B parameters) and FLUX.1 (12B parameters) across all evaluated step counts. Importantly, unlike previous few-step generators, TiM demonstrates monotonic quality improvement as the sampling budget increases. Additionally, when employing our native-resolution strategy, TiM delivers exceptional fidelity at resolutions up to 4096x4096.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04394</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 17:05:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Few-step Flow for 3D Generation via Marginal-Data Transport Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04406</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04406.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zanwei Zhou, Taoran Yi, Jiemin Fang, Chen Yang, Lingxi Xie, Xinggang Wang, Wei Shen, Qi Tian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Flow-based 3D generation models typically require dozens of sampling steps during inference. Though few-step distillation methods, particularly Consistency Models (CMs), have achieved substantial advancements in accelerating 2D diffusion models, they remain under-explored for more complex 3D generation tasks. In this study, we propose a novel framework, MDT-dist, for few-step 3D flow distillation. Our approach is built upon a primary objective: distilling the pretrained model to learn the Marginal-Data Transport. Directly learning this objective needs to integrate the velocity fields, while this integral is intractable to be implemented. Therefore, we propose two optimizable objectives, Velocity Matching (VM) and Velocity Distillation (VD), to equivalently convert the optimization target from the transport level to the velocity and the distribution level respectively. Velocity Matching (VM) learns to stably match the velocity fields between the student and the teacher, but inevitably provides biased gradient estimates. Velocity Distillation (VD) further enhances the optimization process by leveraging the learned velocity fields to perform probability density distillation. When evaluated on the pioneer 3D generation framework TRELLIS, our method reduces sampling steps of each flow transformer from 25 to 1 or 2, achieving 0.68s (1 step x 2) and 0.94s (2 steps x 2) latency with 9.0x and 6.5x speedup on A800, while preserving high visual and geometric fidelity. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method significantly outperforms existing CM distillation methods, and enables TRELLIS to achieve superior performance in few-step 3D generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04406</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 17:24:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Unified View of Large Language Model Post-Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04419</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04419.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xingtai Lv, Yuxin Zuo, Youbang Sun, Hongyi Liu, Yuntian Wei, Zhekai Chen, Lixuan He, Xuekai Zhu, Kaiyan Zhang, Bingning Wang, Ning Ding, Bowen Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Two major sources of training data exist for post-training modern language models: online (model-generated rollouts) data, and offline (human or other-model demonstrations) data. These two types of data are typically used by approaches like Reinforcement Learning (RL) and Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT), respectively. In this paper, we show that these approaches are not in contradiction, but are instances of a single optimization process. We derive a Unified Policy Gradient Estimator, and present the calculations of a wide spectrum of post-training approaches as the gradient of a common objective under different data distribution assumptions and various bias-variance tradeoffs. The gradient estimator is constructed with four interchangeable parts: stabilization mask, reference policy denominator, advantage estimate, and likelihood gradient. Motivated by our theoretical findings, we propose Hybrid Post-Training (HPT), an algorithm that dynamically selects different training signals. HPT is designed to yield both effective exploitation of demonstration and stable exploration without sacrificing learned reasoning patterns. We provide extensive experiments and ablation studies to verify the effectiveness of our unified theoretical framework and HPT. Across six mathematical reasoning benchmarks and two out-of-distribution suites, HPT consistently surpasses strong baselines across models of varying scales and families.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04419</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 17:40:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Durian: Dual Reference-guided Portrait Animation with Attribute Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04434</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04434.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyunsoo Cha, Byungjun Kim, Hanbyul Joo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Durian, the first method for generating portrait animation videos with facial attribute transfer from a given reference image to a target portrait in a zero-shot manner. To enable high-fidelity and spatially consistent attribute transfer across frames, we introduce dual reference networks that inject spatial features from both the portrait and attribute images into the denoising process of a diffusion model. We train the model using a self-reconstruction formulation, where two frames are sampled from the same portrait video: one is treated as the attribute reference and the other as the target portrait, and the remaining frames are reconstructed conditioned on these inputs and their corresponding masks. To support the transfer of attributes with varying spatial extent, we propose a mask expansion strategy using keypoint-conditioned image generation for training. In addition, we further augment the attribute and portrait images with spatial and appearance-level transformations to improve robustness to positional misalignment between them. These strategies allow the model to effectively generalize across diverse attributes and in-the-wild reference combinations, despite being trained without explicit triplet supervision. Durian achieves state-of-the-art performance on portrait animation with attribute transfer, and notably, its dual reference design enables multi-attribute composition in a single generation pass without additional training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04434</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 17:53:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delta Activations: A Representation for Finetuned Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04442</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04442.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiqiu Xu, Amish Sethi, Mayur Naik, Ser-Nam Lim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The success of powerful open source Large Language Models (LLMs) has enabled the community to create a vast collection of post-trained models adapted to specific tasks and domains. However, navigating and understanding these models remains challenging due to inconsistent metadata and unstructured repositories. We introduce Delta Activations, a method to represent finetuned models as vector embeddings by measuring shifts in their internal activations relative to a base model. This representation allows for effective clustering by domain and task, revealing structure in the model landscape. Delta Activations also demonstrate desirable properties: it is robust across finetuning settings and exhibits an additive property when finetuning datasets are mixed. In addition, we show that Delta Activations can embed tasks via few-shot finetuning, and further explore its use for model selection and merging. We hope Delta Activations can facilitate the practice of reusing publicly available models. Code is available at https://github.com/OscarXZQ/delta_activations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04442</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 17:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
