<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:11:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>TUN3D: Towards Real-World Scene Understanding from Unposed Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21388</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21388.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anton Konushin, Nikita Drozdov, Bulat Gabdullin, Alexey Zakharov, Anna Vorontsova, Danila Rukhovich, Maksim Kolodiazhnyi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Layout estimation and 3D object detection are two fundamental tasks in indoor scene understanding. When combined, they enable the creation of a compact yet semantically rich spatial representation of a scene. Existing approaches typically rely on point cloud input, which poses a major limitation since most consumer cameras lack depth sensors and visual-only data remains far more common. We address this issue with TUN3D, the first method that tackles joint layout estimation and 3D object detection in real scans, given multi-view images as input, and does not require ground-truth camera poses or depth supervision. Our approach builds on a lightweight sparse-convolutional backbone and employs two dedicated heads: one for 3D object detection and one for layout estimation, leveraging a novel and effective parametric wall representation. Extensive experiments show that TUN3D achieves state-of-the-art performance across three challenging scene understanding benchmarks: (i) using ground-truth point clouds, (ii) using posed images, and (iii) using unposed images. While performing on par with specialized 3D object detection methods, TUN3D significantly advances layout estimation, setting a new benchmark in holistic indoor scene understanding. Code is available at https://github.com/col14m/tun3d .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21388</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 20:24:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PromptCoT 2.0: Scaling Prompt Synthesis for Large Language Model   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19894</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19894.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xueliang Zhao, Wei Wu, Jian Guan, Zhuocheng Gong, Lingpeng Kong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are evolving from conversational systems into strong reasoners for tasks such as Olympiad mathematics and competitive programming. While scaling parameters and test-time computation has driven progress, a key bottleneck is the lack of high-quality training problems: human-curated datasets are costly and limited, while existing synthetic corpora are often too easy or narrow. PromptCoT 1.0 showed that injecting rationales into prompt synthesis increases problem difficulty. Building on this, we present PromptCoT 2.0, a scalable framework that replaces hand-crafted heuristics with an expectation-maximization (EM) loop, where rationales are iteratively refined to guide prompt construction. This produces problems that are both harder and more diverse than prior corpora. The synthetic prompts support two post-training regimes: (1) Self-Play, where strong models improve autonomously via verifiable feedback without stronger teachers; and (2) Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT), where weaker models learn from teacher-distilled traces. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of this approach. In self-play, applying PromptCoT 2.0 to Qwen3-30B-A3B-Thinking-2507 sets new state-of-the-art results at the 30B scale, with +4.4, +4.8, and +5.3 on AIME 24/25 and HMMT 25, +6.1 and +5.0 on LiveCodeBench v5/v6, and +35 Elo on Codeforces. In SFT, training Qwen2.5-7B-Instruct solely on synthetic prompts boosts accuracy to 73.1 (AIME 24), 65.6 (AIME 25), and 53.4 (LiveCodeBench v5), surpassing models trained on human or hybrid data. Analyses further confirm that PromptCoT 2.0 yields fundamentally harder and distributionally distinct problems. These results establish prompt synthesis as a new axis for scaling reasoning and position PromptCoT 2.0 as a scalable foundation for future open-source models. The implementation is available at https://github.com/inclusionAI/PromptCoT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19894</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 08:46:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chasing the Tail: Effective Rubric-based Reward Modeling for Large   Language Model Post-Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21500</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21500.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junkai Zhang, Zihao Wang, Lin Gui, Swarnashree Mysore Sathyendra, Jaehwan Jeong, Victor Veitch, Wei Wang, Yunzhong He, Bing Liu, Lifeng Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement fine-tuning (RFT) often suffers from reward over-optimization, where a policy model hacks the reward signals to achieve high scores while producing low-quality outputs. Our theoretical analysis shows that the key lies in reward misspecification at the high-reward tail: the inability to reliably distinguish Excellent responses from merely Great ones. This motivate us to focus on the high-reward region. However, such tail examples are scarce under the base LLM. While off-policy exemplars (e.g. from stronger models or rewrites) are easier to obtain, naively training on them yields a misspecified reward for the policy we aim to align. To address this, we study rubric-based rewards. By design, rubrics can leverage off-policy examples while remaining insensitive to their artifacts. To elicit rubrics that capture the high-reward tail, we highlight the importance of distinguishing among great and diverse responses, and introduce a workflow to implement this idea. We empirically demonstrate that rubric-based rewards substantially mitigate reward over-optimization and deliver effective LLM post-training improvements. Our code can be accessed at https://github.com/Jun-Kai-Zhang/rubrics.git .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21500</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 19:57:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReviewScore: Misinformed Peer Review Detection with Large Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21679</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21679.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyun Ryu, Doohyuk Jang, Hyemin S. Lee, Joonhyun Jeong, Gyeongman Kim, Donghyeon Cho, Gyouk Chu, Minyeong Hwang, Hyeongwon Jang, Changhun Kim, Haechan Kim, Jina Kim, Joowon Kim, Yoonjeon Kim, Kwanhyung Lee, Chanjae Park, Heecheol Yun, Gregor Betz, Eunho Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Peer review serves as a backbone of academic research, but in most AI conferences, the review quality is degrading as the number of submissions explodes. To reliably detect low-quality reviews, we define misinformed review points as either "weaknesses" in a review that contain incorrect premises, or "questions" in a review that can be already answered by the paper. We verify that 15.2% of weaknesses and 26.4% of questions are misinformed and introduce ReviewScore indicating if a review point is misinformed. To evaluate the factuality of each premise of weaknesses, we propose an automated engine that reconstructs every explicit and implicit premise from a weakness. We build a human expert-annotated ReviewScore dataset to check the ability of LLMs to automate ReviewScore evaluation. Then, we measure human-model agreements on ReviewScore using eight current state-of-the-art LLMs and verify moderate agreements. We also prove that evaluating premise-level factuality shows significantly higher agreements than evaluating weakness-level factuality. A thorough disagreement analysis further supports a potential of fully automated ReviewScore evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21679</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 22:55:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Think-on-Graph 3.0: Efficient and Adaptive LLM Reasoning on   Heterogeneous Graphs via Multi-Agent Dual-Evolving Context Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21710</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21710.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaojun Wu, Cehao Yang, Xueyuan Lin, Chengjin Xu, Xuhui Jiang, Yuanliang Sun, Hui Xiong, Jia Li, Jian Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) and Graph-based RAG has become the important paradigm for enhancing Large Language Models (LLMs) with external knowledge. However, existing approaches face a fundamental trade-off. While graph-based methods are inherently dependent on high-quality graph structures, they face significant practical constraints: manually constructed knowledge graphs are prohibitively expensive to scale, while automatically extracted graphs from corpora are limited by the performance of the underlying LLM extractors, especially when using smaller, local-deployed models. This paper presents Think-on-Graph 3.0 (ToG-3), a novel framework that introduces Multi-Agent Context Evolution and Retrieval (MACER) mechanism to overcome these limitations. Our core innovation is the dynamic construction and refinement of a Chunk-Triplets-Community heterogeneous graph index, which pioneeringly incorporates a dual-evolution mechanism of Evolving Query and Evolving Sub-Graph for precise evidence retrieval. This approach addresses a critical limitation of prior Graph-based RAG methods, which typically construct a static graph index in a single pass without adapting to the actual query. A multi-agent system, comprising Constructor, Retriever, Reflector, and Responser agents, collaboratively engages in an iterative process of evidence retrieval, answer generation, sufficiency reflection, and, crucially, evolving query and subgraph. This dual-evolving multi-agent system allows ToG-3 to adaptively build a targeted graph index during reasoning, mitigating the inherent drawbacks of static, one-time graph construction and enabling deep, precise reasoning even with lightweight LLMs. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ToG-3 outperforms compared baselines on both deep and broad reasoning benchmarks, and ablation studies confirm the efficacy of the components of MACER framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21710</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:13:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UltraHorizon: Benchmarking Agent Capabilities in Ultra Long-Horizon   Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21766</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21766.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haotian Luo, Huaisong Zhang, Xuelin Zhang, Haoyu Wang, Zeyu Qin, Wenjie Lu, Guozheng Ma, Haiying He, Yingsha Xie, Qiyang Zhou, Zixuan Hu, Hongze Mi, Yibo Wang, Naiqiang Tan, Hong Chen, Yi R. Fung, Chun Yuan, Li Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autonomous agents have recently achieved remarkable progress across diverse domains, yet most evaluations focus on short-horizon, fully observable tasks. In contrast, many critical real-world tasks, such as large-scale software development, commercial investment, and scientific discovery, unfold in long-horizon and partially observable scenarios where success hinges on sustained reasoning, planning, memory management, and tool use. Existing benchmarks rarely capture these long-horizon challenges, leaving a gap in systematic evaluation. To bridge this gap, we introduce UltraHorizon a novel benchmark that measures the foundational capabilities essential for complex real-world challenges. We use exploration as a unifying task across three distinct environments to validate these core competencies. Agents are designed in long-horizon discovery tasks where they must iteratively uncover hidden rules through sustained reasoning, planning, memory and tools management, and interaction with environments. Under the heaviest scale setting, trajectories average 200k+ tokens and 400+ tool calls, whereas in standard configurations they still exceed 35k tokens and involve more than 60 tool calls on average. Our extensive experiments reveal that LLM-agents consistently underperform in these settings, whereas human participants achieve higher scores, underscoring a persistent gap in agents' long-horizon abilities. We also observe that simple scaling fails in our task. To better illustrate the failure of agents, we conduct an in-depth analysis of collected trajectories. We identify eight types of errors and attribute them to two primary causes: in-context locking and functional fundamental capability gaps. https://github.com/StarDewXXX/UltraHorizon{Our code will be available here.}&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21766</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 02:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No Prompt Left Behind: Exploiting Zero-Variance Prompts in LLM   Reinforcement Learning via Entropy-Guided Advantage Shaping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21880</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21880.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Thanh-Long V. Le, Myeongho Jeon, Kim Vu, Viet Lai, Eunho Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) is a powerful framework for improving the reasoning abilities of Large Language Models (LLMs). However, current methods such as GRPO rely only on problems where the model responses to the same input differ in correctness, while ignoring those where all responses receive the same reward - so-called zero-variance prompts. In this work, we argue that such prompts are not useless but can, in fact, provide meaningful feedback for policy optimization. To this end, we introduce RL with Zero-Variance Prompts (RL-ZVP), a novel algorithm that extract learning signals from zero-variance prompts. RL-ZVP directly rewards correctness and penalizes errors even without contrasting responses, modulating feedback with token-level characteristics to preserve informative, nuanced signals. Across six math reasoning benchmarks, RL-ZVP achieves significant improvements of up to 8.61 points in accuracy and 7.77 points in pass rate over GRPO, while consistently outperforming other baselines that filter out zero-variance prompts. These results highlight the untapped potential of learning from zero-variance prompts in RLVR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21880</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 05:03:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mind-the-Glitch: Visual Correspondence for Detecting Inconsistencies in   Subject-Driven Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21989</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21989.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abdelrahman Eldesokey, Aleksandar Cvejic, Bernard Ghanem, Peter Wonka&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel approach for disentangling visual and semantic features from the backbones of pre-trained diffusion models, enabling visual correspondence in a manner analogous to the well-established semantic correspondence. While diffusion model backbones are known to encode semantically rich features, they must also contain visual features to support their image synthesis capabilities. However, isolating these visual features is challenging due to the absence of annotated datasets. To address this, we introduce an automated pipeline that constructs image pairs with annotated semantic and visual correspondences based on existing subject-driven image generation datasets, and design a contrastive architecture to separate the two feature types. Leveraging the disentangled representations, we propose a new metric, Visual Semantic Matching (VSM), that quantifies visual inconsistencies in subject-driven image generation. Empirical results show that our approach outperforms global feature-based metrics such as CLIP, DINO, and vision--language models in quantifying visual inconsistencies while also enabling spatial localization of inconsistent regions. To our knowledge, this is the first method that supports both quantification and localization of inconsistencies in subject-driven generation, offering a valuable tool for advancing this task. Project Page:https://abdo-eldesokey.github.io/mind-the-glitch/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21989</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 07:11:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rogue Scalpel: Activation Steering Compromises LLM Safety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22067</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22067.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anton Korznikov, Andrey Galichin, Alexey Dontsov, Oleg Y. Rogov, Ivan Oseledets, Elena Tutubalina&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Activation steering is a promising technique for controlling LLM behavior by adding semantically meaningful vectors directly into a model's hidden states during inference. It is often framed as a precise, interpretable, and potentially safer alternative to fine-tuning. We demonstrate the opposite: steering systematically breaks model alignment safeguards, making it comply with harmful requests. Through extensive experiments on different model families, we show that even steering in a random direction can increase the probability of harmful compliance from 0% to 2-27%. Alarmingly, steering benign features from a sparse autoencoder (SAE), a common source of interpretable directions, increases these rates by a further 2-4%. Finally, we show that combining 20 randomly sampled vectors that jailbreak a single prompt creates a universal attack, significantly increasing harmful compliance on unseen requests. These results challenge the paradigm of safety through interpretability, showing that precise control over model internals does not guarantee precise control over model behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22067</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 08:49:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fine-tuning Done Right in Model Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22072</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22072.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wanli Yang, Fei Sun, Rui Tang, Hongyu Zang, Du Su, Qi Cao, Jingang Wang, Huawei Shen, Xueqi Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-tuning, a foundational method for adapting large language models, has long been considered ineffective for model editing. Here, we challenge this belief, arguing that the reported failure arises not from the inherent limitation of fine-tuning itself, but from adapting it to the sequential nature of the editing task, a single-pass depth-first pipeline that optimizes each sample to convergence before moving on. While intuitive, this depth-first pipeline coupled with sample-wise updating over-optimizes each edit and induces interference across edits. Our controlled experiments reveal that simply restoring fine-tuning to the standard breadth-first (i.e., epoch-based) pipeline with mini-batch optimization substantially improves its effectiveness for model editing. Moreover, fine-tuning in editing also suffers from suboptimal tuning parameter locations inherited from prior methods. Through systematic analysis of tuning locations, we derive LocFT-BF, a simple and effective localized editing method built on the restored fine-tuning framework. Extensive experiments across diverse LLMs and datasets demonstrate that LocFT-BF outperforms state-of-the-art methods by large margins. Notably, to our knowledge, it is the first to sustain 100K edits and 72B-parameter models,10 x beyond prior practice, without sacrificing general capabilities. By clarifying a long-standing misconception and introducing a principled localized tuning strategy, we advance fine-tuning from an underestimated baseline to a leading method for model editing, establishing a solid foundation for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22072</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 08:53:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>COSPADI: Compressing LLMs via Calibration-Guided Sparse Dictionary   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22075</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22075.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dmitriy Shopkhoev, Denis Makhov, Magauiya Zhussip, Ammar Ali, Stamatios Lefkimmiatis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Post-training compression of large language models (LLMs) largely relies on low-rank weight approximation, which represents each column of a weight matrix in a shared low-dimensional subspace. While this is a computationally efficient strategy, the imposed structural constraint is rigid and can lead to a noticeable model accuracy drop. In this work, we propose CoSpaDi (Compression via Sparse Dictionary Learning), a novel training-free compression framework that replaces low-rank decomposition with a more flexible structured sparse factorization in which each weight matrix is represented with a dense dictionary and a column-sparse coefficient matrix. This formulation enables a union-of-subspaces representation: different columns of the original weight matrix are approximated in distinct subspaces spanned by adaptively selected dictionary atoms, offering greater expressiveness than a single invariant basis. Crucially, CoSpaDi leverages a small calibration dataset to optimize the factorization such that the output activations of compressed projection layers closely match those of the original ones, thereby minimizing functional reconstruction error rather than mere weight approximation. This data-aware strategy preserves better model fidelity without any fine-tuning under reasonable compression ratios. Moreover, the resulting structured sparsity allows efficient sparse-dense matrix multiplication and is compatible with post-training quantization for further memory and latency gains. We evaluate CoSpaDi across multiple Llama and Qwen models under per-layer and per-group settings at 20-50\% compression ratios, demonstrating consistent superiority over state-of-the-art data-aware low-rank methods both in accuracy and perplexity. Our results establish structured sparse dictionary learning as a powerful alternative to conventional low-rank approaches for efficient LLM deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22075</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 08:55:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MinerU2.5: A Decoupled Vision-Language Model for Efficient   High-Resolution Document Parsing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22186</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22186.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junbo Niu, Zheng Liu, Zhuangcheng Gu, Bin Wang, Linke Ouyang, Zhiyuan Zhao, Tao Chu, Tianyao He, Fan Wu, Qintong Zhang, Zhenjiang Jin, Guang Liang, Rui Zhang, Wenzheng Zhang, Yuan Qu, Zhifei Ren, Yuefeng Sun, Yuanhong Zheng, Dongsheng Ma, Zirui Tang, Boyu Niu, Ziyang Miao, Hejun Dong, Siyi Qian, Junyuan Zhang, Jingzhou Chen, Fangdong Wang, Xiaomeng Zhao, Liqun Wei, Wei Li, Shasha Wang, Ruiliang Xu, Yuanyuan Cao, Lu Chen, Qianqian Wu, Huaiyu Gu, Lindong Lu, Keming Wang, Dechen Lin, Guanlin Shen, Xuanhe Zhou, Linfeng Zhang, Yuhang Zang, Xiaoyi Dong, Jiaqi Wang, Bo Zhang, Lei Bai, Pei Chu, Weijia Li, Jiang Wu, Lijun Wu, Zhenxiang Li, Guangyu Wang, Zhongying Tu, Chao Xu, Kai Chen, Yu Qiao, Bowen Zhou, Dahua Lin, Wentao Zhang, Conghui He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce MinerU2.5, a 1.2B-parameter document parsing vision-language model that achieves state-of-the-art recognition accuracy while maintaining exceptional computational efficiency. Our approach employs a coarse-to-fine, two-stage parsing strategy that decouples global layout analysis from local content recognition. In the first stage, the model performs efficient layout analysis on downsampled images to identify structural elements, circumventing the computational overhead of processing high-resolution inputs. In the second stage, guided by the global layout, it performs targeted content recognition on native-resolution crops extracted from the original image, preserving fine-grained details in dense text, complex formulas, and tables. To support this strategy, we developed a comprehensive data engine that generates diverse, large-scale training corpora for both pretraining and fine-tuning. Ultimately, MinerU2.5 demonstrates strong document parsing ability, achieving state-of-the-art performance on multiple benchmarks, surpassing both general-purpose and domain-specific models across various recognition tasks, while maintaining significantly lower computational overhead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22186</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 10:45:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Does Reasoning Matter? A Controlled Study of Reasoning's   Contribution to Model Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22193</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22193.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nicolas Boizard, Hippolyte Gisserot-Boukhlef, Kevin El-Haddad, Céline Hudelot, Pierre Colombo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) with reasoning capabilities have achieved state-of-the-art performance on a wide range of tasks. Despite its empirical success, the tasks and model scales at which reasoning becomes effective, as well as its training and inference costs, remain underexplored. In this work, we rely on a synthetic data distillation framework to conduct a large-scale supervised study. We compare Instruction Fine-Tuning (IFT) and reasoning models of varying sizes, on a wide range of math-centric and general-purpose tasks, evaluating both multiple-choice and open-ended formats. Our analysis reveals that reasoning consistently improves model performance, often matching or surpassing significantly larger IFT systems. Notably, while IFT remains Pareto-optimal in training and inference costs, reasoning models become increasingly valuable as model size scales, overcoming IFT performance limits on reasoning-intensive and open-ended tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22193</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 10:53:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StableToken: A Noise-Robust Semantic Speech Tokenizer for Resilient   SpeechLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22220</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22220.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhan Song, Linhao Zhang, Chuhan Wu, Aiwei Liu, Wei Jia, Houfeng Wang, Xiao Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Prevalent semantic speech tokenizers, designed to capture linguistic content, are surprisingly fragile. We find they are not robust to meaning-irrelevant acoustic perturbations; even at high Signal-to-Noise Ratios (SNRs) where speech is perfectly intelligible, their output token sequences can change drastically, increasing the learning burden for downstream LLMs. This instability stems from two flaws: a brittle single-path quantization architecture and a distant training signal indifferent to intermediate token stability. To address this, we introduce StableToken, a tokenizer that achieves stability through a consensus-driven mechanism. Its multi-branch architecture processes audio in parallel, and these representations are merged via a powerful bit-wise voting mechanism to form a single, stable token sequence. StableToken sets a new state-of-the-art in token stability, drastically reducing Unit Edit Distance (UED) under diverse noise conditions. This foundational stability translates directly to downstream benefits, significantly improving the robustness of SpeechLLMs on a variety of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22220</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 11:32:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MesaTask: Towards Task-Driven Tabletop Scene Generation via 3D Spatial   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22281</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22281.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinkun Hao, Naifu Liang, Zhen Luo, Xudong Xu, Weipeng Zhong, Ran Yi, Yichen Jin, Zhaoyang Lyu, Feng Zheng, Lizhuang Ma, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The ability of robots to interpret human instructions and execute manipulation tasks necessitates the availability of task-relevant tabletop scenes for training. However, traditional methods for creating these scenes rely on time-consuming manual layout design or purely randomized layouts, which are limited in terms of plausibility or alignment with the tasks. In this paper, we formulate a novel task, namely task-oriented tabletop scene generation, which poses significant challenges due to the substantial gap between high-level task instructions and the tabletop scenes. To support research on such a challenging task, we introduce MesaTask-10K, a large-scale dataset comprising approximately 10,700 synthetic tabletop scenes with manually crafted layouts that ensure realistic layouts and intricate inter-object relations. To bridge the gap between tasks and scenes, we propose a Spatial Reasoning Chain that decomposes the generation process into object inference, spatial interrelation reasoning, and scene graph construction for the final 3D layout. We present MesaTask, an LLM-based framework that utilizes this reasoning chain and is further enhanced with DPO algorithms to generate physically plausible tabletop scenes that align well with given task descriptions. Exhaustive experiments demonstrate the superior performance of MesaTask compared to baselines in generating task-conforming tabletop scenes with realistic layouts. Project page is at https://mesatask.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22281</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 12:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LucidFlux: Caption-Free Universal Image Restoration via a Large-Scale   Diffusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22414</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22414.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Song Fei, Tian Ye, Lujia Wang, Lei Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal image restoration (UIR) aims to recover images degraded by unknown mixtures while preserving semantics -- conditions under which discriminative restorers and UNet-based diffusion priors often oversmooth, hallucinate, or drift. We present LucidFlux, a caption-free UIR framework that adapts a large diffusion transformer (Flux.1) without image captions. LucidFlux introduces a lightweight dual-branch conditioner that injects signals from the degraded input and a lightly restored proxy to respectively anchor geometry and suppress artifacts. Then, a timestep- and layer-adaptive modulation schedule is designed to route these cues across the backbone's hierarchy, in order to yield coarse-to-fine and context-aware updates that protect the global structure while recovering texture. After that, to avoid the latency and instability of text prompts or MLLM captions, we enforce caption-free semantic alignment via SigLIP features extracted from the proxy. A scalable curation pipeline further filters large-scale data for structure-rich supervision. Across synthetic and in-the-wild benchmarks, LucidFlux consistently outperforms strong open-source and commercial baselines, and ablation studies verify the necessity of each component. LucidFlux shows that, for large DiTs, when, where, and what to condition on -- rather than adding parameters or relying on text prompts -- is the governing lever for robust and caption-free universal image restoration in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22414</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 14:39:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EPO: Entropy-regularized Policy Optimization for LLM Agents   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22576</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22576.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xu Wujiang, Wentian Zhao, Zhenting Wang, Li Yu-Jhe, Jin Can, Jin Mingyu, Mei Kai, Wan Kun, Metaxas Dimitris&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 124&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training LLM agents in multi-turn environments with sparse rewards, where completing a single task requires 30+ turns of interaction within an episode, presents a fundamental challenge for reinforcement learning. We identify a critical failure mode unique to this setting: the exploration-exploitation cascade failure. This cascade begins with early-stage policy premature convergence, where sparse feedback causes agents to commit to flawed, low-entropy strategies. Subsequently, agents enter late-stage policy collapse, where conventional entropy regularization becomes counterproductive, promoting chaotic exploration that destabilizes training. We propose Entropy-regularized Policy Optimization (EPO), a general framework that breaks this failure cycle through three synergistic mechanisms: (1) adopting entropy regularization in multi-turn settings to enhance exploration, (2) an entropy smoothing regularizer that bounds policy entropy within historical averages to prevent abrupt fluctuations, and (3) adaptive phase-based weighting that balances exploration and exploitation across training. Our analysis justifies that EPO guarantees monotonically decreasing entropy variance while maintaining convergence. EPO achieves up to 152% performance improvement on ScienceWorld and up to 19.8% on ALFWorld. Our work demonstrates that multi-turn sparse-reward settings require fundamentally different entropy control than traditional RL, with broad implications for LLM agent training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22576</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 16:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantile Advantage Estimation for Entropy-Safe Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22611</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22611.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junkang Wu, Kexin Huang, Jiancan Wu, An Zhang, Xiang Wang, Xiangnan He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 113&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) strengthens LLM reasoning, but training often oscillates between {entropy collapse} and {entropy explosion}. We trace both hazards to the mean baseline used in value-free RL (e.g., GRPO and DAPO), which improperly penalizes negative-advantage samples under reward outliers. We propose {Quantile Advantage Estimation} (QAE), replacing the mean with a group-wise K-quantile baseline. QAE induces a response-level, two-regime gate: on hard queries (p &lt;= 1 - K) it reinforces rare successes, while on easy queries (p &gt; 1 - K) it targets remaining failures. Under first-order softmax updates, we prove {two-sided entropy safety}, giving lower and upper bounds on one-step entropy change that curb explosion and prevent collapse. Empirically, this minimal modification stabilizes entropy, sparsifies credit assignment (with tuned K, roughly 80% of responses receive zero advantage), and yields sustained pass@1 gains on Qwen3-8B/14B-Base across AIME 2024/2025 and AMC 2023. These results identify {baseline design} -- rather than token-level heuristics -- as the primary mechanism for scaling RLVR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22611</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:37:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongLive: Real-time Interactive Long Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22622</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22622.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuai Yang, Wei Huang, Ruihang Chu, Yicheng Xiao, Yuyang Zhao, Xianbang Wang, Muyang Li, Enze Xie, Yingcong Chen, Yao Lu, Song Han, Yukang Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 168&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present LongLive, a frame-level autoregressive (AR) framework for real-time and interactive long video generation. Long video generation presents challenges in both efficiency and quality. Diffusion and Diffusion-Forcing models can produce high-quality videos but suffer from low efficiency due to bidirectional attention. Causal attention AR models support KV caching for faster inference, but often degrade in quality on long videos due to memory challenges during long-video training. In addition, beyond static prompt-based generation, interactive capabilities, such as streaming prompt inputs, are critical for dynamic content creation, enabling users to guide narratives in real time. This interactive requirement significantly increases complexity, especially in ensuring visual consistency and semantic coherence during prompt transitions. To address these challenges, LongLive adopts a causal, frame-level AR design that integrates a KV-recache mechanism that refreshes cached states with new prompts for smooth, adherent switches; streaming long tuning to enable long video training and to align training and inference (train-long-test-long); and short window attention paired with a frame-level attention sink, shorten as frame sink, preserving long-range consistency while enabling faster generation. With these key designs, LongLive fine-tunes a 1.3B-parameter short-clip model to minute-long generation in just 32 GPU-days. At inference, LongLive sustains 20.7 FPS on a single NVIDIA H100, achieves strong performance on VBench in both short and long videos. LongLive supports up to 240-second videos on a single H100 GPU. LongLive further supports INT8-quantized inference with only marginal quality loss.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22622</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:48:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPARK: Synergistic Policy And Reward Co-Evolving Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22624</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22624.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyu Liu, Yuhang Zang, Shengyuan Ding, Yuhang Cao, Xiaoyi Dong, Haodong Duan, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent Large Language Models (LLMs) and Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs) increasingly use Reinforcement Learning (RL) for post-pretraining, such as RL with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) for objective tasks and RL from Human Feedback (RLHF) for subjective tasks. However, RLHF incurs high costs and potential reward-policy mismatch due to reliance on human preferences, while RLVR still wastes supervision by discarding rollouts and correctness signals after each update. To address these challenges, we introduce the Synergistic Policy And Reward Co-Evolving Framework (SPARK), an efficient, on-policy, and stable method that builds on RLVR. Instead of discarding rollouts and correctness data, SPARK recycles this valuable information to simultaneously train the model itself as a generative reward model. This auxiliary training uses a mix of objectives, such as pointwise reward score, pairwise comparison, and evaluation conditioned on further-reflection responses, to teach the model to evaluate and improve its own responses. Our process eliminates the need for a separate reward model and costly human preference data. SPARK creates a positive co-evolving feedback loop: improved reward accuracy yields better policy gradients, which in turn produce higher-quality rollouts that further refine the reward model. Our unified framework supports test-time scaling via self-reflection without external reward models and their associated costs. We show that SPARK achieves significant performance gains on multiple LLM and LVLM models and multiple reasoning, reward models, and general benchmarks. For example, SPARK-VL-7B achieves an average 9.7% gain on 7 reasoning benchmarks, 12.1% on 2 reward benchmarks, and 1.5% on 8 general benchmarks over the baselines, demonstrating robustness and broad generalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22624</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:50:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLP: Reinforcement as a Pretraining Objective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01265</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01265.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ali Hatamizadeh, Syeda Nahida Akter, Shrimai Prabhumoye, Jan Kautz, Mostofa Patwary, Mohammad Shoeybi, Bryan Catanzaro, Yejin Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The dominant paradigm for training large reasoning models starts with pre-training using next-token prediction loss on vast amounts of data. Reinforcement learning, while powerful in scaling reasoning, is introduced only as the very last phase of post-training, preceded by supervised fine-tuning. While dominant, is this an optimal way of training? In this paper, we present RLP, an information-driven reinforcement pretraining objective, that brings the core spirit of reinforcement learning -- exploration -- to the last phase of pretraining. The key idea is to treat chain-of-thought as an exploratory action, with rewards computed based on the information gain it provides for predicting future tokens. This training objective essentially encourages the model to think for itself before predicting what comes next, thus teaching an independent thinking behavior earlier in the pretraining. More concretely, the reward signal measures the increase in log-likelihood of the next token when conditioning on both context and a sampled reasoning chain, compared to conditioning on context alone. This approach yields a verifier-free dense reward signal, allowing for efficient training for the full document stream during pretraining. Specifically, RLP reframes reinforcement learning for reasoning as a pretraining objective on ordinary text, bridging the gap between next-token prediction and the emergence of useful chain-of-thought reasoning. Pretraining with RLP on Qwen3-1.7B-Base lifts the overall average across an eight-benchmark math-and-science suite by 19%. With identical post-training, the gains compound, with the largest improvements on reasoning-heavy tasks such as AIME25 and MMLU-Pro. Applying RLP to the hybrid Nemotron-Nano-12B-v2 increases the overall average from 42.81% to 61.32% and raises the average on scientific reasoning by 23%, demonstrating scalability across architectures and model sizes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01265</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:53:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Reasoning for Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22637</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22637.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangxin Zhou, Zichen Liu, Haonan Wang, Chao Du, Min Lin, Chongxuan Li, Liang Wang, Tianyu Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 66&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce a variational reasoning framework for language models that treats thinking traces as latent variables and optimizes them through variational inference. Starting from the evidence lower bound (ELBO), we extend it to a multi-trace objective for tighter bounds and propose a forward-KL formulation that stabilizes the training of the variational posterior. We further show that rejection sampling finetuning and binary-reward RL, including GRPO, can be interpreted as local forward-KL objectives, where an implicit weighting by model accuracy naturally arises from the derivation and reveals a previously unnoticed bias toward easier questions. We empirically validate our method on the Qwen 2.5 and Qwen 3 model families across a wide range of reasoning tasks. Overall, our work provides a principled probabilistic perspective that unifies variational inference with RL-style methods and yields stable objectives for improving the reasoning ability of language models. Our code is available at https://github.com/sail-sg/variational-reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22637</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:58:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Language Models Can Learn from Verbal Feedback Without Scalar Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22638</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22638.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Renjie Luo, Zichen Liu, Xiangyan Liu, Chao Du, Min Lin, Wenhu Chen, Wei Lu, Tianyu Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLMs are often trained with RL from human or AI feedback, yet such methods typically compress nuanced feedback into scalar rewards, discarding much of their richness and inducing scale imbalance. We propose treating verbal feedback as a conditioning signal. Inspired by language priors in text-to-image generation, which enable novel outputs from unseen prompts, we introduce the feedback-conditional policy (FCP). FCP learns directly from response-feedback pairs, approximating the feedback-conditional posterior through maximum likelihood training on offline data. We further develop an online bootstrapping stage where the policy generates under positive conditions and receives fresh feedback to refine itself. This reframes feedback-driven learning as conditional generation rather than reward optimization, offering a more expressive way for LLMs to directly learn from verbal feedback. Our code is available at https://github.com/sail-sg/feedback-conditional-policy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22638</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:58:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebGen-Agent: Enhancing Interactive Website Generation with Multi-Level   Feedback and Step-Level Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22644</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22644.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zimu Lu, Houxing Ren, Yunqiao Yang, Ke Wang, Zhuofan Zong, Junting Pan, Mingjie Zhan, Hongsheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agent systems powered by large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive performance on repository-level code-generation tasks. However, for tasks such as website codebase generation, which depend heavily on visual effects and user-interaction feedback, current code agents rely only on simple code execution for feedback and verification. This approach fails to capture the actual quality of the generated code. In this paper, we propose WebGen-Agent, a novel website-generation agent that leverages comprehensive and multi-level visual feedback to iteratively generate and refine the website codebase. Detailed and expressive text descriptions and suggestions regarding the screenshots and GUI-agent testing of the websites are generated by a visual language model (VLM), together with scores that quantify their quality. The screenshot and GUI-agent scores are further integrated with a backtracking and select-best mechanism, enhancing the performance of the agent. Utilizing the accurate visual scores inherent in the WebGen-Agent workflow, we further introduce Step-GRPO with Screenshot and GUI-agent Feedback to improve the ability of LLMs to act as the reasoning engine of WebGen-Agent. By using the screenshot and GUI-agent scores at each step as the reward in Step-GRPO, we provide a dense and reliable process supervision signal, which effectively improves the model's website-generation ability. On the WebGen-Bench dataset, WebGen-Agent increases the accuracy of Claude-3.5-Sonnet from 26.4% to 51.9% and its appearance score from 3.0 to 3.9, outperforming the previous state-of-the-art agent system. Additionally, our Step-GRPO training approach increases the accuracy of Qwen2.5-Coder-7B-Instruct from 38.9% to 45.4% and raises the appearance score from 3.4 to 3.7.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22644</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Human-Perceived Fakeness in AI-Generated Videos via Multimodal   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22646</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22646.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xingyu Fu, Siyi Liu, Yinuo Xu, Pan Lu, Guangqiuse Hu, Tianbo Yang, Taran Anantasagar, Christopher Shen, Yikai Mao, Yuanzhe Liu, Keyush Shah, Chung Un Lee, Yejin Choi, James Zou, Dan Roth, Chris Callison-Burch&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Can humans identify AI-generated (fake) videos and provide grounded reasons? While video generation models have advanced rapidly, a critical dimension -- whether humans can detect deepfake traces within a generated video, i.e., spatiotemporal grounded visual artifacts that reveal a video as machine generated -- has been largely overlooked. We introduce DeeptraceReward, the first fine-grained, spatially- and temporally- aware benchmark that annotates human-perceived fake traces for video generation reward. The dataset comprises 4.3K detailed annotations across 3.3K high-quality generated videos. Each annotation provides a natural-language explanation, pinpoints a bounding-box region containing the perceived trace, and marks precise onset and offset timestamps. We consolidate these annotations into 9 major categories of deepfake traces that lead humans to identify a video as AI-generated, and train multimodal language models (LMs) as reward models to mimic human judgments and localizations. On DeeptraceReward, our 7B reward model outperforms GPT-5 by 34.7% on average across fake clue identification, grounding, and explanation. Interestingly, we observe a consistent difficulty gradient: binary fake v.s. real classification is substantially easier than fine-grained deepfake trace detection; within the latter, performance degrades from natural language explanations (easiest), to spatial grounding, to temporal labeling (hardest). By foregrounding human-perceived deepfake traces, DeeptraceReward provides a rigorous testbed and training signal for socially aware and trustworthy video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22646</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CapRL: Stimulating Dense Image Caption Capabilities via Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22647</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22647.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Long Xing, Xiaoyi Dong, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Jianze Liang, Qidong Huang, Jiaqi Wang, Feng Wu, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Image captioning is a fundamental task that bridges the visual and linguistic domains, playing a critical role in pre-training Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs). Current state-of-the-art captioning models are typically trained with Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT), a paradigm that relies on expensive, non-scalable data annotated by humans or proprietary models. This approach often leads to models that memorize specific ground-truth answers, limiting their generality and ability to generate diverse, creative descriptions. To overcome the limitation of SFT, we propose applying the Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) paradigm to the open-ended task of image captioning. A primary challenge, however, is designing an objective reward function for the inherently subjective nature of what constitutes a "good" caption. We introduce Captioning Reinforcement Learning (CapRL), a novel training framework that redefines caption quality through its utility: a high-quality caption should enable a non-visual language model to accurately answer questions about the corresponding image. CapRL employs a decoupled two-stage pipeline where an LVLM generates a caption, and the objective reward is derived from the accuracy of a separate, vision-free LLM answering Multiple-Choice Questions based solely on that caption. As the first study to apply RLVR to the subjective image captioning task, we demonstrate that CapRL significantly enhances multiple settings. Pretraining on the CapRL-5M caption dataset annotated by CapRL-3B results in substantial gains across 12 benchmarks. Moreover, within the Prism Framework for caption quality evaluation, CapRL achieves performance comparable to Qwen2.5-VL-72B, while exceeding the baseline by an average margin of 8.4%. Code is available here: https://github.com/InternLM/CapRL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22647</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VoiceAssistant-Eval: Benchmarking AI Assistants across Listening,   Speaking, and Viewing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22651</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22651.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ke Wang, Houxing Ren, Zimu Lu, Mingjie Zhan, Hongsheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The growing capabilities of large language models and multimodal systems have spurred interest in voice-first AI assistants, yet existing benchmarks are inadequate for evaluating the full range of these systems' capabilities. We introduce VoiceAssistant-Eval, a comprehensive benchmark designed to assess AI assistants across listening, speaking, and viewing. VoiceAssistant-Eval comprises 10,497 curated examples spanning 13 task categories. These tasks include natural sounds, music, and spoken dialogue for listening; multi-turn dialogue, role-play imitation, and various scenarios for speaking; and highly heterogeneous images for viewing. To demonstrate its utility, we evaluate 21 open-source models and GPT-4o-Audio, measuring the quality of the response content and speech, as well as their consistency. The results reveal three key findings: (1) proprietary models do not universally outperform open-source models; (2) most models excel at speaking tasks but lag in audio understanding; and (3) well-designed smaller models can rival much larger ones. Notably, the mid-sized Step-Audio-2-mini (7B) achieves more than double the listening accuracy of LLaMA-Omni2-32B-Bilingual. However, challenges remain: multimodal (audio plus visual) input and role-play voice imitation tasks are difficult for current models, and significant gaps persist in robustness and safety alignment. VoiceAssistant-Eval identifies these gaps and establishes a rigorous framework for evaluating and guiding the development of next-generation AI assistants. Code and data will be released at https://mathllm.github.io/VoiceAssistantEval/ .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22651</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 17:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoScore2: Think before You Score in Generative Video Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22799</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22799.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuan He, Dongfu Jiang, Ping Nie, Minghao Liu, Zhengxuan Jiang, Mingyi Su, Wentao Ma, Junru Lin, Chun Ye, Yi Lu, Keming Wu, Benjamin Schneider, Quy Duc Do, Zhuofeng Li, Yiming Jia, Yuxuan Zhang, Guo Cheng, Haozhe Wang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Qunshu Lin, Yuanxing Zhang, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in text-to-video generation have produced increasingly realistic and diverse content, yet evaluating such videos remains a fundamental challenge due to their multi-faceted nature encompassing visual quality, semantic alignment, and physical consistency. Existing evaluators and reward models are limited to single opaque scores, lack interpretability, or provide only coarse analysis, making them insufficient for capturing the comprehensive nature of video quality assessment. We present VideoScore2, a multi-dimensional, interpretable, and human-aligned framework that explicitly evaluates visual quality, text-to-video alignment, and physical/common-sense consistency while producing detailed chain-of-thought rationales. Our model is trained on a large-scale dataset VideoFeedback2 containing 27,168 human-annotated videos with both scores and reasoning traces across three dimensions, using a two-stage pipeline of supervised fine-tuning followed by reinforcement learning with Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) to enhance analytical robustness. Extensive experiments demonstrate that VideoScore2 achieves superior performance with 44.35 (+5.94) accuracy on our in-domain benchmark VideoScore-Bench-v2 and 50.37 (+4.32) average performance across four out-of-domain benchmarks (VideoGenReward-Bench, VideoPhy2, etc), while providing interpretable assessments that bridge the gap between evaluation and controllable generation through effective reward modeling for Best-of-N sampling. Project Page: https://tiger-ai-lab.github.io/VideoScore2/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22799</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 18:09:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMPB: It's Time for Multi-Modal Personalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22820</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22820.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaeik Kim, Woojin Kim, Woohyeon Park, Jaeyoung Do&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual personalization is essential in user-facing AI systems such as smart homes and healthcare, where aligning model behavior with user-centric concepts is critical. However, recent large Vision-Language Models (VLMs), despite their broad applicability, remain underexplored in their ability to adapt to individual users. In this paper, we introduce MMPB, the first extensive benchmark for evaluating VLMs on personalization. MMPB comprises 10k image-query pairs and includes 111 personalizable concepts across four categories: humans, animals, objects, and characters, with the human category enriched with preference-grounded queries. We structure personalization into three main task types, each highlighting a different key property of VLMs. Using 23 widely used VLMs including both open- and closed-source models, we evaluate personalization performance via a three-stage protocol: concept injection, multi-turn dialogue, and personalized querying. Our findings indicate that most VLMs (including some closed-source models) struggle with personalization, particularly in maintaining consistency over dialogue, handling user preferences, and adapting to visual cues. Our analysis reveals that the challenges in VLM personalization (such as refusal behaviors and long-context forgetting) highlight substantial room for improvement. By identifying these limitations and offering a scalable benchmark, MMPB offers valuable insights and a solid foundation for future research toward truly personalized multi-modal AI. Project Page: aidaslab.github.io/MMPB&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22820</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 18:24:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critique-Coder: Enhancing Coder Models by Critique Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22824</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22824.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chi Ruan, Dongfu Jiang, Yubo Wang, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning (RL) has emerged as a popular training paradigm, particularly when paired with reasoning models. While effective, it primarily focuses on generating responses and lacks mechanisms to explicitly foster critique or reflection. Several recent studies, like Critique-Fine-Tuning (CFT) and Critique-Guided-Distillation (CGD) have shown the benefits of explicitly teaching LLMs how to critique. Motivated by them, we propose Critique Reinforcement Learning (CRL), where the model is tasked with generating a critique for a given (question, solution) pair. The reward is determined solely by whether the final judgment label c in {True, False} of the generated critique aligns with the ground-truth judgment c^*. Building on this point, we introduce Critique-Coder, which is trained on a hybrid of RL and CRL by substituting 20\% of the standard RL data with CRL data. We fine-tune multiple models (Critique-Coder) and evaluate them on different benchmarks to show their advantages over RL-only models. We show that Critique-Coder consistently outperforms RL-only baselines on all the evaluated benchmarks. Notably, our Critique-Coder-8B can reach over 60\% on LiveCodeBench (v5), outperforming other reasoning models like DeepCoder-14B and GPT-o1. Beyond code generation, Critique-Coder also demonstrates enhanced general reasoning abilities, as evidenced by its better performance on logic reasoning tasks from the BBEH dataset. This indicates that the application of CRL on coding datasets enhances general reasoning and critique abilities, which are transferable across a broad range of tasks. Hence, we believe that CRL works as a great complement to standard RL for LLM reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22824</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 18:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SINQ: Sinkhorn-Normalized Quantization for Calibration-Free   Low-Precision LLM Weights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22944</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.22944.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lorenz K. Müller, Philippe Bich, Jiawei Zhuang, Ahmet Çelik, Luca Benfenati, Lukas Cavigelli&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Post-training quantization has emerged as the most widely used strategy for deploying large language models at low precision. Still, current methods show perplexity degradation at bit-widths less than or equal to 4, partly because representing outliers causes precision issues in parameters that share the same scales as these outliers. This problem is especially pronounced for calibration-free, uniform quantization methods. We introduce SINQ to augment existing post-training quantizers with an additional second-axis scale factor and a fast Sinkhorn-Knopp-style algorithm that finds scales to normalize per-row and per-column variances, thereby minimizing a novel per-matrix proxy target for quantization: the matrix imbalance. Our method has no interactions between layers and can be trivially applied to new architectures to quantize any linear layers. We evaluate our method on the Qwen3 model family and DeepSeek-V2.5. SINQ improves WikiText2 and C4 perplexity significantly against uncalibrated uniform quantization baselines and can be further enhanced by combining it with calibration and non-uniform quantization levels. Code to reproduce the results of this work and to easily quantize models using SINQ is available at https://github.com/huawei-csl/SINQ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22944</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 21:22:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Language Prior of LVLMs by Contrasting Chain-of-Embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23050</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23050.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lin Long, Changdae Oh, Seongheon Park, Yixuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large vision-language models (LVLMs) achieve strong performance on multimodal tasks, yet they often default to their language prior (LP) -- memorized textual patterns from pre-training while under-utilizing visual evidence. Prior analyses of LP mostly rely on input-output probing, which fails to reveal the internal mechanisms governing when and how vision influences model behavior. To address this gap, we present the first systematic analysis of language prior through the lens of chain-of-embedding, which examines the layer-wise representation dynamics within LVLMs. Our analysis reveals a universal phenomenon: each model exhibits a Visual Integration Point (VIP), a critical layer at which visual information begins to meaningfully reshape hidden representations and influence decoding. Building on this observation, we introduce the Total Visual Integration (TVI) estimator, which aggregates representation distance beyond the VIP to quantify how strongly visual query influences response generation. Across 54 model-dataset combinations spanning 9 contemporary LVLMs and 6 benchmarks, we demonstrate that VIP consistently emerges, and that TVI reliably predicts the strength of language prior. This offers a principled toolkit for diagnosing and understanding language prior in LVLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23050</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 02:12:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplayer Nash Preference Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23102</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23102.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fang Wu, Xu Huang, Weihao Xuan, Zhiwei Zhang, Yijia Xiao, Guancheng Wan, Xiaomin Li, Bing Hu, Peng Xia, Jure Leskovec, Yejin Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF) has emerged as the standard paradigm for aligning large language models (LLMs) with human preferences. However, reward-based methods built on the Bradley-Terry assumption struggle to capture the non-transitive and heterogeneous nature of real-world preferences. To address this, recent studies have reframed alignment as a two-player Nash game, giving rise to Nash learning from human feedback (NLHF). While this perspective has inspired algorithms such as INPO, ONPO, and EGPO with strong theoretical and empirical guarantees, they remain fundamentally restricted to two-player interactions, creating a single-opponent bias that fails to capture the full complexity of realistic preference structures. In this work, we introduce Multiplayer Nash Preference Optimization (MNPO), a novel framework that generalizes NLHF to the multiplayer regime. It formulates alignment as an n-player game, where each policy competes against a population of opponents while being regularized toward a reference model. Our framework establishes well-defined Nash equilibria in multiplayer settings and extends the concept of duality gap to quantify approximation quality. We demonstrate that MNPO inherits the equilibrium guarantees of two-player methods while enabling richer competitive dynamics and improved coverage of diverse preference structures. Through comprehensive empirical evaluation, we show that MNPO consistently outperforms existing NLHF baselines on instruction-following benchmarks, achieving superior alignment quality under heterogeneous annotator conditions and mixed-policy evaluation scenarios. Together, these results establish MNPO as a principled and scalable framework for aligning LLMs with complex, non-transitive human preferences. Code is available at https://github.com/smiles724/MNPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23102</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 04:18:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WirelessMathLM: Teaching Mathematical Reasoning for LLMs in Wireless   Communications with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23219</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23219.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Li, Mengbing Liu, Yiyang Zhu, Wenhe Zhang, Li Wei, Jiancheng An, Chau Yuen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) excel at general mathematical reasoning but fail catastrophically on specialized technical mathematics. In wireless communications, where problems require precise manipulation of information-theoretic bounds, optimization constraints, and signal processing formulations, even state-of-the-art models struggle to achieve competent performance. We present WirelessMathLM, demonstrating that compact models (0.5B-7B parameters) can match or exceed much larger models through domain-specific reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards. Our key insight is that wireless mathematics problems possess a unique property--verifiable correctness--that enables effective reinforcement learning without human feedback. We construct WirelessMathBench-XL, a comprehensive benchmark of 4,027 problems from 970 papers. Using Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) with binary verification rewards, we train models directly from base checkpoints without supervised warm-start. Our 7B model achieves 39.5% accuracy on WirelessMathBench-XL, approaching GPT-4o (40.4%) while using about 100 times fewer parameters than DeepSeek-R1 (671B, 57.4%). Remarkably, GRPO training nearly doubles performance across all model scales (0.5B +11%, 3B +103%, 7B +81%), with positive transfer to general mathematics benchmarks--our models gain +8.4 points on average across MATH, Minerva-Math, OlympiadBench, AMC, and AIME without any training on these tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23219</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 09:58:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democratizing AI scientists using ToolUniverse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23426</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23426.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shanghua Gao, Richard Zhu, Pengwei Sui, Zhenglun Kong, Sufian Aldogom, Yepeng Huang, Ayush Noori, Reza Shamji, Krishna Parvataneni, Theodoros Tsiligkaridis, Marinka Zitnik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI scientists are emerging computational systems that serve as collaborative partners in discovery. These systems remain difficult to build because they are bespoke, tied to rigid workflows, and lack shared environments that unify tools, data, and analyses into a common ecosystem. In omics, unified ecosystems have transformed research by enabling interoperability, reuse, and community-driven development; AI scientists require comparable infrastructure. We present ToolUniverse, an ecosystem for building AI scientists from any language or reasoning model, whether open or closed. TOOLUNIVERSE standardizes how AI scientists identify and call tools, integrating more than 600 machine learning models, datasets, APIs, and scientific packages for data analysis, knowledge retrieval, and experimental design. It automatically refines tool interfaces for correct use by AI scientists, creates new tools from natural language descriptions, iteratively optimizes tool specifications, and composes tools into agentic workflows. In a case study of hypercholesterolemia, ToolUniverse was used to create an AI scientist to identify a potent analog of a drug with favorable predicted properties. The open-source ToolUniverse is available at https://aiscientist.tools.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23426</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 17:38:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLaVA-OneVision-1.5: Fully Open Framework for Democratized Multimodal   Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23661</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23661.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiang An, Yin Xie, Kaicheng Yang, Wenkang Zhang, Xiuwei Zhao, Zheng Cheng, Yirui Wang, Songcen Xu, Changrui Chen, Chunsheng Wu, Huajie Tan, Chunyuan Li, Jing Yang, Jie Yu, Xiyao Wang, Bin Qin, Yumeng Wang, Zizhen Yan, Ziyong Feng, Ziwei Liu, Bo Li, Jiankang Deng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present LLaVA-OneVision-1.5, a novel family of Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) that achieve state-of-the-art performance with significantly reduced computational and financial costs. Different from the existing works, LLaVA-OneVision-1.5 provides an open, efficient, and reproducible framework for building high-quality vision-language models entirely from scratch. The LLaVA-OneVision-1.5 release comprises three primary components: (1) Large-Scale Curated Datasets: We construct an 85M concept-balanced pretraining dataset LLaVA-OneVision-1.5-Mid-Traning and a meticulously curated 26M instruction dataset LLaVA-OneVision-1.5-Instruct, collectively encompassing 64B compressed multimodal tokens. (2) Efficient Training Framework: We develop a complete end-to-end efficient training framework leveraging an offline parallel data packing strategy to facilitate the training of LLaVA-OneVision-1.5 within a $16,000 budget. (3) State-of-the-art Performance: Experimental results demonstrate that LLaVA-OneVision1.5 yields exceptionally competitive performance across a broad range of downstream tasks. Specifically, LLaVA-OneVision-1.5-8B outperforms Qwen2.5-VL-7B on 18 of 27 benchmarks, and LLaVA-OneVision-1.5-4B surpasses Qwen2.5-VL-3B on all 27 benchmarks. We anticipate releasing LLaVA-OneVision-1.5-RL shortly and encourage the community to await further updates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23661</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 05:52:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Exploration-Exploitation Trade-off: A Hidden State Approach   for LLM Reasoning in RLVR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23808</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23808.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fanding Huang, Guanbo Huang, Xiao Fan, Yi He, Xiao Liang, Xiao Chen, Qinting Jiang, Faisal Nadeem Khan, Jingyan Jiang, Zhi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A prevailing view in Reinforcement Learning for Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) interprets recent progress through the lens of an exploration-exploitation trade-off, a perspective largely shaped by token-level metrics. We re-examine this perspective, proposing that this perceived trade-off may not be a fundamental constraint but rather an artifact of the measurement level. To investigate this, we shift the analysis to the semantically rich hidden-state space, adopting Effective Rank (ER) to quantify exploration and proposing its novel first- and second-order derivatives, named Effective Rank Velocity (ERV) and Effective Rank Acceleration (ERA), to capture exploitation dynamics. Our analysis reveals that at the hidden-state level, exploration and exploitation could be decoupled (Sec. 4). This finding reveals an opportunity to enhance both capacities simultaneously. This insight motivates our method, Velocity-Exploiting Rank-Learning (VERL), the first to operationalize the principle of synergistic exploration-exploitation enhancement by directly shaping the RL advantage function. The key innovation is leveraging the theoretically stable ERA as a predictive meta-controller to create a synergistic, dual-channel incentive structure. Instead of forcing a trade-off, VERL prospectively amplifies rewards for exploration to preempt overconfidence and reinforces exploitative gains to consolidate reasoning. Experiments across diverse LLMs and reasoning benchmarks show consistent gains, including up to 21.4% absolute accuracy improvement on the challenging Gaokao 2024 dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23808</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 11:14:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Winning the Pruning Gamble: A Unified Approach to Joint Sample and Token   Pruning for Efficient Supervised Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23873</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23873.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaobo Wang, Jiaming Wang, Jiajun Zhang, Cong Wang, Yue Min, Zichen Wen, Fei Huang, Huiqiang Jiang, Junyang Lin, Dayiheng Liu, Linfeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As supervised fine-tuning (SFT) evolves from a lightweight post-training step into a compute-intensive phase rivaling mid-training in scale, data efficiency has become critical for aligning large language models (LLMs) under tight budgets. Existing data pruning methods suffer from a fragmented design: they operate either at the sample level or the token level in isolation, failing to jointly optimize both dimensions. This disconnect leads to significant inefficiencies--high-value samples may still contain redundant tokens, while token-level pruning often discards crucial instructional or corrective signals embedded in individual examples. To address this bottleneck, we introduce the Error-Uncertainty (EU) Plane, a diagnostic framework that jointly characterizes the heterogeneous utility of training data across samples and tokens. Guided by this insight, we propose Quadrant-based Tuning (Q-Tuning), a unified framework that strategically coordinates sample pruning and token pruning. Q-Tuning employs a two-stage strategy: first, it performs sample-level triage to retain examples rich in informative misconceptions or calibration signals; second, it applies an asymmetric token-pruning policy, using a context-aware scoring mechanism to trim less salient tokens exclusively from misconception samples while preserving calibration samples in their entirety. Our method sets a new state of the art across five diverse benchmarks. Remarkably, on SmolLM2-1.7B, Q-Tuning achieves a +38\% average improvement over the full-data SFT baseline using only 12.5\% of the original training data. As the first dynamic pruning approach to consistently outperform full-data training, Q-Tuning provides a practical and scalable blueprint for maximizing data utilization in budget-constrained LLM SFT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23873</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 13:27:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EditScore: Unlocking Online RL for Image Editing via High-Fidelity   Reward Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23909</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23909.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Luo, Jiahao Wang, Chenyuan Wu, Shitao Xiao, Xiyan Jiang, Defu Lian, Jiajun Zhang, Dong Liu, Zheng liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-guided image editing has achieved remarkable progress, yet current models still face challenges with complex instructions and often require multiple samples to produce a desired result. Reinforcement Learning (RL) offers a promising solution, but its adoption in image editing has been severely hindered by the lack of a high-fidelity, efficient reward signal. In this work, we present a comprehensive methodology to overcome this barrier, centered on the development of a state-of-the-art, specialized reward model. We first introduce EditReward-Bench, a comprehensive benchmark to systematically evaluate reward models on editing quality. Building on this benchmark, we develop EditScore, a series of reward models (7B-72B) for evaluating the quality of instruction-guided image editing. Through meticulous data curation and filtering, EditScore effectively matches the performance of learning proprietary VLMs. Furthermore, coupled with an effective self-ensemble strategy tailored for the generative nature of EditScore, our largest variant even surpasses GPT-5 in the benchmark. We then demonstrate that a high-fidelity reward model is the key to unlocking online RL for image editing. Our experiments show that, while even the largest open-source VLMs fail to provide an effective learning signal, EditScore enables efficient and robust policy optimization. Applying our framework to a strong base model, OmniGen2, results in a final model that shows a substantial and consistent performance uplift. Overall, this work provides the first systematic path from benchmarking to reward modeling to RL training in image editing, showing that a high-fidelity, domain-specialized reward model is the key to unlocking the full potential of RL in this domain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23909</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 14:28:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HunyuanImage 3.0 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23951</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.23951.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyu Cao, Hangting Chen, Peng Chen, Yiji Cheng, Yutao Cui, Xinchi Deng, Ying Dong, Kipper Gong, Tianpeng Gu, Xiusen Gu, Tiankai Hang, Duojun Huang, Jie Jiang, Zhengkai Jiang, Weijie Kong, Changlin Li, Donghao Li, Junzhe Li, Xin Li, Yang Li, Zhenxi Li, Zhimin Li, Jiaxin Lin, Linus, Lucaz Liu, Shu Liu, Songtao Liu, Yu Liu, Yuhong Liu, Yanxin Long, Fanbin Lu, Qinglin Lu, Yuyang Peng, Yuanbo Peng, Xiangwei Shen, Yixuan Shi, Jiale Tao, Yangyu Tao, Qi Tian, Pengfei Wan, Chunyu Wang, Kai Wang, Lei Wang, Linqing Wang, Lucas Wang, Qixun Wang, Weiyan Wang, Hao Wen, Bing Wu, Jianbing Wu, Yue Wu, Senhao Xie, Fang Yang, Miles Yang, Xiaofeng Yang, Xuan Yang, Zhantao Yang, Jingmiao Yu, Zheng Yuan, Chao Zhang, Jian-Wei Zhang, Peizhen Zhang, Shi-Xue Zhang, Tao Zhang, Weigang Zhang, Yepeng Zhang, Yingfang Zhang, Zihao Zhang, Zijian Zhang, Penghao Zhao, Zhiyuan Zhao, Xuefei Zhe, Jianchen Zhu, Zhao Zhong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present HunyuanImage 3.0, a native multimodal model that unifies multimodal understanding and generation within an autoregressive framework, with its image generation module publicly available. The achievement of HunyuanImage 3.0 relies on several key components, including meticulous data curation, advanced architecture design, a native Chain-of-Thoughts schema, progressive model pre-training, aggressive model post-training, and an efficient infrastructure that enables large-scale training and inference. With these advancements, we successfully trained a Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) model comprising over 80 billion parameters in total, with 13 billion parameters activated per token during inference, making it the largest and most powerful open-source image generative model to date. We conducted extensive experiments and the results of automatic and human evaluation of text-image alignment and visual quality demonstrate that HunyuanImage 3.0 rivals previous state-of-the-art models. By releasing the code and weights of HunyuanImage 3.0, we aim to enable the community to explore new ideas with a state-of-the-art foundation model, fostering a dynamic and vibrant multimodal ecosystem. All open source assets are publicly available at https://github.com/Tencent-Hunyuan/HunyuanImage-3.0&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23951</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 16:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MCPMark: A Benchmark for Stress-Testing Realistic and Comprehensive MCP   Use</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24002</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24002.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijian Wu, Xiangyan Liu, Xinyuan Zhang, Lingjun Chen, Fanqing Meng, Lingxiao Du, Yiran Zhao, Fanshi Zhang, Yaoqi Ye, Jiawei Wang, Zirui Wang, Jinjie Ni, Yufan Yang, Arvin Xu, Michael Qizhe Shieh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 151&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; MCP standardizes how LLMs interact with external systems, forming the foundation for general agents. However, existing MCP benchmarks remain narrow in scope: they focus on read-heavy tasks or tasks with limited interaction depth, and fail to capture the complexity and realism of real-world workflows. To address this gap, we propose MCPMark, a benchmark designed to evaluate MCP use in a more realistic and comprehensive manner. It consists of 127 high-quality tasks collaboratively created by domain experts and AI agents. Each task begins with a curated initial state and includes a programmatic script for automatic verification. These tasks demand richer and more diverse interactions with the environment, involving a broad range of create, read, update, and delete (CRUD) operations. We conduct a comprehensive evaluation of cutting-edge LLMs using a minimal agent framework that operates in a tool-calling loop. Empirical results show that the best-performing model, gpt-5-medium, reaches only 52.56\% pass@1 and 33.86\% pass^4, while other widely regarded strong models, including claude-sonnet-4 and o3, fall below 30\% pass@1 and 15\% pass^4. On average, LLMs require 16.2 execution turns and 17.4 tool calls per task, significantly surpassing those in previous MCP benchmarks and highlighting the stress-testing nature of MCPMark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24002</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 17:53:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SLA: Beyond Sparsity in Diffusion Transformers via Fine-Tunable   Sparse-Linear Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24006</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24006.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Haoxu Wang, Kai Jiang, Shuo Yang, Kaiwen Zheng, Haocheng Xi, Ziteng Wang, Hongzhou Zhu, Min Zhao, Ion Stoica, Joseph E. Gonzalez, Jun Zhu, Jianfei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 108&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In Diffusion Transformer (DiT) models, particularly for video generation, attention latency is a major bottleneck due to the long sequence length and the quadratic complexity. We find that attention weights can be separated into two parts: a small fraction of large weights with high rank and the remaining weights with very low rank. This naturally suggests applying sparse acceleration to the first part and low-rank acceleration to the second. Based on this finding, we propose SLA (Sparse-Linear Attention), a trainable attention method that fuses sparse and linear attention to accelerate diffusion models. SLA classifies attention weights into critical, marginal, and negligible categories, applying O(N^2) attention to critical weights, O(N) attention to marginal weights, and skipping negligible ones. SLA combines these computations into a single GPU kernel and supports both forward and backward passes. With only a few fine-tuning steps using SLA, DiT models achieve a 20x reduction in attention computation, resulting in significant acceleration without loss of generation quality. Experiments show that SLA reduces attention computation by 95% without degrading end-to-end generation quality, outperforming baseline methods. In addition, we implement an efficient GPU kernel for SLA, which yields a 13.7x speedup in attention computation and a 2.2x end-to-end speedup in video generation on Wan2.1-1.3B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24006</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 17:58:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24007</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24007.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yangzhou Liu, Yue Cao, Hao Li, Gen Luo, Zhe Chen, Weiyun Wang, Xiaobo Liang, Biqing Qi, Lijun Wu, Changyao Tian, Yanting Zhang, Yuqiang Li, Tong Lu, Yu Qiao, Jifeng Dai, Wenhai Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion language models (DLMs) have strong theoretical efficiency but are limited by fixed-length decoding and incompatibility with key-value (KV) caches. Block diffusion mitigates these issues, yet still enforces a fixed block size and requires expensive training. We introduce Next Sequence Prediction (NSP), which unifies next-token and next-block prediction, enabling the model to adaptively determine the generation length at each step. When the length is fixed to 1, NSP reduces to standard next-token prediction. Building on NSP, we propose Sequential Diffusion Language Model (SDLM), which can retrofit pre-trained autoregressive language models (ALMs) at minimal cost. Specifically, SDLM performs diffusion inference within fixed-size mask blocks, but dynamically decodes consecutive subsequences based on model confidence, thereby preserving KV-cache compatibility and improving robustness to varying uncertainty and semantics across the sequence. Experiments show that SDLM matches or surpasses strong autoregressive baselines using only 3.5M training samples, while achieving 2.1 higher throughput than Qwen-2.5. Notably, the SDLM-32B model delivers even more pronounced efficiency gains, demonstrating the strong scalability potential of our modeling paradigm. Project page and codes: https://github.com/OpenGVLab/SDLM&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24007</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 17:59:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SparseD: Sparse Attention for Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24014</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24014.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeqing Wang, Gongfan Fang, Xinyin Ma, Xingyi Yang, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While diffusion language models (DLMs) offer a promising alternative to autoregressive models (ARs), existing open-source DLMs suffer from high inference latency. This bottleneck is mainly due to the attention's quadratic complexity with respect to context length in computing all query-key pairs. Intuitively, to reduce this complexity, a natural strategy is to restrict attention to sparse patterns that retain only the most relevant connections. Such approaches are well-established in ARs, where attention follows fixed and clearly defined sparse patterns. However, in DLMs, we observe distinct sparsity behaviors: (1) attention patterns vary across heads, (2) attention patterns in each head remain highly similar across denoising steps, and (3) early denoising steps are critical for generation. These findings render sparse attention methods designed for ARs largely incompatible with DLMs, as they fail to capture head-specific structures and risk degrading generation when applied in early denoising steps. To address these challenges, we propose SparseD, a novel sparse attention method for DLMs. Leveraging the observations, SparseD only requires pre-computing head-specific sparse patterns one time, and reuses them across all steps. This prevents recomputing sparse patterns at each denoising step. Meanwhile, SparseD uses full attention in the early steps, then switches to sparse attention later to maintain generation quality. Together, these establish SparseD as a practical and efficient solution for deploying DLMs in long-context applications. Experimental results demonstrate that SparseD achieves lossless acceleration, delivering up to 1.50times speedup over FlashAttention at a 64k context length with 1,024 denoising steps.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24014</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 18:10:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclid's Gift: Enhancing Spatial Perception and Reasoning in   Vision-Language Models via Geometric Surrogate Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24473</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24473.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shijie Lian, Changti Wu, Laurence Tianruo Yang, Hang Yuan, Bin Yu, Lei Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatial intelligence spans a rich suite of abilities, including visualising and transforming shapes, mentally rotating objects, judging relational positions and containment, and estimating numerosity. However, it still remains a critical unresolved challenge for Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs).To fill this gap, we propose to treat Euclidean geometry problem-solving as a surrogate task. Specifically, we meticulously constructed a curated multimodal dataset, called Euclid30K, comprising approximately 30K plane and solid geometry problems. To enable the model to acquire and apply Euclidean principles from these geometry problems, we employed Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) to finetune the Qwen2.5VL family and RoboBrain2.0 family, inspiring the models to identify shapes, count, and relate entities, and perform multi-step deductive reasoning using Euclidean principles. Our experiments demonstrate that the resulting models achieve substantial zero-shot gains across four spatial reasoning benchmarks (Super-CLEVR, Omni3DBench, VSI-Bench, and MindCube) without any task-specific adaptations. Notably, after training on the Euclid30K, the mean VSI-Bench accuracy of all evaluated models rose from 34.5% to 40.5%, improving by 5.5 percentage points. Among them, RoboBrain2.0-Euclid-7B achieves 49.6\% accuracy, surpassing the previous state-of-the-art model, Spatial-MLLM.To our knowledge, this is the first systematic study showing that geometry-centric fine-tuning can confer vision-language models with broadly transferable spatial skills. Code and Euclid30K dataset can be found in https://zgca-ai4edu.github.io/Euclids_Gift.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24473</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 08:49:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SANA-Video: Efficient Video Generation with Block Linear Diffusion   Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24695</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24695.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junsong Chen, Yuyang Zhao, Jincheng Yu, Ruihang Chu, Junyu Chen, Shuai Yang, Xianbang Wang, Yicheng Pan, Daquan Zhou, Huan Ling, Haozhe Liu, Hongwei Yi, Hao Zhang, Muyang Li, Yukang Chen, Han Cai, Sanja Fidler, Ping Luo, Song Han, Enze Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SANA-Video, a small diffusion model that can efficiently generate videos up to 720x1280 resolution and minute-length duration. SANA-Video synthesizes high-resolution, high-quality and long videos with strong text-video alignment at a remarkably fast speed, deployable on RTX 5090 GPU. Two core designs ensure our efficient, effective and long video generation: (1) Linear DiT: We leverage linear attention as the core operation, which is more efficient than vanilla attention given the large number of tokens processed in video generation. (2) Constant-Memory KV cache for Block Linear Attention: we design block-wise autoregressive approach for long video generation by employing a constant-memory state, derived from the cumulative properties of linear attention. This KV cache provides the Linear DiT with global context at a fixed memory cost, eliminating the need for a traditional KV cache and enabling efficient, minute-long video generation. In addition, we explore effective data filters and model training strategies, narrowing the training cost to 12 days on 64 H100 GPUs, which is only 1% of the cost of MovieGen. Given its low cost, SANA-Video achieves competitive performance compared to modern state-of-the-art small diffusion models (e.g., Wan 2.1-1.3B and SkyReel-V2-1.3B) while being 16x faster in measured latency. Moreover, SANA-Video can be deployed on RTX 5090 GPUs with NVFP4 precision, accelerating the inference speed of generating a 5-second 720p video from 71s to 29s (2.4x speedup). In summary, SANA-Video enables low-cost, high-quality video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24695</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 12:28:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Socratic-Zero : Bootstrapping Reasoning via Data-Free Agent Co-evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24726</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24726.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaobo Wang, Zhengbo Jiao, Zifan Zhang, Yilang Peng, Xu Ze, Boyu Yang, Wei Wang, Hu Wei, Linfeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent breakthroughs in large language models (LLMs) on reasoning tasks rely heavily on massive, high-quality datasets-typically human-annotated and thus difficult to scale. While data synthesis or distillation offers a promising alternative, existing methods struggle with inconsistent data quality and an inability to dynamically adapt to the evolving capabilities of the model, leading to suboptimal training signals. To address these limitations, we introduce Socratic-Zero, a fully autonomous framework that generates high-quality training data from minimal seed examples through the co-evolution of three agents: the Teacher, the Solver, and the Generator. The Solver continuously refines its reasoning by learning from preference feedback on both successful and failed trajectories; the Teacher adaptively crafts increasingly challenging questions based on the Solver's weaknesses; and the Generator distills the Teacher's question-design strategy to enable scalable, high-fidelity curriculum generation. This closed-loop system produces a self-improving curriculum-requiring no pre-existing tasks or labels. Remarkably, starting from only 100 seed questions, our Socratic-Solver-8B achieves an average gain of +20.2 percentage points over prior data synthesis methods across seven mathematical reasoning benchmarks (AMC23, AIME24-25, Olympiad, MATH-500, Minerva, and GSM8K), with consistent gains on both Qwen3 and GLM4 series models. Even more surprisingly, synthetic data from Socratic-Generator-32B enables student LLMs to achieve superior performance compared to other state-of-the-art (SOTA) commercial LLMs on these benchmarks, including Qwen3-235B-A22B, DeepSeek-V3.1-671B, GPT-5, Gemini-2.5-Pro, Grok-4, and Claude-4.1-Opus.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24726</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 12:54:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RealUnify: Do Unified Models Truly Benefit from Unification? A   Comprehensive Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24897</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24897.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Shi, Yuhao Dong, Yue Ding, Yuran Wang, Xuanyu Zhu, Sheng Zhou, Wenting Liu, Haochen Tian, Rundong Wang, Huanqian Wang, Zuyan Liu, Bohan Zeng, Ruizhe Chen, Qixun Wang, Zhuoran Zhang, Xinlong Chen, Chengzhuo Tong, Bozhou Li, Chaoyou Fu, Qiang Liu, Haotian Wang, Wenjing Yang, Yuanxing Zhang, Pengfei Wan, Yi-Fan Zhang, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The integration of visual understanding and generation into unified multimodal models represents a significant stride toward general-purpose AI. However, a fundamental question remains unanswered by existing benchmarks: does this architectural unification actually enable synergetic interaction between the constituent capabilities? Existing evaluation paradigms, which primarily assess understanding and generation in isolation, are insufficient for determining whether a unified model can leverage its understanding to enhance its generation, or use generative simulation to facilitate deeper comprehension. To address this critical gap, we introduce RealUnify, a benchmark specifically designed to evaluate bidirectional capability synergy. RealUnify comprises 1,000 meticulously human-annotated instances spanning 10 categories and 32 subtasks. It is structured around two core axes: 1) Understanding Enhances Generation, which requires reasoning (e.g., commonsense, logic) to guide image generation, and 2) Generation Enhances Understanding, which necessitates mental simulation or reconstruction (e.g., of transformed or disordered visual inputs) to solve reasoning tasks. A key contribution is our dual-evaluation protocol, which combines direct end-to-end assessment with a diagnostic stepwise evaluation that decomposes tasks into distinct understanding and generation phases. This protocol allows us to precisely discern whether performance bottlenecks stem from deficiencies in core abilities or from a failure to integrate them. Through large-scale evaluations of 12 leading unified models and 6 specialized baselines, we find that current unified models still struggle to achieve effective synergy, indicating that architectural unification alone is insufficient. These results highlight the need for new training strategies and inductive biases to fully unlock the potential of unified modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24897</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 15:07:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenGPT-4o-Image: A Comprehensive Dataset for Advanced Image Generation   and Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24900</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24900.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhihong Chen, Xuehai Bai, Yang Shi, Chaoyou Fu, Huanyu Zhang, Haotian Wang, Xiaoyan Sun, Zhang Zhang, Liang Wang, Yuanxing Zhang, Pengfei Wan, Yi-Fan Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The performance of unified multimodal models for image generation and editing is fundamentally constrained by the quality and comprehensiveness of their training data. While existing datasets have covered basic tasks like style transfer and simple object manipulation, they often lack the systematic structure and challenging scenarios required for real-world applications. To address this bottleneck, we introduce OpenGPT-4o-Image, a large-scale dataset constructed using a novel methodology that combines hierarchical task taxonomy with automated data generation. Our taxonomy not only includes fundamental capabilities such as text rendering and style control but also introduces highly practical yet challenging categories like scientific imagery for chemistry illustrations and complex instruction editing requiring simultaneous execution of multiple operations. Through an automated pipeline leveraging structured resource pools and GPT-4o, we generate 80k high-quality instruction-image pairs with controlled diversity, covering 11 major domains and 51 subtasks. Extensive experiments show that fine-tuning leading models on our dataset achieves significant performance gains across multiple benchmarks, with improvements of up to 18\% on editing tasks (UniWorld-V1 on ImgEdit-Bench) and 13% on generation tasks (Harmon on GenEval). Our work demonstrates that systematic data construction is key to advancing multimodal AI capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24900</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 15:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Policy Valuation is Enough for LLM Reasoning with Verifiable   Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24981</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.24981.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran He, Yuxiao Ye, Qingpeng Cai, Chen Hu, Binxing Jiao, Daxin Jiang, Ling Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; RL with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as a promising paradigm for improving the reasoning abilities of large language models (LLMs). Current methods rely primarily on policy optimization frameworks like PPO and GRPO, which follow generalized policy iteration that alternates between evaluating the current policy's value and improving the policy based on evaluation. While effective, they often suffer from training instability and diversity collapse, requiring complex heuristic tricks and careful tuning. We observe that standard RLVR in math reasoning can be formalized as a specialized finite-horizon Markov Decision Process with deterministic state transitions, tree-structured dynamics, and binary terminal rewards. Though large in scale, the underlying structure is simpler than general-purpose control settings for which popular RL algorithms (e.g., PPO) were developed, suggesting that several sophisticated techniques in existing methods may be reduced or even omitted. Based on this insight, we prove a surprising result: the optimal action can be recovered from the Q-function of a fixed uniformly random policy, thereby bypassing the generalized policy iteration loop and its associated heuristics. We introduce Random Policy Valuation for Diverse Reasoning (ROVER) to translate this principle into a practical and scalable algorithm for LLM math reasoning, a minimalist yet highly effective RL method that samples actions from a softmax over these uniform-policy Q-values. ROVER preserves diversity throughout training, allowing sustained exploration of multiple valid pathways. Across multiple base models and standard math reasoning benchmarks, ROVER demonstrates superior performance in both quality (+8.2 on pass@1, +16.8 on pass@256) and diversity (+17.6\%), despite its radical simplification compared to strong, complicated existing methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24981</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 16:09:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Generalist Data-Analytic Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25084</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25084.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuofei Qiao, Yanqiu Zhao, Zhisong Qiu, Xiaobin Wang, Jintian Zhang, Zhao Bin, Ningyu Zhang, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Huajun Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data-analytic agents are emerging as a key catalyst for automated scientific discovery and for the vision of Innovating AI. Current approaches, however, rely heavily on prompt engineering over proprietary models, while open-source models struggle to face diverse-format, large-scale data files and long-horizon, multi-step reasoning that real-world analytics demands. This paper introduces DataMind, a scalable data synthesis and agent training recipe designed to build generalist data-analytic agents. DataMind tackles three key challenges in building open-source data-analytic agents, including insufficient data resources, improper training strategy, and unstable code-based multi-turn rollout. Concretely, DataMind applies 1) a fine-grained task taxonomy and a recursive easy-to-hard task composition mechanism to increase the diversity and difficulty of synthesized queries; 2) a knowledge-augmented trajectory sampling strategy followed by model-based and rule-based filtering; 3) a dynamically adjustable training objective combining both SFT and RL losses; 4) a memory-frugal and stable code-based multi-turn rollout framework. Built on DataMind, we curate DataMind-12K, a high-quality trajectory set spanning diverse domains, task categories, and data file formats for data-analytic tasks. Trained on DataMind-12K, our DataMind-14B achieves state-of-the-art with an average score of 71.16% on multiple data analysis benchmarks, outperforming the strongest proprietary baselines DeepSeek-V3.1 and GPT-5. Our DataMind-7B also performs best among all open-source models with a score of 68.10%. We also incorporate some empirical insights gained from our exploratory trials into the analysis experiments, aiming to provide actionable insights about agentic training for the community. We will release DataMind-12K and DataMind-7B,14B for the community's future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25084</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:23:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Personalized Deep Research: Benchmarks and Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuan Liang, Jiaxian Li, Yuqing Wang, Piaohong Wang, Motong Tian, Pai Liu, Shuofei Qiao, Runnan Fang, He Zhu, Ge Zhang, Minghao Liu, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Ningyu Zhang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep Research Agents (DRAs) can autonomously conduct complex investigations and generate comprehensive reports, demonstrating strong real-world potential. However, existing evaluations mostly rely on close-ended benchmarks, while open-ended deep research benchmarks remain scarce and typically neglect personalized scenarios. To bridge this gap, we introduce Personalized Deep Research Bench, the first benchmark for evaluating personalization in DRAs. It pairs 50 diverse research tasks across 10 domains with 25 authentic user profiles that combine structured persona attributes with dynamic real-world contexts, yielding 250 realistic user-task queries. To assess system performance, we propose the PQR Evaluation Framework, which jointly measures (P) Personalization Alignment, (Q) Content Quality, and (R) Factual Reliability. Our experiments on a range of systems highlight current capabilities and limitations in handling personalized deep research. This work establishes a rigorous foundation for developing and evaluating the next generation of truly personalized AI research assistants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25106</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:39:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From f(x) and g(x) to f(g(x)): LLMs Learn New Skills in RL by   Composing Old Ones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25123</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25123.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lifan Yuan, Weize Chen, Yuchen Zhang, Ganqu Cui, Hanbin Wang, Ziming You, Ning Ding, Zhiyuan Liu, Maosong Sun, Hao Peng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Does RL teach LLMs genuinely new skills, or does it merely activate existing ones? This question lies at the core of ongoing debates about the role of RL in LLM post-training. On one side, strong empirical results can be achieved with RL even without preceding supervised finetuning; on the other, critics argue that RL contributes little beyond reweighting existing reasoning strategies. This work provides concrete evidence that LLMs can acquire genuinely new skills during RL by composing existing ones, mirroring one of the central mechanisms by which humans acquire new cognitive skills. To mitigate data contamination and other confounding factors, and to allow precise control over task complexity, we develop a synthetic framework for our investigation. Specifically, we define a skill as the ability to infer the output of a string transformation function f(x) given x. When an LLM has already learned f and g prior to RL, our experiments reveal that RL enables it to learn unseen compositions of them h(x)=g(f(x)). Further, this compositional ability generalizes to more difficult problems such as compositions of &gt;2 functions unseen during RL training. Surprisingly, our experiments show that compositional skill acquired on a source task transfers to a different target task. This transfer happens even without compositional training on the target, requiring only prior knowledge of the target's atomic skills. Our qualitative analysis shows that RL fundamentally changes the reasoning behaviors of the models. In contrast, next-token training with the same data yields none of these findings. Our systematic experiments provide fresh insights into LLM learning, suggesting the value of first building base models with basic skills, then using RL to incentivize advanced, generalizable skills for complex problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25123</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:44:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Era of Real-World Human Interaction: RL from User Conversations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25137</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25137.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chuanyang Jin, Jing Xu, Bo Liu, Leitian Tao, Olga Golovneva, Tianmin Shu, Wenting Zhao, Xian Li, Jason Weston&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We posit that to achieve continual model improvement and multifaceted alignment, future models must learn from natural human interaction. Current conversational models are aligned using pre-annotated, expert-generated human feedback. In this work, we introduce Reinforcement Learning from Human Interaction (RLHI), a paradigm that learns directly from in-the-wild user conversations. We develop two complementary methods: (1) RLHI with User-Guided Rewrites, which revises unsatisfactory model outputs based on users' natural-language follow-up responses, (2) RLHI with User-Based Rewards, which learns via a reward model conditioned on knowledge of the user's long-term interaction history (termed persona). Together, these methods link long-term user personas to turn-level preferences via persona-conditioned preference optimization. Trained on conversations derived from WildChat, both RLHI variants outperform strong baselines in personalization and instruction-following, and similar feedback enhances performance on reasoning benchmarks. These results suggest organic human interaction offers scalable, effective supervision for personalized alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25137</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:50:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who's Your Judge? On the Detectability of LLM-Generated Judgments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25154</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25154.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dawei Li, Zhen Tan, Chengshuai Zhao, Bohan Jiang, Baixiang Huang, Pingchuan Ma, Abdullah Alnaibari, Kai Shu, Huan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Model (LLM)-based judgments leverage powerful LLMs to efficiently evaluate candidate content and provide judgment scores. However, the inherent biases and vulnerabilities of LLM-generated judgments raise concerns, underscoring the urgent need for distinguishing them in sensitive scenarios like academic peer reviewing. In this work, we propose and formalize the task of judgment detection and systematically investigate the detectability of LLM-generated judgments. Unlike LLM-generated text detection, judgment detection relies solely on judgment scores and candidates, reflecting real-world scenarios where textual feedback is often unavailable in the detection process. Our preliminary analysis shows that existing LLM-generated text detection methods perform poorly given their incapability to capture the interaction between judgment scores and candidate content -- an aspect crucial for effective judgment detection. Inspired by this, we introduce J-Detector, a lightweight and transparent neural detector augmented with explicitly extracted linguistic and LLM-enhanced features to link LLM judges' biases with candidates' properties for accurate detection. Experiments across diverse datasets demonstrate the effectiveness of J-Detector and show how its interpretability enables quantifying biases in LLM judges. Finally, we analyze key factors affecting the detectability of LLM-generated judgments and validate the practical utility of judgment detection in real-world scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25154</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:54:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GSM8K-V: Can Vision Language Models Solve Grade School Math Word   Problems in Visual Contexts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25160</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25160.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fan Yuan, Yuchen Yan, Yifan Jiang, Haoran Zhao, Tao Feng, Jinyan Chen, Yanwei Lou, Wenqi Zhang, Yongliang Shen, Weiming Lu, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision language models (VLMs) achieve unified modeling of images and text, enabling them to accomplish complex real-world tasks through perception, planning, and reasoning. Among these tasks, reasoning is particularly representative, with mathematical reasoning serving as a prominent example. It highlights the high-level capability of VLMs to comprehend mathematical information in images and to perform sophisticated reasoning. Recently, numerous visual mathematical reasoning benchmarks have been proposed, but they are often restricted to geometry, lack coverage of math word problems, and rarely assess reasoning across multiple images. To address these gaps, we introduce GSM8K-V, a purely visual multi-image mathematical reasoning benchmark. GSM8K-V is built by systematically mapping each sample from the widely used text-based GSM8K into visual form. Through a carefully designed automated image-generation pipeline combined with meticulous human annotation, we curate 1,319 high-quality samples. We evaluate a wide range of open-source and closed-source models on GSM8K-V. Results show that although existing VLMs have nearly saturated performance on text-based GSM8K, there remains substantial room for improvement on GSM8K-V. For example, the best-performing model, Gemini-2.5-Pro, achieves 95.22% accuracy on GSM8K but only 46.93% on GSM8K-V. We conduct a comprehensive analysis of GSM8K-V, examining the limitations of current models as well as potential directions for improvement. GSM8K-V offers a new perspective on visual mathematical reasoning and establishes a benchmark to guide the development of more robust and generalizable VLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25160</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:57:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rolling Forcing: Autoregressive Long Video Diffusion in Real Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25161</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25161.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kunhao Liu, Wenbo Hu, Jiale Xu, Ying Shan, Shijian Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Streaming video generation, as one fundamental component in interactive world models and neural game engines, aims to generate high-quality, low-latency, and temporally coherent long video streams. However, most existing work suffers from severe error accumulation that often significantly degrades the generated stream videos over long horizons. We design Rolling Forcing, a novel video generation technique that enables streaming long videos with minimal error accumulation. Rolling Forcing comes with three novel designs. First, instead of iteratively sampling individual frames, which accelerates error propagation, we design a joint denoising scheme that simultaneously denoises multiple frames with progressively increasing noise levels. This design relaxes the strict causality across adjacent frames, effectively suppressing error growth. Second, we introduce the attention sink mechanism into the long-horizon stream video generation task, which allows the model to keep key value states of initial frames as a global context anchor and thereby enhances long-term global consistency. Third, we design an efficient training algorithm that enables few-step distillation over largely extended denoising windows. This algorithm operates on non-overlapping windows and mitigates exposure bias conditioned on self-generated histories. Extensive experiments show that Rolling Forcing enables real-time streaming generation of multi-minute videos on a single GPU, with substantially reduced error accumulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25161</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:57:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EasySteer: A Unified Framework for High-Performance and Extensible LLM   Steering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25175</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25175.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haolei Xu, Xinyu Mei, Yuchen Yan, Rui Zhou, Wenqi Zhang, Weiming Lu, Yueting Zhuang, Yongliang Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM) steering has emerged as a promising paradigm for controlling model behavior at inference time through targeted manipulation of hidden states, offering a lightweight alternative to expensive retraining. However, existing steering frameworks suffer from critical limitations: computational inefficiency, limited extensibility, and restricted functionality that hinder both research progress and practical deployment. We present EasySteer, a unified framework for high-performance, extensible LLM steering built on vLLM. Our system features modular architecture with pluggable interfaces for both analysis-based and learning-based methods, fine-grained parameter control, pre-computed steering vectors for eight application domains, and an interactive demonstration system. Through deep integration with vLLM's optimized inference engine, EasySteer achieves 5.5-11.4times speedup over existing frameworks. Extensive experiments demonstrate its effectiveness in overthinking mitigation, hallucination reduction, and other key applications. EasySteer transforms steering from research technique to production-ready capability, establishing critical infrastructure for deployable, controllable language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25175</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DC-VideoGen: Efficient Video Generation with Deep Compression Video   Autoencoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25182</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25182.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyu Chen, Wenkun He, Yuchao Gu, Yuyang Zhao, Jincheng Yu, Junsong Chen, Dongyun Zou, Yujun Lin, Zhekai Zhang, Muyang Li, Haocheng Xi, Ligeng Zhu, Enze Xie, Song Han, Han Cai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce DC-VideoGen, a post-training acceleration framework for efficient video generation. DC-VideoGen can be applied to any pre-trained video diffusion model, improving efficiency by adapting it to a deep compression latent space with lightweight fine-tuning. The framework builds on two key innovations: (i) a Deep Compression Video Autoencoder with a novel chunk-causal temporal design that achieves 32x/64x spatial and 4x temporal compression while preserving reconstruction quality and generalization to longer videos; and (ii) AE-Adapt-V, a robust adaptation strategy that enables rapid and stable transfer of pre-trained models into the new latent space. Adapting the pre-trained Wan-2.1-14B model with DC-VideoGen requires only 10 GPU days on the NVIDIA H100 GPU. The accelerated models achieve up to 14.8x lower inference latency than their base counterparts without compromising quality, and further enable 2160x3840 video generation on a single GPU. Code: https://github.com/dc-ai-projects/DC-VideoGen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25182</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Jigsaw Post-Training Improves MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25190</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25190.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Penghao Wu, Yushan Zhang, Haiwen Diao, Bo Li, Lewei Lu, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning based post-training has recently emerged as a powerful paradigm for enhancing the alignment and reasoning capabilities of multimodal large language models (MLLMs). While vision-centric post-training is crucial for enhancing MLLMs' intrinsic understanding of visual signals, current post-training paradigms are predominantly text-centric, where dense visual inputs are only leveraged to extract sparse cues for text-based reasoning. There exist a few approaches in this direction, however, they often still rely on text as an intermediate mediator or introduce additional visual generative designs. In this work, we introduce Visual Jigsaw, a generic self-supervised post-training framework designed to strengthen visual understanding in MLLMs. Visual Jigsaw is formulated as a general ordering task: visual inputs are partitioned, shuffled, and the model must reconstruct the visual information by producing the correct permutation in natural language. This naturally aligns with reinforcement learning from verifiable rewards (RLVR), requires no additional visual generative components, and derives its supervisory signal automatically without any annotations. We instantiate Visual Jigsaw across three visual modalities, including images, videos, and 3D data. Extensive experiments demonstrate substantial improvements in fine-grained perception, temporal reasoning, and 3D spatial understanding. Our findings highlight the potential of self-supervised vision-centric tasks in post-training MLLMs and aim to inspire further research on vision-centric pretext designs. Project Page: https://penghao-wu.github.io/visual_jigsaw/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25190</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VGGT-X: When VGGT Meets Dense Novel View Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25191</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25191.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Liu, Chuanchen Luo, Zimo Tang, Junran Peng, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We study the problem of applying 3D Foundation Models (3DFMs) to dense Novel View Synthesis (NVS). Despite significant progress in Novel View Synthesis powered by NeRF and 3DGS, current approaches remain reliant on accurate 3D attributes (e.g., camera poses and point clouds) acquired from Structure-from-Motion (SfM), which is often slow and fragile in low-texture or low-overlap captures. Recent 3DFMs showcase orders of magnitude speedup over the traditional pipeline and great potential for online NVS. But most of the validation and conclusions are confined to sparse-view settings. Our study reveals that naively scaling 3DFMs to dense views encounters two fundamental barriers: dramatically increasing VRAM burden and imperfect outputs that degrade initialization-sensitive 3D training. To address these barriers, we introduce VGGT-X, incorporating a memory-efficient VGGT implementation that scales to 1,000+ images, an adaptive global alignment for VGGT output enhancement, and robust 3DGS training practices. Extensive experiments show that these measures substantially close the fidelity gap with COLMAP-initialized pipelines, achieving state-of-the-art results in dense COLMAP-free NVS and pose estimation. Additionally, we analyze the causes of remaining gaps with COLMAP-initialized rendering, providing insights for the future development of 3D foundation models and dense NVS. Our project page is available at https://dekuliutesla.github.io/vggt-x.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25191</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 17:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSearch: Overcome the Bottleneck of Reinforcement Learning with   Verifiable Rewards via Monte Carlo Tree Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25454</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25454.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fang Wu, Weihao Xuan, Heli Qi, Ximing Lu, Aaron Tu, Li Erran Li, Yejin Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 115&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although RLVR has become an essential component for developing advanced reasoning skills in LLMs, contemporary studies have documented training plateaus that emerge following thousands of optimization steps, demonstrating notable decreases in performance gains despite increased computational investment. This limitation stems from the sparse exploration patterns inherent in current RLVR practices, where models rely on limited rollouts that often miss critical reasoning paths and fail to provide systematic coverage of the solution space. We present DeepSearch, a framework that integrates Monte Carlo Tree Search directly into RLVR training. In contrast to existing methods that rely on tree search only at inference, DeepSearch embeds structured search into the training loop, enabling systematic exploration and fine-grained credit assignment across reasoning steps. Through training-time exploration, DeepSearch addresses the fundamental bottleneck of insufficient exploration, which leads to diminishing performance improvements over prolonged training steps. Our contributions include: (1) a global frontier selection strategy that prioritizes promising nodes across the search tree, (2) selection with entropy-based guidance that identifies confident paths for supervision, and (3) adaptive replay buffer training with solution caching for efficiency. Experiments on mathematical reasoning benchmarks show that DeepSearch achieves 62.95% average accuracy and establishes a new state-of-the-art for 1.5B reasoning models - using 5.7x fewer GPU hours than extended training approaches. These results highlight the importance of strategic exploration over brute-force scaling and demonstrate the promise of algorithmic innovation for advancing RLVR methodologies. DeepSearch establishes a new direction for scaling reasoning capabilities through systematic search rather than prolonged computation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25454</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 20:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PIPer: On-Device Environment Setup via Online Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25455</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25455.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Kovrigin, Aleksandra Eliseeva, Konstantin Grotov, Egor Bogomolov, Yaroslav Zharov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Environment setup-the process of configuring the system to work with a specific software project-represents a persistent challenge in Software Engineering (SE). Automated environment setup methods could assist developers by providing fully configured environments for arbitrary repositories without manual effort. This also helps SE researchers to scale execution-based benchmarks. However, recent studies reveal that even state-of-the-art Large Language Models (LLMs) achieve limited success in automating this task. To address this limitation, we tune a specialized model for environment setup. We combine supervised fine-tuning for generating correct Bash scripts and Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) to adapt it to the task of environment setup. On EnvBench-Python, our method enables Qwen3-8B (a model runnable on consumer hardware) to perform on par with larger models-Qwen3-32B and GPT-4o. The training code and model checkpoints are available online: https://github.com/JetBrains-Research/PIPer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25455</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 20:03:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision-Zero: Scalable VLM Self-Improvement via Strategic Gamified   Self-Play</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25541</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25541.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qinsi Wang, Bo Liu, Tianyi Zhou, Jing Shi, Yueqian Lin, Yiran Chen, Hai Helen Li, Kun Wan, Wentian Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 122&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although reinforcement learning (RL) can effectively enhance the reasoning capabilities of vision-language models (VLMs), current methods remain heavily dependent on labor-intensive datasets that require extensive manual construction and verification, leading to extremely high training costs and consequently constraining the practical deployment of VLMs. To address this challenge, we propose Vision-Zero, a domain-agnostic framework enabling VLM self-improvement through competitive visual games generated from arbitrary image pairs. Specifically, Vision-Zero encompasses three main attributes: (1) Strategic Self-Play Framework: Vision-Zero trains VLMs in "Who Is the Spy"-style games, where the models engage in strategic reasoning and actions across multiple roles. Through interactive gameplay, models autonomously generate their training data without human annotation. (2) Gameplay from Arbitrary Images: Unlike existing gamified frameworks, Vision-Zero can generate games from arbitrary images, thereby enhancing the model's reasoning ability across diverse domains and showing strong generalization to different tasks. We demonstrate this versatility using three distinct types of image datasets: CLEVR-based synthetic scenes, charts, and real-world images. (3) Sustainable Performance Gain: We introduce Iterative Self-Play Policy Optimization (Iterative-SPO), a novel training algorithm that alternates between Self-Play and reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR), mitigating the performance plateau often seen in self-play-only training and achieving sustained long-term improvements. Despite using label-free data, Vision-Zero achieves state-of-the-art performance on reasoning, chart question answering, and vision-centric understanding tasks, surpassing other annotation-based methods. Models and code has been released at https://github.com/wangqinsi1/Vision-Zero.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25541</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 21:55:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking Sparks!: Emergent Attention Heads in Reasoning Models During   Post Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25758</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25758.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yein Park, Minbyul Jeong, Jaewoo Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The remarkable capabilities of modern large reasoning models are largely unlocked through post-training techniques such as supervised fine-tuning and reinforcement learning. However, the architectural mechanisms behind such improvements remain largely opaque. In this work, we use circuit analysis to demonstrate that post-training for complex reasoning sparks the emergence of novel, functionally specialized attention heads. These heads collectively support structured reasoning and computation. Our comparative analysis across Qwen families and DeepSeek-distilled model reveals that these emergent heads evolve differently under different training regimes. Distillation and SFT foster a cumulative addition of stable reasoning heads. In contrast, group relative policy optimization operates in a dynamic search mode: relatively few attention heads are iteratively activated, evaluated, and pruned, with their survival closely tracking fluctuations in the task reward signal. Furthermore, we find that controllable think on/off models do not possess dedicated thinking heads. Instead, turning off explicit reasoning triggers a broader-but less efficient-set of compensatory heads. Through ablation and qualitative analyses, we connect these circuit-level dynamics to a crucial performance trade-off: strengthened heads enable sophisticated problem-solving strategies for difficult problems but can also introduce over-thinking failure modes, such as calculation errors or logical loops on simpler tasks. These findings connect circuit-level dynamics to macro-level performance, identifying an inherent tension where complex reasoning comes at the cost of elementary computations. More broadly, our work points to future directions for training policy design, emphasizing the need to balance the development of effective reasoning strategies with the assurance of reliable, flawless execution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25758</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 04:23:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TruthRL: Incentivizing Truthful LLMs via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25760</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25760.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhepei Wei, Xiao Yang, Kai Sun, Jiaqi Wang, Rulin Shao, Sean Chen, Mohammad Kachuee, Teja Gollapudi, Tony Liao, Nicolas Scheffer, Rakesh Wanga, Anuj Kumar, Yu Meng, Wen-tau Yih, Xin Luna Dong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated strong performance on factoid question answering, they are still prone to hallucination and untruthful responses, particularly when tasks demand information outside their parametric knowledge. Indeed, truthfulness requires more than accuracy -- models must also recognize uncertainty and abstain when unsure to avoid hallucinations. This presents a fundamental challenge for existing methods: approaches that optimize for accuracy often amplify hallucinations, while those that encourage abstention can become overly conservative, sacrificing correct answers. Both extremes ultimately compromise truthfulness. In this work, we present TruthRL, a general reinforcement learning (RL) framework that directly optimizes the truthfulness of LLMs. Specifically, we implement TruthRL using GRPO with a simple yet effective ternary reward that distinguishes correct answers, hallucinations, and abstentions. It incentivizes models to reduce hallucinations not only by providing correct responses, but also by enabling abstention when uncertain, thereby improving truthfulness. Extensive experiments across four knowledge-intensive benchmarks show that, compared to vanilla RL, TruthRL significantly reduces hallucinations by 28.9% and improves truthfulness by 21.1%, with consistent gains across various backbone models (e.g., Qwen, Llama) under both retrieval and non-retrieval setups. In-depth ablation study demonstrates that vanilla accuracy-driven methods, such as supervised fine-tuning or RL with a binary reward, struggle to balance factual correctness and uncertainty. In contrast, our proposed truthfulness-driven TruthRL achieves strong performance in both accuracy and truthfulness, underscoring the importance of learning objective design for developing truthful LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25760</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 04:25:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Thought, Less Accuracy? On the Dual Nature of Reasoning in   Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25848</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25848.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinyu Tian, Shu Zou, Zhaoyuan Yang, Mengqi He, Fabian Waschkowski, Lukas Wesemann, Peter Tu, Jing Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning has emerged as a pivotal capability in Large Language Models (LLMs). Through Reinforcement Learning (RL), typically Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), these models are able to solve complex tasks such as mathematics and code generation. Building on these advances, recent research has sought to extend reasoning to Vision-Language Models (VLMs), yielding promising results across diverse visual tasks. Despite this progress, our study uncovers the dual nature of multimodal reasoning: while it substantially enhances logical inference and facilitates performance on challenging problems, it may gradually impair perceptual grounding, leading to recognition failures on otherwise basic visual questions. Through further analysis, we attribute this phenomenon to visual forgetting, wherein prolonged reasoning causes the model to increasingly disregard visual input. To address this, we propose Vision-Anchored Policy Optimization (VAPO), a simple yet effective method that explicitly steers the reasoning process toward visually grounded trajectories. Our result model, VAPO-Thinker-7B, significantly strengthens the model's reliance on visual information and achieves new state-of-the-art results on a wide range of established benchmarks. Project page: https://xytian1008.github.io/VAPO/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25848</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 06:37:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knapsack RL: Unlocking Exploration of LLMs via Optimizing Budget   Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25849</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.25849.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziniu Li, Congliang Chen, Tianyun Yang, Tian Ding, Ruoyu Sun, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Zhi-Quan Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) can self-improve through reinforcement learning, where they generate trajectories to explore and discover better solutions. However, this exploration process is computationally expensive, often forcing current methods to assign limited exploration budgets to each task. This uniform allocation creates problematic edge cases: easy tasks consistently succeed while difficult tasks consistently fail, both producing zero gradients during training updates for the widely used Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO). We address this problem from the lens of exploration budget allocation. Viewing each task's exploration as an "item" with a distinct "value" and "cost", we establish a connection to the classical knapsack problem. This formulation allows us to derive an optimal assignment rule that adaptively distributes resources based on the model's current learning status. When applied to GRPO, our method increases the effective ratio of non-zero policy gradients by 20-40% during training. Acting as a computational "free lunch", our approach could reallocate exploration budgets from tasks where learning is saturated to those where it is most impactful. This enables significantly larger budgets (e.g., 93 rollouts) for especially challenging problems, which would be computationally prohibitive under a uniform allocation. These improvements translate to meaningful gains on mathematical reasoning benchmarks, with average improvements of 2-4 points and peak gains of 9 points on specific tasks. Notably, achieving comparable performance with traditional homogeneous allocation would require about 2x the computational resources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25849</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 06:41:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muon Outperforms Adam in Tail-End Associative Memory Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26030</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26030.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuche Wang, Fengzhuo Zhang, Jiaxiang Li, Cunxiao Du, Chao Du, Tianyu Pang, Zhuoran Yang, Mingyi Hong, Vincent Y. F. Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Muon optimizer is consistently faster than Adam in training Large Language Models (LLMs), yet the mechanism underlying its success remains unclear. This paper demystifies this mechanism through the lens of associative memory. By ablating the transformer components optimized by Muon, we reveal that the associative memory parameters of LLMs, namely the Value and Output (VO) attention weights and Feed-Forward Networks (FFNs), are the primary contributors to Muon's superiority. Motivated by this associative memory view, we then explain Muon's superiority on real-world corpora, which are intrinsically heavy-tailed: a few classes (tail classes) appear far less frequently than others. The superiority is explained through two key properties: (i) its update rule consistently yields a more isotropic singular spectrum than Adam; and as a result, (ii) on heavy-tailed data, it optimizes tail classes more effectively than Adam. Beyond empirical evidence, we theoretically confirm these findings by analyzing a one-layer associative memory model under class-imbalanced data. We prove that Muon consistently achieves balanced learning across classes regardless of feature embeddings, whereas Adam can induce large disparities in learning errors depending on embedding properties. In summary, our empirical observations and theoretical analyses reveal Muon's core advantage: its update rule aligns with the outer-product structure of linear associative memories, enabling more balanced and effective learning of tail classes in heavy-tailed distributions than Adam.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26030</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 10:04:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking-Free Policy Initialization Makes Distilled Reasoning Models   More Effective and Efficient Reasoners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26226</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26226.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Xu, Cliveb AI, Kai Yang, Tianhao Chen, Yang Wang, Saiyong Yang, Can Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Reward (RLVR) effectively solves complex tasks but demands extremely long context lengths during training, leading to substantial computational costs. While multi-stage training can partially mitigate this, starting with overly short contexts often causes irreversible performance degradation, ultimately failing to reduce overall training compute significantly. In this paper, we introduce **T**hinking-**F**ree **P**olicy **I**nitialization (**TFPI**), a simple yet effective adaptation to RLVR that bridges long Chain-of-Thought (CoT) distillation and standard RLVR. TFPI employs a simple *ThinkFree* operation, explicitly discarding the thinking content via a direct *&lt;/think&gt;* append, to reduce token usage during inference. Training with *ThinkFree*-adapted inputs improves performance and lowers token consumption, even in the original slow-thinking mode. Extensive experiments across various benchmarks have shown that TFPI accelerates RL convergence, achieves a higher performance ceiling, and yields more token-efficient reasoning models without specialized rewards or complex training designs. With TFPI only, we train a 4B model to reach 89.0% accuracy on AIME24 and 65.5% on LiveCodeBench using less than 4K H20 hours.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26226</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 13:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IMG: Calibrating Diffusion Models via Implicit Multimodal Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26231</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26231.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiayi Guo, Chuanhao Yan, Xingqian Xu, Yulin Wang, Kai Wang, Gao Huang, Humphrey Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Ensuring precise multimodal alignment between diffusion-generated images and input prompts has been a long-standing challenge. Earlier works finetune diffusion weight using high-quality preference data, which tends to be limited and difficult to scale up. Recent editing-based methods further refine local regions of generated images but may compromise overall image quality. In this work, we propose Implicit Multimodal Guidance (IMG), a novel re-generation-based multimodal alignment framework that requires no extra data or editing operations. Specifically, given a generated image and its prompt, IMG a) utilizes a multimodal large language model (MLLM) to identify misalignments; b) introduces an Implicit Aligner that manipulates diffusion conditioning features to reduce misalignments and enable re-generation; and c) formulates the re-alignment goal into a trainable objective, namely Iteratively Updated Preference Objective. Extensive qualitative and quantitative evaluations on SDXL, SDXL-DPO, and FLUX show that IMG outperforms existing alignment methods. Furthermore, IMG acts as a flexible plug-and-play adapter, seamlessly enhancing prior finetuning-based alignment methods. Our code will be available at https://github.com/SHI-Labs/IMG-Multimodal-Diffusion-Alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26231</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 13:27:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EditReward: A Human-Aligned Reward Model for Instruction-Guided Image   Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26346</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26346.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Keming Wu, Sicong Jiang, Max Ku, Ping Nie, Minghao Liu, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, we have witnessed great progress in image editing with natural language instructions. Several closed-source models like GPT-Image-1, Seedream, and Google-Nano-Banana have shown highly promising progress. However, the open-source models are still lagging. The main bottleneck is the lack of a reliable reward model to scale up high-quality synthetic training data. To address this critical bottleneck, we built \mname, trained with our new large-scale human preference dataset, meticulously annotated by trained experts following a rigorous protocol containing over 200K preference pairs. \mname demonstrates superior alignment with human preferences in instruction-guided image editing tasks. Experiments show that \mname achieves state-of-the-art human correlation on established benchmarks such as GenAI-Bench, AURORA-Bench, ImagenHub, and our new \benchname, outperforming a wide range of VLM-as-judge models. Furthermore, we use \mname to select a high-quality subset from the existing noisy ShareGPT-4o-Image dataset. We train Step1X-Edit on the selected subset, which shows significant improvement over training on the full set. This demonstrates \mname's ability to serve as a reward model to scale up high-quality training data for image editing. Furthermore, its strong alignment suggests potential for advanced applications like reinforcement learning-based post-training and test-time scaling of image editing models. \mname with its training dataset will be released to help the community build more high-quality image editing training datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26346</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 14:51:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MotionRAG: Motion Retrieval-Augmented Image-to-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26391</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26391.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenhui Zhu, Yilu Wu, Shuai Wang, Gangshan Wu, Limin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Image-to-video generation has made remarkable progress with the advancements in diffusion models, yet generating videos with realistic motion remains highly challenging. This difficulty arises from the complexity of accurately modeling motion, which involves capturing physical constraints, object interactions, and domain-specific dynamics that are not easily generalized across diverse scenarios. To address this, we propose MotionRAG, a retrieval-augmented framework that enhances motion realism by adapting motion priors from relevant reference videos through Context-Aware Motion Adaptation (CAMA). The key technical innovations include: (i) a retrieval-based pipeline extracting high-level motion features using video encoder and specialized resamplers to distill semantic motion representations; (ii) an in-context learning approach for motion adaptation implemented through a causal transformer architecture; (iii) an attention-based motion injection adapter that seamlessly integrates transferred motion features into pretrained video diffusion models. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method achieves significant improvements across multiple domains and various base models, all with negligible computational overhead during inference. Furthermore, our modular design enables zero-shot generalization to new domains by simply updating the retrieval database without retraining any components. This research enhances the core capability of video generation systems by enabling the effective retrieval and transfer of motion priors, facilitating the synthesis of realistic motion dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26391</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 15:26:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>dParallel: Learnable Parallel Decoding for dLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26488</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26488.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zigeng Chen, Gongfan Fang, Xinyin Ma, Ruonan Yu, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion large language models (dLLMs) have recently drawn considerable attention within the research community as a promising alternative to autoregressive generation, offering parallel token prediction and lower inference latency. Yet, their parallel decoding potential remains largely underexplored, as existing open-source models still require nearly token-length decoding steps to ensure performance. To address this, we introduce dParallel, a simple and effective method that unlocks the inherent parallelism of dLLMs for fast sampling. We identify that the key bottleneck to parallel decoding arises from the sequential certainty convergence for masked tokens. Building on this insight, we introduce the core of our approach: certainty-forcing distillation, a novel training strategy that distills the model to follow its original sampling trajectories while enforcing it to achieve high certainty on masked tokens more rapidly and in parallel. Extensive experiments across various benchmarks demonstrate that our method can dramatically reduce the number of decoding steps while maintaining performance. When applied to the LLaDA-8B-Instruct model, dParallel reduces decoding steps from 256 to 30 on GSM8K, achieving an 8.5x speedup without performance degradation. On the MBPP benchmark, it cuts decoding steps from 256 to 24, resulting in a 10.5x speedup while maintaining accuracy. Our code is available at https://github.com/czg1225/dParallel&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26488</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 16:32:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VitaBench: Benchmarking LLM Agents with Versatile Interactive Tasks in   Real-world Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26490</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26490.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei He, Yueqing Sun, Hongyan Hao, Xueyuan Hao, Zhikang Xia, Qi Gu, Chengcheng Han, Dengchang Zhao, Hui Su, Kefeng Zhang, Man Gao, Xi Su, Xiaodong Cai, Xunliang Cai, Yu Yang, Yunke Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As LLM-based agents are increasingly deployed in real-life scenarios, existing benchmarks fail to capture their inherent complexity of handling extensive information, leveraging diverse resources, and managing dynamic user interactions. To address this gap, we introduce VitaBench, a challenging benchmark that evaluates agents on versatile interactive tasks grounded in real-world settings. Drawing from daily applications in food delivery, in-store consumption, and online travel services, VitaBench presents agents with the most complex life-serving simulation environment to date, comprising 66 tools. Through a framework that eliminates domain-specific policies, we enable flexible composition of these scenarios and tools, yielding 100 cross-scenario tasks (main results) and 300 single-scenario tasks. Each task is derived from multiple real user requests and requires agents to reason across temporal and spatial dimensions, utilize complex tool sets, proactively clarify ambiguous instructions, and track shifting user intent throughout multi-turn conversations. Moreover, we propose a rubric-based sliding window evaluator, enabling robust assessment of diverse solution pathways in complex environments and stochastic interactions. Our comprehensive evaluation reveals that even the most advanced models achieve only 30% success rate on cross-scenario tasks, and less than 50% success rate on others. Overall, we believe VitaBench will serve as a valuable resource for advancing the development of AI agents in practical real-world applications. The code, dataset, and leaderboard are available at https://vitabench.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26490</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 16:33:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dragon Hatchling: The Missing Link between the Transformer and   Models of the Brain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26507</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26507.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Adrian Kosowski, Przemysław Uznański, Jan Chorowski, Zuzanna Stamirowska, Michał Bartoszkiewicz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 359&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The relationship between computing systems and the brain has served as motivation for pioneering theoreticians since John von Neumann and Alan Turing. Uniform, scale-free biological networks, such as the brain, have powerful properties, including generalizing over time, which is the main barrier for Machine Learning on the path to Universal Reasoning Models.   We introduce `Dragon Hatchling' (BDH), a new Large Language Model architecture based on a scale-free biologically inspired network of \n locally-interacting neuron particles. BDH couples strong theoretical foundations and inherent interpretability without sacrificing Transformer-like performance.   BDH is a practical, performant state-of-the-art attention-based state space sequence learning architecture. In addition to being a graph model, BDH admits a GPU-friendly formulation. It exhibits Transformer-like scaling laws: empirically BDH rivals GPT2 performance on language and translation tasks, at the same number of parameters (10M to 1B), for the same training data.   BDH can be represented as a brain model. The working memory of BDH during inference entirely relies on synaptic plasticity with Hebbian learning using spiking neurons. We confirm empirically that specific, individual synapses strengthen connection whenever BDH hears or reasons about a specific concept while processing language inputs. The neuron interaction network of BDH is a graph of high modularity with heavy-tailed degree distribution. The BDH model is biologically plausible, explaining one possible mechanism which human neurons could use to achieve speech.   BDH is designed for interpretability. Activation vectors of BDH are sparse and positive. We demonstrate monosemanticity in BDH on language tasks. Interpretability of state, which goes beyond interpretability of neurons and model parameters, is an inherent feature of the BDH architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26507</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 16:49:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OceanGym: A Benchmark Environment for Underwater Embodied Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26536</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26536.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yida Xue, Mingjun Mao, Xiangyuan Ru, Yuqi Zhu, Baochang Ren, Shuofei Qiao, Mengru Wang, Shumin Deng, Xinyu An, Ningyu Zhang, Ying Chen, Huajun Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce OceanGym, the first comprehensive benchmark for ocean underwater embodied agents, designed to advance AI in one of the most demanding real-world environments. Unlike terrestrial or aerial domains, underwater settings present extreme perceptual and decision-making challenges, including low visibility, dynamic ocean currents, making effective agent deployment exceptionally difficult. OceanGym encompasses eight realistic task domains and a unified agent framework driven by Multi-modal Large Language Models (MLLMs), which integrates perception, memory, and sequential decision-making. Agents are required to comprehend optical and sonar data, autonomously explore complex environments, and accomplish long-horizon objectives under these harsh conditions. Extensive experiments reveal substantial gaps between state-of-the-art MLLM-driven agents and human experts, highlighting the persistent difficulty of perception, planning, and adaptability in ocean underwater environments. By providing a high-fidelity, rigorously designed platform, OceanGym establishes a testbed for developing robust embodied AI and transferring these capabilities to real-world autonomous ocean underwater vehicles, marking a decisive step toward intelligent agents capable of operating in one of Earth's last unexplored frontiers. The code and data are available at https://github.com/OceanGPT/OceanGym.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26536</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 17:09:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DA^2: Depth Anything in Any Direction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haodong Li, Wangguangdong Zheng, Jing He, Yuhao Liu, Xin Lin, Xin Yang, Ying-Cong Chen, Chunchao Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Panorama has a full FoV (360^circtimes180^circ), offering a more complete visual description than perspective images. Thanks to this characteristic, panoramic depth estimation is gaining increasing traction in 3D vision. However, due to the scarcity of panoramic data, previous methods are often restricted to in-domain settings, leading to poor zero-shot generalization. Furthermore, due to the spherical distortions inherent in panoramas, many approaches rely on perspective splitting (e.g., cubemaps), which leads to suboptimal efficiency. To address these challenges, we propose DA^{2}: Depth Anything in Any Direction, an accurate, zero-shot generalizable, and fully end-to-end panoramic depth estimator. Specifically, for scaling up panoramic data, we introduce a data curation engine for generating high-quality panoramic depth data from perspective, and create sim543K panoramic RGB-depth pairs, bringing the total to sim607K. To further mitigate the spherical distortions, we present SphereViT, which explicitly leverages spherical coordinates to enforce the spherical geometric consistency in panoramic image features, yielding improved performance. A comprehensive benchmark on multiple datasets clearly demonstrates DA^{2}'s SoTA performance, with an average 38% improvement on AbsRel over the strongest zero-shot baseline. Surprisingly, DA^{2} even outperforms prior in-domain methods, highlighting its superior zero-shot generalization. Moreover, as an end-to-end solution, DA^{2} exhibits much higher efficiency over fusion-based approaches. Both the code and the curated panoramic data will be released. Project page: https://depth-any-in-any-dir.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26618</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 17:55:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to See Before Seeing: Demystifying LLM Visual Priors from   Language Pre-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26625</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.26625.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junlin Han, Shengbang Tong, David Fan, Yufan Ren, Koustuv Sinha, Philip Torr, Filippos Kokkinos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs), despite being trained on text alone, surprisingly develop rich visual priors. These priors allow latent visual capabilities to be unlocked for vision tasks with a relatively small amount of multimodal data, and in some cases, to perform visual tasks without ever having seen an image. Through systematic analysis, we reveal that visual priors-the implicit, emergent knowledge about the visual world acquired during language pre-training-are composed of separable perception and reasoning priors with unique scaling trends and origins. We show that an LLM's latent visual reasoning ability is predominantly developed by pre-training on reasoning-centric data (e.g., code, math, academia) and scales progressively. This reasoning prior acquired from language pre-training is transferable and universally applicable to visual reasoning. In contrast, a perception prior emerges more diffusely from broad corpora, and perception ability is more sensitive to the vision encoder and visual instruction tuning data. In parallel, text describing the visual world proves crucial, though its performance impact saturates rapidly. Leveraging these insights, we propose a data-centric recipe for pre-training vision-aware LLMs and verify it in 1T token scale pre-training. Our findings are grounded in over 100 controlled experiments consuming 500,000 GPU-hours, spanning the full MLLM construction pipeline-from LLM pre-training to visual alignment and supervised multimodal fine-tuning-across five model scales, a wide range of data categories and mixtures, and multiple adaptation setups. Along with our main findings, we propose and investigate several hypotheses, and introduce the Multi-Level Existence Bench (MLE-Bench). Together, this work provides a new way of deliberately cultivating visual priors from language pre-training, paving the way for the next generation of multimodal LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.26625</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 17:57:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Can't Transformers Learn Multiplication? Reverse-Engineering Reveals   Long-Range Dependency Pitfalls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00184</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.00184.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoyan Bai, Itamar Pres, Yuntian Deng, Chenhao Tan, Stuart Shieber, Fernanda Viégas, Martin Wattenberg, Andrew Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language models are increasingly capable, yet still fail at a seemingly simple task of multi-digit multiplication. In this work, we study why, by reverse-engineering a model that successfully learns multiplication via implicit chain-of-thought, and report three findings: (1) Evidence of long-range structure: Logit attributions and linear probes indicate that the model encodes the necessary long-range dependencies for multi-digit multiplication. (2) Mechanism: the model encodes long-range dependencies using attention to construct a directed acyclic graph to ``cache'' and ``retrieve'' pairwise partial products. (3) Geometry: the model implements partial products in attention heads by forming Minkowski sums between pairs of digits, and digits are represented using a Fourier basis, both of which are intuitive and efficient representations that the standard fine-tuning model lacks. With these insights, we revisit the learning dynamics of standard fine-tuning and find that the model converges to a local optimum that lacks the required long-range dependencies. We further validate this understanding by introducing an auxiliary loss that predicts the ``running sum'' via a linear regression probe, which provides an inductive bias that enables the model to successfully learn multi-digit multiplication. In summary, by reverse-engineering the mechanisms of an implicit chain-of-thought model we uncover a pitfall for learning long-range dependencies in Transformers and provide an example of how the correct inductive bias can address this issue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00184</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 19:03:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BiasFreeBench: a Benchmark for Mitigating Bias in Large Language Model   Responses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00232</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.00232.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Xu, Xunzhi He, Churan Zhi, Ruizhe Chen, Julian McAuley, Zexue He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing studies on bias mitigation methods for large language models (LLMs) use diverse baselines and metrics to evaluate debiasing performance, leading to inconsistent comparisons among them. Moreover, their evaluations are mostly based on the comparison between LLMs' probabilities of biased and unbiased contexts, which ignores the gap between such evaluations and real-world use cases where users interact with LLMs by reading model responses and expect fair and safe outputs rather than LLMs' probabilities. To enable consistent evaluation across debiasing methods and bridge this gap, we introduce BiasFreeBench, an empirical benchmark that comprehensively compares eight mainstream bias mitigation techniques (covering four prompting-based and four training-based methods) on two test scenarios (multi-choice QA and open-ended multi-turn QA) by reorganizing existing datasets into a unified query-response setting. We further introduce a response-level metric, Bias-Free Score, to measure the extent to which LLM responses are fair, safe, and anti-stereotypical. Debiasing performances are systematically compared and analyzed across key dimensions: the prompting vs. training paradigm, model size, and generalization of different training strategies to unseen bias types. We will publicly release our benchmark, aiming to establish a unified testbed for bias mitigation research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00232</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 19:56:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ovi: Twin Backbone Cross-Modal Fusion for Audio-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01284</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01284.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chetwin Low, Weimin Wang, Calder Katyal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Audio-video generation has often relied on complex multi-stage architectures or sequential synthesis of sound and visuals. We introduce Ovi, a unified paradigm for audio-video generation that models the two modalities as a single generative process. By using blockwise cross-modal fusion of twin-DiT modules, Ovi achieves natural synchronization and removes the need for separate pipelines or post hoc alignment. To facilitate fine-grained multimodal fusion modeling, we initialize an audio tower with an architecture identical to that of a strong pretrained video model. Trained from scratch on hundreds of thousands of hours of raw audio, the audio tower learns to generate realistic sound effects, as well as speech that conveys rich speaker identity and emotion. Fusion is obtained by jointly training the identical video and audio towers via blockwise exchange of timing (via scaled-RoPE embeddings) and semantics (through bidirectional cross-attention) on a vast video corpus. Our model enables cinematic storytelling with natural speech and accurate, context-matched sound effects, producing movie-grade video clips. All the demos, code and model weights are published at https://aaxwaz.github.io/Ovi&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01284</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 21:03:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VLA-RFT: Vision-Language-Action Reinforcement Fine-tuning with Verified   Rewards in World Simulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00406</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.00406.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hengtao Li, Pengxiang Ding, Runze Suo, Yihao Wang, Zirui Ge, Dongyuan Zang, Kexian Yu, Mingyang Sun, Hongyin Zhang, Donglin Wang, Weihua Su&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models enable embodied decision-making but rely heavily on imitation learning, leading to compounding errors and poor robustness under distribution shift. Reinforcement learning (RL) can mitigate these issues yet typically demands costly real-world interactions or suffers from sim-to-real gaps. We introduce VLA-RFT, a reinforcement fine-tuning framework that leverages a data-driven world model as a controllable simulator. Trained from real interaction data, the simulator predicts future visual observations conditioned on actions, allowing policy rollouts with dense, trajectory-level rewards derived from goal-achieving references. This design delivers an efficient and action-aligned learning signal, drastically lowering sample requirements. With fewer than 400 fine-tuning steps, VLA-RFT surpasses strong supervised baselines and achieves greater efficiency than simulator-based RL. Moreover, it exhibits strong robustness under perturbed conditions, sustaining stable task execution. Our results establish world-model-based RFT as a practical post-training paradigm to enhance the generalization and robustness of VLA models. For more details, please refer to https://vla-rft.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00406</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 01:33:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongCodeZip: Compress Long Context for Code Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00446</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.00446.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuling Shi, Yichun Qian, Hongyu Zhang, Beijun Shen, Xiaodong Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 90&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Code generation under long contexts is becoming increasingly critical as Large Language Models (LLMs) are required to reason over extensive information in the codebase. While recent advances enable code LLMs to process long inputs, high API costs and generation latency remain substantial bottlenecks. Existing context pruning techniques, such as LLMLingua, achieve promising results for general text but overlook code-specific structures and dependencies, leading to suboptimal performance in programming tasks. In this paper, we propose LongCodeZip, a novel plug-and-play code compression framework designed specifically for code LLMs. LongCodeZip employs a dual-stage strategy: (1) coarse-grained compression, which identifies and ranks function-level chunks using conditional perplexity with respect to the instruction, retaining only the most relevant functions; and (2) fine-grained compression, which segments retained functions into blocks based on perplexity and selects an optimal subset under an adaptive token budget to maximize relevance. Evaluations across multiple tasks, including code completion, summarization, and question answering, show that LongCodeZip consistently outperforms baseline methods, achieving up to a 5.6x compression ratio without degrading task performance. By effectively reducing context size while preserving essential information, LongCodeZip enables LLMs to better scale to real-world, large-scale code scenarios, advancing the efficiency and capability of code intelligence applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00446</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 02:54:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Reward Models for Multi-Domain Test-Time Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00492</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.00492.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dong Bok Lee, Seanie Lee, Sangwoo Park, Minki Kang, Jinheon Baek, Dongki Kim, Dominik Wagner, Jiongdao Jin, Heejun Lee, Tobias Bocklet, Jinyu Wang, Jingjing Fu, Sung Ju Hwang, Jiang Bia, Lei Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The reliability of large language models (LLMs) during test-time scaling is often assessed with external verifiers or reward models that distinguish correct reasoning from flawed logic. Prior work generally assumes that process reward models (PRMs), which score every intermediate reasoning step, outperform outcome reward models (ORMs) that assess only the final answer. This view is based mainly on evidence from narrow, math-adjacent domains. We present the first unified evaluation of four reward model variants, discriminative ORM and PRM (\DisORM, \DisPRM) and generative ORM and PRM (\GenORM, \GenPRM), across 14 diverse domains. Contrary to conventional wisdom, we find that (i) \DisORM performs on par with \DisPRM, (ii) \GenPRM is not competitive, and (iii) overall, \GenORM is the most robust, yielding significant and consistent gains across every tested domain. We attribute this to PRM-style stepwise scoring, which inherits label noise from LLM auto-labeling and has difficulty evaluating long reasoning trajectories, including those involving self-correcting reasoning. Our theoretical analysis shows that step-wise aggregation compounds errors as reasoning length grows, and our empirical observations confirm this effect. These findings challenge the prevailing assumption that fine-grained supervision is always better and support generative outcome verification for multi-domain deployment. We publicly release our code, datasets, and checkpoints at https://github.com/db-Lee/Multi-RM{\small\texttt{https://github.com/db-Lee/Multi-RM}} to facilitate future research in multi-domain settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00492</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 04:21:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ACON: Optimizing Context Compression for Long-horizon LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00615</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.00615.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minki Kang, Wei-Ning Chen, Dongge Han, Huseyin A. Inan, Lukas Wutschitz, Yanzhi Chen, Robert Sim, Saravan Rajmohan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly deployed as agents in dynamic, real-world environments, where success requires both reasoning and effective tool use. A central challenge for agentic tasks is the growing context length, as agents must accumulate long histories of actions and observations. This expansion raises costs and reduces efficiency in long-horizon tasks, yet prior work on context compression has mostly focused on single-step tasks or narrow applications. We introduce Agent Context Optimization (ACON), a unified framework that optimally compresses both environment observations and interaction histories into concise yet informative condensations. ACON leverages compression guideline optimization in natural language space: given paired trajectories where full context succeeds but compressed context fails, capable LLMs analyze the causes of failure, and the compression guideline is updated accordingly. Furthermore, we propose distilling the optimized LLM compressor into smaller models to reduce the overhead of the additional module. Experiments on AppWorld, OfficeBench, and Multi-objective QA show that ACON reduces memory usage by 26-54% (peak tokens) while largely preserving task performance, preserves over 95% of accuracy when distilled into smaller compressors, and enhances smaller LMs as long-horizon agents with up to 46% performance improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00615</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 07:43:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It Takes Two: Your GRPO Is Secretly DPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00977</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.00977.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yihong Wu, Liheng Ma, Lei Ding, Muzhi Li, Xinyu Wang, Kejia Chen, Zhan Su, Zhanguang Zhang, Chenyang Huang, Yingxue Zhang, Mark Coates, Jian-Yun Nie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) is a prominent reinforcement learning algorithm for post-training Large Language Models (LLMs). It is commonly believed that GRPO necessitates a large group size to ensure stable training via precise statistical estimation, which incurs substantial computational overhead. In this work, we challenge this assumption by reframing GRPO as a form of contrastive learning, which reveals a fundamental connection to Direct Preference Optimization (DPO). Motivated by DPO's empirical success, we investigate the minimal two-rollout case (2-GRPO), a configuration previously deemed infeasible. We provide a rigorous theoretical analysis to validate 2-GRPO and demonstrate empirically that it achieves performance on par with 16-GRPO, despite using only 1/8 of the rollouts and reducing training time by over 70%.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00977</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 14:52:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GEM: A Gym for Agentic LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01051</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01051.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zichen Liu, Anya Sims, Keyu Duan, Changyu Chen, Simon Yu, Xiangxin Zhou, Haotian Xu, Shaopan Xiong, Bo Liu, Chenmien Tan, Chuen Yang Beh, Weixun Wang, Hao Zhu, Weiyan Shi, Diyi Yang, Michael Shieh, Yee Whye Teh, Wee Sun Lee, Min Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 71&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The training paradigm for large language models (LLMs) is moving from static datasets to experience-based learning, where agents acquire skills via interacting with complex environments. To facilitate this transition we introduce GEM (General Experience Maker), an open-source environment simulator designed for the age of LLMs. Analogous to OpenAI-Gym for traditional reinforcement learning (RL), GEM provides a standardized framework for the environment-agent interface, including asynchronous vectorized execution for high throughput, and flexible wrappers for easy extensibility. GEM also features a diverse suite of environments, robust integrated tools, and single-file example scripts demonstrating using GEM with five popular RL training frameworks. Along with this, we also provide a set of baselines across 24 environments using REINFORCE with Return Batch Normalization (ReBN), which -- unlike GRPO -- is compatible with the full RL setting of dense per-turn rewards and offers better credit assignment. We further conduct apple-to-apple benchmarking of PPO, GRPO and REINFORCE in both single- and multi-turn settings using GEM to shed light on the algorithmic designs. Lastly, GEM also functions as a convenient evaluation toolkit besides a training environment. We hope this framework can help accelerate future agentic LLM research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01051</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 15:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ModernVBERT: Towards Smaller Visual Document Retrievers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01149</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01149.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Paul Teiletche, Quentin Macé, Max Conti, Antonio Loison, Gautier Viaud, Pierre Colombo, Manuel Faysse&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal embedding models are gaining prevalence, notably for document retrieval as efficient alternatives to text-only pipelines. These models are typically built by finetuning large vision-language decoders (VLMs) with contrastive losses on text-image pairs. In this work, we show that, while cost-efficient, this repurposing approach often bottlenecks retrieval performance. Through controlled experiments, we establish a principled recipe for improving visual document retrieval models. We notably measure the impact of attention masking, image resolution, modality alignment data regimes, and late interaction centered contrastive objectives which emerge as central performance factors. Building on these insights, we release ModernVBERT, a compact 250M-parameter vision-language encoder that outperforms models up to 10 times larger when finetuned on document retrieval tasks. Models and code are made available at https://huggingface.co/ModernVBERT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01149</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 17:41:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code2Video: A Code-centric Paradigm for Educational Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01174</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01174.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanzhe Chen, Kevin Qinghong Lin, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While recent generative models advance pixel-space video synthesis, they remain limited in producing professional educational videos, which demand disciplinary knowledge, precise visual structures, and coherent transitions, limiting their applicability in educational scenarios. Intuitively, such requirements are better addressed through the manipulation of a renderable environment, which can be explicitly controlled via logical commands (e.g., code). In this work, we propose Code2Video, a code-centric agent framework for generating educational videos via executable Python code. The framework comprises three collaborative agents: (i) Planner, which structures lecture content into temporally coherent flows and prepares corresponding visual assets; (ii) Coder, which converts structured instructions into executable Python codes while incorporating scope-guided auto-fix to enhance efficiency; and (iii) Critic, which leverages vision-language models (VLM) with visual anchor prompts to refine spatial layout and ensure clarity. To support systematic evaluation, we build MMMC, a benchmark of professionally produced, discipline-specific educational videos. We evaluate MMMC across diverse dimensions, including VLM-as-a-Judge aesthetic scores, code efficiency, and particularly, TeachQuiz, a novel end-to-end metric that quantifies how well a VLM, after unlearning, can recover knowledge by watching the generated videos. Our results demonstrate the potential of Code2Video as a scalable, interpretable, and controllable approach, achieving 40% improvement over direct code generation and producing videos comparable to human-crafted tutorials. The code and datasets are available at https://github.com/showlab/Code2Video.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01174</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 17:56:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TOUCAN: Synthesizing 1.5M Tool-Agentic Data from Real-World MCP   Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01179</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01179.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhangchen Xu, Adriana Meza Soria, Shawn Tan, Anurag Roy, Ashish Sunil Agrawal, Radha Poovendran, Rameswar Panda&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Model (LLM) agents are rapidly emerging as powerful systems for automating tasks across domains. Yet progress in the open-source community is constrained by the lack of high quality permissively licensed tool-agentic training data. Existing datasets are often limited in diversity, realism, and complexity, particularly regarding multi-tool and multi-turn interactions. To address this gap, we introduce Toucan, the largest publicly available tool-agentic dataset to date, containing 1.5 million trajectories synthesized from nearly 500 real-world Model Context Protocols (MCPs). Unlike prior work, Toucan leverages authentic MCP environments to generate diverse, realistic, and challenging tasks with trajectories involving real tool execution. Our pipeline first produces a broad spectrum of tool-use queries using five distinct models, applies model-based quality filtering, and then generates agentic trajectories with three teacher models using two agentic frameworks. Rigorous rule-based and model-based validation ensures high-quality outputs. We also introduce three extension mechanisms to further diversify tasks and simulate multi-turn conversations. Models fine-tuned on Toucan outperform larger closed-source counterparts on the BFCL V3 benchmark and push the Pareto frontier forward on MCP-Universe Bench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01179</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 17:58:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BroRL: Scaling Reinforcement Learning via Broadened Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01180</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01180.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jian Hu, Mingjie Liu, Ximing Lu, Fang Wu, Zaid Harchaoui, Shizhe Diao, Yejin Choi, Pavlo Molchanov, Jun Yang, Jan Kautz, Yi Dong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as a key ingredient for unlocking complex reasoning capabilities in large language models. Recent work ProRL has shown promise in scaling RL by increasing the number of training steps. However, performance plateaus after thousands of steps, with clear diminishing returns from allocating more computation to additional training. In this work, we investigate a complementary paradigm for scaling RL, BroR-Lincreasing the number of rollouts per example to hundreds to exhaustively Broaden exploration, which yields continuous performance gains beyond the saturation point observed in ProRL when scaling the number of training steps. Our approach is motivated by a mass balance equation analysis allowing us to characterize the rate of change in probability mass for correct and incorrect tokens during the reinforcement process. We show that under a one-step RL assumption, sampled rollout tokens always contribute to correct-mass expansion, while unsampled tokens outside rollouts may lead to gains or losses depending on their distribution and the net reward balance. Importantly, as the number of rollouts per example N increases, the effect of unsampled terms diminishes, ensuring overall correct-mass expansion. To validate our theoretical analysis, we conduct simulations under more relaxed conditions and find that a sufficiently large rollout size N-corresponding to ample exploration-guarantees an increase in the probability mass of all correct tokens. Empirically, BroRL revives models saturated after 3K ProRL training steps and demonstrates robust, continuous improvement, achieving state-of-the-art results for the 1.5B model across diverse benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01180</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VOGUE: Guiding Exploration with Visual Uncertainty Improves Multimodal   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01444</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01444.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui Liu, Dian Yu, Tong Zheng, Runpeng Dai, Zongxia Li, Wenhao Yu, Zhenwen Liang, Linfeng Song, Haitao Mi, Pratap Tokekar, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) improves reasoning in large language models (LLMs) but struggles with exploration, an issue that still persists for multimodal LLMs (MLLMs). Current methods treat the visual input as a fixed, deterministic condition, overlooking a critical source of ambiguity and struggling to build policies robust to plausible visual variations. We introduce VOGUE (Visual Uncertainty Guided Exploration), a novel method that shifts exploration from the output (text) to the input (visual) space. By treating the image as a stochastic context, VOGUE quantifies the policy's sensitivity to visual perturbations using the symmetric KL divergence between a "raw" and "noisy" branch, creating a direct signal for uncertainty-aware exploration. This signal shapes the learning objective via an uncertainty-proportional bonus, which, combined with a token-entropy bonus and an annealed sampling schedule, effectively balances exploration and exploitation. Implemented within GRPO on two model scales (Qwen2.5-VL-3B/7B), VOGUE boosts pass@1 accuracy by an average of 2.6% on three visual math benchmarks and 3.7% on three general-domain reasoning benchmarks, while simultaneously increasing pass@4 performance and mitigating the exploration decay commonly observed in RL fine-tuning. Our work shows that grounding exploration in the inherent uncertainty of visual inputs is an effective strategy for improving multimodal reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01444</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 20:32:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CLUE: Non-parametric Verification from Experience via Hidden-State   Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01591</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.01591.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenwen Liang, Ruosen Li, Yujun Zhou, Linfeng Song, Dian Yu, Xinya Du, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Assessing the quality of Large Language Model (LLM) outputs presents a critical challenge. Previous methods either rely on text-level information (e.g., reward models, majority voting), which can overfit to superficial cues, or on calibrated confidence from token probabilities, which would fail on less-calibrated models. Yet both of these signals are, in fact, partial projections of a richer source of information: the model's internal hidden states. Early layers, closer to token embeddings, preserve semantic and lexical features that underpin text-based judgments, while later layers increasingly align with output logits, embedding confidence-related information. This paper explores hidden states directly as a unified foundation for verification. We show that the correctness of a solution is encoded as a geometrically separable signature within the trajectory of hidden activations. To validate this, we present Clue (Clustering and Experience-based Verification), a deliberately minimalist, non-parametric verifier. With no trainable parameters, CLUE only summarizes each reasoning trace by an hidden state delta and classifies correctness via nearest-centroid distance to ``success'' and ``failure'' clusters formed from past experience. The simplicity of this method highlights the strength of the underlying signal. Empirically, CLUE consistently outperforms LLM-as-a-judge baselines and matches or exceeds modern confidence-based methods in reranking candidates, improving both top-1 and majority-vote accuracy across AIME 24/25 and GPQA. As a highlight, on AIME 24 with a 1.5B model, CLUE boosts accuracy from 56.7% (majority@64) to 70.0% (top-maj@16).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01591</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 02:14:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Reason for Hallucination Span Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02173</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02173.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hsuan Su, Ting-Yao Hu, Hema Swetha Koppula, Kundan Krishna, Hadi Pouransari, Cheng-Yu Hsieh, Cem Koc, Joseph Yitan Cheng, Oncel Tuzel, Raviteja Vemulapalli&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) often generate hallucinations -- unsupported content that undermines reliability. While most prior works frame hallucination detection as a binary task, many real-world applications require identifying hallucinated spans, which is a multi-step decision making process. This naturally raises the question of whether explicit reasoning can help the complex task of detecting hallucination spans. To answer this question, we first evaluate pretrained models with and without Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning, and show that CoT reasoning has the potential to generate at least one correct answer when sampled multiple times. Motivated by this, we propose RL4HS, a reinforcement learning framework that incentivizes reasoning with a span-level reward function. RL4HS builds on Group Relative Policy Optimization and introduces Class-Aware Policy Optimization to mitigate reward imbalance issue. Experiments on the RAGTruth benchmark (summarization, question answering, data-to-text) show that RL4HS surpasses pretrained reasoning models and supervised fine-tuning, demonstrating the necessity of reinforcement learning with span-level rewards for detecting hallucination spans.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02173</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 16:24:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Rigorous Benchmark with Multidimensional Evaluation for Deep Research   Agents: From Answers to Reports</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02190</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02190.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Yao, Yixu Wang, Yuxuan Zhang, Yi Lu, Tianle Gu, Lingyu Li, Dingyi Zhao, Keming Wu, Haozhe Wang, Ping Nie, Yan Teng, Yingchun Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Artificial intelligence is undergoing the paradigm shift from closed language models to interconnected agent systems capable of external perception and information integration. As a representative embodiment, Deep Research Agents (DRAs) systematically exhibit the capabilities for task decomposition, cross-source retrieval, multi-stage reasoning, and structured output, which markedly enhance performance on complex and open-ended tasks. However, existing benchmarks remain deficient in evaluation dimensions, response formatting, and scoring mechanisms, limiting their capacity to assess such systems effectively. This paper introduces a rigorous benchmark and a multidimensional evaluation framework tailored to DRAs and report-style responses. The benchmark comprises 214 expert-curated challenging queries distributed across 10 broad thematic domains, each accompanied by manually constructed reference bundles to support composite evaluation. The framework enables comprehensive evaluation of long-form reports generated by DRAs, incorporating integrated scoring metrics for semantic quality, topical focus, and retrieval trustworthiness. Extensive experimentation confirms the superior performance of mainstream DRAs over web-search-tool-augmented reasoning models, yet reveals considerable scope for further improvement. This study provides a robust foundation for capability assessment, architectural refinement, and paradigm advancement in DRA systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02190</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 16:40:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StockBench: Can LLM Agents Trade Stocks Profitably In Real-world   Markets?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02209</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02209.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanxu Chen, Zijun Yao, Yantao Liu, Jin Ye, Jianing Yu, Lei Hou, Juanzi Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have recently demonstrated strong capabilities as autonomous agents, showing promise in reasoning, tool use, and sequential decision-making. While prior benchmarks have evaluated LLM agents in domains such as software engineering and scientific discovery, the finance domain remains underexplored, despite its direct relevance to economic value and high-stakes decision-making. Existing financial benchmarks primarily test static knowledge through question answering, but they fall short of capturing the dynamic and iterative nature of trading. To address this gap, we introduce StockBench, a contamination-free benchmark designed to evaluate LLM agents in realistic, multi-month stock trading environments. Agents receive daily market signals -- including prices, fundamentals, and news -- and must make sequential buy, sell, or hold decisions. Performance is assessed using financial metrics such as cumulative return, maximum drawdown, and the Sortino ratio. Our evaluation of state-of-the-art proprietary (e.g., GPT-5, Claude-4) and open-weight (e.g., Qwen3, Kimi-K2, GLM-4.5) models shows that while most LLM agents struggle to outperform the simple buy-and-hold baseline, several models demonstrate the potential to deliver higher returns and manage risk more effectively. These findings highlight both the challenges and opportunities in developing LLM-powered financial agents, showing that excelling at static financial knowledge tasks does not necessarily translate into successful trading strategies. We release StockBench as an open-source resource to support reproducibility and advance future research in this domain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02209</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 16:54:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RewardMap: Tackling Sparse Rewards in Fine-grained Visual Reasoning via   Multi-Stage Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02240</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02240.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sicheng Feng, Kaiwen Tuo, Song Wang, Lingdong Kong, Jianke Zhu, Huan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-grained visual reasoning remains a core challenge for multimodal large language models (MLLMs). The recently introduced ReasonMap highlights this gap by showing that even advanced MLLMs struggle with spatial reasoning in structured and information-rich settings such as transit maps, a task of clear practical and scientific importance. However, standard reinforcement learning (RL) on such tasks is impeded by sparse rewards and unstable optimization. To address this, we first construct ReasonMap-Plus, an extended dataset that introduces dense reward signals through Visual Question Answering (VQA) tasks, enabling effective cold-start training of fine-grained visual understanding skills. Next, we propose RewardMap, a multi-stage RL framework designed to improve both visual understanding and reasoning capabilities of MLLMs. RewardMap incorporates two key designs. First, we introduce a difficulty-aware reward design that incorporates detail rewards, directly tackling the sparse rewards while providing richer supervision. Second, we propose a multi-stage RL scheme that bootstraps training from simple perception to complex reasoning tasks, offering a more effective cold-start strategy than conventional Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT). Experiments on ReasonMap and ReasonMap-Plus demonstrate that each component of RewardMap contributes to consistent performance gains, while their combination yields the best results. Moreover, models trained with RewardMap achieve an average improvement of 3.47% across 6 benchmarks spanning spatial reasoning, fine-grained visual reasoning, and general tasks beyond transit maps, underscoring enhanced visual understanding and reasoning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02240</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 17:29:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ExGRPO: Learning to Reason from Experience</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02245</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02245.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runzhe Zhan, Yafu Li, Zhi Wang, Xiaoye Qu, Dongrui Liu, Jing Shao, Derek F. Wong, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning from verifiable rewards (RLVR) is an emerging paradigm for improving the reasoning ability of large language models. However, standard on-policy training discards rollout experiences after a single update, leading to computational inefficiency and instability. While prior work on RL has highlighted the benefits of reusing past experience, the role of experience characteristics in shaping learning dynamics of large reasoning models remains underexplored. In this paper, we are the first to investigate what makes a reasoning experience valuable and identify rollout correctness and entropy as effective indicators of experience value. Based on these insights, we propose ExGRPO (Experiential Group Relative Policy Optimization), a framework that organizes and prioritizes valuable experiences, and employs a mixed-policy objective to balance exploration with experience exploitation. Experiments on five backbone models (1.5B-8B parameters) show that ExGRPO consistently improves reasoning performance on mathematical/general benchmarks, with an average gain of +3.5/7.6 points over on-policy RLVR. Moreover, ExGRPO stabilizes training on both stronger and weaker models where on-policy methods fail. These results highlight principled experience management as a key ingredient for efficient and scalable RLVR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02245</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 17:31:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Scaling Agents for Computer Use</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02250</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02250.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gonzalo Gonzalez-Pumariega, Vincent Tu, Chih-Lun Lee, Jiachen Yang, Ang Li, Xin Eric Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Computer-use agents (CUAs) hold promise for automating everyday digital tasks, but their unreliability and high variance hinder their application to long-horizon, complex tasks. We introduce Behavior Best-of-N (bBoN), a method that scales over agents by generating multiple rollouts and selecting among them using behavior narratives that describe the agents' rollouts. It enables both wide exploration and principled trajectory selection, substantially improving robustness and success rates. On OSWorld, our bBoN scaling method establishes a new state of the art (SoTA) at 69.9%, significantly outperforming prior methods and approaching human-level performance at 72%, with comprehensive ablations validating key design choices. We further demonstrate strong generalization results to different operating systems on WindowsAgentArena and AndroidWorld. Crucially, our results highlight the unreasonable effectiveness of scaling CUAs, when you do it right: effective scaling requires structured trajectory understanding and selection, and bBoN provides a practical framework to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02250</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 17:37:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Forcing++: Towards Minute-Scale High-Quality Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02283</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02283.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Justin Cui, Jie Wu, Ming Li, Tao Yang, Xiaojie Li, Rui Wang, Andrew Bai, Yuanhao Ban, Cho-Jui Hsieh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion models have revolutionized image and video generation, achieving unprecedented visual quality. However, their reliance on transformer architectures incurs prohibitively high computational costs, particularly when extending generation to long videos. Recent work has explored autoregressive formulations for long video generation, typically by distilling from short-horizon bidirectional teachers. Nevertheless, given that teacher models cannot synthesize long videos, the extrapolation of student models beyond their training horizon often leads to pronounced quality degradation, arising from the compounding of errors within the continuous latent space. In this paper, we propose a simple yet effective approach to mitigate quality degradation in long-horizon video generation without requiring supervision from long-video teachers or retraining on long video datasets. Our approach centers on exploiting the rich knowledge of teacher models to provide guidance for the student model through sampled segments drawn from self-generated long videos. Our method maintains temporal consistency while scaling video length by up to 20x beyond teacher's capability, avoiding common issues such as over-exposure and error-accumulation without recomputing overlapping frames like previous methods. When scaling up the computation, our method shows the capability of generating videos up to 4 minutes and 15 seconds, equivalent to 99.9% of the maximum span supported by our base model's position embedding and more than 50x longer than that of our baseline model. Experiments on standard benchmarks and our proposed improved benchmark demonstrate that our approach substantially outperforms baseline methods in both fidelity and consistency. Our long-horizon videos demo can be found at https://self-forcing-plus-plus.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02283</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 17:55:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tree-based Dialogue Reinforced Policy Optimization for Red-Teaming   Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02286</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02286.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruohao Guo, Afshin Oroojlooy, Roshan Sridhar, Miguel Ballesteros, Alan Ritter, Dan Roth&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite recent rapid progress in AI safety, current large language models remain vulnerable to adversarial attacks in multi-turn interaction settings, where attackers strategically adapt their prompts across conversation turns and pose a more critical yet realistic challenge. Existing approaches that discover safety vulnerabilities either rely on manual red-teaming with human experts or employ automated methods using pre-defined templates and human-curated attack data, with most focusing on single-turn attacks. However, these methods did not explore the vast space of possible multi-turn attacks, failing to consider novel attack trajectories that emerge from complex dialogue dynamics and strategic conversation planning. This gap is particularly critical given recent findings that LLMs exhibit significantly higher vulnerability to multi-turn attacks compared to single-turn attacks. We propose DialTree-RPO, an on-policy reinforcement learning framework integrated with tree search that autonomously discovers diverse multi-turn attack strategies by treating the dialogue as a sequential decision-making problem, enabling systematic exploration without manually curated data. Through extensive experiments, our approach not only achieves more than 25.9% higher ASR across 10 target models compared to previous state-of-the-art approaches, but also effectively uncovers new attack strategies by learning optimal dialogue policies that maximize attack success across multiple turns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02286</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 17:57:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F2LLM Technical Report: Matching SOTA Embedding Performance with 6   Million Open-Source Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02294</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02294.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyin Zhang, Zihan Liao, Hang Yu, Peng Di, Rui Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce F2LLM - Foundation to Feature Large Language Models, a suite of state-of-the-art embedding models in three sizes: 0.6B, 1.7B, and 4B. Unlike previous top-ranking embedding models that require massive contrastive pretraining, sophisticated training pipelines, and costly synthetic training data, F2LLM is directly finetuned from foundation models on 6 million query-document-negative tuples curated from open-source, non-synthetic datasets, striking a strong balance between training cost, model size, and embedding performance. On the MTEB English leaderboard, F2LLM-4B ranks 2nd among models with approximately 4B parameters and 7th overall, while F2LLM-1.7B ranks 1st among models in the 1B-2B size range. To facilitate future research in the field, we release the models, training dataset, and code, positioning F2LLM as a strong, reproducible, and budget-friendly baseline for future works.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02294</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 17:58:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Training: Feedback-Driven Neural Network Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02297</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02297.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wentao Zhang, Yang Young Lu, Yuntian Deng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional neural network training typically follows fixed, predefined optimization recipes, lacking the flexibility to dynamically respond to instabilities or emerging training issues. In this paper, we introduce Interactive Training, an open-source framework that enables real-time, feedback-driven intervention during neural network training by human experts or automated AI agents. At its core, Interactive Training uses a control server to mediate communication between users or agents and the ongoing training process, allowing users to dynamically adjust optimizer hyperparameters, training data, and model checkpoints. Through three case studies, we demonstrate that Interactive Training achieves superior training stability, reduced sensitivity to initial hyperparameters, and improved adaptability to evolving user needs, paving the way toward a future training paradigm where AI agents autonomously monitor training logs, proactively resolve instabilities, and optimize training dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02297</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 17:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StealthAttack: Robust 3D Gaussian Splatting Poisoning via Density-Guided   Illusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02314</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.02314.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bo-Hsu Ke, You-Zhe Xie, Yu-Lun Liu, Wei-Chen Chiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D scene representation methods like Neural Radiance Fields (NeRF) and 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) have significantly advanced novel view synthesis. As these methods become prevalent, addressing their vulnerabilities becomes critical. We analyze 3DGS robustness against image-level poisoning attacks and propose a novel density-guided poisoning method. Our method strategically injects Gaussian points into low-density regions identified via Kernel Density Estimation (KDE), embedding viewpoint-dependent illusory objects clearly visible from poisoned views while minimally affecting innocent views. Additionally, we introduce an adaptive noise strategy to disrupt multi-view consistency, further enhancing attack effectiveness. We propose a KDE-based evaluation protocol to assess attack difficulty systematically, enabling objective benchmarking for future research. Extensive experiments demonstrate our method's superior performance compared to state-of-the-art techniques. Project page: https://hentci.github.io/stealthattack/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02314</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
