<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:11:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>MedReseacher-R1: Expert-Level Medical Deep Researcher via A   Knowledge-Informed Trajectory Synthesis Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14880</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14880.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ailing Yu, Lan Yao, Jingnan Liu, Zhe Chen, Jiajun Yin, Yuan Wang, Xinhao Liao, Zhiling Ye, Ji Li, Yun Yue, Hansong Xiao, Hualei Zhou, Chunxiao Guo, Peng Wei, Jinjie Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent developments in Large Language Model (LLM)-based agents have shown impressive capabilities spanning multiple domains, exemplified by deep research systems that demonstrate superior performance on complex information-seeking and synthesis tasks. While general-purpose deep research agents have shown impressive capabilities, they struggle significantly with medical domain challenges, as evidenced by leading proprietary systems achieving limited accuracy on complex medical benchmarks. The key limitations are: (1) the model lacks sufficient dense medical knowledge for clinical reasoning, and (2) the framework is constrained by the absence of specialized retrieval tools tailored for medical contexts.We present a medical deep research agent that addresses these challenges through two core innovations. First, we develop a novel data synthesis framework using medical knowledge graphs, extracting the longest chains from subgraphs around rare medical entities to generate complex multi-hop question-answer pairs. Second, we integrate a custom-built private medical retrieval engine alongside general-purpose tools, enabling accurate medical information synthesis. Our approach generates 2100+ diverse trajectories across 12 medical specialties, each averaging 4.2 tool interactions.Through a two-stage training paradigm combining supervised fine-tuning and online reinforcement learning with composite rewards, our MedResearcher-R1-32B model demonstrates exceptional performance, establishing new state-of-the-art results on medical benchmarks while maintaining competitive performance on general deep research tasks. Our work demonstrates that strategic domain-specific innovations in architecture, tool design, and training data construction can enable smaller open-source models to outperform much larger proprietary systems in specialized domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14880</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 17:51:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAT: Causal Attention Tuning For Injecting Fine-grained Causal Knowledge   into Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01535</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.01535.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kairong Han, Wenshuo Zhao, Ziyu Zhao, JunJian Ye, Lujia Pan, Kun Kuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have achieved remarkable success across various domains. However, a fundamental question remains: Can LLMs effectively utilize causal knowledge for prediction and generation? Through empirical studies, we find that LLMs trained directly on large-scale data often capture spurious correlations rather than true causal relationships, leading to suboptimal performance, especially in out-of-distribution (OOD) scenarios. To address this challenge, we propose Causal Attention Tuning (CAT), a novel approach that injects fine-grained causal knowledge into the attention mechanism. We propose an automated pipeline that leverages human priors to automatically generate token-level causal signals and introduce the Re-Attention mechanism to guide training, helping the model focus on causal structures while mitigating noise and biases in attention scores. Experimental results on our proposed Spurious Token Game (STG) benchmark and multiple downstream tasks demonstrate that our approach effectively leverages causal knowledge for prediction and remains robust in OOD scenarios. Implementation details can be found at https://github.com/Kairong-Han/CAT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01535</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 15:13:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Context Engineering for Trustworthiness: Rescorla Wagner Steering Under   Mixed and Inappropriate Contexts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04500</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04500.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rushi Wang, Jiateng Liu, Cheng Qian, Yifan Shen, Yanzhou Pan, Zhaozhuo Xu, Ahmed Abbasi, Heng Ji, Denghui Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Incorporating external context can significantly enhance the response quality of Large Language Models (LLMs). However, real-world contexts often mix relevant information with disproportionate inappropriate content, posing reliability risks. How do LLMs process and prioritize mixed context? To study this, we introduce the Poisoned Context Testbed, pairing queries with real-world contexts containing relevant and inappropriate content. Inspired by associative learning in animals, we adapt the Rescorla-Wagner (RW) model from neuroscience to quantify how competing contextual signals influence LLM outputs. Our adapted model reveals a consistent behavioral pattern: LLMs exhibit a strong tendency to incorporate information that is less prevalent in the context. This susceptibility is harmful in real-world settings, where small amounts of inappropriate content can substantially degrade response quality. Empirical evaluations on our testbed further confirm this vulnerability. To tackle this, we introduce RW-Steering, a two-stage finetuning-based approach that enables the model to internally identify and ignore inappropriate signals. Unlike prior methods that rely on extensive supervision across diverse context mixtures, RW-Steering generalizes robustly across varying proportions of inappropriate content. Experiments show that our best fine-tuned model improves response quality by 39.8% and reverses the undesirable behavior curve, establishing RW-Steering as a robust, generalizable context engineering solution for improving LLM safety in real-world use.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04500</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:40:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FLOWER: Democratizing Generalist Robot Policies with Efficient   Vision-Language-Action Flow Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04996</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04996.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Moritz Reuss, Hongyi Zhou, Marcel Rühle, Ömer Erdinç Yağmurlu, Fabian Otto, Rudolf Lioutikov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Developing efficient Vision-Language-Action (VLA) policies is crucial for practical robotics deployment, yet current approaches face prohibitive computational costs and resource requirements. Existing diffusion-based VLA policies require multi-billion-parameter models and massive datasets to achieve strong performance. We tackle this efficiency challenge with two contributions: intermediate-modality fusion, which reallocates capacity to the diffusion head by pruning up to 50% of LLM layers, and action-specific Global-AdaLN conditioning, which cuts parameters by 20% through modular adaptation. We integrate these advances into a novel 950 M-parameter VLA called FLOWER. Pretrained in just 200 H100 GPU hours, FLOWER delivers competitive performance with bigger VLAs across 190 tasks spanning ten simulation and real-world benchmarks and demonstrates robustness across diverse robotic embodiments. In addition, FLOWER achieves a new SoTA of 4.53 on the CALVIN ABC benchmark. Demos, code and pretrained weights are available at https://intuitive-robots.github.io/flower_vla/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04996</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 10:43:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Reasoning for Science: Technical Report and 1st Place   Solution to the ICML 2025 SeePhys Challenge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06079</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.06079.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Liang, Ruitao Wu, Bohan Zeng, Junbo Niu, Wentao Zhang, Bin Dong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal reasoning remains a fundamental challenge in artificial intelligence. Despite substantial advances in text-based reasoning, even state-of-the-art models such as GPT-o3 struggle to maintain strong performance in multimodal scenarios. To address this gap, we introduce a caption-assisted reasoning framework that effectively bridges visual and textual modalities. Our approach achieved 1st place in the ICML 2025 AI for Math Workshop \&amp; Challenge 2: SeePhys, highlighting its effectiveness and robustness. Furthermore, we validate its generalization on the MathVerse benchmark for geometric reasoning, demonstrating the versatility of our method. Our code is publicly available at https://github.com/OpenDCAI/SciReasoner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06079</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 14:47:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agentic Software Engineering: Foundational Pillars and a Research   Roadmap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06216</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.06216.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ahmed E. Hassan, Hao Li, Dayi Lin, Bram Adams, Tse-Hsun Chen, Yutaro Kashiwa, Dong Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic Software Engineering (SE 3.0) represents a new era where intelligent agents are tasked not with simple code generation, but with achieving complex, goal-oriented SE objectives. To harness these new capabilities while ensuring trustworthiness, we must recognize a fundamental duality within the SE field in the Agentic SE era, comprising two symbiotic modalities: SE for Humans and SE for Agents. This duality demands a radical reimagining of the foundational pillars of SE (actors, processes, tools, and artifacts) which manifest differently across each modality. We propose two purpose-built workbenches to support this vision. The Agent Command Environment (ACE) serves as a command center where humans orchestrate and mentor agent teams, handling outputs such as Merge-Readiness Packs (MRPs) and Consultation Request Packs (CRPs). The Agent Execution Environment (AEE) is a digital workspace where agents perform tasks while invoking human expertise when facing ambiguity or complex trade-offs. This bi-directional partnership, which supports agent-initiated human callbacks and handovers, gives rise to new, structured engineering activities (i.e., processes) that redefine human-AI collaboration, elevating the practice from agentic coding to true agentic software engineering. This paper presents the Structured Agentic Software Engineering (SASE) vision, outlining several of the foundational pillars for the future of SE. The paper culminates in a research roadmap that identifies a few key challenges and opportunities while briefly discussing the resulting impact of this future on SE education. Our goal is not to offer a definitive solution, but to provide a conceptual scaffold with structured vocabulary to catalyze a community-wide dialogue, pushing the SE community to think beyond its classic, human-centric tenets toward a disciplined, scalable, and trustworthy agentic future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06216</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 21:40:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HANRAG: Heuristic Accurate Noise-resistant Retrieval-Augmented   Generation for Multi-hop Question Answering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09713</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09713.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Duolin Sun, Dan Yang, Yue Shen, Yihan Jiao, Zhehao Tan, Jie Feng, Lianzhen Zhong, Jian Wang, Peng Wei, Jinjie Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) approach enhances question-answering systems and dialogue generation tasks by integrating information retrieval (IR) technologies with large language models (LLMs). This strategy, which retrieves information from external knowledge bases to bolster the response capabilities of generative models, has achieved certain successes. However, current RAG methods still face numerous challenges when dealing with multi-hop queries. For instance, some approaches overly rely on iterative retrieval, wasting too many retrieval steps on compound queries. Additionally, using the original complex query for retrieval may fail to capture content relevant to specific sub-queries, resulting in noisy retrieved content. If the noise is not managed, it can lead to the problem of noise accumulation. To address these issues, we introduce HANRAG, a novel heuristic-based framework designed to efficiently tackle problems of varying complexity. Driven by a powerful revelator, HANRAG routes queries, decomposes them into sub-queries, and filters noise from retrieved documents. This enhances the system's adaptability and noise resistance, making it highly capable of handling diverse queries. We compare the proposed framework against other leading industry methods across various benchmarks. The results demonstrate that our framework obtains superior performance in both single-hop and multi-hop question-answering tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09713</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 06:22:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FSG-Net: Frequency-Spatial Synergistic Gated Network for High-Resolution   Remote Sensing Change Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06482</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.06482.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongxiang Xie, Shuangxi Miao, Yuhan Jiang, Zhewei Zhang, Jing Yao, Xuecao Li, Jianxi Huang, Pedram Ghamisi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Change detection from high-resolution remote sensing images lies as a cornerstone of Earth observation applications, yet its efficacy is often compromised by two critical challenges. First, false alarms are prevalent as models misinterpret radiometric variations from temporal shifts (e.g., illumination, season) as genuine changes. Second, a non-negligible semantic gap between deep abstract features and shallow detail-rich features tends to obstruct their effective fusion, culminating in poorly delineated boundaries. To step further in addressing these issues, we propose the Frequency-Spatial Synergistic Gated Network (FSG-Net), a novel paradigm that aims to systematically disentangle semantic changes from nuisance variations. Specifically, FSG-Net first operates in the frequency domain, where a Discrepancy-Aware Wavelet Interaction Module (DAWIM) adaptively mitigates pseudo-changes by discerningly processing different frequency components. Subsequently, the refined features are enhanced in the spatial domain by a Synergistic Temporal-Spatial Attention Module (STSAM), which amplifies the saliency of genuine change regions. To finally bridge the semantic gap, a Lightweight Gated Fusion Unit (LGFU) leverages high-level semantics to selectively gate and integrate crucial details from shallow layers. Comprehensive experiments on the CDD, GZ-CD, and LEVIR-CD benchmarks validate the superiority of FSG-Net, establishing a new state-of-the-art with F1-scores of 94.16%, 89.51%, and 91.27%, respectively. The code will be made available at https://github.com/zxXie-Air/FSG-Net after a possible publication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06482</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 09:46:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IntrEx: A Dataset for Modeling Engagement in Educational Conversations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06652</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.06652.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xingwei Tan, Mahathi Parvatham, Chiara Gambi, Gabriele Pergola&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Engagement and motivation are crucial for second-language acquisition, yet maintaining learner interest in educational conversations remains a challenge. While prior research has explored what makes educational texts interesting, still little is known about the linguistic features that drive engagement in conversations. To address this gap, we introduce IntrEx, the first large dataset annotated for interestingness and expected interestingness in teacher-student interactions. Built upon the Teacher-Student Chatroom Corpus (TSCC), IntrEx extends prior work by incorporating sequence-level annotations, allowing for the study of engagement beyond isolated turns to capture how interest evolves over extended dialogues. We employ a rigorous annotation process with over 100 second-language learners, using a comparison-based rating approach inspired by reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF) to improve agreement. We investigate whether large language models (LLMs) can predict human interestingness judgments. We find that LLMs (7B/8B parameters) fine-tuned on interestingness ratings outperform larger proprietary models like GPT-4o, demonstrating the potential for specialised datasets to model engagement in educational settings. Finally, we analyze how linguistic and cognitive factors, such as concreteness, comprehensibility (readability), and uptake, influence engagement in educational dialogues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06652</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 13:07:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongEmotion: Measuring Emotional Intelligence of Large Language Models   in Long-Context Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07403</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.07403.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weichu Liu, Jing Xiong, Yuxuan Hu, Zixuan Li, Minghuan Tan, Ningning Mao, Chenyang Zhao, Zhongwei Wan, Chaofan Tao, Wendong Xu, Hui Shen, Chengming Li, Lingpeng Kong, Ngai Wong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) make significant progress in Emotional Intelligence (EI) and long-context understanding. However, existing benchmarks tend to overlook certain aspects of EI in long-context scenarios, especially under realistic, practical settings where interactions are lengthy, diverse, and often noisy. To move towards such realistic settings, we present LongEmotion, a benchmark specifically designed for long-context EI tasks. It covers a diverse set of tasks, including Emotion Classification, Emotion Detection, Emotion QA, Emotion Conversation, Emotion Summary, and Emotion Expression. On average, the input length for these tasks reaches 8,777 tokens, with long-form generation required for Emotion Expression. To enhance performance under realistic constraints, we incorporate Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) and Collaborative Emotional Modeling (CoEM), and compare them with standard prompt-based methods. Unlike conventional approaches, our RAG method leverages both the conversation context and the large language model itself as retrieval sources, avoiding reliance on external knowledge bases. The CoEM method further improves performance by decomposing the task into five stages, integrating both retrieval augmentation and limited knowledge injection. Experimental results show that both RAG and CoEM consistently enhance EI-related performance across most long-context tasks, advancing LLMs toward more practical and real-world EI applications. Furthermore, we conducted a comparative case study experiment on the GPT series to demonstrate the differences among various models in terms of EI. Code is available on GitHub at https://github.com/LongEmotion/LongEmotion, and the project page can be found at https://longemotion.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07403</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 05:32:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VStyle: A Benchmark for Voice Style Adaptation with Spoken Instructions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09716</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09716.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jun Zhan, Mingyang Han, Yuxuan Xie, Chen Wang, Dong Zhang, Kexin Huang, Haoxiang Shi, DongXiao Wang, Tengtao Song, Qinyuan Cheng, Shimin Li, Jun Song, Xipeng Qiu, Bo Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spoken language models (SLMs) have emerged as a unified paradigm for speech understanding and generation, enabling natural human machine interaction. However, while most progress has focused on semantic accuracy and instruction following, the ability of SLMs to adapt their speaking style based on spoken instructions has received limited attention. We introduce Voice Style Adaptation (VSA), a new task that examines whether SLMs can modify their speaking style, such as timbre, prosody, or persona following natural language spoken commands. To study this task, we present VStyle, a bilingual (Chinese &amp; English) benchmark covering four categories of speech generation: acoustic attributes, natural language instruction, role play, and implicit empathy. We also introduce the Large Audio Language Model as a Judge (LALM as a Judge) framework, which progressively evaluates outputs along textual faithfulness, style adherence, and naturalness, ensuring reproducible and objective assessment. Experiments on commercial systems and open source SLMs demonstrate that current models face clear limitations in controllable style adaptation, highlighting both the novelty and challenge of this task. By releasing VStyle and its evaluation toolkit, we aim to provide the community with a foundation for advancing human centered spoken interaction. The dataset and code are publicly available at https://junzhan2000.github.io/VStyle.github.io/{project's homepage}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09716</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 14:28:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual-TableQA: Open-Domain Benchmark for Reasoning over Table Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07966</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.07966.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Boammani Aser Lompo, Marc Haraoui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual reasoning over structured data such as tables is a critical capability for modern vision-language models (VLMs), yet current benchmarks remain limited in scale, diversity, or reasoning depth, especially when it comes to rendered table images. Addressing this gap, we introduce Visual-TableQA, a large-scale, open-domain multimodal dataset specifically designed to evaluate and enhance visual reasoning over complex tabular data. Our generation pipeline is modular, scalable, and fully autonomous, involving multiple reasoning LLMs collaborating across distinct roles: generation, validation, and inspiration. Visual-TableQA comprises 2.5k richly structured LaTeX-rendered tables and 6k reasoning-intensive QA pairs, all produced at a cost of under USD 100. To promote diversity and creativity, our pipeline performs multi-model collaborative data generation via cross-model prompting ('inspiration') and LLM-jury filtering. Stronger models seed layouts and topics that weaker models elaborate, collectively distilling diverse reasoning patterns and visual structures into the dataset. Empirical results show that models fine-tuned on Visual-TableQA generalize robustly to external benchmarks, outperforming several proprietary models despite the dataset's synthetic nature. The full pipeline and resources are publicly available at https://github.com/AI-4-Everyone/Visual-TableQA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07966</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 17:52:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretable Physics Reasoning and Performance Taxonomy in   Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08270</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.08270.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pranav Pawar, Kavish Shah, Akshat Bhalani, Komal Kasat, Dev Mittal, Hadi Gala, Deepali Patil, Nikita Raichada, Monali Deshmukh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As Vision-Language Models (VLMs) grow in sophistication, their ability to perform reasoning is coming under increasing supervision. While they excel at many tasks, their grasp of fundamental scientific principles, such as physics, remains an underexplored frontier. To reflect the advancements in these capabilities, we introduce a novel and accessible framework designed to rigorously evaluate VLMs on their understanding of 2D physics. Our framework features a pragmatic scenario generator that creates a diverse testbed of over 400 problems across four core domains: Projectile Motion, Collision Dynamics, Mechanics, and Fluid Dynamics. Through comprehensive evaluation of four state-of-the-art VLMs, we demonstrate a strong correlation between model scale and reasoning ability, with our top-performing model, Qwen2.5-VL-7B, achieving an overall score of 0.815. We find that while models excel at formulaic problems, they struggle significantly with domains requiring abstract spatial reasoning. By designing this framework, we aim to democratize the study of scientific reasoning in VLMs and foster deeper insights into their capabilities and limitations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08270</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 04:15:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MCP-AgentBench: Evaluating Real-World Language Agent Performance with   MCP-Mediated Tools</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09734</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09734.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zikang Guo, Benfeng Xu, Chiwei Zhu, Wentao Hong, Xiaorui Wang, Zhendong Mao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Model Context Protocol (MCP) is rapidly emerging as a pivotal open standard, designed to enhance agent-tool integration and interoperability, and is positioned to unlock a new era of powerful, interconnected, and genuinely utilitarian agentic AI. However, despite MCP's growing adoption, existing benchmarks often fail to capture real-world agent performance within this new paradigm, leading to a distorted perception of their true operational value and an inability to reliably differentiate proficiencies. To bridge this critical evaluation gap, we introduce MCP-AgentBench -- a comprehensive benchmark specifically engineered to rigorously assess language agent capabilities in MCP-mediated tool interactions. Core contributions of MCP-AgentBench include: the establishment of a robust MCP testbed comprising 33 operational servers with 188 distinct tools; the development of a benchmark featuring 600 systematically designed queries distributed across 6 distinct categories of varying interaction complexity; and the introduction of MCP-Eval, a novel outcome-oriented evaluation methodology prioritizing real-world task success. Through extensive empirical evaluation of leading language agents, we provide foundational insights. MCP-AgentBench aims to equip the research community with a standardized and reliable framework to build, validate, and advance agents capable of fully leveraging MCP's transformative benefits, thereby accelerating progress toward truly capable and interoperable AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09734</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 14:08:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-Part: high fidelity and structure coherent shape decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08643</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.08643.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinhao Yan, Jiachen Xu, Yang Li, Changfeng Ma, Yunhan Yang, Chunshi Wang, Zibo Zhao, Zeqiang Lai, Yunfei Zhao, Zhuo Chen, Chunchao Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating 3D shapes at part level is pivotal for downstream applications such as mesh retopology, UV mapping, and 3D printing. However, existing part-based generation methods often lack sufficient controllability and suffer from poor semantically meaningful decomposition. To this end, we introduce X-Part, a controllable generative model designed to decompose a holistic 3D object into semantically meaningful and structurally coherent parts with high geometric fidelity. X-Part exploits the bounding box as prompts for the part generation and injects point-wise semantic features for meaningful decomposition. Furthermore, we design an editable pipeline for interactive part generation. Extensive experimental results show that X-Part achieves state-of-the-art performance in part-level shape generation. This work establishes a new paradigm for creating production-ready, editable, and structurally sound 3D assets. Codes will be released for public research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08643</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 14:37:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Model Hacking: Quantifying the Hidden Risks of Using LLMs   for Text Annotation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08825</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.08825.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Joachim Baumann, Paul Röttger, Aleksandra Urman, Albert Wendsjö, Flor Miriam Plaza-del-Arco, Johannes B. Gruber, Dirk Hovy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are rapidly transforming social science research by enabling the automation of labor-intensive tasks like data annotation and text analysis. However, LLM outputs vary significantly depending on the implementation choices made by researchers (e.g., model selection, prompting strategy, or temperature settings). Such variation can introduce systematic biases and random errors, which propagate to downstream analyses and cause Type I, Type II, Type S, or Type M errors. We call this LLM hacking.   We quantify the risk of LLM hacking by replicating 37 data annotation tasks from 21 published social science research studies with 18 different models. Analyzing 13 million LLM labels, we test 2,361 realistic hypotheses to measure how plausible researcher choices affect statistical conclusions. We find incorrect conclusions based on LLM-annotated data in approximately one in three hypotheses for state-of-the-art models, and in half the hypotheses for small language models. While our findings show that higher task performance and better general model capabilities reduce LLM hacking risk, even highly accurate models do not completely eliminate it. The risk of LLM hacking decreases as effect sizes increase, indicating the need for more rigorous verification of findings near significance thresholds. Our extensive analysis of LLM hacking mitigation techniques emphasizes the importance of human annotations in reducing false positive findings and improving model selection. Surprisingly, common regression estimator correction techniques are largely ineffective in reducing LLM hacking risk, as they heavily trade off Type I vs. Type II errors.   Beyond accidental errors, we find that intentional LLM hacking is unacceptably simple. With few LLMs and just a handful of prompt paraphrases, anything can be presented as statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08825</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 17:58:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Modeling with Probabilistic Structure Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09737</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09737.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Klemen Kotar, Wanhee Lee, Rahul Venkatesh, Honglin Chen, Daniel Bear, Jared Watrous, Simon Kim, Khai Loong Aw, Lilian Naing Chen, Stefan Stojanov, Kevin Feigelis, Imran Thobani, Alex Durango, Khaled Jedoui, Atlas Kazemian, Dan Yamins&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Probabilistic Structure Integration (PSI), a system for learning richly controllable and flexibly promptable world models from data. PSI consists of a three-step cycle. The first step, Probabilistic prediction, involves building a probabilistic graphical model Psi of the data, in the form of a random-access autoregressive sequence model. Psi supports a complete set of learned conditional distributions describing the dependence of any variables in the data on any other set of variables. In step 2, Structure extraction, we show how to extract underlying low-dimensional properties in the data, corresponding to a diverse set of meaningful "intermediate structures", in a zero-shot fashion via causal inference on Psi. Step 3, Integration, completes the cycle by converting these structures into new token types that are then continually mixed back into the training diet as conditioning signals and prediction targets. Each such cycle augments the capabilities of Psi, both allowing it to model the underlying data better, and creating new control handles -- akin to an LLM-like universal prompting language. We train an instance of Psi on 1.4 trillion tokens of internet video data; we use it to perform a variety of useful video prediction and understanding inferences; we extract state-of-the-art optical flow, self-supervised depth and object segmentation; and we use these structures to support a full cycle of predictive improvements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09737</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 18:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Multimodal LLMs See Materials Clearly? A Multimodal Benchmark on   Materials Characterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09307</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09307.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengzhao Lai, Youbin Zheng, Zhenyang Cai, Haonan Lyu, Jinpu Yang, Hongqing Liang, Yan Hu, Benyou Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Materials characterization is fundamental to acquiring materials information, revealing the processing-microstructure-property relationships that guide material design and optimization. While multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have recently shown promise in generative and predictive tasks within materials science, their capacity to understand real-world characterization imaging data remains underexplored. To bridge this gap, we present MatCha, the first benchmark for materials characterization image understanding, comprising 1,500 questions that demand expert-level domain expertise. MatCha encompasses four key stages of materials research comprising 21 distinct tasks, each designed to reflect authentic challenges faced by materials scientists. Our evaluation of state-of-the-art MLLMs on MatCha reveals a significant performance gap compared to human experts. These models exhibit degradation when addressing questions requiring higher-level expertise and sophisticated visual perception. Simple few-shot and chain-of-thought prompting struggle to alleviate these limitations. These findings highlight that existing MLLMs still exhibit limited adaptability to real-world materials characterization scenarios. We hope MatCha will facilitate future research in areas such as new material discovery and autonomous scientific agents. MatCha is available at https://github.com/FreedomIntelligence/MatCha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09307</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 09:50:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeMeVa at LeWiDi-2025: Modeling Perspectives with In-Context Learning   and Label Distribution Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09524</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09524.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daniil Ignatev, Nan Li, Hugh Mee Wong, Anh Dang, Shane Kaszefski Yaschuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This system paper presents the DeMeVa team's approaches to the third edition of the Learning with Disagreements shared task (LeWiDi 2025; Leonardelli et al., 2025). We explore two directions: in-context learning (ICL) with large language models, where we compare example sampling strategies; and label distribution learning (LDL) methods with RoBERTa (Liu et al., 2019b), where we evaluate several fine-tuning methods. Our contributions are twofold: (1) we show that ICL can effectively predict annotator-specific annotations (perspectivist annotations), and that aggregating these predictions into soft labels yields competitive performance; and (2) we argue that LDL methods are promising for soft label predictions and merit further exploration by the perspectivist community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09524</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 15:04:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Epistemic Humility in Multimodal Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09658</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09658.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bingkui Tong, Jiaer Xia, Sifeng Shang, Kaiyang Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Hallucinations in multimodal large language models (MLLMs) -- where the model generates content inconsistent with the input image -- pose significant risks in real-world applications, from misinformation in visual question answering to unsafe errors in decision-making. Existing benchmarks primarily test recognition accuracy, i.e., evaluating whether models can select the correct answer among distractors. This overlooks an equally critical capability for trustworthy AI: recognizing when none of the provided options are correct, a behavior reflecting epistemic humility. We present HumbleBench, a new hallucination benchmark designed to evaluate MLLMs' ability to reject plausible but incorrect answers across three hallucination types: object, relation, and attribute. Built from a panoptic scene graph dataset, we leverage fine-grained scene graph annotations to extract ground-truth entities and relations, and prompt GPT-4-Turbo to generate multiple-choice questions, followed by a rigorous manual filtering process. Each question includes a "None of the above" option, requiring models not only to recognize correct visual information but also to identify when no provided answer is valid. We evaluate a variety of state-of-the-art MLLMs -- including both general-purpose and specialized reasoning models -- on HumbleBench and share valuable findings and insights with the community. By incorporating explicit false-option rejection, HumbleBench fills a key gap in current evaluation suites, providing a more realistic measure of MLLM reliability in safety-critical settings. Our code and dataset are released publicly and can be accessed at https://github.com/maifoundations/HumbleBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09658</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 17:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locality in Image Diffusion Models Emerges from Data Statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09672</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09672.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Artem Lukoianov, Chenyang Yuan, Justin Solomon, Vincent Sitzmann&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Among generative models, diffusion models are uniquely intriguing due to the existence of a closed-form optimal minimizer of their training objective, often referred to as the optimal denoiser. However, diffusion using this optimal denoiser merely reproduces images in the training set and hence fails to capture the behavior of deep diffusion models. Recent work has attempted to characterize this gap between the optimal denoiser and deep diffusion models, proposing analytical, training-free models that can generate images that resemble those generated by a trained UNet. The best-performing method hypothesizes that shift equivariance and locality inductive biases of convolutional neural networks are the cause of the performance gap, hence incorporating these assumptions into its analytical model. In this work, we present evidence that the locality in deep diffusion models emerges as a statistical property of the image dataset, not due to the inductive bias of convolutional neural networks. Specifically, we demonstrate that an optimal parametric linear denoiser exhibits similar locality properties to the deep neural denoisers. We further show, both theoretically and experimentally, that this locality arises directly from the pixel correlations present in natural image datasets. Finally, we use these insights to craft an analytical denoiser that better matches scores predicted by a deep diffusion model than the prior expert-crafted alternative.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09672</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 17:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Illusion of Diminishing Returns: Measuring Long Horizon Execution in   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09677</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09677.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Akshit Sinha, Arvindh Arun, Shashwat Goel, Steffen Staab, Jonas Geiping&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Does continued scaling of large language models (LLMs) yield diminishing returns? Real-world value often stems from the length of task an agent can complete. We start this work by observing the simple but counterintuitive fact that marginal gains in single-step accuracy can compound into exponential improvements in the length of a task a model can successfully complete. Then, we argue that failures of LLMs when simple tasks are made longer arise from mistakes in execution, rather than an inability to reason. We propose isolating execution capability, by explicitly providing the knowledge and plan needed to solve a long-horizon task. We find that larger models can correctly execute significantly more turns even when small models have 100\% single-turn accuracy. We observe that the per-step accuracy of models degrades as the number of steps increases. This is not just due to long-context limitations -- curiously, we observe a self-conditioning effect -- models become more likely to make mistakes when the context contains their errors from prior turns. Self-conditioning does not reduce by just scaling the model size. In contrast, recent thinking models do not self-condition, and can also execute much longer tasks in a single turn. We conclude by benchmarking frontier thinking models on the length of task they can execute in a single turn. Overall, by focusing on the ability to execute, we hope to reconcile debates on how LLMs can solve complex reasoning problems yet fail at simple tasks when made longer, and highlight the massive benefits of scaling model size and sequential test-time compute for long-horizon tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09677</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 17:59:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LoFT: Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning for Long-tailed Semi-Supervised   Learning in Open-World Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09926</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09926.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiahao Chen, Zhiyuan Huang, Yurou Liu, Bing Su&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-tailed learning has garnered increasing attention due to its wide applicability in real-world scenarios. Among existing approaches, Long-Tailed Semi-Supervised Learning (LTSSL) has emerged as an effective solution by incorporating a large amount of unlabeled data into the imbalanced labeled dataset. However, most prior LTSSL methods are designed to train models from scratch, which often leads to issues such as overconfidence and low-quality pseudo-labels. To address these challenges, we extend LTSSL into the foundation model fine-tuning paradigm and propose a novel framework: LoFT (Long-tailed semi-supervised learning via parameter-efficient Fine-Tuning). We demonstrate that fine-tuned foundation models can generate more reliable pseudolabels, thereby benefiting imbalanced learning. Furthermore, we explore a more practical setting by investigating semi-supervised learning under open-world conditions, where the unlabeled data may include out-of-distribution (OOD) samples. To handle this problem, we propose LoFT-OW (LoFT under Open-World scenarios) to improve the discriminative ability. Experimental results on multiple benchmarks demonstrate that our method achieves superior performance compared to previous approaches, even when utilizing only 1\% of the unlabeled data compared with previous works.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09926</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 02:28:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CMHG: A Dataset and Benchmark for Headline Generation of Minority   Languages in China</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09990</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09990.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guixian Xu, Zeli Su, Ziyin Zhang, Jianing Liu, XU Han, Ting Zhang, Yushuang Dong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Minority languages in China, such as Tibetan, Uyghur, and Traditional Mongolian, face significant challenges due to their unique writing systems, which differ from international standards. This discrepancy has led to a severe lack of relevant corpora, particularly for supervised tasks like headline generation. To address this gap, we introduce a novel dataset, Chinese Minority Headline Generation (CMHG), which includes 100,000 entries for Tibetan, and 50,000 entries each for Uyghur and Mongolian, specifically curated for headline generation tasks. Additionally, we propose a high-quality test set annotated by native speakers, designed to serve as a benchmark for future research in this domain. We hope this dataset will become a valuable resource for advancing headline generation in Chinese minority languages and contribute to the development of related benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09990</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 06:18:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuantAgent: Price-Driven Multi-Agent LLMs for High-Frequency Trading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09995</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.09995.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fei Xiong, Xiang Zhang, Aosong Feng, Siqi Sun, Chenyu You&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive capabilities in financial reasoning and market understanding. Multi-agent LLM frameworks such as TradingAgent and FINMEM augment these models to long-horizon investment tasks, leveraging fundamental and sentiment-based inputs for strategic decision-making. However, such systems are ill-suited for the high-speed, precision-critical demands of High-Frequency Trading (HFT). HFT requires rapid, risk-aware decisions based on structured, short-horizon signals, including technical indicators, chart patterns, and trend-based features, distinct from the long-term semantic reasoning typical of traditional financial LLM applications. To this end, we introduce QuantAgent, the first multi-agent LLM framework explicitly designed for high-frequency algorithmic trading. The system decomposes trading into four specialized agents, Indicator, Pattern, Trend, and Risk, each equipped with domain-specific tools and structured reasoning capabilities to capture distinct aspects of market dynamics over short temporal windows. In zero-shot evaluations across ten financial instruments, including Bitcoin and Nasdaq futures, QuantAgent demonstrates superior performance in both predictive accuracy and cumulative return over 4-hour trading intervals, outperforming strong neural and rule-based baselines. Our findings suggest that combining structured financial priors with language-native reasoning unlocks new potential for traceable, real-time decision systems in high-frequency financial markets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09995</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 06:35:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Color Me Correctly: Bridging Perceptual Color Spaces and Text Embeddings   for Improved Diffusion Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10058</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10058.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sung-Lin Tsai, Bo-Lun Huang, Yu Ting Shen, Cheng Yu Yeo, Chiang Tseng, Bo-Kai Ruan, Wen-Sheng Lien, Hong-Han Shuai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Accurate color alignment in text-to-image (T2I) generation is critical for applications such as fashion, product visualization, and interior design, yet current diffusion models struggle with nuanced and compound color terms (e.g., Tiffany blue, lime green, hot pink), often producing images that are misaligned with human intent. Existing approaches rely on cross-attention manipulation, reference images, or fine-tuning but fail to systematically resolve ambiguous color descriptions. To precisely render colors under prompt ambiguity, we propose a training-free framework that enhances color fidelity by leveraging a large language model (LLM) to disambiguate color-related prompts and guiding color blending operations directly in the text embedding space. Our method first employs a large language model (LLM) to resolve ambiguous color terms in the text prompt, and then refines the text embeddings based on the spatial relationships of the resulting color terms in the CIELAB color space. Unlike prior methods, our approach improves color accuracy without requiring additional training or external reference images. Experimental results demonstrate that our framework improves color alignment without compromising image quality, bridging the gap between text semantics and visual generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10058</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 08:44:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Agent Economies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10147</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10147.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nenad Tomasev, Matija Franklin, Joel Z. Leibo, Julian Jacobs, William A. Cunningham, Iason Gabriel, Simon Osindero&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid adoption of autonomous AI agents is giving rise to a new economic layer where agents transact and coordinate at scales and speeds beyond direct human oversight. We propose the "sandbox economy" as a framework for analyzing this emergent system, characterizing it along two key dimensions: its origins (emergent vs. intentional) and its degree of separateness from the established human economy (permeable vs. impermeable). Our current trajectory points toward a spontaneous emergence of a vast and highly permeable AI agent economy, presenting us with opportunities for an unprecedented degree of coordination as well as significant challenges, including systemic economic risk and exacerbated inequality. Here we discuss a number of possible design choices that may lead to safely steerable AI agent markets. In particular, we consider auction mechanisms for fair resource allocation and preference resolution, the design of AI "mission economies" to coordinate around achieving collective goals, and socio-technical infrastructure needed to ensure trust, safety, and accountability. By doing this, we argue for the proactive design of steerable agent markets to ensure the coming technological shift aligns with humanity's long-term collective flourishing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10147</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 11:20:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inpainting-Guided Policy Optimization for Diffusion Large Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10396</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10396.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyan Zhao, Mengchen Liu, Jing Huang, Miao Liu, Chenyu Wang, Bo Liu, Yuandong Tian, Guan Pang, Sean Bell, Aditya Grover, Feiyu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Masked diffusion large language models (dLLMs) are emerging as promising alternatives to autoregressive LLMs, offering competitive performance while supporting unique generation capabilities such as inpainting. We explore how inpainting can inform RL algorithm design for dLLMs. Aligning LLMs with reinforcement learning faces an exploration challenge: sparse reward signals and sample waste when models fail to discover correct solutions. While this inefficiency affects LLMs broadly, dLLMs offer a distinctive opportunity--their inpainting ability can guide exploration. We introduce IGPO (Inpainting Guided Policy Optimization), an RL framework that strategically inserts partial ground-truth reasoning traces during online sampling. Unlike providing full solutions, inpainting steers exploration toward promising trajectory spaces while preserving self-generated reasoning, bridging supervised fine-tuning and reinforcement learning. We apply IGPO to group-based optimization methods such as GRPO, where exploration failures cause zero advantages and gradients. IGPO restores meaningful gradients while improving sample efficiency. We also propose supervised fine-tuning on synthetically rewritten concise traces that better align with dLLM generation patterns. With additional techniques including entropy-based filtering, our training recipe yields substantial gains across three mathematical benchmarks--GSM8K, Math500, and AMC--achieving new state-of-the-art results for full-attention masked dLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10396</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 16:44:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RecoWorld: Building Simulated Environments for Agentic Recommender   Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10397</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10397.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fei Liu, Xinyu Lin, Hanchao Yu, Mingyuan Wu, Jianyu Wang, Qiang Zhang, Zhuokai Zhao, Yinglong Xia, Yao Zhang, Weiwei Li, Mingze Gao, Qifan Wang, Lizhu Zhang, Benyu Zhang, Xiangjun Fan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present RecoWorld, a blueprint for building simulated environments tailored to agentic recommender systems. Such environments give agents a proper training space where they can learn from errors without impacting real users. RecoWorld distinguishes itself with a dual-view architecture: a simulated user and an agentic recommender engage in multi-turn interactions aimed at maximizing user retention. The user simulator reviews recommended items, updates its mindset, and when sensing potential user disengagement, generates reflective instructions. The agentic recommender adapts its recommendations by incorporating these user instructions and reasoning traces, creating a dynamic feedback loop that actively engages users. This process leverages the exceptional reasoning capabilities of modern LLMs. We explore diverse content representations within the simulator, including text-based, multimodal, and semantic ID modeling, and discuss how multi-turn RL enables the recommender to refine its strategies through iterative interactions. RecoWorld also supports multi-agent simulations, allowing creators to simulate the responses of targeted user populations. It marks an important first step toward recommender systems where users and agents collaboratively shape personalized information streams. We envision new interaction paradigms where "user instructs, recommender responds," jointly optimizing user retention and engagement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10397</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 16:44:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Developer-LLM Conversations: An Empirical Study of Interactions and   Generated Code Quality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10402</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10402.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Suzhen Zhong, Ying Zou, Bram Adams&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are becoming integral to modern software development workflows, assisting developers with code generation, API explanation, and iterative problem-solving through natural language conversations. Despite widespread adoption, there is limited understanding of how developers interact with LLMs in practice and how these conversational dynamics influence task outcomes, code quality, and software engineering workflows. To address this, we leverage CodeChat, a large dataset comprising 82,845 real-world developer-LLM conversations, containing 368,506 code snippets generated across over 20 programming languages, derived from the WildChat dataset. We find that LLM responses are substantially longer than developer prompts, with a median token-length ratio of 14:1. Multi-turn conversations account for 68% of the dataset and often evolve due to shifting requirements, incomplete prompts, or clarification requests. Topic analysis identifies web design (9.6% of conversations) and neural network training (8.7% of conversations) as the most frequent LLM-assisted tasks. Evaluation across five languages (i.e., Python, JavaScript, C++, Java, and C#) reveals prevalent and language-specific issues in LLM-generated code: generated Python and JavaScript code often include undefined variables (83.4% and 75.3% of code snippets, respectively); Java code lacks required comments (75.9%); C++ code frequently omits headers (41.1%) and C# code shows unresolved namespaces (49.2%). During a conversation, syntax and import errors persist across turns; however, documentation quality in Java improves by up to 14.7%, and import handling in Python improves by 3.7% over 5 turns. Prompts that point out mistakes in code generated in prior turns and explicitly request a fix are most effective for resolving errors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10402</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 16:52:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfGen: A Resolution-Agnostic Paradigm for Scalable Image Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10441</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10441.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tao Han, Wanghan Xu, Junchao Gong, Xiaoyu Yue, Song Guo, Luping Zhou, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Arbitrary resolution image generation provides a consistent visual experience across devices, having extensive applications for producers and consumers. Current diffusion models increase computational demand quadratically with resolution, causing 4K image generation delays over 100 seconds. To solve this, we explore the second generation upon the latent diffusion models, where the fixed latent generated by diffusion models is regarded as the content representation and we propose to decode arbitrary resolution images with a compact generated latent using a one-step generator. Thus, we present the InfGen, replacing the VAE decoder with the new generator, for generating images at any resolution from a fixed-size latent without retraining the diffusion models, which simplifies the process, reducing computational complexity and can be applied to any model using the same latent space. Experiments show InfGen is capable of improving many models into the arbitrary high-resolution era while cutting 4K image generation time to under 10 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10441</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 17:48:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable Part Diffusion 4D: Multi-View RGB and Kinematic Parts Video   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10687</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10687.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Zhang, Chun-Han Yao, Simon Donné, Narendra Ahuja, Varun Jampani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Stable Part Diffusion 4D (SP4D), a framework for generating paired RGB and kinematic part videos from monocular inputs. Unlike conventional part segmentation methods that rely on appearance-based semantic cues, SP4D learns to produce kinematic parts - structural components aligned with object articulation and consistent across views and time. SP4D adopts a dual-branch diffusion model that jointly synthesizes RGB frames and corresponding part segmentation maps. To simplify the architecture and flexibly enable different part counts, we introduce a spatial color encoding scheme that maps part masks to continuous RGB-like images. This encoding allows the segmentation branch to share the latent VAE from the RGB branch, while enabling part segmentation to be recovered via straightforward post-processing. A Bidirectional Diffusion Fusion (BiDiFuse) module enhances cross-branch consistency, supported by a contrastive part consistency loss to promote spatial and temporal alignment of part predictions. We demonstrate that the generated 2D part maps can be lifted to 3D to derive skeletal structures and harmonic skinning weights with few manual adjustments. To train and evaluate SP4D, we construct KinematicParts20K, a curated dataset of over 20K rigged objects selected and processed from Objaverse XL (Deitke et al., 2023), each paired with multi-view RGB and part video sequences. Experiments show that SP4D generalizes strongly to diverse scenarios, including real-world videos, novel generated objects, and rare articulated poses, producing kinematic-aware outputs suitable for downstream animation and motion-related tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10687</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 20:39:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Struct-Bench: A Benchmark for Differentially Private Structured Text   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10696</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10696.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuaiqi Wang, Vikas Raunak, Arturs Backurs, Victor Reis, Pei Zhou, Sihao Chen, Longqi Yang, Zinan Lin, Sergey Yekhanin, Giulia Fanti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Differentially private (DP) synthetic data generation is a promising technique for utilizing private datasets that otherwise cannot be exposed for model training or other analytics. While much research literature has focused on generating private unstructured text and image data, in enterprise settings, structured data (e.g., tabular) is more common, often including natural language fields or components. Existing synthetic data evaluation techniques (e.g., FID) struggle to capture the structural properties and correlations of such datasets. In this work, we propose Struct-Bench, a framework and benchmark for evaluating synthetic datasets derived from structured datasets that contain natural language data. The Struct-Bench framework requires users to provide a representation of their dataset structure as a Context-Free Grammar (CFG). Our benchmark comprises 5 real-world and 2 synthetically generated datasets, each annotated with CFGs. We show that these datasets demonstrably present a great challenge even for state-of-the-art DP synthetic data generation methods. Struct-Bench also includes reference implementations of different metrics and a leaderboard, thereby providing researchers a standardized evaluation platform to benchmark and investigate privacy-preserving synthetic data generation methods. Further, we also present a case study showing how to use Struct-Bench to improve the synthetic data quality of Private Evolution (PE) on structured data. The benchmark and the leaderboard have been publicly made available at https://struct-bench.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10696</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 21:18:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sound Matching an Analogue Levelling Amplifier Using the Newton-Raphson   Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10706</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10706.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chin-Yun Yu, György Fazekas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Automatic differentiation through digital signal processing algorithms for virtual analogue modelling has recently gained popularity. These algorithms are typically more computationally efficient than black-box neural networks that rely on dense matrix multiplications. Due to their differentiable nature, they can be integrated with neural networks and jointly trained using gradient descent algorithms, resulting in more efficient systems. Furthermore, signal processing algorithms have significantly fewer parameters than neural networks, allowing the application of the Newton-Raphson method. This method offers faster and more robust convergence than gradient descent at the cost of quadratic storage. This paper presents a method to emulate analogue levelling amplifiers using a feed-forward digital compressor with parameters optimised via the Newton-Raphson method. We demonstrate that a digital compressor can successfully approximate the behaviour of our target unit, the Teletronix LA-2A. Different strategies for computing the Hessian matrix are benchmarked. We leverage parallel algorithms for recursive filters to achieve efficient training on modern GPUs. The resulting model is made into a VST plugin and is open-sourced at https://github.com/aim-qmul/4a2a.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10706</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 21:48:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SearchInstruct: Enhancing Domain Adaptation via Retrieval-Based   Instruction Dataset Creation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10708</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10708.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Iman Barati, Mostafa Amiri, Heshaam Faili&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) is essential for training large language models (LLMs), significantly enhancing critical capabilities such as instruction following and in-context learning. Nevertheless, creating suitable training datasets tailored for specific domains remains challenging due to unique domain constraints and data scarcity. In this paper, we propose SearchInstruct, an innovative method explicitly designed to construct high quality instruction datasets for SFT. Our approach begins with a limited set of domain specific, human generated questions, which are systematically expanded using a large language model. Subsequently, domain relevant resources are dynamically retrieved to generate accurate and contextually appropriate answers for each augmented question. Experimental evaluation demonstrates that SearchInstruct enhances both the diversity and quality of SFT datasets, leading to measurable improvements in LLM performance within specialized domains. Additionally, we show that beyond dataset generation, the proposed method can also effectively facilitate tasks such as model editing, enabling efficient updates to existing models. To facilitate reproducibility and community adoption, we provide full implementation details, the complete set of generated instruction response pairs, and the source code in a publicly accessible Git repository: [https://github.com/mostafaamiri/SearchInstruct](https://github.com/mostafaamiri/SearchInstruct)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10708</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 21:50:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InternScenes: A Large-scale Simulatable Indoor Scene Dataset with   Realistic Layouts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10813</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10813.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weipeng Zhong, Peizhou Cao, Yichen Jin, Li Luo, Wenzhe Cai, Jingli Lin, Hanqing Wang, Zhaoyang Lyu, Tai Wang, Bo Dai, Xudong Xu, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The advancement of Embodied AI heavily relies on large-scale, simulatable 3D scene datasets characterized by scene diversity and realistic layouts. However, existing datasets typically suffer from limitations in data scale or diversity, sanitized layouts lacking small items, and severe object collisions. To address these shortcomings, we introduce InternScenes, a novel large-scale simulatable indoor scene dataset comprising approximately 40,000 diverse scenes by integrating three disparate scene sources, real-world scans, procedurally generated scenes, and designer-created scenes, including 1.96M 3D objects and covering 15 common scene types and 288 object classes. We particularly preserve massive small items in the scenes, resulting in realistic and complex layouts with an average of 41.5 objects per region. Our comprehensive data processing pipeline ensures simulatability by creating real-to-sim replicas for real-world scans, enhances interactivity by incorporating interactive objects into these scenes, and resolves object collisions by physical simulations. We demonstrate the value of InternScenes with two benchmark applications: scene layout generation and point-goal navigation. Both show the new challenges posed by the complex and realistic layouts. More importantly, InternScenes paves the way for scaling up the model training for both tasks, making the generation and navigation in such complex scenes possible. We commit to open-sourcing the data, models, and benchmarks to benefit the whole community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10813</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2025 14:25:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GAPrune: Gradient-Alignment Pruning for Domain-Aware Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10844</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10844.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yixuan Tang, Yi Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Domain-specific embedding models have shown promise for applications that require specialized semantic understanding, such as coding agents and financial retrieval systems, often achieving higher performance gains than general models. However, state-of-the-art embedding models are typically based on LLMs, which contain billions of parameters, making deployment challenging in resource-constrained environments. Model compression through pruning offers a promising solution, but existing pruning methods treat all parameters uniformly, failing to distinguish between general semantic representations and domain-specific patterns, leading to suboptimal pruning decisions. Thus, we propose GAPrune, a pruning framework that addresses this challenge by considering both domain importance and preserving general linguistic foundation. Our method uses Fisher Information to measure importance and general-domain gradient alignment to assess parameter behavior, then combines these signals using our Domain Alignment Importance (DAI) scoring. Lower DAI scores indicate that the parameter is either less important for the domain task or creates conflicts between domain and general objectives. Experiments on two domain benchmarks, FinMTEB and ChemTEB, show that GAPrune maintains performance within 2.5% of dense models in one-shot pruning at 50% sparsity, while outperforming all baselines. With retraining in 100 steps, GAPrune achieves +4.51% improvement on FinMTEB and +1.73% on ChemTEB, demonstrating that our pruning strategy not only preserves but enhances domain-specific capabilities. Our findings demonstrate that principled pruning strategies can achieve model compression and enhanced domain specialization, providing the research community with a new approach for development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10844</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2025 15:03:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nav-R1: Reasoning and Navigation in Embodied Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10884</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.10884.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qingxiang Liu, Ting Huang, Zeyu Zhang, Hao Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Embodied navigation requires agents to integrate perception, reasoning, and action for robust interaction in complex 3D environments. Existing approaches often suffer from incoherent and unstable reasoning traces that hinder generalization across diverse environments, and difficulty balancing long-horizon semantic reasoning with low-latency control for real-time navigation. To address these challenges, we propose Nav-R1, an embodied foundation model that unifies reasoning in embodied environments. We first construct Nav-CoT-110K, a large-scale dataset of step-by-step Chains-of-Thought (CoT) for embodied tasks, which enables cold-start initialization with structured reasoning. Building on this foundation, we design a GRPO-based reinforcement learning framework with three complementary rewards: format, understanding, and navigation, to improve structural adherence, semantic grounding, and path fidelity. Furthermore, we introduce a Fast-in-Slow reasoning paradigm, decoupling deliberate semantic reasoning from low-latency reactive control for efficient yet coherent navigation. Extensive evaluations on embodied AI benchmarks demonstrate that Nav-R1 consistently outperforms strong baselines, with over 8% average improvement in reasoning and navigation performance. Real-world deployment on a mobile robot further validates its robustness under limited onboard resources. Code: https://github.com/AIGeeksGroup/Nav-R1. Website: https://aigeeksgroup.github.io/Nav-R1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10884</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2025 16:31:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WildSmoke: Ready-to-Use Dynamic 3D Smoke Assets from a Single Video in   the Wild</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11114</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11114.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqiu Liu, Jialin Song, Manolis Savva, Wuyang Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a pipeline to extract and reconstruct dynamic 3D smoke assets from a single in-the-wild video, and further integrate interactive simulation for smoke design and editing. Recent developments in 3D vision have significantly improved reconstructing and rendering fluid dynamics, supporting realistic and temporally consistent view synthesis. However, current fluid reconstructions rely heavily on carefully controlled clean lab environments, whereas real-world videos captured in the wild are largely underexplored. We pinpoint three key challenges of reconstructing smoke in real-world videos and design targeted techniques, including smoke extraction with background removal, initialization of smoke particles and camera poses, and inferring multi-view videos. Our method not only outperforms previous reconstruction and generation methods with high-quality smoke reconstructions (+2.22 average PSNR on wild videos), but also enables diverse and realistic editing of fluid dynamics by simulating our smoke assets. We provide our models, data, and 4D smoke assets at [https://autumnyq.github.io/WildSmoke](https://autumnyq.github.io/WildSmoke).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11114</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 06:06:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Brain Restoration for Joint Quantization and Sparsification of   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11177</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11177.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hang Guo, Yawei Li, Luca Benini&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Language Model (LLM) compression, such as quantization and pruning, have achieved notable success. However, as these techniques gradually approach their respective limits, relying on a single method for further compression has become increasingly challenging. In this work, we explore an alternative solution by combining quantization and sparsity. This joint approach, though promising, introduces new difficulties due to the inherently conflicting requirements on weight distributions: quantization favors compact ranges, while pruning benefits from high variance. To attack this problem, we propose Optimal Brain Restoration (OBR), a general and training-free framework that aligns pruning and quantization by error compensation between both. OBR minimizes performance degradation on downstream tasks by building on a second-order Hessian objective, which is then reformulated into a tractable problem through surrogate approximation and ultimately reaches a closed-form solution via group error compensation. Experiments show that OBR enables aggressive W4A4KV4 quantization with 50% sparsity on existing LLMs, and delivers up to 4.72x speedup and 6.4x memory reduction compared to the FP16-dense baseline.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11177</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 09:17:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Quantum-Classical Model for Image Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13353</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13353.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muhammad Adnan Shahzad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This study presents a systematic comparison between hybrid quantum-classical neural networks and purely classical models across three benchmark datasets (MNIST, CIFAR100, and STL10) to evaluate their performance, efficiency, and robustness. The hybrid models integrate parameterized quantum circuits with classical deep learning architectures, while the classical counterparts use conventional convolutional neural networks (CNNs). Experiments were conducted over 50 training epochs for each dataset, with evaluations on validation accuracy, test accuracy, training time, computational resource usage, and adversarial robustness (tested with epsilon=0.1 perturbations).Key findings demonstrate that hybrid models consistently outperform classical models in final accuracy, achieving {99.38\% (MNIST), 41.69\% (CIFAR100), and 74.05\% (STL10) validation accuracy, compared to classical benchmarks of 98.21\%, 32.25\%, and 63.76\%, respectively. Notably, the hybrid advantage scales with dataset complexity, showing the most significant gains on CIFAR100 (+9.44\%) and STL10 (+10.29\%). Hybrid models also train 5--12times faster (e.g., 21.23s vs. 108.44s per epoch on MNIST) and use 6--32\% fewer parameters} while maintaining superior generalization to unseen test data.Adversarial robustness tests reveal that hybrid models are significantly more resilient on simpler datasets (e.g., 45.27\% robust accuracy on MNIST vs. 10.80\% for classical) but show comparable fragility on complex datasets like CIFAR100 (sim1\% robustness for both). Resource efficiency analyses indicate that hybrid models consume less memory (4--5GB vs. 5--6GB for classical) and lower CPU utilization (9.5\% vs. 23.2\% on average).These results suggest that hybrid quantum-classical architectures offer compelling advantages in accuracy, training efficiency, and parameter scalability, particularly for complex vision tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13353</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 09:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PersonaX: Multimodal Datasets with LLM-Inferred Behavior Traits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11362</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11362.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Loka Li, Wong Yu Kang, Minghao Fu, Guangyi Chen, Zhenhao Chen, Gongxu Luo, Yuewen Sun, Salman Khan, Peter Spirtes, Kun Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding human behavior traits is central to applications in human-computer interaction, computational social science, and personalized AI systems. Such understanding often requires integrating multiple modalities to capture nuanced patterns and relationships. However, existing resources rarely provide datasets that combine behavioral descriptors with complementary modalities such as facial attributes and biographical information. To address this gap, we present PersonaX, a curated collection of multimodal datasets designed to enable comprehensive analysis of public traits across modalities. PersonaX consists of (1) CelebPersona, featuring 9444 public figures from diverse occupations, and (2) AthlePersona, covering 4181 professional athletes across 7 major sports leagues. Each dataset includes behavioral trait assessments inferred by three high-performing large language models, alongside facial imagery and structured biographical features. We analyze PersonaX at two complementary levels. First, we abstract high-level trait scores from text descriptions and apply five statistical independence tests to examine their relationships with other modalities. Second, we introduce a novel causal representation learning (CRL) framework tailored to multimodal and multi-measurement data, providing theoretical identifiability guarantees. Experiments on both synthetic and real-world data demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach. By unifying structured and unstructured analysis, PersonaX establishes a foundation for studying LLM-inferred behavioral traits in conjunction with visual and biographical attributes, advancing multimodal trait analysis and causal reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11362</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 17:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FuseCodec: Semantic-Contextual Fusion and Supervision for Neural Codecs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11425</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11425.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Md Mubtasim Ahasan, Rafat Hasan Khan, Tasnim Mohiuddin, Aman Chadha, Tariq Iqbal, M Ashraful Amin, Amin Ahsan Ali, Md Mofijul Islam, A K M Mahbubur Rahman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Speech tokenization enables discrete representation and facilitates speech language modeling. However, existing neural codecs capture low-level acoustic features, overlooking the semantic and contextual cues inherent to human speech. While recent efforts introduced semantic representations from self-supervised speech models or incorporated contextual representations from pre-trained language models, challenges remain in aligning and unifying the semantic and contextual representations. We introduce FuseCodec, which unifies acoustic, semantic, and contextual representations through strong cross-modal alignment and globally informed supervision. We propose three complementary techniques: (i) Latent Representation Fusion, integrating semantic and contextual features directly into the encoder latent space for robust and unified representation learning; (ii) Global Semantic-Contextual Supervision, supervising discrete tokens with globally pooled and broadcasted representations to enhance temporal consistency and cross-modal alignment; and (iii) Temporally Aligned Contextual Supervision, strengthening alignment by dynamically matching contextual and speech tokens within a local window for fine-grained token-level supervision. We further introduce FuseCodec-TTS, demonstrating our methodology's applicability to zero-shot speech synthesis. Empirically, FuseCodec achieves state-of-the-art performance in LibriSpeech, surpassing EnCodec, SpeechTokenizer, and DAC in transcription accuracy, perceptual quality, intelligibility, and speaker similarity. Results highlight the effectiveness of contextually and semantically guided tokenization for speech tokenization and downstream tasks. Code and pretrained models are available at https://github.com/mubtasimahasan/FuseCodec.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11425</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 20:35:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CognitiveSky: Scalable Sentiment and Narrative Analysis for   Decentralized Social Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11444</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11444.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gaurab Chhetri, Anandi Dutta, Subasish Das&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The emergence of decentralized social media platforms presents new opportunities and challenges for real-time analysis of public discourse. This study introduces CognitiveSky, an open-source and scalable framework designed for sentiment, emotion, and narrative analysis on Bluesky, a federated Twitter or X.com alternative. By ingesting data through Bluesky's Application Programming Interface (API), CognitiveSky applies transformer-based models to annotate large-scale user-generated content and produces structured and analyzable outputs. These summaries drive a dynamic dashboard that visualizes evolving patterns in emotion, activity, and conversation topics. Built entirely on free-tier infrastructure, CognitiveSky achieves both low operational cost and high accessibility. While demonstrated here for monitoring mental health discourse, its modular design enables applications across domains such as disinformation detection, crisis response, and civic sentiment analysis. By bridging large language models with decentralized networks, CognitiveSky offers a transparent, extensible tool for computational social science in an era of shifting digital ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11444</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 21:37:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Optimize Multi-Objective Alignment Through Dynamic Reward   Weighting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11452</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11452.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yining Lu, Zilong Wang, Shiyang Li, Xin Liu, Changlong Yu, Qingyu Yin, Zhan Shi, Zixuan Zhang, Meng Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Prior works in multi-objective reinforcement learning typically use linear reward scalarization with fixed weights, which provably fail to capture non-convex Pareto fronts and thus yield suboptimal results. This limitation becomes especially critical in online preference alignment for large language models. Here, stochastic trajectories generated by parameterized policies create highly non-linear and non-convex mappings from parameters to objectives that no single static weighting scheme can find optimal trade-offs. We address this limitation by introducing dynamic reward weighting, which adaptively adjusts reward weights during the online reinforcement learning process. Unlike existing approaches that rely on fixed-weight interpolation, our dynamic weighting continuously balances and prioritizes objectives in training, facilitating effective exploration of Pareto fronts in objective space. We introduce two approaches of increasing sophistication and generalizability: (1) hypervolume-guided weight adaptation and (2) gradient-based weight optimization, offering a versatile toolkit for online multi-objective alignment. Our extensive experiments demonstrate their compatibility with commonly used online reinforcement learning algorithms (including GRPO, REINFORCE, and RLOO), effectiveness across multiple mathematical reasoning datasets, and applicability to different model families, consistently achieving Pareto dominant solutions with fewer training steps than fixed-weight linear scalarization baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11452</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 21:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAPTOR: A Foundation Policy for Quadrotor Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11481</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11481.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jonas Eschmann, Dario Albani, Giuseppe Loianno&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humans are remarkably data-efficient when adapting to new unseen conditions, like driving a new car. In contrast, modern robotic control systems, like neural network policies trained using Reinforcement Learning (RL), are highly specialized for single environments. Because of this overfitting, they are known to break down even under small differences like the Simulation-to-Reality (Sim2Real) gap and require system identification and retraining for even minimal changes to the system. In this work, we present RAPTOR, a method for training a highly adaptive foundation policy for quadrotor control. Our method enables training a single, end-to-end neural-network policy to control a wide variety of quadrotors. We test 10 different real quadrotors from 32 g to 2.4 kg that also differ in motor type (brushed vs. brushless), frame type (soft vs. rigid), propeller type (2/3/4-blade), and flight controller (PX4/Betaflight/Crazyflie/M5StampFly). We find that a tiny, three-layer policy with only 2084 parameters is sufficient for zero-shot adaptation to a wide variety of platforms. The adaptation through In-Context Learning is made possible by using a recurrence in the hidden layer. The policy is trained through a novel Meta-Imitation Learning algorithm, where we sample 1000 quadrotors and train a teacher policy for each of them using Reinforcement Learning. Subsequently, the 1000 teachers are distilled into a single, adaptive student policy. We find that within milliseconds, the resulting foundation policy adapts zero-shot to unseen quadrotors. We extensively test the capabilities of the foundation policy under numerous conditions (trajectory tracking, indoor/outdoor, wind disturbance, poking, different propellers).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11481</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:05:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ClaimIQ at CheckThat! 2025: Comparing Prompted and Fine-Tuned Language   Models for Verifying Numerical Claims</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11492</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11492.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anirban Saha Anik, Md Fahimul Kabir Chowdhury, Andrew Wyckoff, Sagnik Ray Choudhury&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents our system for Task 3 of the CLEF 2025 CheckThat! Lab, which focuses on verifying numerical and temporal claims using retrieved evidence. We explore two complementary approaches: zero-shot prompting with instruction-tuned large language models (LLMs) and supervised fine-tuning using parameter-efficient LoRA. To enhance evidence quality, we investigate several selection strategies, including full-document input and top-k sentence filtering using BM25 and MiniLM. Our best-performing model LLaMA fine-tuned with LoRA achieves strong performance on the English validation set. However, a notable drop in the test set highlights a generalization challenge. These findings underscore the importance of evidence granularity and model adaptation for robust numerical fact verification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11492</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 01:03:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Instance Learning Framework with Masked Hard Instance Mining   for Gigapixel Histopathology Image Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11526</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11526.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenhao Tang, Sheng Huang, Heng Fang, Fengtao Zhou, Bo Liu, Qingshan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Digitizing pathological images into gigapixel Whole Slide Images (WSIs) has opened new avenues for Computational Pathology (CPath). As positive tissue comprises only a small fraction of gigapixel WSIs, existing Multiple Instance Learning (MIL) methods typically focus on identifying salient instances via attention mechanisms. However, this leads to a bias towards easy-to-classify instances while neglecting challenging ones. Recent studies have shown that hard examples are crucial for accurately modeling discriminative boundaries. Applying such an idea at the instance level, we elaborate a novel MIL framework with masked hard instance mining (MHIM-MIL), which utilizes a Siamese structure with a consistency constraint to explore the hard instances. Using a class-aware instance probability, MHIM-MIL employs a momentum teacher to mask salient instances and implicitly mine hard instances for training the student model. To obtain diverse, non-redundant hard instances, we adopt large-scale random masking while utilizing a global recycle network to mitigate the risk of losing key features. Furthermore, the student updates the teacher using an exponential moving average, which identifies new hard instances for subsequent training iterations and stabilizes optimization. Experimental results on cancer diagnosis, subtyping, survival analysis tasks, and 12 benchmarks demonstrate that MHIM-MIL outperforms the latest methods in both performance and efficiency. The code is available at: https://github.com/DearCaat/MHIM-MIL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11526</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 02:31:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI-S1: Advancing GUI Automation via Semi-online Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11543</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11543.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengxi Lu, Jiabo Ye, Fei Tang, Yongliang Shen, Haiyang Xu, Ziwei Zheng, Weiming Lu, Ming Yan, Fei Huang, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graphical User Interface (GUI) agents have demonstrated remarkable progress in automating complex user interface interactions through reinforcement learning. However, current approaches face a fundamental dilemma: offline RL enables stable training on pre-collected trajectories, but struggles with multi-step task execution for lack of trajectory-level reward signals; online RL captures these signals through environment interaction, but suffers from sparse rewards and prohibitive deployment costs. To address it, we present Semi-online Reinforcement Learning, a novel paradigm that simulates online RL on offline trajectories. During each rollout process, we preserve the original model output within the multi-turn dialogue, where a Patch Module adaptively recovers the divergence between rollout and expert trajectories. To capture long-term training signals, Semi-online RL introduces discounted future returns into the reward computation and optimizes the policy with weighted step-level and episode-level advantages. We further introduce Semi-Online Performance (SOP), a metric that aligns better with true online performance, serving as a practical and effective proxy for real-world evaluation. Experiments show that ours Semi-online RL achieves SOTA performance among 7B models across four dynamic benchmarks, with significant gains over the base model (e.g., +12.0% on AndroidWorld, +23.8% on AITW), demonstrating significant progress in bridging the gap between offline training efficiency and online multi-turn reasoning. The code is available at https://github.com/X-PLUG/MobileAgent/tree/main/UI-S1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11543</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 03:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EthicsMH: A Pilot Benchmark for Ethical Reasoning in Mental Health AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11648</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11648.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sai Kartheek Reddy Kasu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The deployment of large language models (LLMs) in mental health and other sensitive domains raises urgent questions about ethical reasoning, fairness, and responsible alignment. Yet, existing benchmarks for moral and clinical decision-making do not adequately capture the unique ethical dilemmas encountered in mental health practice, where confidentiality, autonomy, beneficence, and bias frequently intersect. To address this gap, we introduce Ethical Reasoning in Mental Health (EthicsMH), a pilot dataset of 125 scenarios designed to evaluate how AI systems navigate ethically charged situations in therapeutic and psychiatric contexts. Each scenario is enriched with structured fields, including multiple decision options, expert-aligned reasoning, expected model behavior, real-world impact, and multi-stakeholder viewpoints. This structure enables evaluation not only of decision accuracy but also of explanation quality and alignment with professional norms. Although modest in scale and developed with model-assisted generation, EthicsMH establishes a task framework that bridges AI ethics and mental health decision-making. By releasing this dataset, we aim to provide a seed resource that can be expanded through community and expert contributions, fostering the development of AI systems capable of responsibly handling some of society's most delicate decisions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11648</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 07:35:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr.V: A Hierarchical Perception-Temporal-Cognition Framework to Diagnose   Video Hallucination by Fine-grained Spatial-Temporal Grounding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11866</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11866.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Meng Luo, Shengqiong Wu, Liqiang Jing, Tianjie Ju, Li Zheng, Jinxiang Lai, Tianlong Wu, Xinya Du, Jian Li, Siyuan Yan, Jiebo Luo, William Yang Wang, Hao Fei, Mong-Li Lee, Wynne Hsu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in large video models (LVMs) have significantly enhance video understanding. However, these models continue to suffer from hallucinations, producing content that conflicts with input videos. To address this issue, we propose Dr.V, a hierarchical framework covering perceptive, temporal, and cognitive levels to diagnose video hallucination by fine-grained spatial-temporal grounding. Dr.V comprises of two key components: a benchmark dataset Dr.V-Bench and a satellite video agent Dr.V-Agent. Dr.V-Bench includes 10k instances drawn from 4,974 videos spanning diverse tasks, each enriched with detailed spatial-temporal annotation. Dr.V-Agent detects hallucinations in LVMs by systematically applying fine-grained spatial-temporal grounding at the perceptive and temporal levels, followed by cognitive level reasoning. This step-by-step pipeline mirrors human-like video comprehension and effectively identifies hallucinations. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Dr.V-Agent is effective in diagnosing hallucination while enhancing interpretability and reliability, offering a practical blueprint for robust video understanding in real-world scenarios. All our data and code are available at https://github.com/Eurekaleo/Dr.V.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11866</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 12:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ToolRM: Outcome Reward Models for Tool-Calling Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11963</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11963.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mayank Agarwal, Ibrahim Abdelaziz, Kinjal Basu, Merve Unuvar, Luis A. Lastras, Yara Rizk, Pavan Kapanipathi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language models (LLMs) increasingly interact with external tools, reward modeling for tool use has become a critical yet underexplored area. Existing reward models, trained primarily on natural language outputs, struggle to evaluate tool-based reasoning and execution. To quantify this gap, we introduce FC-RewardBench, the first benchmark designed to systematically assess reward models' performance in tool-calling scenarios. Our analysis shows that current reward models often miss key signals of effective tool use, highlighting the need for domain-specific modeling. To address this, we propose a training framework for outcome-based reward models using data synthesized from permissively licensed, open-weight LLMs. We train models ranging from 1.7B to 14B parameters and evaluate them across seven out-of-domain benchmarks. These models consistently outperform general-purpose baselines, achieving up to 25\% average improvement in downstream task performance and enabling data-efficient fine-tuning through reward-guided filtering.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11963</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:17:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lost in Embeddings: Information Loss in Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11986</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.11986.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenyan Li, Raphael Tang, Chengzu Li, Caiqi Zhang, Ivan Vulić, Anders Søgaard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision--language models (VLMs) often process visual inputs through a pretrained vision encoder, followed by a projection into the language model's embedding space via a connector component. While crucial for modality fusion, the potential information loss induced by this projection step and its direct impact on model capabilities remain understudied. We introduce two complementary approaches to examine and quantify this loss by analyzing the latent representation space. First, we evaluate semantic information preservation by analyzing changes in k-nearest neighbor relationships between image representations, before and after projection. Second, we directly measure information loss by reconstructing visual embeddings from the projected representation, localizing loss at an image patch level. Experiments reveal that connectors substantially distort the local geometry of visual representations, with k-nearest neighbors diverging by 40--60\% post-projection, correlating with degradation in retrieval performance. The patch-level embedding reconstruction provides interpretable insights for model behavior on visually grounded question-answering tasks, finding that areas of high information loss reliably predict instances where models struggle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11986</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 14:38:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Look Again, Think Slowly: Enhancing Visual Reflection in Vision-Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12132</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12132.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pu Jian, Junhong Wu, Wei Sun, Chen Wang, Shuo Ren, Jiajun Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in text-only "slow-thinking" reasoning have prompted efforts to transfer this capability to vision-language models (VLMs), for training visual reasoning models (VRMs). owever, such transfer faces critical challenges: Effective "slow thinking" in VRMs requires visual reflection, the ability to check the reasoning process based on visual information. Through quantitative analysis, we observe that current VRMs exhibit limited visual reflection, as their attention to visual information diminishes rapidly with longer generated responses. To address this challenge, we propose a new VRM Reflection-V, which enhances visual reflection based on reasoning data construction for cold-start and reward design for reinforcement learning (RL). Firstly, we construct vision-centered reasoning data by leveraging an agent that interacts between VLMs and reasoning LLMs, enabling cold-start learning of visual reflection patterns. Secondly, a visual attention based reward model is employed during RL to encourage reasoning based on visual information. Therefore, Reflection-V demonstrates significant improvements across multiple visual reasoning benchmarks. Furthermore, Reflection-V maintains a stronger and more consistent reliance on visual information during visual reasoning, indicating effective enhancement in visual reflection capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12132</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 16:57:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniWorld: A Multi-Domain and Multi-Modal Dataset for 4D World Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12201</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12201.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Zhou, Yifan Wang, Jianjun Zhou, Wenzheng Chang, Haoyu Guo, Zizun Li, Kaijing Ma, Xinyue Li, Yating Wang, Haoyi Zhu, Mingyu Liu, Dingning Liu, Jiange Yang, Zhoujie Fu, Junyi Chen, Chunhua Shen, Jiangmiao Pang, Kaipeng Zhang, Tong He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 98&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The field of 4D world modeling - aiming to jointly capture spatial geometry and temporal dynamics - has witnessed remarkable progress in recent years, driven by advances in large-scale generative models and multimodal learning. However, the development of truly general 4D world models remains fundamentally constrained by the availability of high-quality data. Existing datasets and benchmarks often lack the dynamic complexity, multi-domain diversity, and spatial-temporal annotations required to support key tasks such as 4D geometric reconstruction, future prediction, and camera-control video generation. To address this gap, we introduce OmniWorld, a large-scale, multi-domain, multi-modal dataset specifically designed for 4D world modeling. OmniWorld consists of a newly collected OmniWorld-Game dataset and several curated public datasets spanning diverse domains. Compared with existing synthetic datasets, OmniWorld-Game provides richer modality coverage, larger scale, and more realistic dynamic interactions. Based on this dataset, we establish a challenging benchmark that exposes the limitations of current state-of-the-art (SOTA) approaches in modeling complex 4D environments. Moreover, fine-tuning existing SOTA methods on OmniWorld leads to significant performance gains across 4D reconstruction and video generation tasks, strongly validating OmniWorld as a powerful resource for training and evaluation. We envision OmniWorld as a catalyst for accelerating the development of general-purpose 4D world models, ultimately advancing machines' holistic understanding of the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12201</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 17:59:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LazyDrag: Enabling Stable Drag-Based Editing on Multi-Modal Diffusion   Transformers via Explicit Correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12203</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12203.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zixin Yin, Xili Dai, Duomin Wang, Xianfang Zeng, Lionel M. Ni, Gang Yu, Heung-Yeung Shum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The reliance on implicit point matching via attention has become a core bottleneck in drag-based editing, resulting in a fundamental compromise on weakened inversion strength and costly test-time optimization (TTO). This compromise severely limits the generative capabilities of diffusion models, suppressing high-fidelity inpainting and text-guided creation. In this paper, we introduce LazyDrag, the first drag-based image editing method for Multi-Modal Diffusion Transformers, which directly eliminates the reliance on implicit point matching. In concrete terms, our method generates an explicit correspondence map from user drag inputs as a reliable reference to boost the attention control. This reliable reference opens the potential for a stable full-strength inversion process, which is the first in the drag-based editing task. It obviates the necessity for TTO and unlocks the generative capability of models. Therefore, LazyDrag naturally unifies precise geometric control with text guidance, enabling complex edits that were previously out of reach: opening the mouth of a dog and inpainting its interior, generating new objects like a ``tennis ball'', or for ambiguous drags, making context-aware changes like moving a hand into a pocket. Additionally, LazyDrag supports multi-round workflows with simultaneous move and scale operations. Evaluated on the DragBench, our method outperforms baselines in drag accuracy and perceptual quality, as validated by VIEScore and human evaluation. LazyDrag not only establishes new state-of-the-art performance, but also paves a new way to editing paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12203</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 17:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Coset Sampling for Quantum Lattice Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12341</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12341.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We give a simple, fully correct, and assumption-light replacement for the contested "domain-extension" in Step 9 of a recent windowed-QFT lattice algorithm with complex-Gaussian windows~chen2024quantum. The published Step~9 suffers from a periodicity/support mismatch. We present a pair-shift difference construction that coherently cancels all unknown offsets, produces an exact uniform CRT-coset state over Z_{P}, and then uses the QFT to enforce the intended modular linear relation. The unitary is reversible, uses poly(log M_2) gates, and preserves the algorithm's asymptotics. Project Page: https://github.com/yifanzhang-pro/quantum-lattice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12341</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 18:10:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image Tokenizer Needs Post-Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12474</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12474.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kai Qiu, Xiang Li, Hao Chen, Jason Kuen, Xiaohao Xu, Jiuxiang Gu, Yinyi Luo, Bhiksha Raj, Zhe Lin, Marios Savvides&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent image generative models typically capture the image distribution in a pre-constructed latent space, relying on a frozen image tokenizer. However, there exists a significant discrepancy between the reconstruction and generation distribution, where current tokenizers only prioritize the reconstruction task that happens before generative training without considering the generation errors during sampling. In this paper, we comprehensively analyze the reason for this discrepancy in a discrete latent space, and, from which, we propose a novel tokenizer training scheme including both main-training and post-training, focusing on improving latent space construction and decoding respectively. During the main training, a latent perturbation strategy is proposed to simulate sampling noises, \ie, the unexpected tokens generated in generative inference. Specifically, we propose a plug-and-play tokenizer training scheme, which significantly enhances the robustness of tokenizer, thus boosting the generation quality and convergence speed, and a novel tokenizer evaluation metric, \ie, pFID, which successfully correlates the tokenizer performance to generation quality. During post-training, we further optimize the tokenizer decoder regarding a well-trained generative model to mitigate the distribution difference between generated and reconstructed tokens. With a sim400M generator, a discrete tokenizer trained with our proposed main training achieves a notable 1.60 gFID and further obtains 1.36 gFID with the additional post-training. Further experiments are conducted to broadly validate the effectiveness of our post-training strategy on off-the-shelf discrete and continuous tokenizers, coupled with autoregressive and diffusion-based generators.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12474</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 21:38:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phi: Preference Hijacking in Multi-modal Large Language Models at   Inference Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12521</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12521.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Lan, Yuanpu Cao, Weitong Zhang, Lu Lin, Jinghui Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have gained significant attention across various domains. However, their widespread adoption has also raised serious safety concerns. In this paper, we uncover a new safety risk of MLLMs: the output preference of MLLMs can be arbitrarily manipulated by carefully optimized images. Such attacks often generate contextually relevant yet biased responses that are neither overtly harmful nor unethical, making them difficult to detect. Specifically, we introduce a novel method, Preference Hijacking (Phi), for manipulating the MLLM response preferences using a preference hijacked image. Our method works at inference time and requires no model modifications. Additionally, we introduce a universal hijacking perturbation -- a transferable component that can be embedded into different images to hijack MLLM responses toward any attacker-specified preferences. Experimental results across various tasks demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach. The code for Phi is accessible at https://github.com/Yifan-Lan/Phi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12521</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 23:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>zELO: ELO-inspired Training Method for Rerankers and Embedding Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12541</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12541.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nicholas Pipitone, Ghita Houir Alami, Advaith Avadhanam, Anton Kaminskyi, Ashley Khoo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce a novel training methodology named zELO, which optimizes retrieval performance via the analysis that ranking tasks are statically equivalent to a Thurstone model. Based on the zELO method, we use unsupervised data in order train a suite of state-of-the-art open-weight reranker models: zerank-1 and zerank-1-small. These models achieve the highest retrieval scores in multiple domains, including finance, legal, code, and STEM, outperforming closed-source proprietary rerankers on both NDCG@10 and Recall. These models also demonstrate great versatility, maintaining their 0-shot performance on out-of-domain and private customer datasets. The training data included 112,000 queries and 100 documents per query, and was trained end-to-end from unannotated queries and documents in less than 10,000 H100-hours.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12541</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:44:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EconProver: Towards More Economical Test-Time Scaling for Automated   Theorem Proving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12603</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12603.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mukai Li, Linfeng Song, Zhenwen Liang, Jiahao Xu, Shansan Gong, Qi Liu, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have recently advanced the field of Automated Theorem Proving (ATP), attaining substantial performance gains through widely adopted test-time scaling strategies, notably reflective Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning and increased sampling passes. However, they both introduce significant computational overhead for inference. Moreover, existing cost analyses typically regulate only the number of sampling passes, while neglecting the substantial disparities in sampling costs introduced by different scaling strategies. In this paper, we systematically compare the efficiency of different test-time scaling strategies for ATP models and demonstrate the inefficiency of the current state-of-the-art (SOTA) open-source approaches. We then investigate approaches to significantly reduce token usage and sample passes while maintaining the original performance. Specifically, we propose two complementary methods that can be integrated into a unified EconRL pipeline for amplified benefits: (1) a dynamic Chain-of-Thought (CoT) switching mechanism designed to mitigate unnecessary token consumption, and (2) Diverse parallel-scaled reinforcement learning (RL) with trainable prefixes to enhance pass rates under constrained sampling passes. Experiments on miniF2F and ProofNet demonstrate that our EconProver achieves comparable performance to baseline methods with only 12% of the computational cost. This work provides actionable insights for deploying lightweight ATP models without sacrificing performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12603</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 03:00:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hunyuan3D Studio: End-to-End AI Pipeline for Game-Ready 3D Asset   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12815</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12815.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Biwen Lei, Yang Li, Xinhai Liu, Shuhui Yang, Lixin Xu, Jingwei Huang, Ruining Tang, Haohan Weng, Jian Liu, Jing Xu, Zhen Zhou, Yiling Zhu, Jiankai Xing, Jiachen Xu, Changfeng Ma, Xinhao Yan, Yunhan Yang, Chunshi Wang, Duoteng Xu, Xueqi Ma, Yuguang Chen, Jing Li, Mingxin Yang, Sheng Zhang, Yifei Feng, Xin Huang, Di Luo, Zebin He, Puhua Jiang, Changrong Hu, Zihan Qin, Shiwei Miao, Haolin Liu, Yunfei Zhao, Zeqiang Lai, Qingxiang Lin, Zibo Zhao, Kunhong Li, Xianghui Yang, Huiwen Shi, Xin Yang, Yuxuan Wang, Zebin Yao, Yihang Lian, Sicong Liu, Xintong Han, Wangchen Qin, Caisheng Ouyang, Jianyin Liu, Tianwen Yuan, Shuai Jiang, Hong Duan, Yanqi Niu, Wencong Lin, Yifu Sun, Shirui Huang, Lin Niu, Gu Gong, Guojian Xiao, Bojian Zheng, Xiang Yuan, Qi Chen, Jie Xiao, Dongyang Zheng, Xiaofeng Yang, Kai Liu, Jianchen Zhu, Lifu Wang, Qinglin Lu, Jie Liu, Liang Dong, Fan Jiang, Ruibin Chen, Lei Wang, Chao Zhang, Jiaxin Lin, Hao Zhang, Zheng Ye, Peng He, Runzhou Wu, Yinhe Wu, Jiayao Du, Jupeng Chen, Xinyue Mao, Dongyuan Guo, Yixuan Tang, Yulin Tsai, Yonghao Tan, Jiaao Yu, Junlin Yu, Keren Zhang, Yifan Li, Peng Chen, Tian Liu, Di Wang, Yuhong Liu, Linus, Jie Jiang, Zhuo Chen, Chunchao Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The creation of high-quality 3D assets, a cornerstone of modern game development, has long been characterized by labor-intensive and specialized workflows. This paper presents Hunyuan3D Studio, an end-to-end AI-powered content creation platform designed to revolutionize the game production pipeline by automating and streamlining the generation of game-ready 3D assets. At its core, Hunyuan3D Studio integrates a suite of advanced neural modules (such as Part-level 3D Generation, Polygon Generation, Semantic UV, etc.) into a cohesive and user-friendly system. This unified framework allows for the rapid transformation of a single concept image or textual description into a fully-realized, production-quality 3D model complete with optimized geometry and high-fidelity PBR textures. We demonstrate that assets generated by Hunyuan3D Studio are not only visually compelling but also adhere to the stringent technical requirements of contemporary game engines, significantly reducing iteration time and lowering the barrier to entry for 3D content creation. By providing a seamless bridge from creative intent to technical asset, Hunyuan3D Studio represents a significant leap forward for AI-assisted workflows in game development and interactive media.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12815</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 08:33:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PANORAMA: The Rise of Omnidirectional Vision in the Embodied AI Era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12989</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.12989.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xu Zheng, Chenfei Liao, Ziqiao Weng, Kaiyu Lei, Zihao Dongfang, Haocong He, Yuanhuiyi Lyu, Lutao Jiang, Lu Qi, Li Chen, Danda Pani Paudel, Kailun Yang, Linfeng Zhang, Luc Van Gool, Xuming Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Omnidirectional vision, using 360-degree vision to understand the environment, has become increasingly critical across domains like robotics, industrial inspection, and environmental monitoring. Compared to traditional pinhole vision, omnidirectional vision provides holistic environmental awareness, significantly enhancing the completeness of scene perception and the reliability of decision-making. However, foundational research in this area has historically lagged behind traditional pinhole vision. This talk presents an emerging trend in the embodied AI era: the rapid development of omnidirectional vision, driven by growing industrial demand and academic interest. We highlight recent breakthroughs in omnidirectional generation, omnidirectional perception, omnidirectional understanding, and related datasets. Drawing on insights from both academia and industry, we propose an ideal panoramic system architecture in the embodied AI era, PANORAMA, which consists of four key subsystems. Moreover, we offer in-depth opinions related to emerging trends and cross-community impacts at the intersection of panoramic vision and embodied AI, along with the future roadmap and open challenges. This overview synthesizes state-of-the-art advancements and outlines challenges and opportunities for future research in building robust, general-purpose omnidirectional AI systems in the embodied AI era.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12989</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 11:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FinSearchComp: Towards a Realistic, Expert-Level Evaluation of Financial   Search and Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13160</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13160.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liang Hu, Jianpeng Jiao, Jiashuo Liu, Yanle Ren, Zhoufutu Wen, Kaiyuan Zhang, Xuanliang Zhang, Xiang Gao, Tianci He, Fei Hu, Yali Liao, Zaiyuan Wang, Chenghao Yang, Qianyu Yang, Mingren Yin, Zhiyuan Zeng, Ge Zhang, Xinyi Zhang, Xiying Zhao, Zhenwei Zhu, Hongseok Namkoong, Wenhao Huang, Yuwen Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Search has emerged as core infrastructure for LLM-based agents and is widely viewed as critical on the path toward more general intelligence. Finance is a particularly demanding proving ground: analysts routinely conduct complex, multi-step searches over time-sensitive, domain-specific data, making it ideal for assessing both search proficiency and knowledge-grounded reasoning. Yet no existing open financial datasets evaluate data searching capability of end-to-end agents, largely because constructing realistic, complicated tasks requires deep financial expertise and time-sensitive data is hard to evaluate. We present FinSearchComp, the first fully open-source agent benchmark for realistic, open-domain financial search and reasoning. FinSearchComp comprises three tasks -- Time-Sensitive Data Fetching, Simple Historical Lookup, and Complex Historical Investigation -- closely reproduce real-world financial analyst workflows. To ensure difficulty and reliability, we engage 70 professional financial experts for annotation and implement a rigorous multi-stage quality-assurance pipeline. The benchmark includes 635 questions spanning global and Greater China markets, and we evaluate 21 models (products) on it. Grok 4 (web) tops the global subset, approaching expert-level accuracy. DouBao (web) leads on the Greater China subset. Experimental analyses show that equipping agents with web search and financial plugins substantially improves results on FinSearchComp, and the country origin of models and tools impact performance significantly.By aligning with realistic analyst tasks and providing end-to-end evaluation, FinSearchComp offers a professional, high-difficulty testbed for complex financial search and reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13160</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 15:13:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ROOM: A Physics-Based Continuum Robot Simulator for Photorealistic   Medical Datasets Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13177</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13177.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Salvatore Esposito, Matías Mattamala, Daniel Rebain, Francis Xiatian Zhang, Kevin Dhaliwal, Mohsen Khadem, Subramanian Ramamoorthy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Continuum robots are advancing bronchoscopy procedures by accessing complex lung airways and enabling targeted interventions. However, their development is limited by the lack of realistic training and test environments: Real data is difficult to collect due to ethical constraints and patient safety concerns, and developing autonomy algorithms requires realistic imaging and physical feedback. We present ROOM (Realistic Optical Observation in Medicine), a comprehensive simulation framework designed for generating photorealistic bronchoscopy training data. By leveraging patient CT scans, our pipeline renders multi-modal sensor data including RGB images with realistic noise and light specularities, metric depth maps, surface normals, optical flow and point clouds at medically relevant scales. We validate the data generated by ROOM in two canonical tasks for medical robotics -- multi-view pose estimation and monocular depth estimation, demonstrating diverse challenges that state-of-the-art methods must overcome to transfer to these medical settings. Furthermore, we show that the data produced by ROOM can be used to fine-tune existing depth estimation models to overcome these challenges, also enabling other downstream applications such as navigation. We expect that ROOM will enable large-scale data generation across diverse patient anatomies and procedural scenarios that are challenging to capture in clinical settings. Code and data: https://github.com/iamsalvatore/room.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13177</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 15:30:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-stream Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13232</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13232.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongwen Xu, Zihan Ding&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We revisit policy-gradient optimization for Large Language Models (LLMs) from a single-stream perspective. Prevailing group-based methods like GRPO reduce variance with on-the-fly baselines but suffer from critical flaws: frequent degenerate groups erase learning signals, and synchronization barriers hinder scalability. We introduce Single-stream Policy Optimization (SPO), which eliminates these issues by design. SPO replaces per-group baselines with a persistent, KL-adaptive value tracker and normalizes advantages globally across the batch, providing a stable, low-variance learning signal for every sample. Being group-free, SPO enables higher throughput and scales effectively in long-horizon or tool-integrated settings where generation times vary. Furthermore, the persistent value tracker naturally enables an adaptive curriculum via prioritized sampling. Experiments using Qwen3-8B show that SPO converges more smoothly and attains higher accuracy than GRPO, while eliminating computation wasted on degenerate groups. Ablation studies confirm that SPO's gains stem from its principled approach to baseline estimation and advantage normalization, offering a more robust and efficient path for LLM reasoning. Across five hard math benchmarks with Qwen3 8B, SPO improves the average maj@32 by +3.4 percentage points (pp) over GRPO, driven by substantial absolute point gains on challenging datasets, including +7.3 pp on BRUMO 25, +4.4 pp on AIME 25, +3.3 pp on HMMT 25, and achieves consistent relative gain in pass@k across the evaluated k values. SPO's success challenges the prevailing trend of adding incidental complexity to RL algorithms, highlighting a path where fundamental principles, not architectural workarounds, drive the next wave of progress in LLM reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13232</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 16:39:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sum Leaks More Than Its Parts: Compositional Privacy Risks and   Mitigations in Multi-Agent Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14284</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14284.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vaidehi Patil, Elias Stengel-Eskin, Mohit Bansal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language models (LLMs) become integral to multi-agent systems, new privacy risks emerge that extend beyond memorization, direct inference, or single-turn evaluations. In particular, seemingly innocuous responses, when composed across interactions, can cumulatively enable adversaries to recover sensitive information, a phenomenon we term compositional privacy leakage. We present the first systematic study of such compositional privacy leaks and possible mitigation methods in multi-agent LLM systems. First, we develop a framework that models how auxiliary knowledge and agent interactions jointly amplify privacy risks, even when each response is benign in isolation. Next, to mitigate this, we propose and evaluate two defense strategies: (1) Theory-of-Mind defense (ToM), where defender agents infer a questioner's intent by anticipating how their outputs may be exploited by adversaries, and (2) Collaborative Consensus Defense (CoDef), where responder agents collaborate with peers who vote based on a shared aggregated state to restrict sensitive information spread. Crucially, we balance our evaluation across compositions that expose sensitive information and compositions that yield benign inferences. Our experiments quantify how these defense strategies differ in balancing the privacy-utility trade-off. We find that while chain-of-thought alone offers limited protection to leakage (~39% sensitive blocking rate), our ToM defense substantially improves sensitive query blocking (up to 97%) but can reduce benign task success. CoDef achieves the best balance, yielding the highest Balanced Outcome (79.8%), highlighting the benefit of combining explicit reasoning with defender collaboration. Together, our results expose a new class of risks in collaborative LLM deployments and provide actionable insights for designing safeguards against compositional, context-driven privacy leakage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14284</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 16:57:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EdiVal-Agent: An Object-Centric Framework for Automated, Scalable,   Fine-Grained Evaluation of Multi-Turn Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13399</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13399.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Chen, Yasi Zhang, Zhi Zhang, Peiyu Yu, Shu Wang, Zhendong Wang, Kevin Lin, Xiaofei Wang, Zhengyuan Yang, Linjie Li, Chung-Ching Lin, Jianwen Xie, Oscar Leong, Lijuan Wang, Ying Nian Wu, Mingyuan Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-based image editing has advanced rapidly, yet reliable and interpretable evaluation remains a bottleneck. Current protocols either (i) depend on paired reference images -- resulting in limited coverage and inheriting biases from prior generative models -- or (ii) rely solely on zero-shot vision-language models (VLMs), whose prompt-based assessments of instruction following, content consistency, and visual quality are often imprecise.   To address this, we introduce EdiVal-Agent, an automated, scalable, and fine-grained evaluation framework for multi-turn instruction-based editing from an object-centric perspective, supported by a suite of expert tools. Given an image, EdiVal-Agent first decomposes it into semantically meaningful objects, then synthesizes diverse, context-aware editing instructions. For evaluation, it integrates VLMs with open-vocabulary object detectors to assess instruction following, uses semantic-level feature extractors to evaluate content consistency, and leverages human preference models to judge visual quality. We show that combining VLMs with object detectors yields stronger agreement with human judgments in instruction-following evaluation compared to using VLMs alone and CLIP-based metrics. Furthermore, the pipeline's modular design allows future tools to be seamlessly integrated, enhancing evaluation accuracy over time.   Instantiating this pipeline, we build EdiVal-Bench, a multi-turn editing benchmark covering 9 instruction types and 11 state-of-the-art editing models spanning autoregressive (AR) (including Nano Banana, GPT-Image-1), flow-matching, and diffusion paradigms. We demonstrate that EdiVal-Agent can be used to identify existing failure modes, thereby informing the development of the next generation of editing models. Project page: https://tianyucodings.github.io/EdiVAL-page/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13399</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:45:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebSailor-V2: Bridging the Chasm to Proprietary Agents via Synthetic   Data and Scalable Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13305</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13305.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kuan Li, Zhongwang Zhang, Huifeng Yin, Rui Ye, Yida Zhao, Liwen Zhang, Litu Ou, Dingchu Zhang, Xixi Wu, Jialong Wu, Xinyu Wang, Zile Qiao, Zhen Zhang, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Transcending human cognitive limitations represents a critical frontier in LLM training. Proprietary agentic systems like DeepResearch have demonstrated superhuman capabilities on extremely complex information-seeking benchmarks such as BrowseComp, a feat previously unattainable. We posit that their success hinges on a sophisticated reasoning pattern absent in open-source models: the ability to systematically reduce extreme uncertainty when navigating vast information landscapes. Based on this insight, we introduce WebSailor, a complete post-training methodology designed to instill this crucial capability. Our approach involves generating novel, high-uncertainty tasks through structured sampling and information obfuscation, RFT cold start, and an efficient agentic RL training algorithm, Duplicating Sampling Policy Optimization (DUPO). With this integrated pipeline, WebSailor significantly outperforms all open-source agents in complex information-seeking tasks, matching proprietary agents' performance and closing the capability gap.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13305</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:57:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebResearcher: Unleashing unbounded reasoning capability in Long-Horizon   Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13309</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13309.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zile Qiao, Guoxin Chen, Xuanzhong Chen, Donglei Yu, Wenbiao Yin, Xinyu Wang, Zhen Zhang, Baixuan Li, Huifeng Yin, Kuan Li, Rui Min, Minpeng Liao, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in deep-research systems have demonstrated the potential for AI agents to autonomously discover and synthesize knowledge from external sources. In this paper, we introduce WebResearcher, a novel framework for building such agents through two key components: (1) WebResearcher, an iterative deep-research paradigm that reformulates deep research as a Markov Decision Process, where agents periodically consolidate findings into evolving reports while maintaining focused workspaces, overcoming the context suffocation and noise contamination that plague existing mono-contextual approaches; and (2) WebFrontier, a scalable data synthesis engine that generates high-quality training data through tool-augmented complexity escalation, enabling systematic creation of research tasks that bridge the gap between passive knowledge recall and active knowledge construction. Notably, we find that the training data from our paradigm significantly enhances tool-use capabilities even for traditional mono-contextual methods. Furthermore, our paradigm naturally scales through parallel thinking, enabling concurrent multi-agent exploration for more comprehensive conclusions. Extensive experiments across 6 challenging benchmarks demonstrate that WebResearcher achieves state-of-the-art performance, even surpassing frontier proprietary systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13309</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:57:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Agents via Continual Pre-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13310</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13310.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liangcai Su, Zhen Zhang, Guangyu Li, Zhuo Chen, Chenxi Wang, Maojia Song, Xinyu Wang, Kuan Li, Jialong Wu, Xuanzhong Chen, Zile Qiao, Zhongwang Zhang, Huifeng Yin, Shihao Cai, Runnan Fang, Zhengwei Tao, Wenbiao Yin, Chenxiong Qian, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 93&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have evolved into agentic systems capable of autonomous tool use and multi-step reasoning for complex problem-solving. However, post-training approaches building upon general-purpose foundation models consistently underperform in agentic tasks, particularly in open-source implementations. We identify the root cause: the absence of robust agentic foundation models forces models during post-training to simultaneously learn diverse agentic behaviors while aligning them to expert demonstrations, thereby creating fundamental optimization tensions. To this end, we are the first to propose incorporating Agentic Continual Pre-training (Agentic CPT) into the deep research agents training pipeline to build powerful agentic foundational models. Based on this approach, we develop a deep research agent model named AgentFounder. We evaluate our AgentFounder-30B on 10 benchmarks and achieve state-of-the-art performance while retains strong tool-use ability, notably 39.9% on BrowseComp-en, 43.3% on BrowseComp-zh, and 31.5% Pass@1 on HLE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13310</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:57:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards General Agentic Intelligence via Environment Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13311</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13311.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runnan Fang, Shihao Cai, Baixuan Li, Jialong Wu, Guangyu Li, Wenbiao Yin, Xinyu Wang, Xiaobin Wang, Liangcai Su, Zhen Zhang, Shibin Wu, Zhengwei Tao, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 65&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Advanced agentic intelligence is a prerequisite for deploying Large Language Models in practical, real-world applications. Diverse real-world APIs demand precise, robust function-calling intelligence, which needs agents to develop these capabilities through interaction in varied environments. The breadth of function-calling competence is closely tied to the diversity of environments in which agents are trained. In this work, we scale up environments as a step towards advancing general agentic intelligence. This gives rise to two central challenges: (i) how to scale environments in a principled manner, and (ii) how to effectively train agentic capabilities from experiences derived through interactions with these environments. To address these, we design a scalable framework that automatically constructs heterogeneous environments that are fully simulated, systematically broadening the space of function-calling scenarios. We further adapt a two-phase agent fine-tuning strategy: first endowing agents with fundamental agentic capabilities, then specializing them for domain-specific contexts. Extensive experiments on agentic benchmarks, tau-bench, tau2-Bench, and ACEBench, demonstrate that our trained model, AgentScaler, significantly enhances the function-calling capability of models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13311</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:57:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebWeaver: Structuring Web-Scale Evidence with Dynamic Outlines for   Open-Ended Deep Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13312</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13312.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijian Li, Xin Guan, Bo Zhang, Shen Huang, Houquan Zhou, Shaopeng Lai, Ming Yan, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jun Zhang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 94&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper tackles open-ended deep research (OEDR), a complex challenge where AI agents must synthesize vast web-scale information into insightful reports. Current approaches are plagued by dual-fold limitations: static research pipelines that decouple planning from evidence acquisition and one-shot generation paradigms that easily suffer from long-context failure issues like "loss in the middle" and hallucinations. To address these challenges, we introduce WebWeaver, a novel dual-agent framework that emulates the human research process. The planner operates in a dynamic cycle, iteratively interleaving evidence acquisition with outline optimization to produce a comprehensive, source-grounded outline linking to a memory bank of evidence. The writer then executes a hierarchical retrieval and writing process, composing the report section by section. By performing targeted retrieval of only the necessary evidence from the memory bank for each part, it effectively mitigates long-context issues. Our framework establishes a new state-of-the-art across major OEDR benchmarks, including DeepResearch Bench, DeepConsult, and DeepResearchGym. These results validate our human-centric, iterative methodology, demonstrating that adaptive planning and focused synthesis are crucial for producing high-quality, reliable, and well-structured reports.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13312</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:57:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReSum: Unlocking Long-Horizon Search Intelligence via Context   Summarization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13313</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13313.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xixi Wu, Kuan Li, Yida Zhao, Liwen Zhang, Litu Ou, Huifeng Yin, Zhongwang Zhang, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Minhao Cheng, Shuai Wang, Hong Cheng, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Model (LLM)-based web agents demonstrate strong performance on knowledge-intensive tasks but are hindered by context window limitations in paradigms like ReAct. Complex queries involving multiple entities, intertwined relationships, and high uncertainty demand extensive search cycles that rapidly exhaust context budgets before reaching complete solutions. To overcome this challenge, we introduce ReSum, a novel paradigm that enables indefinite exploration through periodic context summarization. ReSum converts growing interaction histories into compact reasoning states, maintaining awareness of prior discoveries while bypassing context constraints. For paradigm adaptation, we propose ReSum-GRPO, integrating GRPO with segmented trajectory training and advantage broadcasting to familiarize agents with summary-conditioned reasoning. Extensive experiments on web agents of varying scales across three benchmarks demonstrate that ReSum delivers an average absolute improvement of 4.5\% over ReAct, with further gains of up to 8.2\% following ReSum-GRPO training. Notably, with only 1K training samples, our WebResummer-30B (a ReSum-GRPO-trained version of WebSailor-30B) achieves 33.3\% Pass@1 on BrowseComp-zh and 18.3\% on BrowseComp-en, surpassing existing open-source web agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13313</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:57:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Aware Region Prompted Vision Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; An-Chieh Cheng, Yang Fu, Yukang Chen, Zhijian Liu, Xiaolong Li, Subhashree Radhakrishnan, Song Han, Yao Lu, Jan Kautz, Pavlo Molchanov, Hongxu Yin, Xiaolong Wang, Sifei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Spatial Region 3D (SR-3D) aware vision-language model that connects single-view 2D images and multi-view 3D data through a shared visual token space. SR-3D supports flexible region prompting, allowing users to annotate regions with bounding boxes, segmentation masks on any frame, or directly in 3D, without the need for exhaustive multi-frame labeling. We achieve this by enriching 2D visual features with 3D positional embeddings, which allows the 3D model to draw upon strong 2D priors for more accurate spatial reasoning across frames, even when objects of interest do not co-occur within the same view. Extensive experiments on both general 2D vision language and specialized 3D spatial benchmarks demonstrate that SR-3D achieves state-of-the-art performance, underscoring its effectiveness for unifying 2D and 3D representation space on scene understanding. Moreover, we observe applicability to in-the-wild videos without sensory 3D inputs or ground-truth 3D annotations, where SR-3D accurately infers spatial relationships and metric measurements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13317</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 17:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SteeringControl: Holistic Evaluation of Alignment Steering in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13450</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13450.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vincent Siu, Nicholas Crispino, David Park, Nathan W. Henry, Zhun Wang, Yang Liu, Dawn Song, Chenguang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SteeringControl, a benchmark for evaluating representation steering methods across core alignment objectives--bias, harmful generation, and hallucination--and their effects on secondary behaviors such as sycophancy and commonsense morality. While prior alignment work often highlights truthfulness or reasoning ability to demonstrate the side effects of representation steering, we find there are many unexplored tradeoffs not yet understood in a systematic way. We collect a dataset of safety-relevant primary and secondary behaviors to evaluate steering effectiveness and behavioral entanglement centered around five popular steering methods. To enable this, we craft a modular steering framework based on unique components that serve as the building blocks of many existing methods. Our results on Qwen-2.5-7B and Llama-3.1-8B find that strong steering performance is dependent on the specific combination of steering method, model, and targeted behavior, and that severe concept entanglement can result from poor combinations of these three as well. We release our code here: https://github.com/wang-research-lab/SteeringControl.git.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13450</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 18:36:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AERIS: Argonne Earth Systems Model for Reliable and Skillful Predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13523</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13523.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Väinö Hatanpää, Eugene Ku, Jason Stock, Murali Emani, Sam Foreman, Chunyong Jung, Sandeep Madireddy, Tung Nguyen, Varuni Sastry, Ray A. O. Sinurat, Sam Wheeler, Huihuo Zheng, Troy Arcomano, Venkatram Vishwanath, Rao Kotamarthi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative machine learning offers new opportunities to better understand complex Earth system dynamics. Recent diffusion-based methods address spectral biases and improve ensemble calibration in weather forecasting compared to deterministic methods, yet have so far proven difficult to scale stably at high resolutions. We introduce AERIS, a 1.3 to 80B parameter pixel-level Swin diffusion transformer to address this gap, and SWiPe, a generalizable technique that composes window parallelism with sequence and pipeline parallelism to shard window-based transformers without added communication cost or increased global batch size. On Aurora (10,080 nodes), AERIS sustains 10.21 ExaFLOPS (mixed precision) and a peak performance of 11.21 ExaFLOPS with 1 times 1 patch size on the 0.25{\deg} ERA5 dataset, achieving 95.5% weak scaling efficiency, and 81.6% strong scaling efficiency. AERIS outperforms the IFS ENS and remains stable on seasonal scales to 90 days, highlighting the potential of billion-parameter diffusion models for weather and climate prediction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13523</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 20:38:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM-I: LLMs are Naturally Interleaved Multimodal Creators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13642</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13642.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zirun Guo, Feng Zhang, Kai Jia, Tao Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose LLM-Interleaved (LLM-I), a flexible and dynamic framework that reframes interleaved image-text generation as a tool-use problem. LLM-I is designed to overcome the "one-tool" bottleneck of current unified models, which are limited to synthetic imagery and struggle with tasks requiring factual grounding or programmatic precision. Our framework empowers a central LLM or MLLM agent to intelligently orchestrate a diverse toolkit of specialized visual tools, including online image search, diffusion-based generation, code execution, and image editing. The agent is trained to select and apply these tools proficiently via a Reinforcement Learning (RL) framework that features a hybrid reward system combining rule-based logic with judgments from LLM and MLLM evaluators. Trained on a diverse new dataset using four different model backbones, LLM-I demonstrates state-of-the-art performance, outperforming existing methods by a large margin across four benchmarks. We also introduce a novel test-time scaling strategy that provides further performance gains. Project Page: https://github.com/ByteDance-BandAI/LLM-I.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13642</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 02:33:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Context Fidelity via Native Retrieval-Augmented Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13683</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13683.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Suyuchen Wang, Jinlin Wang, Xinyu Wang, Shiqi Li, Xiangru Tang, Sirui Hong, Xiao-Wen Chang, Chenglin Wu, Bang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) often struggle with context fidelity, producing inconsistent answers when responding to questions based on provided information. Existing approaches either rely on expensive supervised fine-tuning to generate evidence post-answer or train models to perform web searches without necessarily improving utilization of the given context. We propose CARE, a novel native retrieval-augmented reasoning framework that teaches LLMs to explicitly integrate in-context evidence within their reasoning process with the model's own retrieval capabilities. Our method requires limited labeled evidence data while significantly enhancing both retrieval accuracy and answer generation performance through strategically retrieved in-context tokens in the reasoning chain. Extensive experiments on multiple real-world and counterfactual QA benchmarks demonstrate that our approach substantially outperforms supervised fine-tuning, traditional retrieval-augmented generation methods, and external retrieval solutions. This work represents a fundamental advancement in making LLMs more accurate, reliable, and efficient for knowledge-intensive tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13683</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 04:28:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scrub It Out! Erasing Sensitive Memorization in Code Language Models via   Machine Unlearning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13755</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13755.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoyang Chu, Yao Wan, Zhikun Zhang, Di Wang, Zhou Yang, Hongyu Zhang, Pan Zhou, Xuanhua Shi, Hai Jin, David Lo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Code Language Models (CLMs) have demonstrated superior performance in software engineering tasks such as code generation and summarization, recent empirical studies reveal a critical privacy vulnerability: these models exhibit unintended memorization of sensitive training data, enabling verbatim reproduction of confidential information when specifically prompted. To address this issue, several approaches, including training data de-duplication and differential privacy augmentation, have been proposed. However, these methods require full-model retraining for deployed CLMs, which incurs substantial computational costs. In this paper, we aim to answer the following research question: Can sensitive information memorized by CLMs be erased effectively and efficiently?   We conduct a pioneering investigation into erasing sensitive memorization in CLMs through machine unlearning - a post-hoc modification method that removes specific information from trained models without requiring full retraining. Specifically, we first quantify the memorization risks of sensitive data within CLM training datasets and curate a high-risk dataset of 50,000 sensitive memorized samples as unlearning targets. We study two widely used gradient ascent-based unlearning approaches: the vanilla and constraint-based methods, and introduce CodeEraser, an advanced variant that selectively unlearns sensitive memorized segments in code while preserving the structural integrity and functional correctness of the surrounding code. Extensive experiments on three families of CLMs, i.e., CodeParrot, CodeGen-Mono, and Qwen2.5-Coder, validate the effectiveness and efficiency of CodeEraser in erasing targeted sensitive memorization while maintaining model utility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13755</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 07:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>THOR: Tool-Integrated Hierarchical Optimization via RL for Mathematical   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13761</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13761.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qikai Chang, Zhenrong Zhang, Pengfei Hu, Jiefeng Ma, Yicheng Pan, Jianshu Zhang, Jun Du, Quan Liu, Jianqing Gao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have made remarkable progress in mathematical reasoning, but still continue to struggle with high-precision tasks like numerical computation and formal symbolic manipulation. Integrating external tools has emerged as a promising approach to bridge this gap. Despite recent advances, existing methods struggle with three key challenges: constructing tool-integrated reasoning data, performing fine-grained optimization, and enhancing inference. To overcome these limitations, we propose THOR (Tool-Integrated Hierarchical Optimization via RL). First, we introduce TIRGen, a multi-agent actor-critic-based pipeline for constructing high-quality datasets of tool-integrated reasoning paths, aligning with the policy and generalizing well across diverse models. Second, to perform fine-grained hierarchical optimization, we introduce an RL strategy that jointly optimizes for both trajectory-level problem solving and step-level code generation. This is motivated by our key insight that the success of an intermediate tool call is a strong predictor of the final answer's correctness. Finally, THOR incorporates a self-correction mechanism that leverages immediate tool feedback to dynamically revise erroneous reasoning paths during inference. Our approach demonstrates strong generalization across diverse models, performing effectively in both reasoning and non-reasoning models. It further achieves state-of-the-art performance for models of a similar scale on multiple mathematical benchmarks, while also delivering consistent improvements on code benchmarks. Our code will be publicly available at https://github.com/JingMog/THOR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13761</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 07:16:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hala Technical Report: Building Arabic-Centric Instruction &amp; Translation   Models at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14008</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14008.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hasan Abed Al Kader Hammoud, Mohammad Zbeeb, Bernard Ghanem&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 81&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Hala, a family of Arabic-centric instruction and translation models built with our translate-and-tune pipeline. We first compress a strong ARleftrightarrowEN teacher to FP8 (yielding sim2times higher throughput with no quality loss) and use it to create high-fidelity bilingual supervision. A lightweight language model LFM2-1.2B is then fine-tuned on this data and used to translate high-quality English instruction sets into Arabic, producing a million-scale corpus tailored to instruction following. We train Hala models at 350M, 700M, 1.2B, and 9B parameters, and apply slerp merging to balance Arabic specialization with base-model strengths. On Arabic-centric benchmarks, Hala achieves state-of-the-art results within both the "nano" (leq2B) and "small" (7-9B) categories, outperforming their bases. We release models, data, evaluation, and recipes to accelerate research in Arabic NLP.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14008</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 14:19:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Variational Activation Functions Empower Kolmogorov-Arnold   Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14026</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14026.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiun-Cheng Jiang, Morris Yu-Chao Huang, Tianlong Chen, Hsi-Sheng Goan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Variational quantum circuits (VQCs) are central to quantum machine learning, while recent progress in Kolmogorov-Arnold networks (KANs) highlights the power of learnable activation functions. We unify these directions by introducing quantum variational activation functions (QVAFs), realized through single-qubit data re-uploading circuits called DatA Re-Uploading ActivatioNs (DARUANs). We show that DARUAN with trainable weights in data pre-processing possesses an exponentially growing frequency spectrum with data repetitions, enabling an exponential reduction in parameter size compared with Fourier-based activations without loss of expressivity. Embedding DARUAN into KANs yields quantum-inspired KANs (QKANs), which retain the interpretability of KANs while improving their parameter efficiency, expressivity, and generalization. We further introduce two novel techniques to enhance scalability, feasibility and computational efficiency, such as layer extension and hybrid QKANs (HQKANs) as drop-in replacements of multi-layer perceptrons (MLPs) for feed-forward networks in large-scale models. We provide theoretical analysis and extensive experiments on function regression, image classification, and autoregressive generative language modeling, demonstrating the efficiency and scalability of QKANs. DARUANs and QKANs offer a promising direction for advancing quantum machine learning on both noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) hardware and classical quantum simulators.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14026</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 14:28:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAIL-VL2 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14033</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14033.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weijie Yin, Yongjie Ye, Fangxun Shu, Yue Liao, Zijian Kang, Hongyuan Dong, Haiyang Yu, Dingkang Yang, Jiacong Wang, Han Wang, Wenzhuo Liu, Xiao Liang, Shuicheng Yan, Chao Feng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SAIL-VL2, an open-suite vision-language foundation model (LVM) for comprehensive multimodal understanding and reasoning. As the successor to SAIL-VL, SAIL-VL2 achieves state-of-the-art performance at the 2B and 8B parameter scales across diverse image and video benchmarks, demonstrating strong capabilities from fine-grained perception to complex reasoning. Three core innovations drive its effectiveness. First, a large-scale data curation pipeline with scoring and filtering strategies enhances both quality and distribution across captioning, OCR, QA, and video data, improving training efficiency. Second, a progressive training framework begins with a powerful pre-trained vision encoder (SAIL-ViT), advances through multimodal pre-training, and culminates in a thinking-fusion SFT-RL hybrid paradigm that systematically strengthens model capabilities. Third, architectural advances extend beyond dense LLMs to efficient sparse Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) designs. With these contributions, SAIL-VL2 demonstrates competitive performance across 106 datasets and achieves state-of-the-art results on challenging reasoning benchmarks such as MMMU and MathVista. Furthermore, on the OpenCompass leaderboard, SAIL-VL2-2B ranks first among officially released open-source models under the 4B parameter scale, while serving as an efficient and extensible foundation for the open-source multimodal community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14033</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 14:34:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wan-Animate: Unified Character Animation and Replacement with Holistic   Replication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14055</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14055.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gang Cheng, Xin Gao, Li Hu, Siqi Hu, Mingyang Huang, Chaonan Ji, Ju Li, Dechao Meng, Jinwei Qi, Penchong Qiao, Zhen Shen, Yafei Song, Ke Sun, Linrui Tian, Feng Wang, Guangyuan Wang, Qi Wang, Zhongjian Wang, Jiayu Xiao, Sheng Xu, Bang Zhang, Peng Zhang, Xindi Zhang, Zhe Zhang, Jingren Zhou, Lian Zhuo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Wan-Animate, a unified framework for character animation and replacement. Given a character image and a reference video, Wan-Animate can animate the character by precisely replicating the expressions and movements of the character in the video to generate high-fidelity character videos. Alternatively, it can integrate the animated character into the reference video to replace the original character, replicating the scene's lighting and color tone to achieve seamless environmental integration. Wan-Animate is built upon the Wan model. To adapt it for character animation tasks, we employ a modified input paradigm to differentiate between reference conditions and regions for generation. This design unifies multiple tasks into a common symbolic representation. We use spatially-aligned skeleton signals to replicate body motion and implicit facial features extracted from source images to reenact expressions, enabling the generation of character videos with high controllability and expressiveness. Furthermore, to enhance environmental integration during character replacement, we develop an auxiliary Relighting LoRA. This module preserves the character's appearance consistency while applying the appropriate environmental lighting and color tone. Experimental results demonstrate that Wan-Animate achieves state-of-the-art performance. We are committed to open-sourcing the model weights and its source code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14055</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 15:00:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MARS2 2025 Challenge on Multimodal Reasoning: Datasets, Methods,   Results, Discussion, and Outlook</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14142</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14142.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peng Xu, Shengwu Xiong, Jiajun Zhang, Yaxiong Chen, Bowen Zhou, Chen Change Loy, David A. Clifton, Kyoung Mu Lee, Luc Van Gool, Ruiming He, Ruilin Yao, Xinwei Long, Jirui Huang, Kai Tian, Sa Yang, Yihua Shao, Jin Feng, Yue Zhong, Jiakai Zhou, Cheng Tang, Tianyu Zou, Yifang Zhang, Junming Liang, Guoyou Li, Zhaoxiang Wang, Qiang Zhou, Yichen Zhao, Shili Xiong, Hyeongjin Nam, Jaerin Lee, Jaeyoung Chung, JoonKyu Park, Junghun Oh, Kanggeon Lee, Wooseok Lee, Juneyoung Ro, Turghun Osman, Can Hu, Chaoyang Liao, Cheng Chen, Chengcheng Han, Chenhao Qiu, Chong Peng, Cong Xu, Dailin Li, Feiyu Wang, Feng Gao, Guibo Zhu, Guopeng Tang, Haibo Lu, Han Fang, Han Qi, Hanxiao Wu, Haobo Cheng, Hongbo Sun, Hongyao Chen, Huayong Hu, Hui Li, Jiaheng Ma, Jiang Yu, Jianing Wang, Jie Yang, Jing He, Jinglin Zhou, Jingxuan Li, Josef Kittler, Lihao Zheng, Linnan Zhao, Mengxi Jia, Muyang Yan, Nguyen Thanh Thien, Pu Luo, Qi Li, Shien Song, Shijie Dong, Shuai Shao, Shutao Li, Taofeng Xue, Tianyang Xu, Tianyi Gao, Tingting Li, Wei Zhang, Weiyang Su, Xiaodong Dong, Xiao-Jun Wu, Xiaopeng Zhou, Xin Chen, Xin Wei, Xinyi You, Xudong Kang, Xujie Zhou, Xusheng Liu, Yanan Wang, Yanbin Huang, Yang Liu, Yang Yang, Yanglin Deng, Yashu Kang, Ye Yuan, Yi Wen, Yicen Tian, Yilin Tao, Yin Tang, Yipeng Lin, Yiqing Wang, Yiting Xi, Yongkang Yu, Yumei Li, Yuxin Qin, Yuying Chen, Yuzhe Cen, Zhaofan Zou, Zhaohong Liu, Zhehao Shen, Zhenglin Du, Zhengyang Li, Zhenni Huang, Zhenwei Shao, Zhilong Song, Zhiyong Feng, Zhiyu Wang, Zhou Yu, Ziang Li, Zihan Zhai, Zijian Zhang, Ziyang Peng, Ziyun Xiao, Zongshu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper reviews the MARS2 2025 Challenge on Multimodal Reasoning. We aim to bring together different approaches in multimodal machine learning and LLMs via a large benchmark. We hope it better allows researchers to follow the state-of-the-art in this very dynamic area. Meanwhile, a growing number of testbeds have boosted the evolution of general-purpose large language models. Thus, this year's MARS2 focuses on real-world and specialized scenarios to broaden the multimodal reasoning applications of MLLMs. Our organizing team released two tailored datasets Lens and AdsQA as test sets, which support general reasoning in 12 daily scenarios and domain-specific reasoning in advertisement videos, respectively. We evaluated 40+ baselines that include both generalist MLLMs and task-specific models, and opened up three competition tracks, i.e., Visual Grounding in Real-world Scenarios (VG-RS), Visual Question Answering with Spatial Awareness (VQA-SA), and Visual Reasoning in Creative Advertisement Videos (VR-Ads). Finally, 76 teams from the renowned academic and industrial institutions have registered and 40+ valid submissions (out of 1200+) have been included in our ranking lists. Our datasets, code sets (40+ baselines and 15+ participants' methods), and rankings are publicly available on the MARS2 workshop website and our GitHub organization page https://github.com/mars2workshop/, where our updates and announcements of upcoming events will be continuously provided.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14142</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 16:21:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesizing Behaviorally-Grounded Reasoning Chains: A Data-Generation   Framework for Personal Finance LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14180</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14180.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Akhil Theerthala&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Personalized financial advice requires consideration of user goals, constraints, risk tolerance, and jurisdiction. Prior LLM work has focused on support systems for investors and financial planners. Simultaneously, numerous recent studies examine broader personal finance tasks, including budgeting, debt management, retirement, and estate planning, through agentic pipelines that incur high maintenance costs, yielding less than 25% of their expected financial returns. In this study, we introduce a novel and reproducible framework that integrates relevant financial context with behavioral finance studies to construct supervision data for end-to-end advisors. Using this framework, we create a 19k sample reasoning dataset and conduct a comprehensive fine-tuning of the Qwen-3-8B model on the dataset. Through a held-out test split and a blind LLM-jury study, we demonstrate that through careful data curation and behavioral integration, our 8B model achieves performance comparable to significantly larger baselines (14-32B parameters) across factual accuracy, fluency, and personalization metrics while incurring 80% lower costs than the larger counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14180</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 17:12:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GenExam: A Multidisciplinary Text-to-Image Exam</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14232</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14232.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaokai Wang, Penghao Yin, Xiangyu Zhao, Changyao Tian, Yu Qiao, Wenhai Wang, Jifeng Dai, Gen Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Exams are a fundamental test of expert-level intelligence and require integrated understanding, reasoning, and generation. Existing exam-style benchmarks mainly focus on understanding and reasoning tasks, and current generation benchmarks emphasize the illustration of world knowledge and visual concepts, neglecting the evaluation of rigorous drawing exams. We introduce GenExam, the first benchmark for multidisciplinary text-to-image exams, featuring 1,000 samples across 10 subjects with exam-style prompts organized under a four-level taxonomy. Each problem is equipped with ground-truth images and fine-grained scoring points to enable a precise evaluation of semantic correctness and visual plausibility. Experiments show that even state-of-the-art models such as GPT-Image-1 and Gemini-2.5-Flash-Image achieve less than 15% strict scores, and most models yield almost 0%, suggesting the great challenge of our benchmark. By framing image generation as an exam, GenExam offers a rigorous assessment of models' ability to integrate knowledge, reasoning, and generation, providing insights on the path to general AGI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14232</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 17:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apertus: Democratizing Open and Compliant LLMs for Global Language   Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14233</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14233.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alejandro Hernández-Cano, Alexander Hägele, Allen Hao Huang, Angelika Romanou, Antoni-Joan Solergibert, Barna Pasztor, Bettina Messmer, Dhia Garbaya, Eduard Frank Ďurech, Ido Hakimi, Juan García Giraldo, Mete Ismayilzada, Negar Foroutan, Skander Moalla, Tiancheng Chen, Vinko Sabolčec, Yixuan Xu, Michael Aerni, Badr AlKhamissi, Ines Altemir Marinas, Mohammad Hossein Amani, Matin Ansaripour, Ilia Badanin, Harold Benoit, Emanuela Boros, Nicholas Browning, Fabian Bösch, Maximilian Böther, Niklas Canova, Camille Challier, Clement Charmillot, Jonathan Coles, Jan Deriu, Arnout Devos, Lukas Drescher, Daniil Dzenhaliou, Maud Ehrmann, Dongyang Fan, Simin Fan, Silin Gao, Miguel Gila, María Grandury, Diba Hashemi, Alexander Hoyle, Jiaming Jiang, Mark Klein, Andrei Kucharavy, Anastasiia Kucherenko, Frederike Lübeck, Roman Machacek, Theofilos Manitaras, Andreas Marfurt, Kyle Matoba, Simon Matrenok, Henrique Mendoncça, Fawzi Roberto Mohamed, Syrielle Montariol, Luca Mouchel, Sven Najem-Meyer, Jingwei Ni, Gennaro Oliva, Matteo Pagliardini, Elia Palme, Andrei Panferov, Léo Paoletti, Marco Passerini, Ivan Pavlov, Auguste Poiroux, Kaustubh Ponkshe, Nathan Ranchin, Javi Rando, Mathieu Sauser, Jakhongir Saydaliev, Muhammad Ali Sayfiddinov, Marian Schneider, Stefano Schuppli, Marco Scialanga, Andrei Semenov, Kumar Shridhar, Raghav Singhal, Anna Sotnikova, Alexander Sternfeld, Ayush Kumar Tarun, Paul Teiletche, Jannis Vamvas, Xiaozhe Yao, Hao Zhao Alexander Ilic, Ana Klimovic, Andreas Krause, Caglar Gulcehre, David Rosenthal, Elliott Ash, Florian Tramèr, Joost VandeVondele, Livio Veraldi, Martin Rajman, Thomas Schulthess, Torsten Hoefler, Antoine Bosselut, Martin Jaggi, Imanol Schlag&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Apertus, a fully open suite of large language models (LLMs) designed to address two systemic shortcomings in today's open model ecosystem: data compliance and multilingual representation. Unlike many prior models that release weights without reproducible data pipelines or regard for content-owner rights, Apertus models are pretrained exclusively on openly available data, retroactively respecting robots.txt exclusions and filtering for non-permissive, toxic, and personally identifiable content. To mitigate risks of memorization, we adopt the Goldfish objective during pretraining, strongly suppressing verbatim recall of data while retaining downstream task performance. The Apertus models also expand multilingual coverage, training on 15T tokens from over 1800 languages, with ~40% of pretraining data allocated to non-English content. Released at 8B and 70B scales, Apertus approaches state-of-the-art results among fully open models on multilingual benchmarks, rivalling or surpassing open-weight counterparts. Beyond model weights, we release all scientific artifacts from our development cycle with a permissive license, including data preparation scripts, checkpoints, evaluation suites, and training code, enabling transparent audit and extension.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14233</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 17:59:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AToken: A Unified Tokenizer for Vision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14476</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14476.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiasen Lu, Liangchen Song, Mingze Xu, Byeongjoo Ahn, Yanjun Wang, Chen Chen, Afshin Dehghan, Yinfei Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present AToken, the first unified visual tokenizer that achieves both high-fidelity reconstruction and semantic understanding across images, videos, and 3D assets. Unlike existing tokenizers that specialize in either reconstruction or understanding for single modalities, AToken encodes these diverse visual inputs into a shared 4D latent space, unifying both tasks and modalities in a single framework. Specifically, we introduce a pure transformer architecture with 4D rotary position embeddings to process visual inputs of arbitrary resolutions and temporal durations. To ensure stable training, we introduce an adversarial-free training objective that combines perceptual and Gram matrix losses, achieving state-of-the-art reconstruction quality. By employing a progressive training curriculum, AToken gradually expands from single images, videos, and 3D, and supports both continuous and discrete latent tokens. AToken achieves 0.21 rFID with 82.2% ImageNet accuracy for images, 3.01 rFVD with 32.6% MSRVTT retrieval for videos, and 28.19 PSNR with 90.9% classification accuracy for 3D. In downstream applications, AToken enables both visual generation tasks (e.g., image generation with continuous and discrete tokens, text-to-video generation, image-to-3D synthesis) and understanding tasks (e.g., multimodal LLMs), achieving competitive performance across all benchmarks. These results shed light on the next-generation multimodal AI systems built upon unified visual tokenization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14476</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 23:11:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MultiEdit: Advancing Instruction-based Image Editing on Diverse and   Challenging Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14638</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14638.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingsong Li, Lin Liu, Hongjun Wang, Haoxing Chen, Xijun Gu, Shizhan Liu, Dong Gong, Junbo Zhao, Zhenzhong Lan, Jianguo Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current instruction-based image editing (IBIE) methods struggle with challenging editing tasks, as both editing types and sample counts of existing datasets are limited. Moreover, traditional dataset construction often contains noisy image-caption pairs, which may introduce biases and limit model capabilities in complex editing scenarios. To address these limitations, we introduce MultiEdit, a comprehensive dataset featuring over 107K high-quality image editing samples. It encompasses 6 challenging editing tasks through a diverse collection of 18 non-style-transfer editing types and 38 style transfer operations, covering a spectrum from sophisticated style transfer to complex semantic operations like person reference editing and in-image text editing. We employ a novel dataset construction pipeline that utilizes two multi-modal large language models (MLLMs) to generate visual-adaptive editing instructions and produce high-fidelity edited images, respectively. Extensive experiments demonstrate that fine-tuning foundational open-source models with our MultiEdit-Train set substantially improves models' performance on sophisticated editing tasks in our proposed MultiEdit-Test benchmark, while effectively preserving their capabilities on the standard editing benchmark. We believe MultiEdit provides a valuable resource for advancing research into more diverse and challenging IBIE capabilities. Our dataset is available at https://huggingface.co/datasets/inclusionAI/MultiEdit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14638</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 05:33:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning over Boundaries: Enhancing Specification Alignment via   Test-time Delibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14760</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14760.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran Zhang, Yafu Li, Xuyang Hu, Dongrui Liu, Zhilin Wang, Bo Li, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly applied in diverse real-world scenarios, each governed by bespoke behavioral and safety specifications (spec) custom-tailored by users or organizations. These spec, categorized into safety-spec and behavioral-spec, vary across scenarios and evolve with changing preferences and requirements. We formalize this challenge as specification alignment, focusing on LLMs' ability to follow dynamic, scenario-specific spec from both behavioral and safety perspectives. To address this challenge, we propose Align3, a lightweight method that employs Test-Time Deliberation (TTD) with hierarchical reflection and revision to reason over the specification boundaries. We further present SpecBench, a unified benchmark for measuring specification alignment, covering 5 scenarios, 103 spec, and 1,500 prompts. Experiments on 15 reasoning and 18 instruct models with several TTD methods, including Self-Refine, TPO, and MoreThink, yield three key findings: (i) test-time deliberation enhances specification alignment; (ii) Align3 advances the safety-helpfulness trade-off frontier with minimal overhead; (iii) SpecBench effectively reveals alignment gaps. These results highlight the potential of test-time deliberation as an effective strategy for reasoning over the real-world specification boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14760</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 09:08:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EchoVLM: Dynamic Mixture-of-Experts Vision-Language Model for Universal   Ultrasound Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14977</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14977.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaoyin She, Ruifang Lu, Lida Chen, Wei Wang, Qinghua Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Ultrasound imaging has become the preferred imaging modality for early cancer screening due to its advantages of non-ionizing radiation, low cost, and real-time imaging capabilities. However, conventional ultrasound diagnosis heavily relies on physician expertise, presenting challenges of high subjectivity and low diagnostic efficiency. Vision-language models (VLMs) offer promising solutions for this issue, but existing general-purpose models demonstrate limited knowledge in ultrasound medical tasks, with poor generalization in multi-organ lesion recognition and low efficiency across multi-task diagnostics. To address these limitations, we propose EchoVLM, a vision-language model specifically designed for ultrasound medical imaging. The model employs a Mixture of Experts (MoE) architecture trained on data spanning seven anatomical regions. This design enables the model to perform multiple tasks, including ultrasound report generation, diagnosis and visual question-answering (VQA). The experimental results demonstrated that EchoVLM achieved significant improvements of 10.15 and 4.77 points in BLEU-1 scores and ROUGE-1 scores respectively compared to Qwen2-VL on the ultrasound report generation task. These findings suggest that EchoVLM has substantial potential to enhance diagnostic accuracy in ultrasound imaging, thereby providing a viable technical solution for future clinical applications. Source code and model weights are available at https://github.com/Asunatan/EchoVLM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14977</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 14:07:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mind the Gap: A Closer Look at Tokenization for Multiple-Choice Question   Answering with LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15020</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15020.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mario Sanz-Guerrero, Minh Duc Bui, Katharina von der Wense&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; When evaluating large language models (LLMs) with multiple-choice question answering (MCQA), it is common to end the prompt with the string "Answer:" to facilitate automated answer extraction via next-token probabilities. However, there is no consensus on how to tokenize the space following the colon, often overlooked as a trivial choice. In this paper, we uncover accuracy differences of up to 11% due to this (seemingly irrelevant) tokenization variation as well as reshuffled model rankings, raising concerns about the reliability of LLM comparisons in prior work. Surprisingly, we are able to recommend one specific strategy -- tokenizing the space together with the answer letter -- as we observe consistent and statistically significant performance improvements. Additionally, it improves model calibration, enhancing the reliability of the model's confidence estimates. Our findings underscore the importance of careful evaluation design and highlight the need for standardized, transparent evaluation protocols to ensure reliable and comparable results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15020</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 14:47:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WorldForge: Unlocking Emergent 3D/4D Generation in Video Diffusion Model   via Training-Free Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15130</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15130.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenxi Song, Yanming Yang, Tong Zhao, Ruibo Li, Chi Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent video diffusion models demonstrate strong potential in spatial intelligence tasks due to their rich latent world priors. However, this potential is hindered by their limited controllability and geometric inconsistency, creating a gap between their strong priors and their practical use in 3D/4D tasks. As a result, current approaches often rely on retraining or fine-tuning, which risks degrading pretrained knowledge and incurs high computational costs. To address this, we propose WorldForge, a training-free, inference-time framework composed of three tightly coupled modules. Intra-Step Recursive Refinement introduces a recursive refinement mechanism during inference, which repeatedly optimizes network predictions within each denoising step to enable precise trajectory injection. Flow-Gated Latent Fusion leverages optical flow similarity to decouple motion from appearance in the latent space and selectively inject trajectory guidance into motion-related channels. Dual-Path Self-Corrective Guidance compares guided and unguided denoising paths to adaptively correct trajectory drift caused by noisy or misaligned structural signals. Together, these components inject fine-grained, trajectory-aligned guidance without training, achieving both accurate motion control and photorealistic content generation. Extensive experiments across diverse benchmarks validate our method's superiority in realism, trajectory consistency, and visual fidelity. This work introduces a novel plug-and-play paradigm for controllable video synthesis, offering a new perspective on leveraging generative priors for spatial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15130</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 16:40:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unleashing the Potential of Multimodal LLMs for Zero-Shot   Spatio-Temporal Video Grounding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15178</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15178.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zaiquan Yang, Yuhao Liu, Gerhard Hancke, Rynson W. H. Lau&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatio-temporal video grounding (STVG) aims at localizing the spatio-temporal tube of a video, as specified by the input text query. In this paper, we utilize multimodal large language models (MLLMs) to explore a zero-shot solution in STVG. We reveal two key insights about MLLMs: (1) MLLMs tend to dynamically assign special tokens, referred to as grounding tokens, for grounding the text query; and (2) MLLMs often suffer from suboptimal grounding due to the inability to fully integrate the cues in the text query (e.g., attributes, actions) for inference. Based on these insights, we propose a MLLM-based zero-shot framework for STVG, which includes novel decomposed spatio-temporal highlighting (DSTH) and temporal-augmented assembling (TAS) strategies to unleash the reasoning ability of MLLMs. The DSTH strategy first decouples the original query into attribute and action sub-queries for inquiring the existence of the target both spatially and temporally. It then uses a novel logit-guided re-attention (LRA) module to learn latent variables as spatial and temporal prompts, by regularizing token predictions for each sub-query. These prompts highlight attribute and action cues, respectively, directing the model's attention to reliable spatial and temporal related visual regions. In addition, as the spatial grounding by the attribute sub-query should be temporally consistent, we introduce the TAS strategy to assemble the predictions using the original video frames and the temporal-augmented frames as inputs to help improve temporal consistency. We evaluate our method on various MLLMs, and show that it outperforms SOTA methods on three common STVG benchmarks.   The code will be available at https://github.com/zaiquanyang/LLaVA_Next_STVG.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15178</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 17:35:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understand Before You Generate: Self-Guided Training for Autoregressive   Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15185</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15185.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoyu Yue, Zidong Wang, Yuqing Wang, Wenlong Zhang, Xihui Liu, Wanli Ouyang, Lei Bai, Luping Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have demonstrated the importance of high-quality visual representations in image generation and have highlighted the limitations of generative models in image understanding. As a generative paradigm originally designed for natural language, autoregressive models face similar challenges. In this work, we present the first systematic investigation into the mechanisms of applying the next-token prediction paradigm to the visual domain. We identify three key properties that hinder the learning of high-level visual semantics: local and conditional dependence, inter-step semantic inconsistency, and spatial invariance deficiency. We show that these issues can be effectively addressed by introducing self-supervised objectives during training, leading to a novel training framework, Self-guided Training for AutoRegressive models (ST-AR). Without relying on pre-trained representation models, ST-AR significantly enhances the image understanding ability of autoregressive models and leads to improved generation quality. Specifically, ST-AR brings approximately 42% FID improvement for LlamaGen-L and 49% FID improvement for LlamaGen-XL, while maintaining the same sampling strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15185</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 17:47:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolving Language Models without Labels: Majority Drives Selection,   Novelty Promotes Variation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15194</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15194.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yujun Zhou, Zhenwen Liang, Haolin Liu, Wenhao Yu, Kishan Panaganti, Linfeng Song, Dian Yu, Xiangliang Zhang, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly trained with reinforcement learning from verifiable rewards (RLVR), yet real-world deployment demands models that can self-improve without labels or external judges. Existing label-free methods, confidence minimization, self-consistency, or majority-vote objectives, stabilize learning but steadily shrink exploration, causing an entropy collapse: generations become shorter, less diverse, and brittle. Unlike prior approaches such as Test-Time Reinforcement Learning (TTRL), which primarily adapt models to the immediate unlabeled dataset at hand, our goal is broader: to enable general improvements without sacrificing the model's inherent exploration capacity and generalization ability, i.e., evolving. We formalize this issue and propose EVolution-Oriented and Label-free Reinforcement Learning (EVOL-RL), a simple rule that couples stability with variation under a label-free setting. EVOL-RL keeps the majority-voted answer as a stable anchor (selection) while adding a novelty-aware reward that favors responses whose reasoning differs from what has already been produced (variation), measured in semantic space. Implemented with GRPO, EVOL-RL also uses asymmetric clipping to preserve strong signals and an entropy regularizer to sustain search. This majority-for-selection + novelty-for-variation design prevents collapse, maintains longer and more informative chains of thought, and improves both pass@1 and pass@n. EVOL-RL consistently outperforms the majority-only TTRL baseline; e.g., training on label-free AIME24 lifts Qwen3-4B-Base AIME25 pass@1 from TTRL's 4.6% to 16.4%, and pass@16 from 18.5% to 37.9%. EVOL-RL not only prevents diversity collapse but also unlocks stronger generalization across domains (e.g., GPQA). Furthermore, we demonstrate that EVOL-RL also boosts performance in the RLVR setting, highlighting its broad applicability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15194</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 17:50:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlowRL: Matching Reward Distributions for LLM Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15207</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15207.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuekai Zhu, Daixuan Cheng, Dinghuai Zhang, Hengli Li, Kaiyan Zhang, Che Jiang, Youbang Sun, Ermo Hua, Yuxin Zuo, Xingtai Lv, Qizheng Zhang, Lin Chen, Fanghao Shao, Bo Xue, Yunchong Song, Zhenjie Yang, Ganqu Cui, Ning Ding, Jianfeng Gao, Xiaodong Liu, Bowen Zhou, Hongyuan Mei, Zhouhan Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 85&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose FlowRL: matching the full reward distribution via flow balancing instead of maximizing rewards in large language model (LLM) reinforcement learning (RL). Recent advanced reasoning models adopt reward-maximizing methods (\eg, PPO and GRPO), which tend to over-optimize dominant reward signals while neglecting less frequent but valid reasoning paths, thus reducing diversity. In contrast, we transform scalar rewards into a normalized target distribution using a learnable partition function, and then minimize the reverse KL divergence between the policy and the target distribution. We implement this idea as a flow-balanced optimization method that promotes diverse exploration and generalizable reasoning trajectories. We conduct experiments on math and code reasoning tasks: FlowRL achieves a significant average improvement of 10.0% over GRPO and 5.1% over PPO on math benchmarks, and performs consistently better on code reasoning tasks. These results highlight reward distribution-matching as a key step toward efficient exploration and diverse reasoning in LLM reinforcement learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15207</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 17:56:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RynnVLA-001: Using Human Demonstrations to Improve Robot Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15212</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15212.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuming Jiang, Siteng Huang, Shengke Xue, Yaxi Zhao, Jun Cen, Sicong Leng, Kehan Li, Jiayan Guo, Kexiang Wang, Mingxiu Chen, Fan Wang, Deli Zhao, Xin Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents RynnVLA-001, a vision-language-action(VLA) model built upon large-scale video generative pretraining from human demonstrations. We propose a novel two-stage pretraining methodology. The first stage, Ego-Centric Video Generative Pretraining, trains an Image-to-Video model on 12M ego-centric manipulation videos to predict future frames conditioned on an initial frame and a language instruction. The second stage, Human-Centric Trajectory-Aware Modeling, extends this by jointly predicting future keypoint trajectories, thereby effectively bridging visual frame prediction with action prediction. Furthermore, to enhance action representation, we propose ActionVAE, a variational autoencoder that compresses sequences of actions into compact latent embeddings, reducing the complexity of the VLA output space. When finetuned on the same downstream robotics datasets, RynnVLA-001 achieves superior performance over state-of-the-art baselines, demonstrating that the proposed pretraining strategy provides a more effective initialization for VLA models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15212</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 17:58:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ScaleCUA: Scaling Open-Source Computer Use Agents with Cross-Platform   Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15221</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15221.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoyang Liu, JingJing Xie, Zichen Ding, Zehao Li, Bowen Yang, Zhenyu Wu, Xuehui Wang, Qiushi Sun, Shi Liu, Weiyun Wang, Shenglong Ye, Qingyun Li, Zeyue Tian, Gen Luo, Xiangyu Yue, Biqing Qi, Kai Chen, Bowen Zhou, Yu Qiao, Qifeng Chen, Wenhai Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 93&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language Models (VLMs) have enabled computer use agents (CUAs) that operate GUIs autonomously, showing great potential, yet progress is limited by the lack of large-scale, open-source computer use data and foundation models. In this work, we introduce ScaleCUA, a step toward scaling open-source CUAs. It offers a large-scale dataset spanning 6 operating systems and 3 task domains, built via a closed-loop pipeline uniting automated agents with human experts. Trained on this scaled-up data, ScaleCUA can operate seamlessly across platforms. Specifically, it delivers strong gains over baselines (+26.6 on WebArena-Lite-v2, +10.7 on ScreenSpot-Pro) and sets new state-of-the-art results (94.4% on MMBench-GUI L1-Hard, 60.6% on OSWorld-G, 47.4% on WebArena-Lite-v2). These findings underscore the power of data-driven scaling for general-purpose computer use agents. We will release data, models, and code to advance future research: https://github.com/OpenGVLab/ScaleCUA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15221</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 17:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
