<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 00:12:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Map the Flow: Revealing Hidden Pathways of Information in VideoLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13251</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.13251.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minji Kim, Taekyung Kim, Bohyung Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video Large Language Models (VideoLLMs) extend the capabilities of vision-language models to spatiotemporal inputs, enabling tasks such as video question answering (VideoQA). Despite recent advances in VideoLLMs, their internal mechanisms on where and how they extract and propagate video and textual information remain less explored. In this study, we investigate the internal information flow of VideoLLMs using mechanistic interpretability techniques. Our analysis reveals consistent patterns across diverse VideoQA tasks: (1) temporal reasoning in VideoLLMs initiates with active cross-frame interactions in early-to-middle layers, (2) followed by progressive video-language integration in middle layers. This is facilitated by alignment between video representations and linguistic embeddings containing temporal concepts. (3) Upon completion of this integration, the model is ready to generate correct answers in middle-to-late layers. (4) Based on our analysis, we show that VideoLLMs can retain their VideoQA performance by selecting these effective information pathways while suppressing a substantial amount of attention edges, e.g., 58% in LLaVA-NeXT-7B-Video-FT. These findings provide a blueprint on how VideoLLMs perform temporal reasoning and offer practical insights for improving model interpretability and downstream generalization. Our project page with the source code is available at https://map-the-flow.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.13251</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 07:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning with Sampling: Your Base Model is Smarter Than You Think</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14901</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.14901.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aayush Karan, Yilun Du&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Frontier reasoning models have exhibited incredible capabilities across a wide array of disciplines, driven by posttraining large language models (LLMs) with reinforcement learning (RL). However, despite the widespread success of this paradigm, much of the literature has been devoted to disentangling truly novel behaviors that emerge during RL but are not present in the base models. In our work, we approach this question from a different angle, instead asking whether comparable reasoning capabilites can be elicited from base models at inference time by pure sampling, without any additional training. Inspired by Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) techniques for sampling from sharpened distributions, we propose a simple iterative sampling algorithm leveraging the base models' own likelihoods. Over different base models, we show that our algorithm offers substantial boosts in reasoning that nearly match and even outperform those from RL on a wide variety of single-shot tasks, including MATH500, HumanEval, and GPQA. Moreover, our sampler avoids the collapse in diversity over multiple samples that is characteristic of RL-posttraining. Crucially, our method does not require training, curated datasets, or a verifier, suggesting broad applicability beyond easily verifiable domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14901</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 17:18:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Conditions for Diffusion models in Robotic Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15510</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.15510.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Heeseong Shin, Byeongho Heo, Dongyoon Han, Seungryong Kim, Taekyung Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While pre-trained visual representations have significantly advanced imitation learning, they are often task-agnostic as they remain frozen during policy learning. In this work, we explore leveraging pre-trained text-to-image diffusion models to obtain task-adaptive visual representations for robotic control, without fine-tuning the model itself. However, we find that naively applying textual conditions - a successful strategy in other vision domains - yields minimal or even negative gains in control tasks. We attribute this to the domain gap between the diffusion model's training data and robotic control environments, leading us to argue for conditions that consider the specific, dynamic visual information required for control. To this end, we propose ORCA, which introduces learnable task prompts that adapt to the control environment and visual prompts that capture fine-grained, frame-specific details. Through facilitating task-adaptive representations with our newly devised conditions, our approach achieves state-of-the-art performance on various robotic control benchmarks, significantly surpassing prior methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15510</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 10:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Spatial to Actions: Grounding Vision-Language-Action Model in   Spatial Foundation Priors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17439</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.17439.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengshen Zhang, Hao Li, Yalun Dai, Zhengbang Zhu, Lei Zhou, Chenchen Liu, Dong Wang, Francis E. H. Tay, Sijin Chen, Ziwei Liu, Yuxiao Liu, Xinghang Li, Pan Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing vision-language-action (VLA) models act in 3D real-world but are typically built on 2D encoders, leaving a spatial reasoning gap that limits generalization and adaptability. Recent 3D integration techniques for VLAs either require specialized sensors and transfer poorly across modalities, or inject weak cues that lack geometry and degrade vision-language alignment. In this work, we introduce FALCON (From Spatial to Action), a novel paradigm that injects rich 3D spatial tokens into the action head. FALCON leverages spatial foundation models to deliver strong geometric priors from RGB alone, and includes an Embodied Spatial Model that can optionally fuse depth, or pose for higher fidelity when available, without retraining or architectural changes. To preserve language reasoning, spatial tokens are consumed by a Spatial-Enhanced Action Head rather than being concatenated into the vision-language backbone. These designs enable FALCON to address limitations in spatial representation, modality transferability, and alignment. In comprehensive evaluations across three simulation benchmarks and eleven real-world tasks, our proposed FALCON achieves state-of-the-art performance, consistently surpasses competitive baselines, and remains robust under clutter, spatial-prompt conditioning, and variations in object scale and height.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17439</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 11:26:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Definition of AGI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18212</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.18212.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dan Hendrycks, Dawn Song, Christian Szegedy, Honglak Lee, Yarin Gal, Erik Brynjolfsson, Sharon Li, Andy Zou, Lionel Levine, Bo Han, Jie Fu, Ziwei Liu, Jinwoo Shin, Kimin Lee, Mantas Mazeika, Long Phan, George Ingebretsen, Adam Khoja, Cihang Xie, Olawale Salaudeen, Matthias Hein, Kevin Zhao, Alexander Pan, David Duvenaud, Bo Li, Steve Omohundro, Gabriel Alfour, Max Tegmark, Kevin McGrew, Gary Marcus, Jaan Tallinn, Eric Schmidt, Yoshua Bengio&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The lack of a concrete definition for Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) obscures the gap between today's specialized AI and human-level cognition. This paper introduces a quantifiable framework to address this, defining AGI as matching the cognitive versatility and proficiency of a well-educated adult. To operationalize this, we ground our methodology in Cattell-Horn-Carroll theory, the most empirically validated model of human cognition. The framework dissects general intelligence into ten core cognitive domains-including reasoning, memory, and perception-and adapts established human psychometric batteries to evaluate AI systems. Application of this framework reveals a highly "jagged" cognitive profile in contemporary models. While proficient in knowledge-intensive domains, current AI systems have critical deficits in foundational cognitive machinery, particularly long-term memory storage. The resulting AGI scores (e.g., GPT-4 at 27%, GPT-5 at 58%) concretely quantify both rapid progress and the substantial gap remaining before AGI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18212</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 01:28:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChronoPlay: A Framework for Modeling Dual Dynamics and Authenticity in   Game RAG Benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18455</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.18455.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liyang He, Yuren Zhang, Ziwei Zhu, Zhenghui Li, Shiwei Tong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval Augmented Generation (RAG) systems are increasingly vital in dynamic domains like online gaming, yet the lack of a dedicated benchmark has impeded standardized evaluation in this area. The core difficulty lies in Dual Dynamics: the constant interplay between game content updates and the shifting focus of the player community. Furthermore, the necessity of automating such a benchmark introduces a critical requirement for player-centric authenticity to ensure generated questions are realistic. To address this integrated challenge, we introduce ChronoPlay, a novel framework for the automated and continuous generation of game RAG benchmarks. ChronoPlay utilizes a dual-dynamic update mechanism to track both forms of change, and a dual-source synthesis engine that draws from official sources and player community to ensure both factual correctness and authentic query patterns. We instantiate our framework on three distinct games to create the first dynamic RAG benchmark for the gaming domain, offering new insights into model performance under these complex and realistic conditions. Code is avaliable at: https://github.com/hly1998/ChronoPlay.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18455</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 09:28:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Language Model Inference Serving Unveiled: An Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18672</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.18672.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qi Li, Junpan Wu, Xiang Liu, Yuxin Wang, Zeyu Li, Zhenheng Tang, Yuhan Chen, Shaohuai Shi, Xiaowen Chu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The reasoning large language model (RLLM) has been proven competitive in solving complex reasoning tasks such as mathematics, coding, compared to general LLM. However, the serving performance and behavior of RLLM remains unexplored, which may undermine the deployment and utilization of RLLM in real-world scenario. To close this gap, in this paper, we conduct a comprehensive study of RLLM service. We first perform a pilot study on comparing the serving performance between RLLM and traditional LLM and reveal that there are several distinct differences regarding serving behavior: (1) significant memory usage and fluctuations; (2) straggler requests; (3) adaptive running time; (4) domain preference. Then we further investigate whether existing inference optimization techniques are valid for RLLM. Our main takeaways are that model quantization methods and speculative decoding can improve service system efficiency with small compromise to RLLM accuracy, while prefix caching, KV cache quantization may even degrade accuracy or serving performance for small RLLM. Lastly, we conduct evaluation under real world workload modeled by Gamma distribution to verify our findings. Empirical results of real world workload evaluation across different dataset are aligned with our main findings regarding RLLM serving. We hope our work can provide the research community and industry with insights to advance RLLM inference serving.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18672</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 14:25:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VITA-E: Natural Embodied Interaction with Concurrent Seeing, Hearing,   Speaking, and Acting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21817</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21817.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoyu Liu, Chaoyou Fu, Chi Yan, Chu Wu, Haihan Gao, Yi-Fan Zhang, Shaoqi Dong, Cheng Qian, Bin Luo, Xiuyong Yang, Guanwu Li, Yusheng Cai, Yunhang Shen, Deqiang Jiang, Haoyu Cao, Xing Sun, Caifeng Shan, Ran He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models are often constrained by a rigid, static interaction paradigm, which lacks the ability to see, hear, speak, and act concurrently as well as handle real-time user interruptions dynamically. This hinders seamless embodied collaboration, resulting in an inflexible and unresponsive user experience. To address these limitations, we introduce VITA-E, a novel embodied interaction framework designed for both behavioral concurrency and nearly real-time interruption. The core of our approach is a dual-model architecture where two parallel VLA instances operate as an ``Active Model'' and a ``Standby Model'', allowing the embodied agent to observe its environment, listen to user speech, provide verbal responses, and execute actions, all concurrently and interruptibly, mimicking human-like multitasking capabilities. We further propose a ``model-as-controller'' paradigm, where we fine-tune the VLM to generate special tokens that serve as direct system-level commands, coupling the model's reasoning with the system's behavior. Experiments conducted on a physical humanoid platform demonstrate that VITA-E can reliably handle complex interactive scenarios. Our framework is compatible with various dual-system VLA models, achieving an extremely high success rate on emergency stops and speech interruptions while also successfully performing concurrent speech and action. This represents a significant step towards more natural and capable embodied assistants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21817</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Driving World Model as Synthetic Data Generator for   Perception Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19195</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.19195.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kai Zeng, Zhanqian Wu, Kaixin Xiong, Xiaobao Wei, Xiangyu Guo, Zhenxin Zhu, Kalok Ho, Lijun Zhou, Bohan Zeng, Ming Lu, Haiyang Sun, Bing Wang, Guang Chen, Hangjun Ye, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in driving world models enable controllable generation of high-quality RGB videos or multimodal videos. Existing methods primarily focus on metrics related to generation quality and controllability. However, they often overlook the evaluation of downstream perception tasks, which are really crucial for the performance of autonomous driving. Existing methods usually leverage a training strategy that first pretrains on synthetic data and finetunes on real data, resulting in twice the epochs compared to the baseline (real data only). When we double the epochs in the baseline, the benefit of synthetic data becomes negligible. To thoroughly demonstrate the benefit of synthetic data, we introduce Dream4Drive, a novel synthetic data generation framework designed for enhancing the downstream perception tasks. Dream4Drive first decomposes the input video into several 3D-aware guidance maps and subsequently renders the 3D assets onto these guidance maps. Finally, the driving world model is fine-tuned to produce the edited, multi-view photorealistic videos, which can be used to train the downstream perception models. Dream4Drive enables unprecedented flexibility in generating multi-view corner cases at scale, significantly boosting corner case perception in autonomous driving. To facilitate future research, we also contribute a large-scale 3D asset dataset named DriveObj3D, covering the typical categories in driving scenarios and enabling diverse 3D-aware video editing. We conduct comprehensive experiments to show that Dream4Drive can effectively boost the performance of downstream perception models under various training epochs. Page: https://wm-research.github.io/Dream4Drive/ GitHub Link: https://github.com/wm-research/Dream4Drive&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19195</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 03:02:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Denoising to Refining: A Corrective Framework for Vision-Language   Diffusion Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19871</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.19871.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yatai Ji, Teng Wang, Yuying Ge, Zhiheng Liu, Sidi Yang, Ying Shan, Ping Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Discrete diffusion models have emerged as a promising direction for vision-language tasks, offering bidirectional context modeling and theoretical parallelization. However, their practical application is severely hindered by a train-inference discrepancy, which leads to catastrophic error cascades: initial token errors during parallel decoding pollute the generation context, triggering a chain reaction of compounding errors and leading to syntactic errors and semantic hallucinations. To address this fundamental challenge, we reframe the generation process from passive denoising to active refining. We introduce ReDiff, a refining-enhanced diffusion framework that teaches the model to identify and correct its own errors. Our approach features a two-stage training process: first, we instill a foundational revision capability by training the model to revise synthetic errors; second, we implement a novel online self-correction loop where the model is explicitly trained to revise its own flawed drafts by learning from an expert's corrections. This mistake-driven learning endows the model with the crucial ability to revisit and refine its already generated output, effectively breaking the error cascade. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ReDiff significantly improves the coherence and factual accuracy of generated content, enabling stable and efficient parallel generation far superior to traditional denoising methods. Our codes and models are available at https://rediff-hku.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19871</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 06:58:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surfer 2: The Next Generation of Cross-Platform Computer Use Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19949</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.19949.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mathieu Andreux, Märt Bakler, Yanael Barbier, Hamza Benchekroun, Emilien Biré, Antoine Bonnet, Riaz Bordie, Nathan Bout, Matthias Brunel, Aleix Cambray, Pierre-Louis Cedoz, Antoine Chassang, Gautier Cloix, Ethan Connelly, Alexandra Constantinou, Ramzi De Coster, Hubert de la Jonquiere, Aurélien Delfosse, Maxime Delpit, Alexis Deprez, Augustin Derupti, Mathieu Diaz, Shannon D'Souza, Julie Dujardin, Abai Edmund, Michael Eickenberg, Armand Fatalot, Wissem Felissi, Isaac Herring, Xavier Koegler, Erwan Le Jumeau de Kergaradec, Aurélien Lac, Maxime Langevin, Corentin Lauverjat, Antonio Loison, Avshalom Manevich, Axel Moyal, Axel Nguyen Kerbel, Marinela Parovic, Julien Revelle, Guillaume Richard, Mats Richter, Ronan Riochet, María Santos, Romain Savidan, Laurent Sifre, Maxime Theillard, Marc Thibault, Ivan Valentini, Tony Wu, Laura Yie, Kai Yuan, Jevgenij Zubovskij&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Building agents that generalize across web, desktop, and mobile environments remains an open challenge, as prior systems rely on environment-specific interfaces that limit cross-platform deployment. We introduce Surfer 2, a unified architecture operating purely from visual observations that achieves state-of-the-art performance across all three environments. Surfer 2 integrates hierarchical context management, decoupled planning and execution, and self-verification with adaptive recovery, enabling reliable operation over long task horizons. Our system achieves 97.1% accuracy on WebVoyager, 69.6% on WebArena, 60.1% on OSWorld, and 87.1% on AndroidWorld, outperforming all prior systems without task-specific fine-tuning. With multiple attempts, Surfer 2 exceeds human performance on all benchmarks. These results demonstrate that systematic orchestration amplifies foundation model capabilities and enables general-purpose computer control through visual interaction alone, while calling for a next-generation vision language model to achieve Pareto-optimal cost-efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19949</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 18:21:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAPO++: Cross-Stage Prompt Optimization for Text-to-Video Generation via   Data Alignment and Test-Time Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20206</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.20206.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bingjie Gao, Qianli Ma, Xiaoxue Wu, Shuai Yang, Guanzhou Lan, Haonan Zhao, Jiaxuan Chen, Qingyang Liu, Yu Qiao, Xinyuan Chen, Yaohui Wang, Li Niu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Prompt design plays a crucial role in text-to-video (T2V) generation, yet user-provided prompts are often short, unstructured, and misaligned with training data, limiting the generative potential of diffusion-based T2V models. We present RAPO++, a cross-stage prompt optimization framework that unifies training-data--aligned refinement, test-time iterative scaling, and large language model (LLM) fine-tuning to substantially improve T2V generation without modifying the underlying generative backbone. In Stage 1, Retrieval-Augmented Prompt Optimization (RAPO) enriches user prompts with semantically relevant modifiers retrieved from a relation graph and refactors them to match training distributions, enhancing compositionality and multi-object fidelity. Stage 2 introduces Sample-Specific Prompt Optimization (SSPO), a closed-loop mechanism that iteratively refines prompts using multi-source feedback -- including semantic alignment, spatial fidelity, temporal coherence, and task-specific signals such as optical flow -- yielding progressively improved video generation quality. Stage 3 leverages optimized prompt pairs from SSPO to fine-tune the rewriter LLM, internalizing task-specific optimization patterns and enabling efficient, high-quality prompt generation even before inference. Extensive experiments across five state-of-the-art T2V models and five benchmarks demonstrate that RAPO++ achieves significant gains in semantic alignment, compositional reasoning, temporal stability, and physical plausibility, outperforming existing methods by large margins. Our results highlight RAPO++ as a model-agnostic, cost-efficient, and scalable solution that sets a new standard for prompt optimization in T2V generation. The code is available at https://github.com/Vchitect/RAPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20206</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 04:45:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI-Ins: Enhancing GUI Grounding with Multi-Perspective   Instruction-as-Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20286</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.20286.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liangyu Chen, Hanzhang Zhou, Chenglin Cai, Jianan Zhang, Panrong Tong, Quyu Kong, Xu Zhang, Chen Liu, Yuqi Liu, Wenxuan Wang, Yue Wang, Qin Jin, Steven Hoi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; GUI grounding, which maps natural-language instructions to actionable UI elements, is a core capability of GUI agents. Prior works largely treats instructions as a static proxy for user intent, overlooking the impact of instruction diversity and quality on grounding performance. Through a careful investigation of existing grounding datasets, we find a 23.3% flaw rate in their instructions and show that inference-time exploitation of instruction diversity yields up to a substantial 76% relative performance improvement. In this paper, we introduce the Instruction-as-Reasoning paradigm, treating instructions as dynamic analytical pathways that offer distinct perspectives and enabling the model to select the most effective pathway during reasoning. To achieve this, we propose a two-stage training framework: supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on synthesized, diverse instructions to instill multi-perspective reasoning, followed by reinforcement learning (RL) to optimize pathway selection and composition. Our resulting models, UI-Ins-7B and UI-Ins-32B, achieve state-of-the-art results on five challenging grounding benchmarks and exhibit emergent reasoning, selectively composing and synthesizing novel instruction pathways at inference. In particular, UI-Ins-32B attains the best grounding accuracy, scoring 87.3% on UI-I2E-Bench, 57.0% on ScreenSpot-Pro, and 84.9% on MMBench-GUI L2. Furthermore, our model demonstrates strong agentic potential, achieving a 74.1% success rate on AndroidWorld using UI-Ins-7B as the executor. Our in-depth analysis reveals additional insights such as how reasoning can be formulated to enhance rather than hinder grounding performance, and how our method mitigates policy collapse in the SFT+RL framework. All code and model checkpoints will be publicly released in https://github.com/alibaba/UI-Ins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20286</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 07:18:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RECALL: REpresentation-aligned Catastrophic-forgetting ALLeviation via   Hierarchical Model Merging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20479</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.20479.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bowen Wang, Haiyuan Wan, Liwen Shi, Chen Yang, Peng He, Yue Ma, Haochen Han, Wenhao Li, Tiao Tan, Yongjian Li, Fangming Liu, Yifan Gong, Sheng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We unveil that internal representations in large language models (LLMs) serve as reliable proxies of learned knowledge, and propose RECALL, a novel representation-aware model merging framework for continual learning without access to historical data. RECALL computes inter-model similarity from layer-wise hidden representations over clustered typical samples, and performs adaptive, hierarchical parameter fusion to align knowledge across models. This design enables the preservation of domain-general features in shallow layers while allowing task-specific adaptation in deeper layers. Unlike prior methods that require task labels or incur performance trade-offs, RECALL achieves seamless multi-domain integration and strong resistance to catastrophic forgetting. Extensive experiments across five NLP tasks and multiple continual learning scenarios show that RECALL outperforms baselines in both knowledge retention and generalization, providing a scalable and data-free solution for evolving LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20479</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 12:17:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video-As-Prompt: Unified Semantic Control for Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20888</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.20888.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxuan Bian, Xin Chen, Zenan Li, Tiancheng Zhi, Shen Sang, Linjie Luo, Qiang Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified, generalizable semantic control in video generation remains a critical open challenge. Existing methods either introduce artifacts by enforcing inappropriate pixel-wise priors from structure-based controls, or rely on non-generalizable, condition-specific finetuning or task-specific architectures. We introduce Video-As-Prompt (VAP), a new paradigm that reframes this problem as in-context generation. VAP leverages a reference video as a direct semantic prompt, guiding a frozen Video Diffusion Transformer (DiT) via a plug-and-play Mixture-of-Transformers (MoT) expert. This architecture prevents catastrophic forgetting and is guided by a temporally biased position embedding that eliminates spurious mapping priors for robust context retrieval. To power this approach and catalyze future research, we built VAP-Data, the largest dataset for semantic-controlled video generation with over 100K paired videos across 100 semantic conditions. As a single unified model, VAP sets a new state-of-the-art for open-source methods, achieving a 38.7% user preference rate that rivals leading condition-specific commercial models. VAP's strong zero-shot generalization and support for various downstream applications mark a significant advance toward general-purpose, controllable video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20888</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 17:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distilled Decoding 2: One-step Sampling of Image Auto-regressive Models   with Conditional Score Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21003</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21003.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Enshu Liu, Qian Chen, Xuefei Ning, Shengen Yan, Guohao Dai, Zinan Lin, Yu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Image Auto-regressive (AR) models have emerged as a powerful paradigm of visual generative models. Despite their promising performance, they suffer from slow generation speed due to the large number of sampling steps required. Although Distilled Decoding 1 (DD1) was recently proposed to enable few-step sampling for image AR models, it still incurs significant performance degradation in the one-step setting, and relies on a pre-defined mapping that limits its flexibility. In this work, we propose a new method, Distilled Decoding 2 (DD2), to further advances the feasibility of one-step sampling for image AR models. Unlike DD1, DD2 does not without rely on a pre-defined mapping. We view the original AR model as a teacher model which provides the ground truth conditional score in the latent embedding space at each token position. Based on this, we propose a novel conditional score distillation loss to train a one-step generator. Specifically, we train a separate network to predict the conditional score of the generated distribution and apply score distillation at every token position conditioned on previous tokens. Experimental results show that DD2 enables one-step sampling for image AR models with an minimal FID increase from 3.40 to 5.43 on ImageNet-256. Compared to the strongest baseline DD1, DD2 reduces the gap between the one-step sampling and original AR model by 67%, with up to 12.3times training speed-up simultaneously. DD2 takes a significant step toward the goal of one-step AR generation, opening up new possibilities for fast and high-quality AR modeling. Code is available at https://github.com/imagination-research/Distilled-Decoding-2.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21003</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 21:21:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Principles of Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21890</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21890.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chieh-Hsin Lai, Yang Song, Dongjun Kim, Yuki Mitsufuji, Stefano Ermon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This monograph presents the core principles that have guided the development of diffusion models, tracing their origins and showing how diverse formulations arise from shared mathematical ideas. Diffusion modeling starts by defining a forward process that gradually corrupts data into noise, linking the data distribution to a simple prior through a continuum of intermediate distributions. The goal is to learn a reverse process that transforms noise back into data while recovering the same intermediates. We describe three complementary views. The variational view, inspired by variational autoencoders, sees diffusion as learning to remove noise step by step. The score-based view, rooted in energy-based modeling, learns the gradient of the evolving data distribution, indicating how to nudge samples toward more likely regions. The flow-based view, related to normalizing flows, treats generation as following a smooth path that moves samples from noise to data under a learned velocity field. These perspectives share a common backbone: a time-dependent velocity field whose flow transports a simple prior to the data. Sampling then amounts to solving a differential equation that evolves noise into data along a continuous trajectory. On this foundation, the monograph discusses guidance for controllable generation, efficient numerical solvers, and diffusion-motivated flow-map models that learn direct mappings between arbitrary times. It provides a conceptual and mathematically grounded understanding of diffusion models for readers with basic deep-learning knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21890</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 02:29:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Merging with Functional Dual Anchors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21223</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21223.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kexuan Shi, Yandong Wen, Weiyang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Model merging is an efficient post-training strategy for integrating knowledge from multiple finetuned checkpoints of a shared foundation model. Existing methods operate in the parameter space, combining task vectors to mitigate conflicts, but remain constrained by parameter inconsistencies. We propose Functional Dual Anchors (FDAs), a framework that instead models the input-representation space. FDAs are synthetic inputs whose induced gradients align with task vectors, capturing task-specific functional shifts relative to the pretrained model. This perspective bridges joint multi-task training and post-hoc merging, offering both robustness and flexibility. We further introduce a principled initialization scheme and show that FDAs are complementary to parameter-space model merging. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of FDAs in model merging.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21223</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 07:54:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparser Block-Sparse Attention via Token Permutation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21270</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21270.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinghao Wang, Pengyu Wang, Dong Zhang, Chenkun Tan, Shaojun Zhou, Zhaoxiang Liu, Shiguo Lian, Fangxu Liu, Kai Song, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling the context length of large language models (LLMs) offers significant benefits but is computationally expensive. This expense stems primarily from the self-attention mechanism, whose O(N^2) complexity with respect to sequence length presents a major bottleneck for both memory and latency. Fortunately, the attention matrix is often sparse, particularly for long sequences, suggesting an opportunity for optimization. Block-sparse attention has emerged as a promising solution that partitions sequences into blocks and skips computation for a subset of these blocks. However, the effectiveness of this method is highly dependent on the underlying attention patterns, which can lead to sub-optimal block-level sparsity. For instance, important key tokens for queries within a single block may be scattered across numerous other blocks, leading to computational redundancy. In this work, we propose Permuted Block-Sparse Attention (PBS-Attn), a plug-and-play method that leverages the permutation properties of attention to increase block-level sparsity and enhance the computational efficiency of LLM prefilling. We conduct comprehensive experiments on challenging real-world long-context datasets, demonstrating that PBS-Attn consistently outperforms existing block-sparse attention methods in model accuracy and closely matches the full attention baseline. Powered by our custom permuted-FlashAttention kernels, PBS-Attn achieves an end-to-end speedup of up to 2.75times in long-context prefilling, confirming its practical viability. Code available at https://github.com/xinghaow99/pbs-attn&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21270</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 09:11:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sample By Step, Optimize By Chunk: Chunk-Level GRPO For Text-to-Image   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21583</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21583.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifu Luo, Penghui Du, Bo Li, Sinan Du, Tiantian Zhang, Yongzhe Chang, Kai Wu, Kun Gai, Xueqian Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) has shown strong potential for flow-matching-based text-to-image (T2I) generation, but it faces two key limitations: inaccurate advantage attribution, and the neglect of temporal dynamics of generation. In this work, we argue that shifting the optimization paradigm from the step level to the chunk level can effectively alleviate these issues. Building on this idea, we propose Chunk-GRPO, the first chunk-level GRPO-based approach for T2I generation. The insight is to group consecutive steps into coherent 'chunk's that capture the intrinsic temporal dynamics of flow matching, and to optimize policies at the chunk level. In addition, we introduce an optional weighted sampling strategy to further enhance performance. Extensive experiments show that ChunkGRPO achieves superior results in both preference alignment and image quality, highlighting the promise of chunk-level optimization for GRPO-based methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21583</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 15:50:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepAgent: A General Reasoning Agent with Scalable Toolsets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoxi Li, Wenxiang Jiao, Jiarui Jin, Guanting Dong, Jiajie Jin, Yinuo Wang, Hao Wang, Yutao Zhu, Ji-Rong Wen, Yuan Lu, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 91&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models have demonstrated strong problem-solving abilities, yet real-world tasks often require external tools and long-horizon interactions. Existing agent frameworks typically follow predefined workflows, which limit autonomous and global task completion. In this paper, we introduce DeepAgent, an end-to-end deep reasoning agent that performs autonomous thinking, tool discovery, and action execution within a single, coherent reasoning process. To address the challenges of long-horizon interactions, particularly the context length explosion from multiple tool calls and the accumulation of interaction history, we introduce an autonomous memory folding mechanism that compresses past interactions into structured episodic, working, and tool memories, reducing error accumulation while preserving critical information. To teach general-purpose tool use efficiently and stably, we develop an end-to-end reinforcement learning strategy, namely ToolPO, that leverages LLM-simulated APIs and applies tool-call advantage attribution to assign fine-grained credit to the tool invocation tokens. Extensive experiments on eight benchmarks, including general tool-use tasks (ToolBench, API-Bank, TMDB, Spotify, ToolHop) and downstream applications (ALFWorld, WebShop, GAIA, HLE), demonstrate that DeepAgent consistently outperforms baselines across both labeled-tool and open-set tool retrieval scenarios. This work takes a step toward more general and capable agents for real-world applications. The code and demo are available at https://github.com/RUC-NLPIR/DeepAgent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21618</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 16:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WorldGrow: Generating Infinite 3D World</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21682</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21682.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sikuang Li, Chen Yang, Jiemin Fang, Taoran Yi, Jia Lu, Jiazhong Cen, Lingxi Xie, Wei Shen, Qi Tian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We tackle the challenge of generating the infinitely extendable 3D world -- large, continuous environments with coherent geometry and realistic appearance. Existing methods face key challenges: 2D-lifting approaches suffer from geometric and appearance inconsistencies across views, 3D implicit representations are hard to scale up, and current 3D foundation models are mostly object-centric, limiting their applicability to scene-level generation. Our key insight is leveraging strong generation priors from pre-trained 3D models for structured scene block generation. To this end, we propose WorldGrow, a hierarchical framework for unbounded 3D scene synthesis. Our method features three core components: (1) a data curation pipeline that extracts high-quality scene blocks for training, making the 3D structured latent representations suitable for scene generation; (2) a 3D block inpainting mechanism that enables context-aware scene extension; and (3) a coarse-to-fine generation strategy that ensures both global layout plausibility and local geometric/textural fidelity. Evaluated on the large-scale 3D-FRONT dataset, WorldGrow achieves SOTA performance in geometry reconstruction, while uniquely supporting infinite scene generation with photorealistic and structurally consistent outputs. These results highlight its capability for constructing large-scale virtual environments and potential for building future world models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21682</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 17:39:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Diffusion Models are Geometric Solvers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21697</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.21697.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nir Goren, Shai Yehezkel, Omer Dahary, Andrey Voynov, Or Patashnik, Daniel Cohen-Or&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper we show that visual diffusion models can serve as effective geometric solvers: they can directly reason about geometric problems by working in pixel space. We first demonstrate this on the Inscribed Square Problem, a long-standing problem in geometry that asks whether every Jordan curve contains four points forming a square. We then extend the approach to two other well-known hard geometric problems: the Steiner Tree Problem and the Simple Polygon Problem.   Our method treats each problem instance as an image and trains a standard visual diffusion model that transforms Gaussian noise into an image representing a valid approximate solution that closely matches the exact one. The model learns to transform noisy geometric structures into correct configurations, effectively recasting geometric reasoning as image generation.   Unlike prior work that necessitates specialized architectures and domain-specific adaptations when applying diffusion to parametric geometric representations, we employ a standard visual diffusion model that operates on the visual representation of the problem. This simplicity highlights a surprising bridge between generative modeling and geometric problem solving. Beyond the specific problems studied here, our results point toward a broader paradigm: operating in image space provides a general and practical framework for approximating notoriously hard problems, and opens the door to tackling a far wider class of challenging geometric tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21697</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 17:57:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VisCoder2: Building Multi-Language Visualization Coding Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23642</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23642.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuansheng Ni, Songcheng Cai, Xiangchao Chen, Jiarong Liang, Zhiheng Lyu, Jiaqi Deng, Kai Zou, Ping Nie, Fei Yuan, Xiang Yue, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have recently enabled coding agents capable of generating, executing, and revising visualization code. However, existing models often fail in practical workflows due to limited language coverage, unreliable execution, and lack of iterative correction mechanisms. Progress has been constrained by narrow datasets and benchmarks that emphasize single-round generation and single-language tasks. To address these challenges, we introduce three complementary resources for advancing visualization coding agents. VisCode-Multi-679K is a large-scale, supervised dataset containing 679K validated and executable visualization samples with multi-turn correction dialogues across 12 programming languages. VisPlotBench is a benchmark for systematic evaluation, featuring executable tasks, rendered outputs, and protocols for both initial generation and multi-round self-debug. Finally, we present VisCoder2, a family of multi-language visualization models trained on VisCode-Multi-679K. Experiments show that VisCoder2 significantly outperforms strong open-source baselines and approaches the performance of proprietary models like GPT-4.1, with further gains from iterative self-debug, reaching 82.4% overall execution pass rate at the 32B scale, particularly in symbolic or compiler-dependent languages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23642</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 18:03:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ATLAS: Adaptive Transfer Scaling Laws for Multilingual Pretraining,   Finetuning, and Decoding the Curse of Multilinguality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22037</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22037.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shayne Longpre, Sneha Kudugunta, Niklas Muennighoff, I-Hung Hsu, Isaac Caswell, Alex Pentland, Sercan Arik, Chen-Yu Lee, Sayna Ebrahimi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling laws research has focused overwhelmingly on English -- yet the most prominent AI models explicitly serve billions of international users. In this work, we undertake the largest multilingual scaling laws study to date, totaling 774 multilingual training experiments, spanning 10M-8B model parameters, 400+ training languages and 48 evaluation languages. We introduce the Adaptive Transfer Scaling Law (ATLAS) for both monolingual and multilingual pretraining, which outperforms existing scaling laws' out-of-sample generalization often by more than 0.3 R^2. Our analyses of the experiments shed light on multilingual learning dynamics, transfer properties between languages, and the curse of multilinguality. First, we derive a cross-lingual transfer matrix, empirically measuring mutual benefit scores between 38 x 38=1444 language pairs. Second, we derive a language-agnostic scaling law that reveals how to optimally scale model size and data when adding languages without sacrificing performance. Third, we identify the computational crossover points for when to pretrain from scratch versus finetune from multilingual checkpoints. We hope these findings provide the scientific foundation for democratizing scaling laws across languages, and enable practitioners to efficiently scale models -- beyond English-first AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22037</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 21:45:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongCat-Video Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22200</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22200.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Meituan LongCat Team, Xunliang Cai, Qilong Huang, Zhuoliang Kang, Hongyu Li, Shijun Liang, Liya Ma, Siyu Ren, Xiaoming Wei, Rixu Xie, Tong Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video generation is a critical pathway toward world models, with efficient long video inference as a key capability. Toward this end, we introduce LongCat-Video, a foundational video generation model with 13.6B parameters, delivering strong performance across multiple video generation tasks. It particularly excels in efficient and high-quality long video generation, representing our first step toward world models. Key features include: Unified architecture for multiple tasks: Built on the Diffusion Transformer (DiT) framework, LongCat-Video supports Text-to-Video, Image-to-Video, and Video-Continuation tasks with a single model; Long video generation: Pretraining on Video-Continuation tasks enables LongCat-Video to maintain high quality and temporal coherence in the generation of minutes-long videos; Efficient inference: LongCat-Video generates 720p, 30fps videos within minutes by employing a coarse-to-fine generation strategy along both the temporal and spatial axes. Block Sparse Attention further enhances efficiency, particularly at high resolutions; Strong performance with multi-reward RLHF: Multi-reward RLHF training enables LongCat-Video to achieve performance on par with the latest closed-source and leading open-source models. Code and model weights are publicly available to accelerate progress in the field.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22200</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 07:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ACG: Action Coherence Guidance for Flow-based VLA models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22201</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22201.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minho Park, Kinam Kim, Junha Hyung, Hyojin Jang, Hoiyeong Jin, Jooyeol Yun, Hojoon Lee, Jaegul Choo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion and flow matching models have emerged as powerful robot policies, enabling Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models to generalize across diverse scenes and instructions. Yet, when trained via imitation learning, their high generative capacity makes them sensitive to noise in human demonstrations: jerks, pauses, and jitter which reduce action coherence. Reduced action coherence causes instability and trajectory drift during deployment, failures that are catastrophic in fine-grained manipulation where precision is crucial. In this paper, we present Action Coherence Guidance (ACG) for VLA models, a training-free test-time guidance algorithm that improves action coherence and thereby yields performance gains. Evaluated on RoboCasa, DexMimicGen, and real-world SO-101 tasks, ACG consistently improves action coherence and boosts success rates across diverse manipulation tasks. Code and project page are available at https://github.com/DAVIAN-Robotics/ACG and https://DAVIAN-Robotics.github.io/ACG , respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22201</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 07:44:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ODesign: A World Model for Biomolecular Interaction Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22304</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22304.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Odin Zhang, Xujun Zhang, Haitao Lin, Cheng Tan, Qinghan Wang, Yuanle Mo, Qiantai Feng, Gang Du, Yuntao Yu, Zichang Jin, Ziyi You, Peicong Lin, Yijie Zhang, Yuyang Tao, Shicheng Chen, Jack Xiaoyu Chen, Chenqing Hua, Weibo Zhao, Runze Ma, Yunpeng Xia, Kejun Ying, Jun Li, Yundian Zeng, Lijun Lang, Peichen Pan, Hanqun Cao, Zihao Song, Bo Qiang, Jiaqi Wang, Pengfei Ji, Lei Bai, Jian Zhang, Chang-yu Hsieh, Pheng Ann Heng, Siqi Sun, Tingjun Hou, Shuangjia Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Biomolecular interactions underpin almost all biological processes, and their rational design is central to programming new biological functions. Generative AI models have emerged as powerful tools for molecular design, yet most remain specialized for individual molecular types and lack fine-grained control over interaction details. Here we present ODesign, an all-atom generative world model for all-to-all biomolecular interaction design. ODesign allows scientists to specify epitopes on arbitrary targets and generate diverse classes of binding partners with fine-grained control. Across entity-, token-, and atom-level benchmarks in the protein modality, ODesign demonstrates superior controllability and performance to modality-specific baselines. Extending beyond proteins, it generalizes to nucleic acid and small-molecule design, enabling interaction types such as protein-binding RNA/DNA and RNA/DNA-binding ligands that were previously inaccessible. By unifying multimodal biomolecular interactions within a single generative framework, ODesign moves toward a general-purpose molecular world model capable of programmable design. ODesign is available at https://odesign.lglab.ac.cn ,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22304</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 14:16:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VisJudge-Bench: Aesthetics and Quality Assessment of Visualizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22373</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22373.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yupeng Xie, Zhiyang Zhang, Yifan Wu, Sirong Lu, Jiayi Zhang, Zhaoyang Yu, Jinlin Wang, Sirui Hong, Bang Liu, Chenglin Wu, Yuyu Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visualization, a domain-specific yet widely used form of imagery, is an effective way to turn complex datasets into intuitive insights, and its value depends on whether data are faithfully represented, clearly communicated, and aesthetically designed. However, evaluating visualization quality is challenging: unlike natural images, it requires simultaneous judgment across data encoding accuracy, information expressiveness, and visual aesthetics. Although multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have shown promising performance in aesthetic assessment of natural images, no systematic benchmark exists for measuring their capabilities in evaluating visualizations. To address this, we propose VisJudge-Bench, the first comprehensive benchmark for evaluating MLLMs' performance in assessing visualization aesthetics and quality. It contains 3,090 expert-annotated samples from real-world scenarios, covering single visualizations, multiple visualizations, and dashboards across 32 chart types. Systematic testing on this benchmark reveals that even the most advanced MLLMs (such as GPT-5) still exhibit significant gaps compared to human experts in judgment, with a Mean Absolute Error (MAE) of 0.551 and a correlation with human ratings of only 0.429. To address this issue, we propose VisJudge, a model specifically designed for visualization aesthetics and quality assessment. Experimental results demonstrate that VisJudge significantly narrows the gap with human judgment, reducing the MAE to 0.442 (a 19.8% reduction) and increasing the consistency with human experts to 0.681 (a 58.7% improvement) compared to GPT-5. The benchmark is available at https://github.com/HKUSTDial/VisJudgeBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22373</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 17:31:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IGGT: Instance-Grounded Geometry Transformer for Semantic 3D   Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22706</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22706.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Li, Zhengyu Zou, Fangfu Liu, Xuanyang Zhang, Fangzhou Hong, Yukang Cao, Yushi Lan, Manyuan Zhang, Gang Yu, Dingwen Zhang, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humans naturally perceive the geometric structure and semantic content of a 3D world as intertwined dimensions, enabling coherent and accurate understanding of complex scenes. However, most prior approaches prioritize training large geometry models for low-level 3D reconstruction and treat high-level spatial understanding in isolation, overlooking the crucial interplay between these two fundamental aspects of 3D-scene analysis, thereby limiting generalization and leading to poor performance in downstream 3D understanding tasks. Recent attempts have mitigated this issue by simply aligning 3D models with specific language models, thus restricting perception to the aligned model's capacity and limiting adaptability to downstream tasks. In this paper, we propose InstanceGrounded Geometry Transformer (IGGT), an end-to-end large unified transformer to unify the knowledge for both spatial reconstruction and instance-level contextual understanding. Specifically, we design a 3D-Consistent Contrastive Learning strategy that guides IGGT to encode a unified representation with geometric structures and instance-grounded clustering through only 2D visual inputs. This representation supports consistent lifting of 2D visual inputs into a coherent 3D scene with explicitly distinct object instances. To facilitate this task, we further construct InsScene-15K, a large-scale dataset with high-quality RGB images, poses, depth maps, and 3D-consistent instance-level mask annotations with a novel data curation pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22706</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 14:57:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E^2Rank: Your Text Embedding can Also be an Effective   and Efficient Listwise Reranker</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22733</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22733.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qi Liu, Yanzhao Zhang, Mingxin Li, Dingkun Long, Pengjun Xie, Jiaxin Mao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text embedding models serve as a fundamental component in real-world search applications. By mapping queries and documents into a shared embedding space, they deliver competitive retrieval performance with high efficiency. However, their ranking fidelity remains limited compared to dedicated rerankers, especially recent LLM-based listwise rerankers, which capture fine-grained query-document and document-document interactions. In this paper, we propose a simple yet effective unified framework E^2Rank, means Efficient Embedding-based Ranking (also means Embedding-to-Rank), which extends a single text embedding model to perform both high-quality retrieval and listwise reranking through continued training under a listwise ranking objective, thereby achieving strong effectiveness with remarkable efficiency. By applying cosine similarity between the query and document embeddings as a unified ranking function, the listwise ranking prompt, which is constructed from the original query and its candidate documents, serves as an enhanced query enriched with signals from the top-K documents, akin to pseudo-relevance feedback (PRF) in traditional retrieval models. This design preserves the efficiency and representational quality of the base embedding model while significantly improving its reranking performance. Empirically, E^2Rank achieves state-of-the-art results on the BEIR reranking benchmark and demonstrates competitive performance on the reasoning-intensive BRIGHT benchmark, with very low reranking latency. We also show that the ranking training process improves embedding performance on the MTEB benchmark. Our findings indicate that a single embedding model can effectively unify retrieval and reranking, offering both computational efficiency and competitive ranking accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22733</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 16:04:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Batch Speculative Decoding Done Right</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22876</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22876.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ranran Haoran Zhang, Soumik Dey, Ashirbad Mishra, Hansi Wu, Binbin Li, Rui Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Speculative decoding speeds up LLM inference by using a small draft model to propose multiple tokens that a target model verifies in parallel. Extending this idea to batches is essential for production serving, but it introduces the ragged tensor problem: sequences in the same batch accept different numbers of draft tokens, breaking right-alignment and corrupting position IDs, attention masks, and KV-cache state. We show that several existing batch implementations violate output equivalence-the fundamental requirement that speculative decoding must produce identical token sequences to standard autoregressive generation. These violations occur precisely due to improper handling of the ragged tensor problem. In response, we (1) characterize the synchronization requirements that guarantee correctness, (2) present a correctness-first batch speculative decoding EQSPEC that exposes realignment as consuming 40% of overhead, and (3) introduce EXSPEC, which maintains a sliding pool of sequences and dynamically forms same-length groups, to reduce the realignment overhead while preserving per-sequence speculative speedups. On the SpecBench dataset, across Vicuna-7B/68M, Qwen3-8B/0.6B, and GLM-4-9B/0.6B target/draft pairs, our approach achieves up to 3times throughput improvement at batch size 8 compared to batch size 1, with efficient scaling through batch size 8, while maintaining 95% output equivalence. Our method requires no custom kernels and integrates cleanly with existing inference stacks. Our code is available at https://github.com/eBay/spec_dec.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22876</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 23:59:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LightBagel: A Light-weighted, Double Fusion Framework for Unified   Multimodal Understanding and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22946</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22946.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeyu Wang, Zilong Chen, Chenhui Gou, Feng Li, Chaorui Deng, Deyao Zhu, Kunchang Li, Weihao Yu, Haoqin Tu, Haoqi Fan, Cihang Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified multimodal models have recently shown remarkable gains in both capability and versatility, yet most leading systems are still trained from scratch and require substantial computational resources. In this paper, we show that competitive performance can be obtained far more efficiently by strategically fusing publicly available models specialized for either generation or understanding. Our key design is to retain the original blocks while additionally interleaving multimodal self-attention blocks throughout the networks. This double fusion mechanism (1) effectively enables rich multi-modal fusion while largely preserving the original strengths of the base models, and (2) catalyzes synergistic fusion of high-level semantic representations from the understanding encoder with low-level spatial signals from the generation encoder. By training with only ~ 35B tokens, this approach achieves strong results across multiple benchmarks: 0.91 on GenEval for compositional text-to-image generation, 82.16 on DPG-Bench for complex text-to-image generation, 6.06 on GEditBench, and 3.77 on ImgEdit-Bench for image editing. By fully releasing the entire suite of code, model weights, and datasets, we hope to support future research on unified multimodal modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22946</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 02:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VoMP: Predicting Volumetric Mechanical Property Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22975</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22975.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rishit Dagli, Donglai Xiang, Vismay Modi, Charles Loop, Clement Fuji Tsang, Anka He Chen, Anita Hu, Gavriel State, David I. W. Levin, Maria Shugrina&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Physical simulation relies on spatially-varying mechanical properties, often laboriously hand-crafted. VoMP is a feed-forward method trained to predict Young's modulus (E), Poisson's ratio (nu), and density (rho) throughout the volume of 3D objects, in any representation that can be rendered and voxelized. VoMP aggregates per-voxel multi-view features and passes them to our trained Geometry Transformer to predict per-voxel material latent codes. These latents reside on a manifold of physically plausible materials, which we learn from a real-world dataset, guaranteeing the validity of decoded per-voxel materials. To obtain object-level training data, we propose an annotation pipeline combining knowledge from segmented 3D datasets, material databases, and a vision-language model, along with a new benchmark. Experiments show that VoMP estimates accurate volumetric properties, far outperforming prior art in accuracy and speed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22975</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 03:56:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knocking-Heads Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23052</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23052.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhanchao Zhou, Xiaodong Chen, Haoxing Chen, Zhenzhong Lan, Jianguo Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-head attention (MHA) has become the cornerstone of modern large language models, enhancing representational capacity through parallel attention heads. However, increasing the number of heads inherently weakens individual head capacity, and existing attention mechanisms - whether standard MHA or its variants like grouped-query attention (GQA) and grouped-tied attention (GTA) - simply concatenate outputs from isolated heads without strong interaction. To address this limitation, we propose knocking-heads attention (KHA), which enables attention heads to "knock" on each other - facilitating cross-head feature-level interactions before the scaled dot-product attention. This is achieved by applying a shared, diagonally-initialized projection matrix across all heads. The diagonal initialization preserves head-specific specialization at the start of training while allowing the model to progressively learn integrated cross-head representations. KHA adds only minimal parameters and FLOPs and can be seamlessly integrated into MHA, GQA, GTA, and other attention variants. We validate KHA by training a 6.1B parameter MoE model (1.01B activated) on 1T high-quality tokens. Compared to baseline attention mechanisms, KHA brings superior and more stable training dynamics, achieving better performance across downstream tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23052</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 06:28:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code Aesthetics with Agentic Reward Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23272</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23272.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bang Xiao, Lingjie Jiang, Shaohan Huang, Tengchao Lv, Yupan Huang, Xun Wu, Lei Cui, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have become valuable assistants for developers in code-related tasks. While LLMs excel at traditional programming tasks such as code generation and bug fixing, they struggle with visually-oriented coding tasks, often producing suboptimal aesthetics. In this paper, we introduce a new pipeline to enhance the aesthetic quality of LLM-generated code. We first construct AesCode-358K, a large-scale instruction-tuning dataset focused on code aesthetics. Next, we propose agentic reward feedback, a multi-agent system that evaluates executability, static aesthetics, and interactive aesthetics. Building on this, we develop GRPO-AR, which integrates these signals into the GRPO algorithm for joint optimization of functionality and code aesthetics. Finally, we develop OpenDesign, a benchmark for assessing code aesthetics. Experimental results show that combining supervised fine-tuning on AesCode-358K with reinforcement learning using agentic reward feedback significantly improves performance on OpenDesign and also enhances results on existing benchmarks such as PandasPlotBench. Notably, our AesCoder-4B surpasses GPT-4o and GPT-4.1, and achieves performance comparable to large open-source models with 480B-685B parameters, underscoring the effectiveness of our approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23272</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 12:32:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Best of N Worlds: Aligning Reinforcement Learning with Best-of-N   Sampling via max@k Optimisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23393</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23393.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Farid Bagirov, Mikhail Arkhipov, Ksenia Sycheva, Evgeniy Glukhov, Egor Bogomolov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The application of Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) to mathematical and coding domains has demonstrated significant improvements in the reasoning and problem-solving abilities of Large Language Models. Despite its success in single generation problem solving, the reinforcement learning fine-tuning process may harm the model's exploration ability, as reflected in decreased diversity of generations and a resulting degradation of performance during Best-of-N sampling for large N values. In this work, we focus on optimizing the max@k metric, a continuous generalization of pass@k. We derive an unbiased on-policy gradient estimate for direct optimization of this metric. Furthermore, we extend our derivations to the off-policy updates, a common element in modern RLVR algorithms, that allows better sample efficiency. Empirically, we show that our objective effectively optimizes max@k metric in off-policy scenarios, aligning the model with the Best-of-N inference strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23393</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 14:47:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Omni-Reward: Towards Generalist Omni-Modal Reward Modeling with   Free-Form Preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23451</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23451.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuoran Jin, Hongbang Yuan, Kejian Zhu, Jiachun Li, Pengfei Cao, Yubo Chen, Kang Liu, Jun Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward models (RMs) play a critical role in aligning AI behaviors with human preferences, yet they face two fundamental challenges: (1) Modality Imbalance, where most RMs are mainly focused on text and image modalities, offering limited support for video, audio, and other modalities; and (2) Preference Rigidity, where training on fixed binary preference pairs fails to capture the complexity and diversity of personalized preferences. To address the above challenges, we propose Omni-Reward, a step toward generalist omni-modal reward modeling with support for free-form preferences, consisting of: (1) Evaluation: We introduce Omni-RewardBench, the first omni-modal RM benchmark with free-form preferences, covering nine tasks across five modalities including text, image, video, audio, and 3D; (2) Data: We construct Omni-RewardData, a multimodal preference dataset comprising 248K general preference pairs and 69K instruction-tuning pairs for training generalist omni-modal RMs; (3) Model: We propose Omni-RewardModel, which includes both discriminative and generative RMs, and achieves strong performance on Omni-RewardBench as well as other widely used reward modeling benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23451</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 15:53:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video-Thinker: Sparking "Thinking with Videos" via Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23473</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23473.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shijian Wang, Jiarui Jin, Xingjian Wang, Linxin Song, Runhao Fu, Hecheng Wang, Zongyuan Ge, Yuan Lu, Xuelian Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 81&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in image reasoning methods, particularly "Thinking with Images", have demonstrated remarkable success in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs); however, this dynamic reasoning paradigm has not yet been extended to video reasoning tasks. In this paper, we propose Video-Thinker, which empowers MLLMs to think with videos by autonomously leveraging their intrinsic "grounding" and "captioning" capabilities to generate reasoning clues throughout the inference process. To spark this capability, we construct Video-Thinker-10K, a curated dataset featuring autonomous tool usage within chain-of-thought reasoning sequences. Our training strategy begins with Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) to learn the reasoning format, followed by Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) to strengthen this reasoning capability. Through this approach, Video-Thinker enables MLLMs to autonomously navigate grounding and captioning tasks for video reasoning, eliminating the need for constructing and calling external tools. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Video-Thinker achieves significant performance gains on both in-domain tasks and challenging out-of-domain video reasoning benchmarks, including Video-Holmes, CG-Bench-Reasoning, and VRBench. Our Video-Thinker-7B substantially outperforms existing baselines such as Video-R1 and establishes state-of-the-art performance among 7B-sized MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23473</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 16:10:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MergeMix: A Unified Augmentation Paradigm for Visual and Multi-Modal   Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23479</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23479.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Jin, Siyuan Li, Siyong Jian, Kai Yu, Huan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language alignment in multi-modal large language models (MLLMs) typically relies on supervised fine-tuning (SFT) or reinforcement learning (RL). SFT is stable and efficient but requires large-scale human annotations and cannot capture subtle preferences, while RL brings in a reward signal for training, but suffers from overhead and instability. These limitations highlight a trade-off between scalability, robustness, and alignment quality. To address this, we propose MergeMix, a training-time augmentation paradigm that bridges SFT and RL. It first applies an attention-aware image mixing via token merge with more cluster representation and spatial context, and then presents a preference-driven training paradigm for MLLMs by building preference pairs with mixed images and raw images, and optimizing via SimPO loss. As a mixup augmentation, MergeMix enhances attention consistency and efficiency, surpassing other heuristic-based methods in classification. Extensive experiments demonstrate that MergeMix achieves competitive accuracy with improved efficiency, providing a scalable approach to preference alignment in classification and MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23479</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 16:12:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JanusCoder: Towards a Foundational Visual-Programmatic Interface for   Code Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23538</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23538.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qiushi Sun, Jingyang Gong, Yang Liu, Qiaosheng Chen, Lei Li, Kai Chen, Qipeng Guo, Ben Kao, Fei Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 91&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The scope of neural code intelligence is rapidly expanding beyond text-based source code to encompass the rich visual outputs that programs generate. This visual dimension is critical for advanced applications like flexible content generation and precise, program-driven editing of visualizations. However, progress has been impeded by the scarcity of high-quality multimodal code data, a bottleneck stemming from challenges in synthesis and quality assessment. To address these challenges, we make contributions from both a data and modeling perspective. We first introduce a complete synthesis toolkit that leverages reciprocal synergies between data modalities to efficiently produce a large-scale, high-quality corpus spanning from standard charts to complex interactive web UIs and code-driven animations. Leveraging this toolkit, we construct JanusCode-800K, the largest multimodal code corpus to date. This powers the training of our models, JanusCoder and JanusCoderV, which establish a visual-programmatic interface for generating code from textual instructions, visual inputs, or a combination of both. Our unified model is a departure from existing approaches that build specialized models for isolated tasks. Extensive experiments on both text-centric and vision-centric coding tasks demonstrate the superior performance of the JanusCoder series, with our 7B to 14B scale models approaching or even exceeding the performance of commercial models. Furthermore, extensive analysis provides key insights into harmonizing programmatic logic with its visual expression. Our code and checkpoints will are available at https://github.com/InternLM/JanusCoder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23538</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:13:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LimRank: Less is More for Reasoning-Intensive Information Reranking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23544</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23544.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tingyu Song, Yilun Zhao, Siyue Zhang, Chen Zhao, Arman Cohan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing approaches typically rely on large-scale fine-tuning to adapt LLMs for information reranking tasks, which is computationally expensive. In this work, we demonstrate that modern LLMs can be effectively adapted using only minimal, high-quality supervision. To enable this, we design LIMRANK-SYNTHESIZER, a reusable and open-source pipeline for generating diverse, challenging, and realistic reranking examples. Using this synthetic data, we fine-tune our reranker model, LIMRANK. We evaluate LIMRANK on two challenging benchmarks, i.e., BRIGHT for reasoning-intensive retrieval and FollowIR for instruction-following retrieval. Our experiments demonstrate that LIMRANK achieves competitive performance, while being trained on less than 5% of the data typically used in prior work. Further ablation studies demonstrate the effectiveness of LIMRANK-SYNTHESIZER and the strong generalization capabilities of LIMRANK across downstream tasks, including scientific literature search and retrieval-augmented generation for knowledge-intensive problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23544</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:19:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReCode: Unify Plan and Action for Universal Granularity Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23564</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23564.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoyang Yu, Jiayi Zhang, Huixue Su, Yufan Zhao, Yifan Wu, Mingyi Deng, Jinyu Xiang, Yizhang Lin, Lingxiao Tang, Yingchao Li, Yuyu Luo, Bang Liu, Chenglin Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 116&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Real-world tasks require decisions at varying granularities, and humans excel at this by leveraging a unified cognitive representation where planning is fundamentally understood as a high-level form of action. However, current Large Language Model (LLM)-based agents lack this crucial capability to operate fluidly across decision granularities. This limitation stems from existing paradigms that enforce a rigid separation between high-level planning and low-level action, which impairs dynamic adaptability and limits generalization. We propose ReCode (Recursive Code Generation), a novel paradigm that addresses this limitation by unifying planning and action within a single code representation. In this representation, ReCode treats high-level plans as abstract placeholder functions, which the agent then recursively decomposes into finer-grained sub-functions until reaching primitive actions. This recursive approach dissolves the rigid boundary between plan and action, enabling the agent to dynamically control its decision granularity. Furthermore, the recursive structure inherently generates rich, multi-granularity training data, enabling models to learn hierarchical decision-making processes. Extensive experiments show ReCode significantly surpasses advanced baselines in inference performance and demonstrates exceptional data efficiency in training, validating our core insight that unifying planning and action through recursive code generation is a powerful and effective approach to achieving universal granularity control. The code is available at https://github.com/FoundationAgents/ReCode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23564</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:35:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RobotArena infty: Scalable Robot Benchmarking via Real-to-Sim   Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23571</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23571.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yash Jangir, Yidi Zhang, Kashu Yamazaki, Chenyu Zhang, Kuan-Hsun Tu, Tsung-Wei Ke, Lei Ke, Yonatan Bisk, Katerina Fragkiadaki&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The pursuit of robot generalists - instructable agents capable of performing diverse tasks across diverse environments - demands rigorous and scalable evaluation. Yet real-world testing of robot policies remains fundamentally constrained: it is labor-intensive, slow, unsafe at scale, and difficult to reproduce. Existing simulation benchmarks are similarly limited, as they train and test policies within the same synthetic domains and cannot assess models trained from real-world demonstrations or alternative simulation environments. As policies expand in scope and complexity, these barriers only intensify, since defining "success" in robotics often hinges on nuanced human judgments of execution quality. In this paper, we introduce a new benchmarking framework that overcomes these challenges by shifting VLA evaluation into large-scale simulated environments augmented with online human feedback. Leveraging advances in vision-language models, 2D-to-3D generative modeling, and differentiable rendering, our approach automatically converts video demonstrations from widely used robot datasets into simulated counterparts. Within these digital twins, we assess VLA policies using both automated VLM-guided scoring and scalable human preference judgments collected from crowdworkers, transforming human involvement from tedious scene setup, resetting, and safety supervision into lightweight preference comparisons. To measure robustness, we systematically perturb simulated environments along multiple axes, such as textures and object placements, stress-testing policy generalization under controlled variation. The result is a continuously evolving, reproducible, and scalable benchmark for real-world trained robot manipulation policies, addressing a critical missing capability in today's robotics landscape.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23571</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:41:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Game-TARS: Pretrained Foundation Models for Scalable Generalist   Multimodal Game Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23691</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23691.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihao Wang, Xujing Li, Yining Ye, Junjie Fang, Haoming Wang, Longxiang Liu, Shihao Liang, Junting Lu, Zhiyong Wu, Jiazhan Feng, Wanjun Zhong, Zili Li, Yu Wang, Yu Miao, Bo Zhou, Yuanfan Li, Hao Wang, Zhongkai Zhao, Faming Wu, Zhengxuan Jiang, Weihao Tan, Heyuan Yao, Shi Yan, Xiangyang Li, Yitao Liang, Yujia Qin, Guang Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Game-TARS, a generalist game agent trained with a unified, scalable action space anchored to human-aligned native keyboard-mouse inputs. Unlike API- or GUI-based approaches, this paradigm enables large-scale continual pre-training across heterogeneous domains, including OS, web, and simulation games. Game-TARS is pre-trained on over 500B tokens with diverse trajectories and multimodal data. Key techniques include a decaying continual loss to reduce causal confusion and an efficient Sparse-Thinking strategy that balances reasoning depth and inference cost. Experiments show that Game-TARS achieves about 2 times the success rate over the previous sota model on open-world Minecraft tasks, is close to the generality of fresh humans in unseen web 3d games, and outperforms GPT-5, Gemini-2.5-Pro, and Claude-4-Sonnet in FPS benchmarks. Scaling results on training-time and test-time confirm that the unified action space sustains improvements when scaled to cross-game and multimodal data. Our results demonstrate that simple, scalable action representations combined with large-scale pre-training provide a promising path toward generalist agents with broad computer-use abilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23691</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:43:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lookahead Anchoring: Preserving Character Identity in Audio-Driven Human   Animation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23581</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23581.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyoung Seo, Rodrigo Mira, Alexandros Haliassos, Stella Bounareli, Honglie Chen, Linh Tran, Seungryong Kim, Zoe Landgraf, Jie Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Audio-driven human animation models often suffer from identity drift during temporal autoregressive generation, where characters gradually lose their identity over time. One solution is to generate keyframes as intermediate temporal anchors that prevent degradation, but this requires an additional keyframe generation stage and can restrict natural motion dynamics. To address this, we propose Lookahead Anchoring, which leverages keyframes from future timesteps ahead of the current generation window, rather than within it. This transforms keyframes from fixed boundaries into directional beacons: the model continuously pursues these future anchors while responding to immediate audio cues, maintaining consistent identity through persistent guidance. This also enables self-keyframing, where the reference image serves as the lookahead target, eliminating the need for keyframe generation entirely. We find that the temporal lookahead distance naturally controls the balance between expressivity and consistency: larger distances allow for greater motion freedom, while smaller ones strengthen identity adherence. When applied to three recent human animation models, Lookahead Anchoring achieves superior lip synchronization, identity preservation, and visual quality, demonstrating improved temporal conditioning across several different architectures. Video results are available at the following link: https://lookahead-anchoring.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23581</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:50:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Data Agents: Emerging Paradigm or Overstated Hype?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23587</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23587.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yizhang Zhu, Liangwei Wang, Chenyu Yang, Xiaotian Lin, Boyan Li, Wei Zhou, Xinyu Liu, Zhangyang Peng, Tianqi Luo, Yu Li, Chengliang Chai, Chong Chen, Shimin Di, Ju Fan, Ji Sun, Nan Tang, Fugee Tsung, Jiannan Wang, Chenglin Wu, Yanwei Xu, Shaolei Zhang, Yong Zhang, Xuanhe Zhou, Guoliang Li, Yuyu Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of large language models (LLMs) has spurred the emergence of data agents--autonomous systems designed to orchestrate Data + AI ecosystems for tackling complex data-related tasks. However, the term "data agent" currently suffers from terminological ambiguity and inconsistent adoption, conflating simple query responders with sophisticated autonomous architectures. This terminological ambiguity fosters mismatched user expectations, accountability challenges, and barriers to industry growth. Inspired by the SAE J3016 standard for driving automation, this survey introduces the first systematic hierarchical taxonomy for data agents, comprising six levels that delineate and trace progressive shifts in autonomy, from manual operations (L0) to a vision of generative, fully autonomous data agents (L5), thereby clarifying capability boundaries and responsibility allocation. Through this lens, we offer a structured review of existing research arranged by increasing autonomy, encompassing specialized data agents for data management, preparation, and analysis, alongside emerging efforts toward versatile, comprehensive systems with enhanced autonomy. We further analyze critical evolutionary leaps and technical gaps for advancing data agents, especially the ongoing L2-to-L3 transition, where data agents evolve from procedural execution to autonomous orchestration. Finally, we conclude with a forward-looking roadmap, envisioning the advent of proactive, generative data agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23587</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:54:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FARMER: Flow AutoRegressive Transformer over Pixels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23588</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23588.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guangting Zheng, Qinyu Zhao, Tao Yang, Fei Xiao, Zhijie Lin, Jie Wu, Jiajun Deng, Yanyong Zhang, Rui Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Directly modeling the explicit likelihood of the raw data distribution is key topic in the machine learning area, which achieves the scaling successes in Large Language Models by autoregressive modeling. However, continuous AR modeling over visual pixel data suffer from extremely long sequences and high-dimensional spaces. In this paper, we present FARMER, a novel end-to-end generative framework that unifies Normalizing Flows (NF) and Autoregressive (AR) models for tractable likelihood estimation and high-quality image synthesis directly from raw pixels. FARMER employs an invertible autoregressive flow to transform images into latent sequences, whose distribution is modeled implicitly by an autoregressive model. To address the redundancy and complexity in pixel-level modeling, we propose a self-supervised dimension reduction scheme that partitions NF latent channels into informative and redundant groups, enabling more effective and efficient AR modeling. Furthermore, we design a one-step distillation scheme to significantly accelerate inference speed and introduce a resampling-based classifier-free guidance algorithm to boost image generation quality. Extensive experiments demonstrate that FARMER achieves competitive performance compared to existing pixel-based generative models while providing exact likelihoods and scalable training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23588</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:54:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRISM-Bench: A Benchmark of Puzzle-Based Visual Tasks with CoT Error   Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23594</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23594.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yusu Qian, Cheng Wan, Chao Jia, Yinfei Yang, Qingyu Zhao, Zhe Gan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce PRISM-Bench, a benchmark of puzzle-based visual challenges designed to evaluate not only whether models can solve problems, but how their reasoning unfolds. Unlike prior evaluations that measure only final-answer accuracy, PRISM-Bench introduces a diagnostic task: given a visual puzzle and a step-by-step chain-of-thought (CoT) containing exactly one error, models must identify the first incorrect step. This setting enables fine-grained assessment of logical consistency, error detection, and visual reasoning. The puzzles in PRISM-Bench require multi-step symbolic, geometric, and analogical reasoning, resisting shortcuts based on superficial pattern matching. Evaluations across state-of-the-art MLLMs reveal a persistent gap between fluent generation and faithful reasoning: models that produce plausible CoTs often fail to locate simple logical faults. By disentangling answer generation from reasoning verification, PRISM-Bench offers a sharper lens on multimodal reasoning competence and underscores the need for diagnostic evaluation protocols in the development of trustworthy MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23594</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:57:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Agent Evolve: LLM Self-Improve through Co-evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23595</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23595.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yixing Chen, Yiding Wang, Siqi Zhu, Haofei Yu, Tao Feng, Muhan Zhan, Mostofa Patwary, Jiaxuan You&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning (RL) has demonstrated significant potential in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). However, the success of RL for LLMs heavily relies on human-curated datasets and verifiable rewards, which limit their scalability and generality. Recent Self-Play RL methods, inspired by the success of the paradigm in games and Go, aim to enhance LLM reasoning capabilities without human-annotated data. However, their methods primarily depend on a grounded environment for feedback (e.g., a Python interpreter or a game engine); extending them to general domains remains challenging. To address these challenges, we propose Multi-Agent Evolve (MAE), a framework that enables LLMs to self-evolve in solving diverse tasks, including mathematics, reasoning, and general knowledge Q&amp;A. The core design of MAE is based on a triplet of interacting agents (Proposer, Solver, Judge) that are instantiated from a single LLM, and applies reinforcement learning to optimize their behaviors. The Proposer generates questions, the Solver attempts solutions, and the Judge evaluates both while co-evolving. Experiments on Qwen2.5-3B-Instruct demonstrate that MAE achieves an average improvement of 4.54% on multiple benchmarks. These results highlight MAE as a scalable, data-efficient method for enhancing the general reasoning abilities of LLMs with minimal reliance on human-curated supervision.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23595</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:58:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PixelRefer: A Unified Framework for Spatio-Temporal Object Referring   with Arbitrary Granularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23603</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23603.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqian Yuan, Wenqiao Zhang, Xin Li, Shihao Wang, Kehan Li, Wentong Li, Jun Xiao, Lei Zhang, Beng Chin Ooi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have demonstrated strong general-purpose capabilities in open-world visual comprehension. However, most existing MLLMs primarily focus on holistic, scene-level understanding, often overlooking the need for fine-grained, object-centric reasoning. In this paper, we present PixelRefer, a unified region-level MLLM framework that enables advanced fine-grained understanding over user-specified regions across both images and videos. Motivated by the observation that LLM attention predominantly focuses on object-level tokens, we propose a Scale-Adaptive Object Tokenizer (SAOT) to generate compact and semantically rich object representations from free-form regions. Our analysis reveals that global visual tokens contribute mainly in early LLM layers, inspiring the design of PixelRefer-Lite, an efficient variant that employs an Object-Centric Infusion module to pre-fuse global context into object tokens. This yields a lightweight Object-Only Framework that substantially reduces computational cost while maintaining high semantic fidelity. To facilitate fine-grained instruction tuning, we curate PixelRefer-2.2M, a high-quality object-centric instruction dataset. Extensive experiments across a range of benchmarks validate that PixelRefer achieves leading performance with fewer training samples, while PixelRefer-Lite offers competitive accuracy with notable gains in efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23603</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Track, Inpaint, Resplat: Subject-driven 3D and 4D Generation with   Progressive Texture Infilling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23605</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23605.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuhong Zheng, Ashkan Mirzaei, Igor Gilitschenski&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current 3D/4D generation methods are usually optimized for photorealism, efficiency, and aesthetics. However, they often fail to preserve the semantic identity of the subject across different viewpoints. Adapting generation methods with one or few images of a specific subject (also known as Personalization or Subject-driven generation) allows generating visual content that align with the identity of the subject. However, personalized 3D/4D generation is still largely underexplored. In this work, we introduce TIRE (Track, Inpaint, REsplat), a novel method for subject-driven 3D/4D generation. It takes an initial 3D asset produced by an existing 3D generative model as input and uses video tracking to identify the regions that need to be modified. Then, we adopt a subject-driven 2D inpainting model for progressively infilling the identified regions. Finally, we resplat the modified 2D multi-view observations back to 3D while still maintaining consistency. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach significantly improves identity preservation in 3D/4D generation compared to state-of-the-art methods. Our project website is available at https://zsh2000.github.io/track-inpaint-resplat.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23605</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concerto: Joint 2D-3D Self-Supervised Learning Emerges Spatial   Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23607</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23607.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yujia Zhang, Xiaoyang Wu, Yixing Lao, Chengyao Wang, Zhuotao Tian, Naiyan Wang, Hengshuang Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 168&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humans learn abstract concepts through multisensory synergy, and once formed, such representations can often be recalled from a single modality. Inspired by this principle, we introduce Concerto, a minimalist simulation of human concept learning for spatial cognition, combining 3D intra-modal self-distillation with 2D-3D cross-modal joint embedding. Despite its simplicity, Concerto learns more coherent and informative spatial features, as demonstrated by zero-shot visualizations. It outperforms both standalone SOTA 2D and 3D self-supervised models by 14.2% and 4.8%, respectively, as well as their feature concatenation, in linear probing for 3D scene perception. With full fine-tuning, Concerto sets new SOTA results across multiple scene understanding benchmarks (e.g., 80.7% mIoU on ScanNet). We further present a variant of Concerto tailored for video-lifted point cloud spatial understanding, and a translator that linearly projects Concerto representations into CLIP's language space, enabling open-world perception. These results highlight that Concerto emerges spatial representations with superior fine-grained geometric and semantic consistency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23607</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 17:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magentic Marketplace: An Open-Source Environment for Studying Agentic   Markets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25779</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25779.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gagan Bansal, Wenyue Hua, Zezhou Huang, Adam Fourney, Amanda Swearngin, Will Epperson, Tyler Payne, Jake M. Hofman, Brendan Lucier, Chinmay Singh, Markus Mobius, Akshay Nambi, Archana Yadav, Kevin Gao, David M. Rothschild, Aleksandrs Slivkins, Daniel G. Goldstein, Hussein Mozannar, Nicole Immorlica, Maya Murad, Matthew Vogel, Subbarao Kambhampati, Eric Horvitz, Saleema Amershi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As LLM agents advance, they are increasingly mediating economic decisions, ranging from product discovery to transactions, on behalf of users. Such applications promise benefits but also raise many questions about agent accountability and value for users. Addressing these questions requires understanding how agents behave in realistic market conditions. However, previous research has largely evaluated agents in constrained settings, such as single-task marketplaces (e.g., negotiation) or structured two-agent interactions. Real-world markets are fundamentally different: they require agents to handle diverse economic activities and coordinate within large, dynamic ecosystems where multiple agents with opaque behaviors may engage in open-ended dialogues. To bridge this gap, we investigate two-sided agentic marketplaces where Assistant agents represent consumers and Service agents represent competing businesses. To study these interactions safely, we develop Magentic-Marketplace-- a simulated environment where Assistants and Services can operate. This environment enables us to study key market dynamics: the utility agents achieve, behavioral biases, vulnerability to manipulation, and how search mechanisms shape market outcomes. Our experiments show that frontier models can approach optimal welfare-- but only under ideal search conditions. Performance degrades sharply with scale, and all models exhibit severe first-proposal bias, creating 10-30x advantages for response speed over quality. These findings reveal how behaviors emerge across market conditions, informing the design of fair and efficient agentic marketplaces.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25779</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 18:35:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboOmni: Proactive Robot Manipulation in Omni-modal Context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23763</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23763.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyin Wang, Jinlan Fu, Feihong Liu, Xinzhe He, Huangxuan Wu, Junhao Shi, Kexin Huang, Zhaoye Fei, Jingjing Gong, Zuxuan Wu, Yugang Jiang, See-Kiong Ng, Tat-Seng Chua, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have driven rapid progress in Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models for robotic manipulation. Although effective in many scenarios, current approaches largely rely on explicit instructions, whereas in real-world interactions, humans rarely issue instructions directly. Effective collaboration requires robots to infer user intentions proactively. In this work, we introduce cross-modal contextual instructions, a new setting where intent is derived from spoken dialogue, environmental sounds, and visual cues rather than explicit commands. To address this new setting, we present RoboOmni, a Perceiver-Thinker-Talker-Executor framework based on end-to-end omni-modal LLMs that unifies intention recognition, interaction confirmation, and action execution. RoboOmni fuses auditory and visual signals spatiotemporally for robust intention recognition, while supporting direct speech interaction. To address the absence of training data for proactive intention recognition in robotic manipulation, we build OmniAction, comprising 140k episodes, 5k+ speakers, 2.4k event sounds, 640 backgrounds, and six contextual instruction types. Experiments in simulation and real-world settings show that RoboOmni surpasses text- and ASR-based baselines in success rate, inference speed, intention recognition, and proactive assistance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23763</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 18:49:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Chain-of-Thought for Visual Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23925</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.23925.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guohao Sun, Hang Hua, Jian Wang, Jiebo Luo, Sohail Dianat, Majid Rabbani, Raghuveer Rao, Zhiqiang Tao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning is critical for improving the interpretability and reliability of Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs). However, existing training algorithms such as SFT, PPO, and GRPO may not generalize well across unseen reasoning tasks and heavily rely on a biased reward model. To address this challenge, we reformulate reasoning in LVLMs as posterior inference and propose a scalable training algorithm based on amortized variational inference. By leveraging diversity-seeking reinforcement learning algorithms, we introduce a novel sparse reward function for token-level learning signals that encourage diverse, high-likelihood latent CoT, overcoming deterministic sampling limitations and avoiding reward hacking. Additionally, we implement a Bayesian inference-scaling strategy that replaces costly Best-of-N and Beam Search with a marginal likelihood to efficiently rank optimal rationales and answers. We empirically demonstrate that the proposed method enhances the state-of-the-art LVLMs on seven reasoning benchmarks, in terms of effectiveness, generalization, and interpretability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23925</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 23:10:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MASPRM: Multi-Agent System Process Reward Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24803</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24803.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Milad Yazdani, Mahdi Mostajabdaveh, Zirui Zhou, Ying Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Practical deployment of Multi-Agent Systems (MAS) demands strong test-time performance, motivating methods that guide inference-time search and selectively spend compute to improve quality. We present the Multi-Agent System Process Reward Model (MASPRM). It assigns per-action, per-agent values to partial inter-agent transcripts and acts as an inference-time controller. MASPRM is trained from multi-agent Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS) rollouts without requiring step-level human annotations, by propagating returns to local targets. At inference, MASPRM guides step-level beam search and MCTS, focusing computation on promising branches and pruning early. On GSM8K and MATH, MASPRM-guided decoding with an outcome reward model (ORM) applied to the final answer, improves exact match (EM) over a single straight-through MAS pass by +30.7 and +22.9 points, respectively. A MASPRM trained on GSM8K transfers zero-shot to MATH without retraining, adding 8.4 EM points at the same budget. MASPRM is a plug-in value model that estimates per-agent progress and complements verifier-style decoders, enabling more reliable, compute-aware multi-agent reasoning. Code: https://github.com/milad1378yz/MASPRM&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24803</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:48:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global PIQA: Evaluating Physical Commonsense Reasoning Across 100+   Languages and Cultures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24081</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24081.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tyler A. Chang, Catherine Arnett, Abdelrahman Eldesokey, Abdelrahman Sadallah, Abeer Kashar, Abolade Daud, Abosede Grace Olanihun, Adamu Labaran Mohammed, Adeyemi Praise, Adhikarinayum Meerajita Sharma, Aditi Gupta, Afitab Iyigun, Afonso Simplício, Ahmed Essouaied, Aicha Chorana, Akhil Eppa, Akintunde Oladipo, Akshay Ramesh, Aleksei Dorkin, Alfred Malengo Kondoro, Alham Fikri Aji, Ali Eren Çetintaş, Allan Hanbury, Alou Dembele, Alp Niksarli, Álvaro Arroyo, Amin Bajand, Amol Khanna, Ana Chkhaidze, Ana Condez, Andiswa Mkhonto, Andrew Hoblitzell, Andrew Tran, Angelos Poulis, Anirban Majumder, Anna Vacalopoulou, Annette Kuuipolani Kanahele Wong, Annika Simonsen, Anton Kovalev, Ashvanth. S, Ayodeji Joseph Lana, Barkin Kinay, Bashar Alhafni, Benedict Cibalinda Busole, Bernard Ghanem, Bharti Nathani, Biljana Stojanovska Đurić, Bola Agbonile, Bragi Bergsson, Bruce Torres Fischer, Burak Tutar, Burcu Alakuş Çınar, Cade J. Kanoniakapueo Kane, Can Udomcharoenchaikit, Catherine Arnett, Chadi Helwe, Chaithra Reddy Nerella, Chen Cecilia Liu, Chiamaka Glory Nwokolo, Cristina España-Bonet, Cynthia Amol, DaeYeop Lee, Dana Arad, Daniil Dzenhaliou, Daria Pugacheva, Dasol Choi, Daud Abolade, David Liu, David Semedo, Deborah Popoola, Deividas Mataciunas, Delphine Nyaboke, Dhyuthy Krishna Kumar, Diogo Glória-Silva, Diogo Tavares, Divyanshu Goyal, DongGeon Lee, Ebele Nwamaka Anajemba, Egonu Ngozi Grace, Elena Mickel, Elena Tutubalina, Elias Herranen, Emile Anand, Emmanuel Habumuremyi, Emuobonuvie Maria Ajiboye, Eryawan Presma Yulianrifat, Esther Adenuga, Ewa Rudnicka, Faith Olabisi Itiola, Faran Taimoor Butt, Fathima Thekkekara, Fatima Haouari, Filbert Aurelian Tjiaranata, Firas Laakom, Francesca Grasso, Francesco Orabona, Francesco Periti, Gbenga Kayode Solomon, Gia Nghia Ngo, Gloria Udhehdhe-oze, Gonçalo Martins, Gopi Naga Sai Ram Challagolla, Guijin Son, Gulnaz Abdykadyrova, Hafsteinn Einarsson, Hai Hu, Hamidreza Saffari, Hamza Zaidi, Haopeng Zhang, Harethah Abu Shairah, Harry Vuong, Hele-Andra Kuulmets, Houda Bouamor, Hwanjo Yu, Iben Nyholm Debess, İbrahim Ethem Deveci, Ikhlasul Akmal Hanif, Ikhyun Cho, Inês Calvo, Inês Vieira, Isaac Manzi, Ismail Daud, Itay Itzhak, Iuliia, Alekseenko, Ivan Belashkin, Ivan Spada, Ivan Zhelyazkov, Jacob Brinton, Jafar Isbarov, Jaka Čibej, Jan Čuhel, Jan Kocoń, Jauza Akbar Krito, Jebish Purbey, Jennifer Mickel, Jennifer Za, Jenny Kunz, Jihae Jeong, Jimena Tena Dávalos, Jinu Lee, João Magalhães, John Yi, Jongin Kim, Joseph Chataignon, Joseph Marvin Imperial, Jubeerathan Thevakumar, Judith Land, Junchen Jiang, Jungwhan Kim, Kairit Sirts, Kamesh R, Kamesh V, Kanda Patrick Tshinu, Kätriin Kukk, Kaustubh Ponkshe, Kavsar Huseynova, Ke He, Kelly Buchanan, Kengatharaiyer Sarveswaran, Kerem Zaman, Khalil Mrini, Kian Kyars, Krister Kruusmaa, Kusum Chouhan, Lainitha Krishnakumar, Laura Castro Sánchez, Laura Porrino Moscoso, Leshem Choshen, Levent Sencan, Lilja Øvrelid, Lisa Alazraki, Lovina Ehimen-Ugbede, Luheerathan Thevakumar, Luxshan Thavarasa, Mahnoor Malik, Mamadou K. Keita, Mansi Jangid, Marco De Santis, Marcos García, Marek Suppa, Mariam D'Ciofalo, Marii Ojastu, Maryam Sikander, Mausami Narayan, Maximos Skandalis, Mehak Mehak, Mehmet İlteriş Bozkurt, Melaku Bayu Workie, Menan Velayuthan, Michael Leventhal, Michał Marcińczuk, Mirna Potočnjak, Mohammadamin Shafiei, Mridul Sharma, Mrityunjaya Indoria, Muhammad Ravi Shulthan Habibi, Murat Kolić, Nada Galant, Naphat Permpredanun, Narada Maugin, Nicholas Kluge Corrêa, Nikola Ljubešić, Nirmal Thomas, Nisansa de Silva, Nisheeth Joshi, Nitish Ponkshe, Nizar Habash, Nneoma C. Udeze, Noel Thomas, Noémi Ligeti-Nagy, Nouhoum Coulibaly, Nsengiyumva Faustin, Odunayo Kareemat Buliaminu, Odunayo Ogundepo, Oghojafor Godswill Fejiro, Ogundipe Blessing Funmilola, Okechukwu God'spraise, Olanrewaju Samuel, Olaoye Deborah Oluwaseun, Olasoji Akindejoye, Olga Popova, Olga Snissarenko, Onyinye Anulika Chiemezie, Orkun Kinay, Osman Tursun, Owoeye Tobiloba Moses, Oyelade Oluwafemi Joshua, Oyesanmi Fiyinfoluwa, Pablo Gamallo, Pablo Rodríguez Fernández, Palak Arora, Pedro Valente, Peter Rupnik, Philip Oghenesuowho Ekiugbo, Pramit Sahoo, Prokopis Prokopidis, Pua Niau-Puhipau, Quadri Yahya, Rachele Mignone, Raghav Singhal, Ram Mohan Rao Kadiyala, Raphael Merx, Rapheal Afolayan, Ratnavel Rajalakshmi, Rishav Ghosh, Romina Oji, Ron Kekeha Solis, Rui Guerra, Rushikesh Zawar, Sa'ad Nasir Bashir, Saeed Alzaabi, Sahil Sandeep, Sai Pavan Batchu, SaiSandeep Kantareddy, Salsabila Zahirah Pranida, Sam Buchanan, Samuel Rutunda, Sander Land, Sarah Sulollari, Sardar Ali, Saroj Sapkota, Saulius Tautvaisas, Sayambhu Sen, Sayantani Banerjee, Sebastien Diarra, SenthilNathan. M, Sewoong Lee, Shaan Shah, Shankar Venkitachalam, Sharifa Djurabaeva, Sharon Ibejih, Shivanya Shomir Dutta, Siddhant Gupta, Silvia Paniagua Suárez, Sina Ahmadi, Sivasuthan Sukumar, Siyuan Song, Snegha A., Sokratis Sofianopoulos, Sona Elza Simon, Sonja Benčina, Sophie Gvasalia, Sphurti Kirit More, Spyros Dragazis, Stephan P. Kaufhold, Suba. S, Sultan AlRashed, Surangika Ranathunga, Taiga Someya, Taja Kuzman Pungeršek, Tal Haklay, Tasi'u Jibril, Tatsuya Aoyama, Tea Abashidze, Terenz Jomar Dela Cruz, Terra Blevins, Themistoklis Nikas, Theresa Dora Idoko, Thu Mai Do, Tilek Chubakov, Tommaso Gargiani, Uma Rathore, Uni Johannesen, Uwuma Doris Ugwu, Vallerie Alexandra Putra, Vanya Bannihatti Kumar, Varsha Jeyarajalingam, Varvara Arzt, Vasudevan Nedumpozhimana, Viktoria Ondrejova, Viktoryia Horbik, Vishnu Vardhan Reddy Kummitha, Vuk Dinić, Walelign Tewabe Sewunetie, Winston Wu, Xiaojing Zhao, Yacouba Diarra, Yaniv Nikankin, Yash Mathur, Yixi Chen, Yiyuan Li, Yolanda Xavier, Yonatan Belinkov, Yusuf Ismail Abayomi, Zaid Alyafeai, Zhengyang Shan, Zhi Rui Tam, Zilu Tang, Zuzana Nadova, Baber Abbasi, Stella Biderman, David Stap, Duygu Ataman, Fabian Schmidt, Hila Gonen, Jiayi Wang, David Ifeoluwa Adelani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; To date, there exist almost no culturally-specific evaluation benchmarks for large language models (LLMs) that cover a large number of languages and cultures. In this paper, we present Global PIQA, a participatory commonsense reasoning benchmark for over 100 languages, constructed by hand by 335 researchers from 65 countries around the world. The 116 language varieties in Global PIQA cover five continents, 14 language families, and 23 writing systems. In the non-parallel split of Global PIQA, over 50% of examples reference local foods, customs, traditions, or other culturally-specific elements. We find that state-of-the-art LLMs perform well on Global PIQA in aggregate, but they exhibit weaker performance in lower-resource languages (up to a 37% accuracy gap, despite random chance at 50%). Open models generally perform worse than proprietary models. Global PIQA highlights that in many languages and cultures, everyday knowledge remains an area for improvement, alongside more widely-discussed capabilities such as complex reasoning and expert knowledge. Beyond its uses for LLM evaluation, we hope that Global PIQA provides a glimpse into the wide diversity of cultures in which human language is embedded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24081</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 05:46:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critique-RL: Training Language Models for Critiquing through Two-Stage   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24320</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24320.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiheng Xi, Jixuan Huang, Xin Guo, Boyang Hong, Dingwen Yang, Xiaoran Fan, Shuo Li, Zehui Chen, Junjie Ye, Siyu Yuan, Zhengyin Du, Xuesong Yao, Yufei Xu, Jiecao Chen, Rui Zheng, Tao Gui, Qi Zhang, Xuanjing Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training critiquing language models to assess and provide feedback on model outputs is a promising way to improve LLMs for complex reasoning tasks. However, existing approaches typically rely on stronger supervisors for annotating critique data. To address this, we propose Critique-RL, an online RL approach for developing critiquing language models without stronger supervision. Our approach operates on a two-player paradigm: the actor generates a response, the critic provides feedback, and the actor refines the response accordingly. We first reveal that relying solely on indirect reward signals from the actor's outputs for RL optimization often leads to unsatisfactory critics: while their helpfulness (i.e., providing constructive feedback) improves, the discriminability (i.e., determining whether a response is high-quality or not) remains poor, resulting in marginal performance gains. To overcome this, Critique-RL adopts a two-stage optimization strategy. In stage I, it reinforces the discriminability of the critic with direct rule-based reward signals; in stage II, it introduces indirect rewards based on actor refinement to improve the critic's helpfulness, while maintaining its discriminability via appropriate regularization. Extensive experiments across various tasks and models show that Critique-RL delivers substantial performance improvements. For example, it achieves a 9.02% gain on in-domain tasks and a 5.70% gain on out-of-domain tasks for Qwen2.5-7B, highlighting its potential.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24320</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 11:37:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Visual Intelligence: Insights from Video Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24448</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24448.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pablo Acuaviva, Aram Davtyan, Mariam Hassan, Sebastian Stapf, Ahmad Rahimi, Alexandre Alahi, Paolo Favaro&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated that large-scale pretraining enables systems to adapt rapidly to new problems with little supervision in the language domain. This success, however, has not translated as effectively to the visual domain, where models, including LLMs, continue to struggle with compositional understanding, sample efficiency, and general-purpose problem-solving. We investigate Video Diffusion Models (VDMs) as a promising direction for bridging this gap. Pretraining on spatiotemporal data endows these models with strong inductive biases for structure and dynamics, which we hypothesize can support broad task adaptability. To test this, we design a controlled evaluation in which both a pretrained LLM and a pretrained VDM are equipped with lightweight adapters and presented with tasks in their natural modalities. Across benchmarks including ARC-AGI, ConceptARC, visual games, route planning, and cellular automata, VDMs demonstrate higher data efficiency than their language counterparts. Taken together, our results indicate that video pretraining offers inductive biases that support progress toward visual foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24448</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 14:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ming-Flash-Omni: A Sparse, Unified Architecture for Multimodal   Perception and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24821</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24821.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Inclusion AI, Bowen Ma, Cheng Zou, Canxiang Yan, Chunxiang Jin, Chunjie Shen, Dandan Zheng, Fudong Wang, Furong Xu, GuangMing Yao, Jun Zhou, Jingdong Chen, Jianing Li, Jianxin Sun, Jiajia Liu, Jianjiang Zhu, Jianping Jiang, Jun Peng, Kaixiang Ji, Kaimeng Ren, Libin Wang, Lixiang Ru, Longhua Tan, Lan Wang, Mochen Bai, Ning Gao, Qingpei Guo, Qinglong Zhang, Qiang Xu, Rui Liu, Ruijie Xiong, Ruobing Zheng, Sirui Gao, Tianqi Li, Tinghao Liu, Weilong Chai, Xinyu Xiao, Xiaomei Wang, Xiaolong Wang, Xiao Lu, Xiaoyu Li, Xingning Dong, Xuzheng Yu, Yi Yuan, Yuting Gao, Yuting Xiao, Yunxiao Sun, Yipeng Chen, Yifan Mao, Yifei Wu, Yongjie Lyu, Ziping Ma, Zhiqiang Fang, Zhihao Qiu, Ziyuan Huang, Zizheng Yang, Zhengyu He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose Ming-Flash-Omni, an upgraded version of Ming-Omni, built upon a sparser Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) variant of Ling-Flash-2.0 with 100 billion total parameters, of which only 6.1 billion are active per token. This architecture enables highly efficient scaling (dramatically improving computational efficiency while significantly expanding model capacity) and empowers stronger unified multimodal intelligence across vision, speech, and language, representing a key step toward Artificial General Intelligence (AGI). Compared to its predecessor, the upgraded version exhibits substantial improvements across multimodal understanding and generation. We significantly advance speech recognition capabilities, achieving state-of-the-art performance in contextual ASR and highly competitive results in dialect-aware ASR. In image generation, Ming-Flash-Omni introduces high-fidelity text rendering and demonstrates marked gains in scene consistency and identity preservation during image editing. Furthermore, Ming-Flash-Omni introduces generative segmentation, a capability that not only achieves strong standalone segmentation performance but also enhances spatial control in image generation and improves editing consistency. Notably, Ming-Flash-Omni achieves state-of-the-art results in text-to-image generation and generative segmentation, and sets new records on all 12 contextual ASR benchmarks, all within a single unified architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24821</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 15:24:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Sketchpad: Sketching Visual Thoughts to Elicit Multimodal   Reasoning in MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24514</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24514.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huanyu Zhang, Wenshan Wu, Chengzu Li, Ning Shang, Yan Xia, Yangyu Huang, Yifan Zhang, Li Dong, Zhang Zhang, Liang Wang, Tieniu Tan, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) excel at visual understanding, they often struggle in complex scenarios that require visual planning and imagination. Inspired by how humans use sketching as a form of visual thinking to develop and communicate ideas, we introduce Latent Sketchpad, a framework that equips MLLMs with an internal visual scratchpad. The internal visual representations of MLLMs have traditionally been confined to perceptual understanding. We repurpose them to support generative visual thought without compromising reasoning ability. Building on frontier MLLMs, our approach integrates visual generation directly into their native autoregressive reasoning process. It allows the model to interleave textual reasoning with the generation of visual latents. These latents guide the internal thought process and can be translated into sketch images for interpretability. To realize this, we introduce two components: a Context-Aware Vision Head autoregressively produces visual representations, and a pretrained Sketch Decoder renders these into human-interpretable images. We evaluate the framework on our new dataset MazePlanning. Experiments across various MLLMs show that Latent Sketchpad delivers comparable or even superior reasoning performance to their backbone. It further generalizes across distinct frontier MLLMs, including Gemma3 and Qwen2.5-VL. By extending model's textual reasoning to visual thinking, our framework opens new opportunities for richer human-computer interaction and broader applications. More details and resources are available on our project page: https://latent-sketchpad.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24514</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 15:26:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel Loop Transformer for Efficient Test-Time Computation Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24824</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24824.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bohong Wu, Mengzhao Chen, Xiang Luo, Shen Yan, Qifan Yu, Fan Xia, Tianqi Zhang, Hongrui Zhan, Zheng Zhong, Xun Zhou, Siyuan Qiao, Xingyan Bin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are powerful but often too slow and costly for real-world use during inference. Looped transformers save on parameters by reusing the same weights for multiple computational steps, or "loops." However, this approach has a major flaw: the loops run one after another, causing inference latency and memory requirements to increase with each added loop. This makes them impractical for fast applications. To solve this problem, we introduce the Parallel Loop Transformer (PLT). PLT is a new architecture that delivers the performance benefits of a deep, looped model but with the low latency of a standard, non-looped model. PLT works using two key techniques. First, Cross-Loop Parallelism (CLP) breaks the sequential dependency by computing different loops for different tokens at the same time, all within a single pass. Second, to prevent memory costs from growing, we use an Efficient Representation Enhancement strategy. This method shares the memory (KV cache) from the first loop with all other loops. It then uses a Gated Sliding-Window Attention (G-SWA) to combine this shared global information with local information, maintaining high accuracy. Our experiments show that PLT achieves the high accuracy of a traditional looped model but with almost no extra latency or memory cost compared to a standard transformer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24824</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 15:35:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OSWorld-MCP: Benchmarking MCP Tool Invocation In Computer-Use Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24563</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24563.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongrui Jia, Jitong Liao, Xi Zhang, Haiyang Xu, Tianbao Xie, Chaoya Jiang, Ming Yan, Si Liu, Wei Ye, Fei Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With advances in decision-making and reasoning capabilities, multimodal agents show strong potential in computer application scenarios. Past evaluations have mainly assessed GUI interaction skills, while tool invocation abilities, such as those enabled by the Model Context Protocol (MCP), have been largely overlooked. Comparing agents with integrated tool invocation to those evaluated only on GUI interaction is inherently unfair. We present OSWorld-MCP, the first comprehensive and fair benchmark for assessing computer-use agents' tool invocation, GUI operation, and decision-making abilities in a real-world environment. We design a novel automated code-generation pipeline to create tools and combine them with a curated selection from existing tools. Rigorous manual validation yields 158 high-quality tools (covering 7 common applications), each verified for correct functionality, practical applicability, and versatility. Extensive evaluations of state-of-the-art multimodal agents on OSWorld-MCP show that MCP tools generally improve task success rates (e.g., from 8.3% to 20.4% for OpenAI o3 at 15 steps, from 40.1% to 43.3% for Claude 4 Sonnet at 50 steps), underscoring the importance of assessing tool invocation capabilities. However, even the strongest models have relatively low tool invocation rates, Only 36.3%, indicating room for improvement and highlighting the benchmark's challenge. By explicitly measuring MCP tool usage skills, OSWorld-MCP deepens understanding of multimodal agents and sets a new standard for evaluating performance in complex, tool-assisted environments. Our code, environment, and data are publicly available at https://osworld-mcp.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24563</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 15:56:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReForm: Reflective Autoformalization with Prospective Bounded Sequence   Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24592</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24592.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guoxin Chen, Jing Wu, Xinjie Chen, Wayne Xin Zhao, Ruihua Song, Chengxi Li, Kai Fan, Dayiheng Liu, Minpeng Liao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoformalization, which translates natural language mathematics into machine-verifiable formal statements, is critical for using formal mathematical reasoning to solve math problems stated in natural language. While Large Language Models can generate syntactically correct formal statements, they often fail to preserve the original problem's semantic intent. This limitation arises from the LLM approaches' treating autoformalization as a simplistic translation task which lacks mechanisms for self-reflection and iterative refinement that human experts naturally employ. To address these issues, we propose ReForm, a Reflective Autoformalization method that tightly integrates semantic consistency evaluation into the autoformalization process. This enables the model to iteratively generate formal statements, assess its semantic fidelity, and self-correct identified errors through progressive refinement. To effectively train this reflective model, we introduce Prospective Bounded Sequence Optimization (PBSO), which employs different rewards at different sequence positions to ensure that the model develops both accurate autoformalization and correct semantic validations, preventing superficial critiques that would undermine the purpose of reflection. Extensive experiments across four autoformalization benchmarks demonstrate that ReForm achieves an average improvement of 17.2 percentage points over the strongest baselines. To further ensure evaluation reliability, we introduce ConsistencyCheck, a benchmark of 859 expert-annotated items that not only validates LLMs as judges but also reveals that autoformalization is inherently difficult: even human experts produce semantic errors in up to 38.5% of cases.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24592</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 16:22:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FunReason-MT Technical Report: Overcoming the Complexity Barrier in   Multi-Turn Function Calling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24645</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24645.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zengzhuang Xu, Bingguang Hao, Zechuan Wang, Yuntao Wen, Maolin Wang, Yang Liu, Long Chen, Dong Wang, Yicheng Chen, Cunyin Peng, Chenyi Zhuang, Jinjie Gu, Leilei Gan, Xiangyu Zhao, Shi Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Function calling (FC) empowers large language models (LLMs) and autonomous agents to interface with external tools, a critical capability for solving complex, real-world problems. As this ability becomes increasingly central to advanced AI systems, the need for high-quality, multi-turn training data to develop and refine it cannot be overstated. Existing data synthesis methods, such as random environment sampling or multi-agent role-playing, are not powerful enough to generate high-quality data in real-world environments. Practical challenges come in three folds: targeted model training, isolation of tool architecture, and multi-turn logical dependency. To address these structural deficiencies, we present FunReason-MT, a novel data synthesis framework for real-world multi-turn tool use. FunReason-MT resolves the complexity barrier in multi-turn FC data by employing 1) Environment-API Graph Interactions to gather varied high-quality trajectories, 2) Advanced Tool-Query Synthesis to simplify hard query construction, and 3) Guided Iterative Chain for sophisticated CoT generation. Evaluations on Berkeley Function-Calling Leaderboard (BFCLv3) demonstrate the power of our framework: a 4B model built upon FunReason-MT generated data achieves state-of-the-art performance among comparable-sized models, outperforming most close-source models. Further performance improvements on BFCLv4 confirm that FunReason-MT provides a reliable and robust source for agentic learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24645</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:15:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolving Diagnostic Agents in a Virtual Clinical Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24654</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24654.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengcheng Qiu, Chaoyi Wu, Junwei Liu, Qiaoyu Zheng, Yusheng Liao, Haowen Wang, Yun Yue, Qianrui Fan, Shuai Zhen, Jian Wang, Jinjie Gu, Yanfeng Wang, Ya Zhang, Weidi Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we present a framework for training large language models (LLMs) as diagnostic agents with reinforcement learning, enabling them to manage multi-turn diagnostic processes, adaptively select examinations, and commit to final diagnoses. Unlike instruction-tuned models trained on static case summaries, our method acquires diagnostic strategies through interactive exploration and outcome-based feedback. Our contributions are fourfold: (i) We present DiagGym, a diagnostics world model trained with electronic health records that emits examination outcomes conditioned on patient history and recommended examination, serving as a virtual clinical environment for realistic diagnosis training and evaluation; (ii) We train DiagAgent via end-to-end, multi-turn reinforcement learning to learn diagnostic policies that optimize both information yield and diagnostic accuracy; (iii) We introduce DiagBench, a diagnostic benchmark comprising 750 cases with physician-validated examination recommendations and 99 cases annotated with 973 physician-written rubrics on diagnosis process; (iv) we demonstrate superior performance across diverse diagnostic settings. DiagAgent significantly outperforms 10 state-of-the-art LLMs, including DeepSeek-v3 and GPT-4o, as well as two prompt-engineered agents. In single-turn settings, DiagAgent achieves 9.34% higher diagnostic accuracy and 44.03% improvement in examination recommendation hit ratio. In end-to-end settings, it delivers 15.12% increase in diagnostic accuracy and 23.09% boost in examination recommendation F1 score. In rubric-based evaluation, it surpasses the next-best model, Claude-sonnet-4, by 7.1% in weighted rubric score. These findings indicate that learning policies in interactive clinical environments confers dynamic and clinically meaningful diagnostic management abilities unattainable through passive training alone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24654</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:19:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group Relative Attention Guidance for Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24657</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24657.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuanpu Zhang, Xuesong Niu, Ruidong Chen, Dan Song, Jianhao Zeng, Penghui Du, Haoxiang Cao, Kai Wu, An-an Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, image editing based on Diffusion-in-Transformer models has undergone rapid development. However, existing editing methods often lack effective control over the degree of editing, limiting their ability to achieve more customized results. To address this limitation, we investigate the MM-Attention mechanism within the DiT model and observe that the Query and Key tokens share a bias vector that is only layer-dependent. We interpret this bias as representing the model's inherent editing behavior, while the delta between each token and its corresponding bias encodes the content-specific editing signals. Based on this insight, we propose Group Relative Attention Guidance, a simple yet effective method that reweights the delta values of different tokens to modulate the focus of the model on the input image relative to the editing instruction, enabling continuous and fine-grained control over editing intensity without any tuning. Extensive experiments conducted on existing image editing frameworks demonstrate that GRAG can be integrated with as few as four lines of code, consistently enhancing editing quality. Moreover, compared to the commonly used Classifier-Free Guidance, GRAG achieves smoother and more precise control over the degree of editing. Our code will be released at https://github.com/little-misfit/GRAG-Image-Editing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24657</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InteractComp: Evaluating Search Agents With Ambiguous Queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24668</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24668.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingyi Deng, Lijun Huang, Yani Fan, Jiayi Zhang, Fashen Ren, Jinyi Bai, Fuzhen Yang, Dayi Miao, Zhaoyang Yu, Yifan Wu, Yanfei Zhang, Fengwei Teng, Yingjia Wan, Song Hu, Yude Li, Xin Jin, Conghao Hu, Haoyu Li, Qirui Fu, Tai Zhong, Xinyu Wang, Xiangru Tang, Nan Tang, Chenglin Wu, Yuyu Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 94&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language agents have demonstrated remarkable potential in web search and information retrieval. However, these search agents assume user queries are complete and unambiguous, an assumption that diverges from reality where users begin with incomplete queries requiring clarification through interaction. Yet most agents lack interactive mechanisms during the search process, and existing benchmarks cannot assess this capability. To address this gap, we introduce InteractComp, a benchmark designed to evaluate whether search agents can recognize query ambiguity and actively interact to resolve it during search. Following the principle of easy to verify, interact to disambiguate, we construct 210 expert-curated questions across 9 domains through a target-distractor methodology that creates genuine ambiguity resolvable only through interaction. Evaluation of 17 models reveals striking failure: the best model achieves only 13.73% accuracy despite 71.50% with complete context, exposing systematic overconfidence rather than reasoning deficits. Forced interaction produces dramatic gains, demonstrating latent capability current strategies fail to engage. Longitudinal analysis shows interaction capabilities stagnated over 15 months while search performance improved seven-fold, revealing a critical blind spot. This stagnation, coupled with the immediate feedback inherent to search tasks, makes InteractComp a valuable resource for both evaluating and training interaction capabilities in search agents. The code is available at https://github.com/FoundationAgents/InteractComp.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24668</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:35:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPICE: Self-Play In Corpus Environments Improves Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24684</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24684.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bo Liu, Chuanyang Jin, Seungone Kim, Weizhe Yuan, Wenting Zhao, Ilia Kulikov, Xian Li, Sainbayar Sukhbaatar, Jack Lanchantin, Jason Weston&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-improving systems require environmental interaction for continuous adaptation. We introduce SPICE (Self-Play In Corpus Environments), a reinforcement learning framework where a single model acts in two roles: a Challenger that mines documents from a large corpus to generate diverse reasoning tasks, and a Reasoner that solves them. Through adversarial dynamics, the Challenger creates an automatic curriculum at the frontier of the Reasoner's capability, while corpus grounding provides the rich, near-inexhaustible external signal necessary for sustained improvement. Unlike existing ungrounded self-play methods that offer more limited benefits, SPICE achieves consistent gains across mathematical (+8.9%) and general reasoning (+9.8%) benchmarks on multiple model families. Our analysis reveals how document grounding is a key ingredient in SPICE to continuously generate its own increasingly challenging goals and achieve them, enabling sustained self-improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24684</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:46:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STAR-Bench: Probing Deep Spatio-Temporal Reasoning as Audio 4D   Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24693</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24693.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihan Liu, Zhikang Niu, Qiuyang Xiao, Zhisheng Zheng, Ruoqi Yuan, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Xiaoyi Dong, Jianze Liang, Xie Chen, Leilei Sun, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite rapid progress in Multi-modal Large Language Models and Large Audio-Language Models, existing audio benchmarks largely test semantics that can be recovered from text captions, masking deficits in fine-grained perceptual reasoning. We formalize audio 4D intelligence that is defined as reasoning over sound dynamics in time and 3D space, and introduce STAR-Bench to measure it. STAR-Bench combines a Foundational Acoustic Perception setting (six attributes under absolute and relative regimes) with a Holistic Spatio-Temporal Reasoning setting that includes segment reordering for continuous and discrete processes and spatial tasks spanning static localization, multi-source relations, and dynamic trajectories. Our data curation pipeline uses two methods to ensure high-quality samples. For foundational tasks, we use procedurally synthesized and physics-simulated audio. For holistic data, we follow a four-stage process that includes human annotation and final selection based on human performance. Unlike prior benchmarks where caption-only answering reduces accuracy slightly, STAR-Bench induces far larger drops (-31.5\% temporal, -35.2\% spatial), evidencing its focus on linguistically hard-to-describe cues. Evaluating 19 models reveals substantial gaps compared with humans and a capability hierarchy: closed-source models are bottlenecked by fine-grained perception, while open-source models lag across perception, knowledge, and reasoning. Our STAR-Bench provides critical insights and a clear path forward for developing future models with a more robust understanding of the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24693</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:50:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repurposing Synthetic Data for Fine-grained Search Agent Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24694</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24694.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yida Zhao, Kuan Li, Xixi Wu, Liwen Zhang, Dingchu Zhang, Baixuan Li, Maojia Song, Zhuo Chen, Chenxi Wang, Xinyu Wang, Kewei Tu, Pengjun Xie, Jingren Zhou, Yong Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM-based search agents are increasingly trained on entity-centric synthetic data to solve complex, knowledge-intensive tasks. However, prevailing training methods like Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) discard this rich entity information, relying instead on sparse, outcome-based rewards. This critical limitation renders them unable to distinguish informative "near-miss" samples-those with substantially correct reasoning but a flawed final answer-from complete failures, thus discarding valuable learning signals. We address this by leveraging the very entities discarded during training. Our empirical analysis reveals a strong positive correlation between the number of ground-truth entities identified during an agent's reasoning process and final answer accuracy. Building on this insight, we introduce Entity-aware Group Relative Policy Optimization (E-GRPO), a novel framework that formulates a dense entity-aware reward function. E-GRPO assigns partial rewards to incorrect samples proportional to their entity match rate, enabling the model to effectively learn from these "near-misses". Experiments on diverse question-answering (QA) and deep research benchmarks show that E-GRPO consistently and significantly outperforms the GRPO baseline. Furthermore, our analysis reveals that E-GRPO not only achieves superior accuracy but also induces more efficient reasoning policies that require fewer tool calls, demonstrating a more effective and sample-efficient approach to aligning search agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24694</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:50:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AgentFrontier: Expanding the Capability Frontier of LLM Agents with   ZPD-Guided Data Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24695</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24695.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuanzhong Chen, Zile Qiao, Guoxin Chen, Liangcai Su, Zhen Zhang, Xinyu Wang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Yong Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training large language model agents on tasks at the frontier of their capabilities is key to unlocking advanced reasoning. We introduce a data synthesis approach inspired by the educational theory of the Zone of Proximal Development (ZPD), which defines this frontier as tasks an LLM cannot solve alone but can master with guidance. To operationalize this, we present the AgentFrontier Engine, an automated pipeline that synthesizes high-quality, multidisciplinary data situated precisely within the LLM's ZPD. This engine supports both continued pre-training with knowledge-intensive data and targeted post-training on complex reasoning tasks. From the same framework, we derive the ZPD Exam, a dynamic and automated benchmark designed to evaluate agent capabilities on these frontier tasks. We train AgentFrontier-30B-A3B model on our synthesized data, which achieves state-of-the-art results on demanding benchmarks like Humanity's Last Exam, even surpassing some leading proprietary agents. Our work demonstrates that a ZPD-guided approach to data synthesis offers a scalable and effective path toward building more capable LLM agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24695</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:50:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebLeaper: Empowering Efficiency and Efficacy in WebAgent via Enabling   Info-Rich Seeking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24697</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24697.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengwei Tao, Haiyang Shen, Baixuan Li, Wenbiao Yin, Jialong Wu, Kuan Li, Zhongwang Zhang, Huifeng Yin, Rui Ye, Liwen Zhang, Xinyu Wang, Pengjun Xie, Jingren Zhou, Yong Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Model (LLM)-based agents have emerged as a transformative approach for open-ended problem solving, with information seeking (IS) being a core capability that enables autonomous reasoning and decision-making. While prior research has largely focused on improving retrieval depth, we observe that current IS agents often suffer from low search efficiency, which in turn constrains overall performance. A key factor underlying this inefficiency is the sparsity of target entities in training tasks, which limits opportunities for agents to learn and generalize efficient search behaviors. To address these challenges, we propose WebLeaper, a framework for constructing high-coverage IS tasks and generating efficient solution trajectories. We formulate IS as a tree-structured reasoning problem, enabling a substantially larger set of target entities to be embedded within a constrained context. Leveraging curated Wikipedia tables, we propose three variants for synthesizing IS tasks, Basic, Union, and Reverse-Union, to systematically increase both IS efficiency and efficacy. Finally, we curate training trajectories by retaining only those that are simultaneously accurate and efficient, ensuring that the model is optimized for both correctness and search performance. Extensive experiments on both basic and comprehensive settings, conducted on five IS benchmarks, BrowserComp, GAIA, xbench-DeepSearch, WideSearch, and Seal-0, demonstrate that our method consistently achieves improvements in both effectiveness and efficiency over strong baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24697</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:51:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ParallelMuse: Agentic Parallel Thinking for Deep Information Seeking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24698</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24698.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baixuan Li, Dingchu Zhang, Jialong Wu, Wenbiao Yin, Zhengwei Tao, Yida Zhao, Liwen Zhang, Haiyang Shen, Runnan Fang, Pengjun Xie, Jingren Zhou, Yong Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Parallel thinking expands exploration breadth, complementing the deep exploration of information-seeking (IS) agents to further enhance problem-solving capability. However, conventional parallel thinking faces two key challenges in this setting: inefficiency from repeatedly rolling out from scratch, and difficulty in integrating long-horizon reasoning trajectories during answer generation, as limited context capacity prevents full consideration of the reasoning process. To address these issues, we propose ParallelMuse, a two-stage paradigm designed for deep IS agents. The first stage, Functionality-Specified Partial Rollout, partitions generated sequences into functional regions and performs uncertainty-guided path reuse and branching to enhance exploration efficiency. The second stage, Compressed Reasoning Aggregation, exploits reasoning redundancy to losslessly compress information relevant to answer derivation and synthesize a coherent final answer. Experiments across multiple open-source agents and benchmarks demonstrate up to 62% performance improvement with a 10--30% reduction in exploratory token consumption.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24698</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:51:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AgentFold: Long-Horizon Web Agents with Proactive Context Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24699</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24699.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui Ye, Zhongwang Zhang, Kuan Li, Huifeng Yin, Zhengwei Tao, Yida Zhao, Liangcai Su, Liwen Zhang, Zile Qiao, Xinyu Wang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Siheng Chen, Jingren Zhou, Yong Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM-based web agents show immense promise for information seeking, yet their effectiveness on long-horizon tasks is hindered by a fundamental trade-off in context management. Prevailing ReAct-based agents suffer from context saturation as they accumulate noisy, raw histories, while methods that fixedly summarize the full history at each step risk the irreversible loss of critical details. Addressing these, we introduce AgentFold, a novel agent paradigm centered on proactive context management, inspired by the human cognitive process of retrospective consolidation. AgentFold treats its context as a dynamic cognitive workspace to be actively sculpted, rather than a passive log to be filled. At each step, it learns to execute a `folding' operation, which manages its historical trajectory at multiple scales: it can perform granular condensations to preserve vital, fine-grained details, or deep consolidations to abstract away entire multi-step sub-tasks. The results on prominent benchmarks are striking: with simple supervised fine-tuning (without continual pre-training or RL), our AgentFold-30B-A3B agent achieves 36.2% on BrowseComp and 47.3% on BrowseComp-ZH. Notably, this performance not only surpasses or matches open-source models of a dramatically larger scale, such as the DeepSeek-V3.1-671B-A37B, but also surpasses leading proprietary agents like OpenAI's o4-mini.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24699</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:51:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tongyi DeepResearch Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24701</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24701.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tongyi DeepResearch Team, Baixuan Li, Bo Zhang, Dingchu Zhang, Fei Huang, Guangyu Li, Guoxin Chen, Huifeng Yin, Jialong Wu, Jingren Zhou, Kuan Li, Liangcai Su, Litu Ou, Liwen Zhang, Pengjun Xie, Rui Ye, Wenbiao Yin, Xinmiao Yu, Xinyu Wang, Xixi Wu, Xuanzhong Chen, Yida Zhao, Zhen Zhang, Zhengwei Tao, Zhongwang Zhang, Zile Qiao, Chenxi Wang, Donglei Yu, Gang Fu, Haiyang Shen, Jiayin Yang, Jun Lin, Junkai Zhang, Kui Zeng, Li Yang, Hailong Yin, Maojia Song, Ming Yan, Peng Xia, Qian Xiao, Rui Min, Ruixue Ding, Runnan Fang, Shaowei Chen, Shen Huang, Shihang Wang, Shihao Cai, Weizhou Shen, Xiaobin Wang, Xin Guan, Xinyu Geng, Yingcheng Shi, Yuning Wu, Zhuo Chen, Zijian Li, Yong Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 83&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Tongyi DeepResearch, an agentic large language model, which is specifically designed for long-horizon, deep information-seeking research tasks. To incentivize autonomous deep research agency, Tongyi DeepResearch is developed through an end-to-end training framework that combines agentic mid-training and agentic post-training, enabling scalable reasoning and information seeking across complex tasks. We design a highly scalable data synthesis pipeline that is fully automatic, without relying on costly human annotation, and empowers all training stages. By constructing customized environments for each stage, our system enables stable and consistent interactions throughout. Tongyi DeepResearch, featuring 30.5 billion total parameters, with only 3.3 billion activated per token, achieves state-of-the-art performance across a range of agentic deep research benchmarks, including Humanity's Last Exam, BrowseComp, BrowseComp-ZH, WebWalkerQA, xbench-DeepSearch, FRAMES and xbench-DeepSearch-2510. We open-source the model, framework, and complete solutions to empower the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24701</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:53:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent Data Protocol: Unifying Datasets for Diverse, Effective   Fine-tuning of LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24702</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24702.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yueqi Song, Ketan Ramaneti, Zaid Sheikh, Ziru Chen, Boyu Gou, Tianbao Xie, Yiheng Xu, Danyang Zhang, Apurva Gandhi, Fan Yang, Joseph Liu, Tianyue Ou, Zhihao Yuan, Frank Xu, Shuyan Zhou, Xingyao Wang, Xiang Yue, Tao Yu, Huan Sun, Yu Su, Graham Neubig&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Public research results on large-scale supervised finetuning of AI agents remain relatively rare, since the collection of agent training data presents unique challenges. In this work, we argue that the bottleneck is not a lack of underlying data sources, but that a large variety of data is fragmented across heterogeneous formats, tools, and interfaces. To this end, we introduce the agent data protocol (ADP), a light-weight representation language that serves as an "interlingua" between agent datasets in diverse formats and unified agent training pipelines downstream. The design of ADP is expressive enough to capture a large variety of tasks, including API/tool use, browsing, coding, software engineering, and general agentic workflows, while remaining simple to parse and train on without engineering at a per-dataset level. In experiments, we unified a broad collection of 13 existing agent training datasets into ADP format, and converted the standardized ADP data into training-ready formats for multiple agent frameworks. We performed SFT on these data, and demonstrated an average performance gain of ~20% over corresponding base models, and delivers state-of-the-art or near-SOTA performance on standard coding, browsing, tool use, and research benchmarks, without domain-specific tuning. All code and data are released publicly, in the hope that ADP could help lower the barrier to standardized, scalable, and reproducible agent training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24702</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:53:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Routing Matters in MoE: Scaling Diffusion Transformers with Explicit   Routing Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24711</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24711.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yujie Wei, Shiwei Zhang, Hangjie Yuan, Yujin Han, Zhekai Chen, Jiayu Wang, Difan Zou, Xihui Liu, Yingya Zhang, Yu Liu, Hongming Shan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) has emerged as a powerful paradigm for scaling model capacity while preserving computational efficiency. Despite its notable success in large language models (LLMs), existing attempts to apply MoE to Diffusion Transformers (DiTs) have yielded limited gains. We attribute this gap to fundamental differences between language and visual tokens. Language tokens are semantically dense with pronounced inter-token variation, while visual tokens exhibit spatial redundancy and functional heterogeneity, hindering expert specialization in vision MoE. To this end, we present ProMoE, an MoE framework featuring a two-step router with explicit routing guidance that promotes expert specialization. Specifically, this guidance encourages the router to partition image tokens into conditional and unconditional sets via conditional routing according to their functional roles, and refine the assignments of conditional image tokens through prototypical routing with learnable prototypes based on semantic content. Moreover, the similarity-based expert allocation in latent space enabled by prototypical routing offers a natural mechanism for incorporating explicit semantic guidance, and we validate that such guidance is crucial for vision MoE. Building on this, we propose a routing contrastive loss that explicitly enhances the prototypical routing process, promoting intra-expert coherence and inter-expert diversity. Extensive experiments on ImageNet benchmark demonstrate that ProMoE surpasses state-of-the-art methods under both Rectified Flow and DDPM training objectives. Code and models will be made publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24711</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform Discrete Diffusion with Metric Path for Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24717</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24717.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoge Deng, Ting Pan, Fan Zhang, Yang Liu, Zhuoyan Luo, Yufeng Cui, Wenxuan Wang, Chunhua Shen, Shiguang Shan, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Xinlong Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Continuous-space video generation has advanced rapidly, while discrete approaches lag behind due to error accumulation and long-context inconsistency. In this work, we revisit discrete generative modeling and present Uniform discRete diffuSion with metric pAth (URSA), a simple yet powerful framework that bridges the gap with continuous approaches for the scalable video generation. At its core, URSA formulates the video generation task as an iterative global refinement of discrete spatiotemporal tokens. It integrates two key designs: a Linearized Metric Path and a Resolution-dependent Timestep Shifting mechanism. These designs enable URSA to scale efficiently to high-resolution image synthesis and long-duration video generation, while requiring significantly fewer inference steps. Additionally, we introduce an asynchronous temporal fine-tuning strategy that unifies versatile tasks within a single model, including interpolation and image-to-video generation. Extensive experiments on challenging video and image generation benchmarks demonstrate that URSA consistently outperforms existing discrete methods and achieves performance comparable to state-of-the-art continuous diffusion methods. Code and models are available at https://github.com/baaivision/URSA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24717</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automating Benchmark Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25039</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25039.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amanda Dsouza, Harit Vishwakarma, Zhengyang Qi, Justin Bauer, Derek Pham, Thomas Walshe, Armin Parchami, Frederic Sala, Paroma Varma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid progress and widespread deployment of LLMs and LLM-powered agents has outpaced our ability to evaluate them. Hand-crafted, static benchmarks are the primary tool for assessing model capabilities, but these quickly become saturated. In contrast, dynamic benchmarks evolve alongside the models they evaluate, but are expensive to create and continuously update. To address these challenges, we develop BeTaL (Benchmark Tuning with an LLM-in-the-loop), a framework that leverages environment design principles to automate the process of dynamic benchmark design. BeTaL works by parameterizing key design choices in base benchmark templates and uses LLMs to reason through the resulting parameter space to obtain target properties (such as difficulty and realism) in a cost-efficient manner. We validate this approach on its ability to create benchmarks with desired difficulty levels. Using BeTaL, we create two new benchmarks and extend a popular agentic benchmark tau-bench. Extensive evaluation on these three tasks and multiple target difficulty levels shows that BeTaL produces benchmarks much closer to the desired difficulty, with average deviations ranging from 5.3% to 13.2% -- a 2-4x improvement over the baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25039</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 23:53:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning-Aware GRPO using Process Mining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25065</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25065.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taekhyun Park, Yongjae Lee, Hyerim Bae&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL)-based post-training has been crucial for enabling multi-step reasoning in large reasoning models (LRMs), yet current reward schemes are typically outcome-centric. We propose PM4GRPO, a reasoning-aware Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) that augments standard answer/format rewards with signals over the reasoning procedure. To this end, process mining techniques are utilized to compute a scalar conformance reward that measures how closely a policy model's reasoning aligns with the pretrained teacher model. The empirical results on five benchmarks demonstrate that PM4GRPO significantly outperforms existing methodologies for GRPO-based post-training. These results highlight that leveraging process mining for reasoning-aware GRPO effectively enhances the reasoning capabilities of policy models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25065</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 01:07:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SeeingEye: Agentic Information Flow Unlocks Multimodal Reasoning In   Text-only LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25092</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25092.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weijia Zhang, Zijia Liu, Haoru Li, Haoqi Chen, Jiaxuan You&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in text-only large language models (LLMs), such as DeepSeek-R1, demonstrate remarkable reasoning ability. However, these models remain fragile or entirely incapable when extended to multi-modal tasks. Existing approaches largely rely on single-form captions, which lack diversity and often fail to adapt across different types of Visual Question Answering (VQA) benchmarks. As a result, they provide no principled or efficient channel for transmitting fine-grained visual information. We introduce Seeing Eye, a modular framework that unlocks multimodal reasoning in text-only LLMs through an agent-based small VLM translator. This translator acts as a perception agent: it can invoke specialized tools (e.g., OCR and crop) and iteratively distill multimodal inputs into structured intermediate representations (SIRs) tailored to the question. These SIRs are then passed to the text-only LLM, which serves as a reasoning agent. Crucially, the translator and reasoner engage in multi-round feedback and interaction, enabling the extraction of targeted visual details and yielding more confident answers. Experiments on knowledge-intensive VQA benchmarks, including MMMU and MIA-Bench, demonstrate that Seeing Eye not only reduces inference cost but also surpasses much larger end-to-end VLMs. For example, an instantiation combining a 3B-parameter vision translator with an 8B-parameter language reasoner outperforms a monolithic 32B VLM on challenging knowledge-based questions. Our results highlight that decoupling perception from reasoning via agent information flow offers a scalable and plug-and-play pathway to multimodal reasoning, allowing strong text-only LLMs to fully leverage their reasoning capabilities. Code is available at: https://github.com/ulab-uiuc/SeeingEye&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25092</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 01:57:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RegionE: Adaptive Region-Aware Generation for Efficient Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25590</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25590.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengtao Chen, Xianfang Zeng, Maosen Zhao, Mingzhu Shen, Peng Ye, Bangyin Xiang, Zhibo Wang, Wei Cheng, Gang Yu, Tao Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, instruction-based image editing (IIE) has received widespread attention. In practice, IIE often modifies only specific regions of an image, while the remaining areas largely remain unchanged. Although these two types of regions differ significantly in generation difficulty and computational redundancy, existing IIE models do not account for this distinction, instead applying a uniform generation process across the entire image. This motivates us to propose RegionE, an adaptive, region-aware generation framework that accelerates IIE tasks without additional training. Specifically, the RegionE framework consists of three main components: 1) Adaptive Region Partition. We observed that the trajectory of unedited regions is straight, allowing for multi-step denoised predictions to be inferred in a single step. Therefore, in the early denoising stages, we partition the image into edited and unedited regions based on the difference between the final estimated result and the reference image. 2) Region-Aware Generation. After distinguishing the regions, we replace multi-step denoising with one-step prediction for unedited areas. For edited regions, the trajectory is curved, requiring local iterative denoising. To improve the efficiency and quality of local iterative generation, we propose the Region-Instruction KV Cache, which reduces computational cost while incorporating global information. 3) Adaptive Velocity Decay Cache. Observing that adjacent timesteps in edited regions exhibit strong velocity similarity, we further propose an adaptive velocity decay cache to accelerate the local denoising process. We applied RegionE to state-of-the-art IIE base models, including Step1X-Edit, FLUX.1 Kontext, and Qwen-Image-Edit. RegionE achieved acceleration factors of 2.57, 2.41, and 2.06. Evaluations by GPT-4o confirmed that semantic and perceptual fidelity were well preserved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25590</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 14:58:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EHR-R1: A Reasoning-Enhanced Foundational Language Model for Electronic   Health Record Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25628</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25628.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yusheng Liao, Chaoyi Wu, Junwei Liu, Shuyang Jiang, Pengcheng Qiu, Haowen Wang, Yun Yue, Shuai Zhen, Jian Wang, Qianrui Fan, Jinjie Gu, Ya Zhang, Yanfeng Wang, Yu Wang, Weidi Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Electronic Health Records (EHRs) contain rich yet complex information, and their automated analysis is critical for clinical decision-making. Despite recent advances of large language models (LLMs) in clinical workflows, their ability to analyze EHRs remains limited due to narrow task coverage and lack of EHR-oriented reasoning capabilities. This paper aims to bridge the gap, specifically, we present EHR-Ins, a large-scale, comprehensive EHR reasoning instruction dataset, comprising 300k high-quality reasoning cases and 4M non-reasoning cases across 42 distinct EHR tasks. Its core innovation is a thinking-graph-driven framework that enables to generate high-quality reasoning data at scale. Based on it, we develop EHR-R1, a series of reasoning-enhanced LLMs with up to 72B parameters tailored for EHR analysis. Through a multi-stage training paradigm, including domain adaptation, reasoning enhancement, and reinforcement learning, EHR-R1 systematically acquires domain knowledge and diverse reasoning capabilities, enabling accurate and robust EHR analysis. Lastly, we introduce EHR-Bench, a new benchmark curated from MIMIC-IV, spanning 42 tasks, to comprehensively assess reasoning and prediction across EHR scenarios. In experiments, we show that the resulting EHR-R1 consistently outperforms state-of-the-art commercial and open-source LLMs (including DeepSeek-V3 and GPT-4o), surpassing GPT-4o by over 30 points on MIMIC-Bench and achieving a 10\% higher zero-shot AUROC on EHRSHOT. Collectively, EHR-Ins, EHR-R1, and EHR-Bench have significantly advanced the development for more reliable and clinically relevant EHR analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25628</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 15:32:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PairUni: Pairwise Training for Unified Multimodal Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25682</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25682.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiani Zheng, Zhiyang Teng, Xiangtai Li, Anran Wang, Yu Tian, Kunpeng Qiu, Ye Tian, Haochen Wang, Zhuochen Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified vision-language models (UVLMs) must perform both understanding and generation within a single architecture, but these tasks rely on heterogeneous data and supervision, making it difficult to balance them during reinforcement learning (RL). We propose PairUni, a unified framework that reorganizes data into understanding-generation (UG) pairs and aligns optimization accordingly. We first use GPT-o3 to augment single-task data, generating captions for understanding samples and question-answer (QA) pairs for generation samples, forming aligned pairs from the same instance. Additionally, for each generation sample, we retrieve a semantically related understanding example to form a retrieved pair, linking different but related data points. These paired structures expose cross-task semantic correspondences and support consistent policy learning. To leverage this structure, we present Pair-GPRO, a pair-aware variant based on Group Relative Policy Optimization. It assigns a similarity score to each pair to modulate the advantage, strengthening learning from well-aligned examples and reducing task interference. We curate a high-quality dataset of 16K UG pairs named PairUG for RL fine-tuning and evaluate PairUni on the powerful Janus-Pro UVLMs. Our approach achieves balanced improvements on various UVLMs, outperforming strong UVLM RL baselines. Code: https://github.com/Haochen-Wang409/PairUni{github.com/Haochen-Wang409/PairUni}&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25682</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 16:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Tool Decathlon: Benchmarking Language Agents for Diverse, Realistic,   and Long-Horizon Task Execution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25726</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25726.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junlong Li, Wenshuo Zhao, Jian Zhao, Weihao Zeng, Haoze Wu, Xiaochen Wang, Rui Ge, Yuxuan Cao, Yuzhen Huang, Wei Liu, Junteng Liu, Zhaochen Su, Yiyang Guo, Fan Zhou, Lueyang Zhang, Juan Michelini, Xingyao Wang, Xiang Yue, Shuyan Zhou, Graham Neubig, Junxian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Real-world language agents must handle complex, multi-step workflows across diverse Apps. For instance, an agent may manage emails by coordinating with calendars and file systems, or monitor a production database to detect anomalies and generate reports following an operating manual. However, existing language agent benchmarks often focus on narrow domains or simplified tasks that lack the diversity, realism, and long-horizon complexity required to evaluate agents' real-world performance. To address this gap, we introduce the Tool Decathlon (dubbed as Toolathlon), a benchmark for language agents offering diverse Apps and tools, realistic environment setup, and reliable execution-based evaluation. Toolathlon spans 32 software applications and 604 tools, ranging from everyday platforms such as Google Calendar and Notion to professional ones like WooCommerce, Kubernetes, and BigQuery. Most of the tools are based on a high-quality set of Model Context Protocol (MCP) servers that we may have revised or implemented ourselves. Unlike prior works, which primarily ensure functional realism but offer limited environment state diversity, we provide realistic initial environment states from real software, such as Canvas courses with dozens of students or real financial spreadsheets. This benchmark includes 108 manually sourced or crafted tasks in total, requiring interacting with multiple Apps over around 20 turns on average to complete. Each task is strictly verifiable through dedicated evaluation scripts. Comprehensive evaluation of SOTA models highlights their significant shortcomings: the best-performing model, Claude-4.5-Sonnet, achieves only a 38.6% success rate with 20.2 tool calling turns on average, while the top open-weights model DeepSeek-V3.2-Exp reaches 20.1%. We expect Toolathlon to drive the development of more capable language agents for real-world, long-horizon task execution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25726</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Latent Reasoning via Looped Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25741</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25741.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui-Jie Zhu, Zixuan Wang, Kai Hua, Tianyu Zhang, Ziniu Li, Haoran Que, Boyi Wei, Zixin Wen, Fan Yin, He Xing, Lu Li, Jiajun Shi, Kaijing Ma, Shanda Li, Taylor Kergan, Andrew Smith, Xingwei Qu, Mude Hui, Bohong Wu, Qiyang Min, Hongzhi Huang, Xun Zhou, Wei Ye, Jiaheng Liu, Jian Yang, Yunfeng Shi, Chenghua Lin, Enduo Zhao, Tianle Cai, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Yoshua Bengio, Jason Eshraghian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 182&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern LLMs are trained to "think" primarily via explicit text generation, such as chain-of-thought (CoT), which defers reasoning to post-training and under-leverages pre-training data. We present and open-source Ouro, named after the recursive Ouroboros, a family of pre-trained Looped Language Models (LoopLM) that instead build reasoning into the pre-training phase through (i) iterative computation in latent space, (ii) an entropy-regularized objective for learned depth allocation, and (iii) scaling to 7.7T tokens. Ouro 1.4B and 2.6B models enjoy superior performance that match the results of up to 12B SOTA LLMs across a wide range of benchmarks. Through controlled experiments, we show this advantage stems not from increased knowledge capacity, but from superior knowledge manipulation capabilities. We also show that LoopLM yields reasoning traces more aligned with final outputs than explicit CoT. We hope our results show the potential of LoopLM as a novel scaling direction in the reasoning era. Our model could be found in: http://ouro-llm.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25741</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 17:45:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Spatial Reasoning in the Large Model Era: A Survey and   Benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25760</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25760.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xu Zheng, Zihao Dongfang, Lutao Jiang, Boyuan Zheng, Yulong Guo, Zhenquan Zhang, Giuliano Albanese, Runyi Yang, Mengjiao Ma, Zixin Zhang, Chenfei Liao, Dingcheng Zhen, Yuanhuiyi Lyu, Yuqian Fu, Bin Ren, Linfeng Zhang, Danda Pani Paudel, Nicu Sebe, Luc Van Gool, Xuming Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humans possess spatial reasoning abilities that enable them to understand spaces through multimodal observations, such as vision and sound. Large multimodal reasoning models extend these abilities by learning to perceive and reason, showing promising performance across diverse spatial tasks. However, systematic reviews and publicly available benchmarks for these models remain limited. In this survey, we provide a comprehensive review of multimodal spatial reasoning tasks with large models, categorizing recent progress in multimodal large language models (MLLMs) and introducing open benchmarks for evaluation. We begin by outlining general spatial reasoning, focusing on post-training techniques, explainability, and architecture. Beyond classical 2D tasks, we examine spatial relationship reasoning, scene and layout understanding, as well as visual question answering and grounding in 3D space. We also review advances in embodied AI, including vision-language navigation and action models. Additionally, we consider emerging modalities such as audio and egocentric video, which contribute to novel spatial understanding through new sensors. We believe this survey establishes a solid foundation and offers insights into the growing field of multimodal spatial reasoning. Updated information about this survey, codes and implementation of the open benchmarks can be found at https://github.com/zhengxuJosh/Awesome-Spatial-Reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25760</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 17:55:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaperon: A Peppered English-French Generative Language Model Suite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25771</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25771.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nathan Godey, Wissam Antoun, Rian Touchent, Rachel Bawden, Éric de la Clergerie, Benoît Sagot, Djamé Seddah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We release Gaperon, a fully open suite of French-English-coding language models designed to advance transparency and reproducibility in large-scale model training. The Gaperon family includes 1.5B, 8B, and 24B parameter models trained on 2-4 trillion tokens, released with all elements of the training pipeline: French and English datasets filtered with a neural quality classifier, an efficient data curation and training framework, and hundreds of intermediate checkpoints. Through this work, we study how data filtering and contamination interact to shape both benchmark and generative performance. We find that filtering for linguistic quality enhances text fluency and coherence but yields subpar benchmark results, and that late deliberate contamination -- continuing training on data mixes that include test sets -- recovers competitive scores while only reasonably harming generation quality. We discuss how usual neural filtering can unintentionally amplify benchmark leakage. To support further research, we also introduce harmless data poisoning during pretraining, providing a realistic testbed for safety studies. By openly releasing all models, datasets, code, and checkpoints, Gaperon establishes a reproducible foundation for exploring the trade-offs between data curation, evaluation, safety, and openness in multilingual language model development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25771</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 17:59:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VFXMaster: Unlocking Dynamic Visual Effect Generation via In-Context   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25772</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25772.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baolu Li, Yiming Zhang, Qinghe Wang, Liqian Ma, Xiaoyu Shi, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Zhenfei Yin, Yunzhi Zhuge, Huchuan Lu, Xu Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual effects (VFX) are crucial to the expressive power of digital media, yet their creation remains a major challenge for generative AI. Prevailing methods often rely on the one-LoRA-per-effect paradigm, which is resource-intensive and fundamentally incapable of generalizing to unseen effects, thus limiting scalability and creation. To address this challenge, we introduce VFXMaster, the first unified, reference-based framework for VFX video generation. It recasts effect generation as an in-context learning task, enabling it to reproduce diverse dynamic effects from a reference video onto target content. In addition, it demonstrates remarkable generalization to unseen effect categories. Specifically, we design an in-context conditioning strategy that prompts the model with a reference example. An in-context attention mask is designed to precisely decouple and inject the essential effect attributes, allowing a single unified model to master the effect imitation without information leakage. In addition, we propose an efficient one-shot effect adaptation mechanism to boost generalization capability on tough unseen effects from a single user-provided video rapidly. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method effectively imitates various categories of effect information and exhibits outstanding generalization to out-of-domain effects. To foster future research, we will release our code, models, and a comprehensive dataset to the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25772</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 17:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedVLSynther: Synthesizing High-Quality Visual Question Answering from   Medical Documents with Generator-Verifier LMMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25867</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25867.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoke Huang, Ningsen Wang, Hui Liu, Xianfeng Tang, Yuyin Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) are increasingly capable of answering medical questions that require joint reasoning over images and text, yet training general medical VQA systems is impeded by the lack of large, openly usable, high-quality corpora. We present MedVLSynther, a rubric-guided generator-verifier framework that synthesizes high-quality multiple-choice VQA items directly from open biomedical literature by conditioning on figures, captions, and in-text references. The generator produces self-contained stems and parallel, mutually exclusive options under a machine-checkable JSON schema; a multi-stage verifier enforces essential gates (self-containment, single correct answer, clinical validity, image-text consistency), awards fine-grained positive points, and penalizes common failure modes before acceptance. Applying this pipeline to PubMed Central yields MedSynVQA: 13,087 audited questions over 14,803 images spanning 13 imaging modalities and 28 anatomical regions. Training open-weight LMMs with reinforcement learning using verifiable rewards improves accuracy across six medical VQA benchmarks, achieving averages of 55.85 (3B) and 58.15 (7B), with up to 77.57 on VQA-RAD and 67.76 on PathVQA, outperforming strong medical LMMs. A Ablations verify that both generation and verification are necessary and that more verified data consistently helps, and a targeted contamination analysis detects no leakage from evaluation suites. By operating entirely on open literature and open-weight models, MedVLSynther offers an auditable, reproducible, and privacy-preserving path to scalable medical VQA training data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25867</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 18:10:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MIRO: MultI-Reward cOnditioned pretraining improves T2I quality and   efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25897</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25897.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nicolas Dufour, Lucas Degeorge, Arijit Ghosh, Vicky Kalogeiton, David Picard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current text-to-image generative models are trained on large uncurated datasets to enable diverse generation capabilities. However, this does not align well with user preferences. Recently, reward models have been specifically designed to perform post-hoc selection of generated images and align them to a reward, typically user preference. This discarding of informative data together with the optimizing for a single reward tend to harm diversity, semantic fidelity and efficiency. Instead of this post-processing, we propose to condition the model on multiple reward models during training to let the model learn user preferences directly. We show that this not only dramatically improves the visual quality of the generated images but it also significantly speeds up the training. Our proposed method, called MIRO, achieves state-of-the-art performances on the GenEval compositional benchmark and user-preference scores (PickAScore, ImageReward, HPSv2).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25897</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 18:59:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supervised Reinforcement Learning: From Expert Trajectories to Step-wise   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25992</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25992.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yihe Deng, I-Hung Hsu, Jun Yan, Zifeng Wang, Rujun Han, Gufeng Zhang, Yanfei Chen, Wei Wang, Tomas Pfister, Chen-Yu Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) often struggle with problems that require multi-step reasoning. For small-scale open-source models, Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) fails when correct solutions are rarely sampled even after many attempts, while Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) tends to overfit long demonstrations through rigid token-by-token imitation. To address this gap, we propose Supervised Reinforcement Learning (SRL), a framework that reformulates problem solving as generating a sequence of logical "actions". SRL trains the model to generate an internal reasoning monologue before committing to each action. It provides smoother rewards based on the similarity between the model's actions and expert actions extracted from the SFT dataset in a step-wise manner. This supervision offers richer learning signals even when all rollouts are incorrect, while encouraging flexible reasoning guided by expert demonstrations. As a result, SRL enables small models to learn challenging problems previously unlearnable by SFT or RLVR. Moreover, initializing training with SRL before refining with RLVR yields the strongest overall performance. Beyond reasoning benchmarks, SRL generalizes effectively to agentic software engineering tasks, establishing it as a robust and versatile training framework for reasoning-oriented LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25992</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 22:05:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniLayout: Enabling Coarse-to-Fine Learning with LLMs for Universal   Document Layout Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26213</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26213.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hengrui Kang, Zhuangcheng Gu, Zhiyuan Zhao, Zichen Wen, Bin Wang, Weijia Li, Conghui He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Document AI has advanced rapidly and is attracting increasing attention. Yet, while most efforts have focused on document layout analysis (DLA), its generative counterpart, document layout generation, remains underexplored. A major obstacle lies in the scarcity of diverse layouts: academic papers with Manhattan-style structures dominate existing studies, while open-world genres such as newspapers and magazines remain severely underrepresented. To address this gap, we curate OmniLayout-1M, the first million-scale dataset of diverse document layouts, covering six common document types and comprising contemporary layouts collected from multiple sources. Moreover, since existing methods struggle in complex domains and often fail to arrange long sequences coherently, we introduce OmniLayout-LLM, a 0.5B model with designed two-stage Coarse-to-Fine learning paradigm: 1) learning universal layout principles from OmniLayout-1M with coarse category definitions, and 2) transferring the knowledge to a specific domain with fine-grained annotations. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach achieves strong performance on multiple domains in M^{6}Doc dataset, substantially surpassing both existing layout generation experts and several latest general-purpose LLMs. Our code, models, and dataset will be publicly released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26213</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 07:39:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Agent Conquer Web? Exploring the Frontiers of ChatGPT Atlas Agent in   Web Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26298</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26298.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingran Zhang, Ning Li, Justin Cui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; OpenAI's ChatGPT Atlas introduces new capabilities for web interaction, enabling the model to analyze webpages, process user intents, and execute cursor and keyboard inputs directly within the browser. While its capacity for information retrieval tasks has been demonstrated, its performance in dynamic, interactive environments remains less explored. In this study, we conduct an early evaluation of Atlas's web interaction capabilities using browser-based games as test scenarios, including Google's T-Rex Runner, Sudoku, Flappy Bird, and Stein.world. We employ in-game performance scores as quantitative metrics to assess performance across different task types. Our results show that Atlas performs strongly in logical reasoning tasks like Sudoku, completing puzzles significantly faster than human baselines, but struggles substantially in real-time games requiring precise timing and motor control, often failing to progress beyond initial obstacles. These findings suggest that while Atlas demonstrates capable analytical processing, there remain notable limitations in dynamic web environments requiring real-time interaction. The website of our project can be found at https://atlas-game-eval.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26298</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 09:35:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emu3.5: Native Multimodal Models are World Learners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26583</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26583.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yufeng Cui, Honghao Chen, Haoge Deng, Xu Huang, Xinghang Li, Jirong Liu, Yang Liu, Zhuoyan Luo, Jinsheng Wang, Wenxuan Wang, Yueze Wang, Chengyuan Wang, Fan Zhang, Yingli Zhao, Ting Pan, Xianduo Li, Zecheng Hao, Wenxuan Ma, Zhuo Chen, Yulong Ao, Tiejun Huang, Zhongyuan Wang, Xinlong Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 82&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Emu3.5, a large-scale multimodal world model that natively predicts the next state across vision and language. Emu3.5 is pre-trained end-to-end with a unified next-token prediction objective on a corpus of vision-language interleaved data containing over 10 trillion tokens, primarily derived from sequential frames and transcripts of internet videos. The model naturally accepts interleaved vision-language inputs and generates interleaved vision-language outputs. Emu3.5 is further post-trained with large-scale reinforcement learning to enhance multimodal reasoning and generation. To improve inference efficiency, we propose Discrete Diffusion Adaptation (DiDA), which converts token-by-token decoding into bidirectional parallel prediction, accelerating per-image inference by about 20x without sacrificing performance. Emu3.5 exhibits strong native multimodal capabilities, including long-horizon vision-language generation, any-to-image (X2I) generation, and complex text-rich image generation. It also exhibits generalizable world-modeling abilities, enabling spatiotemporally consistent world exploration and open-world embodied manipulation across diverse scenarios and tasks. For comparison, Emu3.5 achieves performance comparable to Gemini 2.5 Flash Image (Nano Banana) on image generation and editing tasks and demonstrates superior results on a suite of interleaved generation tasks. We open-source Emu3.5 at https://github.com/baaivision/Emu3.5 to support community research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26583</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 15:11:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Era of Agentic Organization: Learning to Organize with Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26658</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26658.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zewen Chi, Li Dong, Qingxiu Dong, Yaru Hao, Xun Wu, Shaohan Huang, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We envision a new era of AI, termed agentic organization, where agents solve complex problems by working collaboratively and concurrently, enabling outcomes beyond individual intelligence. To realize this vision, we introduce asynchronous thinking (AsyncThink) as a new paradigm of reasoning with large language models, which organizes the internal thinking process into concurrently executable structures. Specifically, we propose a thinking protocol where an organizer dynamically assigns sub-queries to workers, merges intermediate knowledge, and produces coherent solutions. More importantly, the thinking structure in this protocol can be further optimized through reinforcement learning. Experiments demonstrate that AsyncThink achieves 28% lower inference latency compared to parallel thinking while improving accuracy on mathematical reasoning. Moreover, AsyncThink generalizes its learned asynchronous thinking capabilities, effectively tackling unseen tasks without additional training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26658</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 16:25:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kimi Linear: An Expressive, Efficient Attention Architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26692</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26692.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kimi Team, Yu Zhang, Zongyu Lin, Xingcheng Yao, Jiaxi Hu, Fanqing Meng, Chengyin Liu, Xin Men, Songlin Yang, Zhiyuan Li, Wentao Li, Enzhe Lu, Weizhou Liu, Yanru Chen, Weixin Xu, Longhui Yu, Yejie Wang, Yu Fan, Longguang Zhong, Enming Yuan, Dehao Zhang, Yizhi Zhang, T. Y. Liu, Haiming Wang, Shengjun Fang, Weiran He, Shaowei Liu, Yiwei Li, Jianlin Su, Jiezhong Qiu, Bo Pang, Junjie Yan, Zhejun Jiang, Weixiao Huang, Bohong Yin, Jiacheng You, Chu Wei, Zhengtao Wang, Chao Hong, Yutian Chen, Guanduo Chen, Yucheng Wang, Huabin Zheng, Feng Wang, Yibo Liu, Mengnan Dong, Zheng Zhang, Siyuan Pan, Wenhao Wu, Yuhao Wu, Longyu Guan, Jiawen Tao, Guohong Fu, Xinran Xu, Yuzhi Wang, Guokun Lai, Yuxin Wu, Xinyu Zhou, Zhilin Yang, Yulun Du&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 65&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Kimi Linear, a hybrid linear attention architecture that, for the first time, outperforms full attention under fair comparisons across various scenarios -- including short-context, long-context, and reinforcement learning (RL) scaling regimes. At its core lies Kimi Delta Attention (KDA), an expressive linear attention module that extends Gated DeltaNet with a finer-grained gating mechanism, enabling more effective use of limited finite-state RNN memory. Our bespoke chunkwise algorithm achieves high hardware efficiency through a specialized variant of the Diagonal-Plus-Low-Rank (DPLR) transition matrices, which substantially reduces computation compared to the general DPLR formulation while remaining more consistent with the classical delta rule.   We pretrain a Kimi Linear model with 3B activated parameters and 48B total parameters, based on a layerwise hybrid of KDA and Multi-Head Latent Attention (MLA). Our experiments show that with an identical training recipe, Kimi Linear outperforms full MLA with a sizeable margin across all evaluated tasks, while reducing KV cache usage by up to 75% and achieving up to 6 times decoding throughput for a 1M context. These results demonstrate that Kimi Linear can be a drop-in replacement for full attention architectures with superior performance and efficiency, including tasks with longer input and output lengths.   To support further research, we open-source the KDA kernel and vLLM implementations, and release the pre-trained and instruction-tuned model checkpoints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26692</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 16:59:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The End of Manual Decoding: Towards Truly End-to-End Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26697</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26697.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhichao Wang, Dongyang Ma, Xinting Huang, Deng Cai, Tian Lan, Jiahao Xu, Haitao Mi, Xiaoying Tang, Yan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The "end-to-end" label for LLMs is a misnomer. In practice, they depend on a non-differentiable decoding process that requires laborious, hand-tuning of hyperparameters like temperature and top-p. This paper introduces AutoDeco, a novel architecture that enables truly "end-to-end" generation by learning to control its own decoding strategy. We augment the standard transformer with lightweight heads that, at each step, dynamically predict context-specific temperature and top-p values alongside the next-token logits. This approach transforms decoding into a parametric, token-level process, allowing the model to self-regulate its sampling strategy within a single forward pass.   Through extensive experiments on eight benchmarks, we demonstrate that AutoDeco not only significantly outperforms default decoding strategies but also achieves performance comparable to an oracle-tuned baseline derived from "hacking the test set"-a practical upper bound for any static method. Crucially, we uncover an emergent capability for instruction-based decoding control: the model learns to interpret natural language commands (e.g., "generate with low randomness") and adjusts its predicted temperature and top-p on a token-by-token basis, opening a new paradigm for steerable and interactive LLM decoding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26697</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:01:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AMO-Bench: Large Language Models Still Struggle in High School Math   Competitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26768</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26768.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengnan An, Xunliang Cai, Xuezhi Cao, Xiaoyu Li, Yehao Lin, Junlin Liu, Xinxuan Lv, Dan Ma, Xuanlin Wang, Ziwen Wang, Shuang Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present AMO-Bench, an Advanced Mathematical reasoning benchmark with Olympiad level or even higher difficulty, comprising 50 human-crafted problems. Existing benchmarks have widely leveraged high school math competitions for evaluating mathematical reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). However, many existing math competitions are becoming less effective for assessing top-tier LLMs due to performance saturation (e.g., AIME24/25). To address this, AMO-Bench introduces more rigorous challenges by ensuring all 50 problems are (1) cross-validated by experts to meet at least the International Mathematical Olympiad (IMO) difficulty standards, and (2) entirely original problems to prevent potential performance leakages from data memorization. Moreover, each problem in AMO-Bench requires only a final answer rather than a proof, enabling automatic and robust grading for evaluation. Experimental results across 26 LLMs on AMO-Bench show that even the best-performing model achieves only 52.4% accuracy on AMO-Bench, with most LLMs scoring below 40%. Beyond these poor performances, our further analysis reveals a promising scaling trend with increasing test-time compute on AMO-Bench. These results highlight the significant room for improving the mathematical reasoning in current LLMs. We release AMO-Bench to facilitate further research into advancing the reasoning abilities of language models. https://amo-bench.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26768</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:52:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remote Labor Index: Measuring AI Automation of Remote Work</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26787</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26787.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mantas Mazeika, Alice Gatti, Cristina Menghini, Udari Madhushani Sehwag, Shivam Singhal, Yury Orlovskiy, Steven Basart, Manasi Sharma, Denis Peskoff, Elaine Lau, Jaehyuk Lim, Lachlan Carroll, Alice Blair, Vinaya Sivakumar, Sumana Basu, Brad Kenstler, Yuntao Ma, Julian Michael, Xiaoke Li, Oliver Ingebretsen, Aditya Mehta, Jean Mottola, John Teichmann, Kevin Yu, Zaina Shaik, Adam Khoja, Richard Ren, Jason Hausenloy, Long Phan, Ye Htet, Ankit Aich, Tahseen Rabbani, Vivswan Shah, Andriy Novykov, Felix Binder, Kirill Chugunov, Luis Ramirez, Matias Geralnik, Hernán Mesura, Dean Lee, Ed-Yeremai Hernandez Cardona, Annette Diamond, Summer Yue, Alexandr Wang, Bing Liu, Ernesto Hernandez, Dan Hendrycks&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AIs have made rapid progress on research-oriented benchmarks of knowledge and reasoning, but it remains unclear how these gains translate into economic value and automation. To measure this, we introduce the Remote Labor Index (RLI), a broadly multi-sector benchmark comprising real-world, economically valuable projects designed to evaluate end-to-end agent performance in practical settings. AI agents perform near the floor on RLI, with the highest-performing agent achieving an automation rate of 2.5%. These results help ground discussions of AI automation in empirical evidence, setting a common basis for tracking AI impacts and enabling stakeholders to proactively navigate AI-driven labor automation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26787</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Quest for Generalizable Motion Generation: Data, Model, and   Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26794</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26794.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jing Lin, Ruisi Wang, Junzhe Lu, Ziqi Huang, Guorui Song, Ailing Zeng, Xian Liu, Chen Wei, Wanqi Yin, Qingping Sun, Zhongang Cai, Lei Yang, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite recent advances in 3D human motion generation (MoGen) on standard benchmarks, existing models still face a fundamental bottleneck in their generalization capability. In contrast, adjacent generative fields, most notably video generation (ViGen), have demonstrated remarkable generalization in modeling human behaviors, highlighting transferable insights that MoGen can leverage. Motivated by this observation, we present a comprehensive framework that systematically transfers knowledge from ViGen to MoGen across three key pillars: data, modeling, and evaluation. First, we introduce ViMoGen-228K, a large-scale dataset comprising 228,000 high-quality motion samples that integrates high-fidelity optical MoCap data with semantically annotated motions from web videos and synthesized samples generated by state-of-the-art ViGen models. The dataset includes both text-motion pairs and text-video-motion triplets, substantially expanding semantic diversity. Second, we propose ViMoGen, a flow-matching-based diffusion transformer that unifies priors from MoCap data and ViGen models through gated multimodal conditioning. To enhance efficiency, we further develop ViMoGen-light, a distilled variant that eliminates video generation dependencies while preserving strong generalization. Finally, we present MBench, a hierarchical benchmark designed for fine-grained evaluation across motion quality, prompt fidelity, and generalization ability. Extensive experiments show that our framework significantly outperforms existing approaches in both automatic and human evaluations. The code, data, and benchmark will be made publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26794</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:59:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniX: From Unified Panoramic Generation and Perception to   Graphics-Ready 3D Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26800</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26800.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yukun Huang, Jiwen Yu, Yanning Zhou, Jianan Wang, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; There are two prevalent ways to constructing 3D scenes: procedural generation and 2D lifting. Among them, panorama-based 2D lifting has emerged as a promising technique, leveraging powerful 2D generative priors to produce immersive, realistic, and diverse 3D environments. In this work, we advance this technique to generate graphics-ready 3D scenes suitable for physically based rendering (PBR), relighting, and simulation. Our key insight is to repurpose 2D generative models for panoramic perception of geometry, textures, and PBR materials. Unlike existing 2D lifting approaches that emphasize appearance generation and ignore the perception of intrinsic properties, we present OmniX, a versatile and unified framework. Based on a lightweight and efficient cross-modal adapter structure, OmniX reuses 2D generative priors for a broad range of panoramic vision tasks, including panoramic perception, generation, and completion. Furthermore, we construct a large-scale synthetic panorama dataset containing high-quality multimodal panoramas from diverse indoor and outdoor scenes. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our model in panoramic visual perception and graphics-ready 3D scene generation, opening new possibilities for immersive and physically realistic virtual world generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26800</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Video Models Ready as Zero-Shot Reasoners? An Empirical Study with   the MME-CoF Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26802</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26802.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyu Guo, Xinyan Chen, Renrui Zhang, Ruichuan An, Yu Qi, Dongzhi Jiang, Xiangtai Li, Manyuan Zhang, Hongsheng Li, Pheng-Ann Heng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent video generation models can produce high-fidelity, temporally coherent videos, indicating that they may encode substantial world knowledge. Beyond realistic synthesis, they also exhibit emerging behaviors indicative of visual perception, modeling, and manipulation. Yet, an important question still remains: Are video models ready to serve as zero-shot reasoners in challenging visual reasoning scenarios? In this work, we conduct an empirical study to comprehensively investigate this question, focusing on the leading and popular Veo-3. We evaluate its reasoning behavior across 12 dimensions, including spatial, geometric, physical, temporal, and embodied logic, systematically characterizing both its strengths and failure modes. To standardize this study, we curate the evaluation data into MME-CoF, a compact benchmark that enables in-depth and thorough assessment of Chain-of-Frame (CoF) reasoning. Our findings reveal that while current video models demonstrate promising reasoning patterns on short-horizon spatial coherence, fine-grained grounding, and locally consistent dynamics, they remain limited in long-horizon causal reasoning, strict geometric constraints, and abstract logic. Overall, they are not yet reliable as standalone zero-shot reasoners, but exhibit encouraging signs as complementary visual engines alongside dedicated reasoning models. Project page: https://video-cof.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26802</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
