<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 00:13:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Can LLMs Predict Their Own Failures? Self-Awareness via Internal Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20578</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.20578.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amirhosein Ghasemabadi, Di Niu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 69&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) generate fluent and complex outputs but often fail to recognize their own mistakes and hallucinations. Existing approaches typically rely on external judges, multi-sample consistency, or text-based self-critique, which incur additional compute or correlate weakly with true correctness. We ask: can LLMs predict their own failures by inspecting internal states during inference? We introduce Gnosis, a lightweight self-awareness mechanism that enables frozen LLMs to perform intrinsic self-verification by decoding signals from hidden states and attention patterns. Gnosis passively observes internal traces, compresses them into fixed-budget descriptors, and predicts correctness with negligible inference cost, adding only ~5M parameters and operating independently of sequence length. Across math reasoning, open-domain question answering, and academic knowledge benchmarks, and over frozen backbones ranging from 1.7B to 20B parameters, Gnosis consistently outperforms strong internal baselines and large external judges in both accuracy and calibration. Moreover, it generalizes zero-shot to partial generations, enabling early detection of failing trajectories and compute-aware control. These results show that reliable correctness cues are intrinsic to generation process and can be extracted efficiently without external supervision.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.20578</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 18:21:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IMA++: ISIC Archive Multi-Annotator Dermoscopic Skin Lesion Segmentation Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21472</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21472.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kumar Abhishek, Jeremy Kawahara, Ghassan Hamarneh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-annotator medical image segmentation is an important research problem, but requires annotated datasets that are expensive to collect. Dermoscopic skin lesion imaging allows human experts and AI systems to observe morphological structures otherwise not discernable from regular clinical photographs. However, currently there are no large-scale publicly available multi-annotator skin lesion segmentation (SLS) datasets with annotator-labels for dermoscopic skin lesion imaging. We introduce ISIC MultiAnnot++, a large public multi-annotator skin lesion segmentation dataset for images from the ISIC Archive. The final dataset contains 17,684 segmentation masks spanning 14,967 dermoscopic images, where 2,394 dermoscopic images have 2-5 segmentations per image, making it the largest publicly available SLS dataset. Further, metadata about the segmentation, including the annotators' skill level and segmentation tool, is included, enabling research on topics such as annotator-specific preference modeling for segmentation and annotator metadata analysis. We provide an analysis on the characteristics of this dataset, curated data partitions, and consensus segmentation masks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21472</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 02:21:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can We Trust AI Explanations? Evidence of Systematic Underreporting in Chain-of-Thought Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00830</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00830.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Deep Pankajbhai Mehta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; When AI systems explain their reasoning step-by-step, practitioners often assume these explanations reveal what actually influenced the AI's answer. We tested this assumption by embedding hints into questions and measuring whether models mentioned them. In a study of over 9,000 test cases across 11 leading AI models, we found a troubling pattern: models almost never mention hints spontaneously, yet when asked directly, they admit noticing them. This suggests models see influential information but choose not to report it. Telling models they are being watched does not help. Forcing models to report hints works, but causes them to report hints even when none exist and reduces their accuracy. We also found that hints appealing to user preferences are especially dangerous-models follow them most often while reporting them least. These findings suggest that simply watching AI reasoning is not enough to catch hidden influences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00830</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 05:29:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Few Tokens Matter: Entropy Guided Attacks on Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21815</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.21815.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengqi He, Xinyu Tian, Xin Shen, Jinhong Ni, Shu Zou, Zhaoyuan Yang, Jing Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language models (VLMs) achieve remarkable performance but remain vulnerable to adversarial attacks. Entropy, a measure of model uncertainty, is strongly correlated with the reliability of VLM. Prior entropy-based attacks maximize uncertainty at all decoding steps, implicitly assuming that every token contributes equally to generation instability. We show instead that a small fraction (about 20%) of high-entropy tokens, i.e., critical decision points in autoregressive generation, disproportionately governs output trajectories. By concentrating adversarial perturbations on these positions, we achieve semantic degradation comparable to global methods while using substantially smaller budgets. More importantly, across multiple representative VLMs, such selective attacks convert 35-49% of benign outputs into harmful ones, exposing a more critical safety risk. Remarkably, these vulnerable high-entropy forks recur across architecturally diverse VLMs, enabling feasible transferability (17-26% harmful rates on unseen targets). Motivated by these findings, we propose Entropy-bank Guided Adversarial attacks (EGA), which achieves competitive attack success rates (93-95%) alongside high harmful conversion, thereby revealing new weaknesses in current VLM safety mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21815</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 01:01:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SciEvalKit: An Open-source Evaluation Toolkit for Scientific General Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22334</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.22334.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiheng Wang, Yixin Chen, Shuo Li, Yifan Zhou, Bo Liu, Hengjian Gao, Jiakang Yuan, Jia Bu, Wanghan Xu, Yuhao Zhou, Xiangyu Zhao, Zhiwang Zhou, Fengxiang Wang, Haodong Duan, Songyang Zhang, Jun Yao, Han Deng, Yizhou Wang, Jiabei Xiao, Jiaqi Liu, Encheng Su, Yujie Liu, Weida Wang, Junchi Yao, Shenghe Zheng, Haoran Sun, Runmin Ma, Xiangchao Yan, Bo Zhang, Dongzhan Zhou, Shufei Zhang, Peng Ye, Xiaosong Wang, Shixiang Tang, Wenlong Zhang, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SciEvalKit, a unified benchmarking toolkit designed to evaluate AI models for science across a broad range of scientific disciplines and task capabilities. Unlike general-purpose evaluation platforms, SciEvalKit focuses on the core competencies of scientific intelligence, including Scientific Multimodal Perception, Scientific Multimodal Reasoning, Scientific Multimodal Understanding, Scientific Symbolic Reasoning, Scientific Code Generation, Science Hypothesis Generation and Scientific Knowledge Understanding. It supports six major scientific domains, spanning from physics and chemistry to astronomy and materials science. SciEvalKit builds a foundation of expert-grade scientific benchmarks, curated from real-world, domain-specific datasets, ensuring that tasks reflect authentic scientific challenges. The toolkit features a flexible, extensible evaluation pipeline that enables batch evaluation across models and datasets, supports custom model and dataset integration, and provides transparent, reproducible, and comparable results. By bridging capability-based evaluation and disciplinary diversity, SciEvalKit offers a standardized yet customizable infrastructure to benchmark the next generation of scientific foundation models and intelligent agents. The toolkit is open-sourced and actively maintained to foster community-driven development and progress in AI4Science.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22334</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 17:36:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RGS-SLAM: Robust Gaussian Splatting SLAM with One-Shot Dense Initialization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00705</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00705.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei-Tse Cheng, Yen-Jen Chiou, Yuan-Fu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce RGS-SLAM, a robust Gaussian-splatting SLAM framework that replaces the residual-driven densification stage of GS-SLAM with a training-free correspondence-to-Gaussian initialization. Instead of progressively adding Gaussians as residuals reveal missing geometry, RGS-SLAM performs a one-shot triangulation of dense multi-view correspondences derived from DINOv3 descriptors refined through a confidence-aware inlier classifier, generating a well-distributed and structure-aware Gaussian seed prior to optimization. This initialization stabilizes early mapping and accelerates convergence by roughly 20\%, yielding higher rendering fidelity in texture-rich and cluttered scenes while remaining fully compatible with existing GS-SLAM pipelines. Evaluated on the TUM RGB-D and Replica datasets, RGS-SLAM achieves competitive or superior localization and reconstruction accuracy compared with state-of-the-art Gaussian and point-based SLAM systems, sustaining real-time mapping performance at up to 925 FPS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00705</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 03:45:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diversity or Precision? A Deep Dive into Next Token Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22955</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.22955.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoyuan Wu, Hai Wang, Jiajia Wu, Jinxiang Ou, Keyao Wang, Weile Chen, Zihao Zheng, Bei Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements have shown that reinforcement learning (RL) can substantially improve the reasoning abilities of large language models (LLMs). The effectiveness of such RL training, however, depends critically on the exploration space defined by the pre-trained model's token-output distribution. In this paper, we revisit the standard cross-entropy loss, interpreting it as a specific instance of policy gradient optimization applied within a single-step episode. To systematically study how the pre-trained distribution shapes the exploration potential for subsequent RL, we propose a generalized pre-training objective that adapts on-policy RL principles to supervised learning. By framing next-token prediction as a stochastic decision process, we introduce a reward-shaping strategy that explicitly balances diversity and precision. Our method employs a positive reward scaling factor to control probability concentration on ground-truth tokens and a rank-aware mechanism that treats high-ranking and low-ranking negative tokens asymmetrically. This allows us to reshape the pre-trained token-output distribution and investigate how to provide a more favorable exploration space for RL, ultimately enhancing end-to-end reasoning performance. Contrary to the intuition that higher distribution entropy facilitates effective exploration, we find that imposing a precision-oriented prior yields a superior exploration space for RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22955</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 14:53:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Stable Semi-Supervised Remote Sensing Segmentation via Co-Guidance and Co-Fusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23035</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.23035.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Zhou, Xuechao Zou, Shun Zhang, Kai Li, Shiying Wang, Jingming Chen, Congyan Lang, Tengfei Cao, Pin Tao, Yuanchun Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Semi-supervised remote sensing (RS) image semantic segmentation offers a promising solution to alleviate the burden of exhaustive annotation, yet it fundamentally struggles with pseudo-label drift, a phenomenon where confirmation bias leads to the accumulation of errors during training. In this work, we propose Co2S, a stable semi-supervised RS segmentation framework that synergistically fuses priors from vision-language models and self-supervised models. Specifically, we construct a heterogeneous dual-student architecture comprising two distinct ViT-based vision foundation models initialized with pretrained CLIP and DINOv3 to mitigate error accumulation and pseudo-label drift. To effectively incorporate these distinct priors, an explicit-implicit semantic co-guidance mechanism is introduced that utilizes text embeddings and learnable queries to provide explicit and implicit class-level guidance, respectively, thereby jointly enhancing semantic consistency. Furthermore, a global-local feature collaborative fusion strategy is developed to effectively fuse the global contextual information captured by CLIP with the local details produced by DINOv3, enabling the model to generate highly precise segmentation results. Extensive experiments on six popular datasets demonstrate the superiority of the proposed method, which consistently achieves leading performance across various partition protocols and diverse scenarios. Project page is available at https://xavierjiezou.github.io/Co2S/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23035</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 18:24:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MindWatcher: Toward Smarter Multimodal Tool-Integrated Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23412</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.23412.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiawei Chen, Xintian Shen, Lihao Zheng, Zhenwei Shao, Hongyuan Zhang, Pengfei Yu, Xudong Rao, Ning Mao, Xiaobo Liu, Lian Wen, Chaoqun Du, Feng Gu, Wei He, Qizhen Li, Shanshan Li, Zide Liu, Jing Luo, Lifu Mu, Xuhao Pan, Chang Ren, Haoyi Sun, Qian Wang, Wei Wang, Hongfu Yang, Jiqing Zhan, Chunpeng Zhou, Zheng Zhou, Hao Ma, Tao Wei, Pan Zhou, Wei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional workflow-based agents exhibit limited intelligence when addressing real-world problems requiring tool invocation. Tool-integrated reasoning (TIR) agents capable of autonomous reasoning and tool invocation are rapidly emerging as a powerful approach for complex decision-making tasks involving multi-step interactions with external environments. In this work, we introduce MindWatcher, a TIR agent integrating interleaved thinking and multimodal chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning. MindWatcher can autonomously decide whether and how to invoke diverse tools and coordinate their use, without relying on human prompts or workflows. The interleaved thinking paradigm enables the model to switch between thinking and tool calling at any intermediate stage, while its multimodal CoT capability allows manipulation of images during reasoning to yield more precise search results. We implement automated data auditing and evaluation pipelines, complemented by manually curated high-quality datasets for training, and we construct a benchmark, called MindWatcher-Evaluate Bench (MWE-Bench), to evaluate its performance. MindWatcher is equipped with a comprehensive suite of auxiliary reasoning tools, enabling it to address broad-domain multimodal problems. A large-scale, high-quality local image retrieval database, covering eight categories including cars, animals, and plants, endows model with robust object recognition despite its small size. Finally, we design a more efficient training infrastructure for MindWatcher, enhancing training speed and hardware utilization. Experiments not only demonstrate that MindWatcher matches or exceeds the performance of larger or more recent models through superior tool invocation, but also uncover critical insights for agent training, such as the genetic inheritance phenomenon in agentic RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23412</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 12:16:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memorization in 3D Shape Generation: An Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23628</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.23628.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shu Pu, Boya Zeng, Kaichen Zhou, Mengyu Wang, Zhuang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative models are increasingly used in 3D vision to synthesize novel shapes, yet it remains unclear whether their generation relies on memorizing training shapes. Understanding their memorization could help prevent training data leakage and improve the diversity of generated results. In this paper, we design an evaluation framework to quantify memorization in 3D generative models and study the influence of different data and modeling designs on memorization. We first apply our framework to quantify memorization in existing methods. Next, through controlled experiments with a latent vector-set (Vecset) diffusion model, we find that, on the data side, memorization depends on data modality, and increases with data diversity and finer-grained conditioning; on the modeling side, it peaks at a moderate guidance scale and can be mitigated by longer Vecsets and simple rotation augmentation. Together, our framework and analysis provide an empirical understanding of memorization in 3D generative models and suggest simple yet effective strategies to reduce it without degrading generation quality. Our code is available at https://github.com/zlab-princeton/3d_mem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23628</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 17:39:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GARDO: Reinforcing Diffusion Models without Reward Hacking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24138</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.24138.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran He, Yuxiao Ye, Jie Liu, Jiajun Liang, Zhiyong Wang, Ziyang Yuan, Xintao Wang, Hangyu Mao, Pengfei Wan, Ling Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-tuning diffusion models via online reinforcement learning (RL) has shown great potential for enhancing text-to-image alignment. However, since precisely specifying a ground-truth objective for visual tasks remains challenging, the models are often optimized using a proxy reward that only partially captures the true goal. This mismatch often leads to reward hacking, where proxy scores increase while real image quality deteriorates and generation diversity collapses. While common solutions add regularization against the reference policy to prevent reward hacking, they compromise sample efficiency and impede the exploration of novel, high-reward regions, as the reference policy is usually sub-optimal. To address the competing demands of sample efficiency, effective exploration, and mitigation of reward hacking, we propose Gated and Adaptive Regularization with Diversity-aware Optimization (GARDO), a versatile framework compatible with various RL algorithms. Our key insight is that regularization need not be applied universally; instead, it is highly effective to selectively penalize a subset of samples that exhibit high uncertainty. To address the exploration challenge, GARDO introduces an adaptive regularization mechanism wherein the reference model is periodically updated to match the capabilities of the online policy, ensuring a relevant regularization target. To address the mode collapse issue in RL, GARDO amplifies the rewards for high-quality samples that also exhibit high diversity, encouraging mode coverage without destabilizing the optimization process. Extensive experiments across diverse proxy rewards and hold-out unseen metrics consistently show that GARDO mitigates reward hacking and enhances generation diversity without sacrificing sample efficiency or exploration, highlighting its effectiveness and robustness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24138</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 10:55:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taming Preference Mode Collapse via Directional Decoupling Alignment in Diffusion Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24146</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.24146.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chubin Chen, Sujie Hu, Jiashu Zhu, Meiqi Wu, Jintao Chen, Yanxun Li, Nisha Huang, Chengyu Fang, Jiahong Wu, Xiangxiang Chu, Xiu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have demonstrated significant progress in aligning text-to-image diffusion models with human preference via Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback. However, while existing methods achieve high scores on automated reward metrics, they often lead to Preference Mode Collapse (PMC)-a specific form of reward hacking where models converge on narrow, high-scoring outputs (e.g., images with monolithic styles or pervasive overexposure), severely degrading generative diversity. In this work, we introduce and quantify this phenomenon, proposing DivGenBench, a novel benchmark designed to measure the extent of PMC. We posit that this collapse is driven by over-optimization along the reward model's inherent biases. Building on this analysis, we propose Directional Decoupling Alignment (D^2-Align), a novel framework that mitigates PMC by directionally correcting the reward signal. Specifically, our method first learns a directional correction within the reward model's embedding space while keeping the model frozen. This correction is then applied to the reward signal during the optimization process, preventing the model from collapsing into specific modes and thereby maintaining diversity. Our comprehensive evaluation, combining qualitative analysis with quantitative metrics for both quality and diversity, reveals that D^2-Align achieves superior alignment with human preference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24146</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 11:17:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Open-Vocabulary Industrial Defect Understanding with a Large-Scale Multimodal Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24160</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.24160.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; TsaiChing Ni, ZhenQi Chen, YuanFu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present IMDD-1M, the first large-scale Industrial Multimodal Defect Dataset comprising 1,000,000 aligned image-text pairs, designed to advance multimodal learning for manufacturing and quality inspection. IMDD-1M contains high-resolution real-world defects spanning over 60 material categories and more than 400 defect types, each accompanied by expert-verified annotations and fine-grained textual descriptions detailing defect location, severity, and contextual attributes. This dataset enables a wide spectrum of applications, including classification, segmentation, retrieval, captioning, and generative modeling. Building upon IMDD-1M, we train a diffusion-based vision-language foundation model from scratch, specifically tailored for industrial scenarios. The model serves as a generalizable foundation that can be efficiently adapted to specialized domains through lightweight fine-tuning. With less than 5% of the task-specific data required by dedicated expert models, it achieves comparable performance, highlighting the potential of data-efficient foundation model adaptation for industrial inspection and generation, paving the way for scalable, domain-adaptive, and knowledge-grounded manufacturing intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24160</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 11:45:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taming Hallucinations: Boosting MLLMs' Video Understanding via Counterfactual Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24271</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.24271.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhe Huang, Hao Wen, Aiming Hao, Bingze Song, Meiqi Wu, Jiahong Wu, Xiangxiang Chu, Sheng Lu, Haoqian Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have made remarkable progress in video understanding. However, they suffer from a critical vulnerability: an over-reliance on language priors, which can lead to visual ungrounded hallucinations, especially when processing counterfactual videos that defy common sense. This limitation, stemming from the intrinsic data imbalance between text and video, is challenging to address due to the substantial cost of collecting and annotating counterfactual data. To address this, we introduce DualityForge, a novel counterfactual data synthesis framework that employs controllable, diffusion-based video editing to transform real-world videos into counterfactual scenarios. By embedding structured contextual information into the video editing and QA generation processes, the framework automatically produces high-quality QA pairs together with original-edited video pairs for contrastive training. Based on this, we build DualityVidQA, a large-scale video dataset designed to reduce MLLM hallucinations. In addition, to fully exploit the contrastive nature of our paired data, we propose Duality-Normalized Advantage Training (DNA-Train), a two-stage SFT-RL training regime where the RL phase applies pair-wise ell_1 advantage normalization, thereby enabling a more stable and efficient policy optimization. Experiments on DualityVidQA-Test demonstrate that our method substantially reduces model hallucinations on counterfactual videos, yielding a relative improvement of 24.0% over the Qwen2.5-VL-7B baseline. Moreover, our approach achieves significant gains across both hallucination and general-purpose benchmarks, indicating strong generalization capability. We will open-source our dataset and code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24271</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 14:53:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SenseNova-MARS: Empowering Multimodal Agentic Reasoning and Search via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24330</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.24330.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yong Xien Chng, Tao Hu, Wenwen Tong, Xueheng Li, Jiandong Chen, Haojia Yu, Jiefan Lu, Hewei Guo, Hanming Deng, Chengjun Xie, Gao Huang, Dahua Lin, Lewei Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Vision-Language Models (VLMs) can solve complex tasks through agentic reasoning, their capabilities remain largely constrained to text-oriented chain-of-thought or isolated tool invocation. They fail to exhibit the human-like proficiency required to seamlessly interleave dynamic tool manipulation with continuous reasoning, particularly in knowledge-intensive and visually complex scenarios that demand coordinated external tools such as search and image cropping. In this work, we introduce SenseNova-MARS, a novel Multimodal Agentic Reasoning and Search framework that empowers VLMs with interleaved visual reasoning and tool-use capabilities via reinforcement learning (RL). Specifically, SenseNova-MARS dynamically integrates the image search, text search, and image crop tools to tackle fine-grained and knowledge-intensive visual understanding challenges. In the RL stage, we propose the Batch-Normalized Group Sequence Policy Optimization (BN-GSPO) algorithm to improve the training stability and advance the model's ability to invoke tools and reason effectively. To comprehensively evaluate the agentic VLMs on complex visual tasks, we introduce the HR-MMSearch benchmark, the first search-oriented benchmark composed of high-resolution images with knowledge-intensive and search-driven questions. Experiments demonstrate that SenseNova-MARS achieves state-of-the-art performance on open-source search and fine-grained image understanding benchmarks. Specifically, on search-oriented benchmarks, SenseNova-MARS-8B scores 67.84 on MMSearch and 41.64 on HR-MMSearch, surpassing proprietary models such as Gemini-3-Flash and GPT-5. SenseNova-MARS represents a promising step toward agentic VLMs by providing effective and robust tool-use capabilities. To facilitate further research in this field, we will release all code, models, and datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24330</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 16:31:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recursive Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24601</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.24601.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alex L. Zhang, Tim Kraska, Omar Khattab&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We study allowing large language models (LLMs) to process arbitrarily long prompts through the lens of inference-time scaling. We propose Recursive Language Models (RLMs), a general inference strategy that treats long prompts as part of an external environment and allows the LLM to programmatically examine, decompose, and recursively call itself over snippets of the prompt. We find that RLMs successfully handle inputs up to two orders of magnitude beyond model context windows and, even for shorter prompts, dramatically outperform the quality of base LLMs and common long-context scaffolds across four diverse long-context tasks, while having comparable (or cheaper) cost per query.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24601</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 03:43:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Youtu-Agent: Scaling Agent Productivity with Automated Generation and Hybrid Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24615</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.24615.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuchen Shi, Yuzheng Cai, Siqi Cai, Zihan Xu, Lichao Chen, Yulei Qin, Zhijian Zhou, Xiang Fei, Chaofan Qiu, Xiaoyu Tan, Gang Li, Zongyi Li, Haojia Lin, Guocan Cai, Yong Mao, Yunsheng Wu, Ke Li, Xing Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 108&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing Large Language Model (LLM) agent frameworks face two significant challenges: high configuration costs and static capabilities. Building a high-quality agent often requires extensive manual effort in tool integration and prompt engineering, while deployed agents struggle to adapt to dynamic environments without expensive fine-tuning. To address these issues, we propose Youtu-Agent, a modular framework designed for the automated generation and continuous evolution of LLM agents. Youtu-Agent features a structured configuration system that decouples execution environments, toolkits, and context management, enabling flexible reuse and automated synthesis. We introduce two generation paradigms: a Workflow mode for standard tasks and a Meta-Agent mode for complex, non-standard requirements, capable of automatically generating tool code, prompts, and configurations. Furthermore, Youtu-Agent establishes a hybrid policy optimization system: (1) an Agent Practice module that enables agents to accumulate experience and improve performance through in-context optimization without parameter updates; and (2) an Agent RL module that integrates with distributed training frameworks to enable scalable and stable reinforcement learning of any Youtu-Agents in an end-to-end, large-scale manner. Experiments demonstrate that Youtu-Agent achieves state-of-the-art performance on WebWalkerQA (71.47\%) and GAIA (72.8\%) using open-weight models. Our automated generation pipeline achieves over 81\% tool synthesis success rate, while the Practice module improves performance on AIME 2024/2025 by +2.7\% and +5.4\% respectively. Moreover, our Agent RL training achieves 40\% speedup with steady performance improvement on 7B LLMs, enhancing coding/reasoning and searching capabilities respectively up to 35\% and 21\% on Maths and general/multi-hop QA benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24615</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 04:17:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nested Learning: The Illusion of Deep Learning Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24695</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.24695.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ali Behrouz, Meisam Razaviyayn, Peilin Zhong, Vahab Mirrokni&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the recent progresses, particularly in developing Language Models, there are fundamental challenges and unanswered questions about how such models can continually learn/memorize, self-improve, and find effective solutions. In this paper, we present a new learning paradigm, called Nested Learning (NL), that coherently represents a machine learning model with a set of nested, multi-level, and/or parallel optimization problems, each of which with its own context flow. Through the lenses of NL, existing deep learning methods learns from data through compressing their own context flow, and in-context learning naturally emerges in large models. NL suggests a philosophy to design more expressive learning algorithms with more levels, resulting in higher-order in-context learning and potentially unlocking effective continual learning capabilities. We advocate for NL by presenting three core contributions: (1) Expressive Optimizers: We show that known gradient-based optimizers, such as Adam, SGD with Momentum, etc., are in fact associative memory modules that aim to compress the gradients' information (by gradient descent). Building on this insight, we present other more expressive optimizers with deep memory and/or more powerful learning rules; (2) Self-Modifying Learning Module: Taking advantage of NL's insights on learning algorithms, we present a sequence model that learns how to modify itself by learning its own update algorithm; and (3) Continuum Memory System: We present a new formulation for memory system that generalizes the traditional viewpoint of long/short-term memory. Combining our self-modifying sequence model with the continuum memory system, we present a continual learning module, called Hope, showing promising results in language modeling, knowledge incorporation, and few-shot generalization tasks, continual learning, and long-context reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24695</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 07:59:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MorphAny3D: Unleashing the Power of Structured Latent in 3D Morphing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00204</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00204.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaokun Sun, Zeyu Cai, Hao Tang, Ying Tai, Jian Yang, Zhenyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D morphing remains challenging due to the difficulty of generating semantically consistent and temporally smooth deformations, especially across categories. We present MorphAny3D, a training-free framework that leverages Structured Latent (SLAT) representations for high-quality 3D morphing. Our key insight is that intelligently blending source and target SLAT features within the attention mechanisms of 3D generators naturally produces plausible morphing sequences. To this end, we introduce Morphing Cross-Attention (MCA), which fuses source and target information for structural coherence, and Temporal-Fused Self-Attention (TFSA), which enhances temporal consistency by incorporating features from preceding frames. An orientation correction strategy further mitigates the pose ambiguity within the morphing steps. Extensive experiments show that our method generates state-of-the-art morphing sequences, even for challenging cross-category cases. MorphAny3D further supports advanced applications such as decoupled morphing and 3D style transfer, and can be generalized to other SLAT-based generative models. Project page: https://xiaokunsun.github.io/MorphAny3D.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00204</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 04:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeoVerse: Enhancing 4D World Model with in-the-wild Monocular Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00393</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00393.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxue Yang, Lue Fan, Ziqi Shi, Junran Peng, Feng Wang, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 109&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we propose NeoVerse, a versatile 4D world model that is capable of 4D reconstruction, novel-trajectory video generation, and rich downstream applications. We first identify a common limitation of scalability in current 4D world modeling methods, caused either by expensive and specialized multi-view 4D data or by cumbersome training pre-processing. In contrast, our NeoVerse is built upon a core philosophy that makes the full pipeline scalable to diverse in-the-wild monocular videos. Specifically, NeoVerse features pose-free feed-forward 4D reconstruction, online monocular degradation pattern simulation, and other well-aligned techniques. These designs empower NeoVerse with versatility and generalization to various domains. Meanwhile, NeoVerse achieves state-of-the-art performance in standard reconstruction and generation benchmarks. Our project page is available at https://neoverse-4d.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00393</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 17:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Delta Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00417</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00417.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Zhang, Yifeng Liu, Mengdi Wang, Quanquan Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The efficacy of deep residual networks is fundamentally predicated on the identity shortcut connection. While this mechanism effectively mitigates the vanishing gradient problem, it imposes a strictly additive inductive bias on feature transformations, thereby limiting the network's capacity to model complex state transitions. In this paper, we introduce Deep Delta Learning (DDL), a novel architecture that generalizes the standard residual connection by modulating the identity shortcut with a learnable, data-dependent geometric transformation. This transformation, termed the Delta Operator, constitutes a rank-1 perturbation of the identity matrix, parameterized by a reflection direction vector k(X) and a gating scalar β(X). We provide a spectral analysis of this operator, demonstrating that the gate β(X) enables dynamic interpolation between identity mapping, orthogonal projection, and geometric reflection. Furthermore, we restructure the residual update as a synchronous rank-1 injection, where the gate acts as a dynamic step size governing both the erasure of old information and the writing of new features. This unification empowers the network to explicitly control the spectrum of its layer-wise transition operator, enabling the modeling of complex, non-monotonic dynamics while preserving the stable training characteristics of gated residual architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00417</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 18:11:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E-GRPO: High Entropy Steps Drive Effective Reinforcement Learning for Flow Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00423</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00423.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengjun Zhang, Zhang Zhang, Chensheng Dai, Yueqi Duan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reinforcement learning has enhanced the flow matching models on human preference alignment. While stochastic sampling enables the exploration of denoising directions, existing methods which optimize over multiple denoising steps suffer from sparse and ambiguous reward signals. We observe that the high entropy steps enable more efficient and effective exploration while the low entropy steps result in undistinguished roll-outs. To this end, we propose E-GRPO, an entropy aware Group Relative Policy Optimization to increase the entropy of SDE sampling steps. Since the integration of stochastic differential equations suffer from ambiguous reward signals due to stochasticity from multiple steps, we specifically merge consecutive low entropy steps to formulate one high entropy step for SDE sampling, while applying ODE sampling on other steps. Building upon this, we introduce multi-step group normalized advantage, which computes group-relative advantages within samples sharing the same consolidated SDE denoising step. Experimental results on different reward settings have demonstrated the effectiveness of our methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00423</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 18:27:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CPPO: Contrastive Perception for Vision Language Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00501</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00501.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ahmad Rezaei, Mohsen Gholami, Saeed Ranjbar Alvar, Kevin Cannons, Mohammad Asiful Hossain, Zhou Weimin, Shunbo Zhou, Yong Zhang, Mohammad Akbari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce CPPO, a Contrastive Perception Policy Optimization method for finetuning vision-language models (VLMs). While reinforcement learning (RL) has advanced reasoning in language models, extending it to multimodal reasoning requires improving both the perception and reasoning aspects. Prior works tackle this challenge mainly with explicit perception rewards, but disentangling perception tokens from reasoning tokens is difficult, requiring extra LLMs, ground-truth data, forced separation of perception from reasoning by policy model, or applying rewards indiscriminately to all output tokens. CPPO addresses this problem by detecting perception tokens via entropy shifts in the model outputs under perturbed input images. CPPO then extends the RL objective function with a Contrastive Perception Loss (CPL) that enforces consistency under information-preserving perturbations and sensitivity under information-removing ones. Experiments show that CPPO surpasses previous perception-rewarding methods, while avoiding extra models, making training more efficient and scalable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00501</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 22:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfoSynth: Information-Guided Benchmark Synthesis for LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00575</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00575.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ishir Garg, Neel Kolhe, Xuandong Zhao, Dawn Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated significant advancements in reasoning and code generation. However, efficiently creating new benchmarks to evaluate these capabilities remains a challenge. Traditional benchmark creation relies on manual human effort, a process that is both expensive and time-consuming. Furthermore, existing benchmarks often contaminate LLM training data, necessitating novel and diverse benchmarks to accurately assess their genuine capabilities. This work introduces InfoSynth, a novel framework for automatically generating and evaluating reasoning benchmarks guided by information-theoretic principles. We propose metrics based on KL-divergence and entropy to quantify benchmark novelty and diversity without relying on costly model evaluations. Building on this framework, we develop an end-to-end pipeline that synthesizes robust Python coding problems from seed datasets using genetic algorithms and iterative code feedback. Our method generates accurate test cases and solutions to new problems 97% of the time, and the synthesized benchmarks consistently exhibit higher novelty and diversity compared to their seed datasets. Moreover, our algorithm provides a method for controlling the novelty/diversity and difficulty of generated problems. InfoSynth offers a scalable, self-verifying pipeline for constructing high-quality, novel and diverse benchmarks for LLMs. Project Page: https://ishirgarg.github.io/infosynth_web/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00575</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 05:26:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Avatar Forcing: Real-Time Interactive Head Avatar Generation for Natural Conversation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00664</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00664.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taekyung Ki, Sangwon Jang, Jaehyeong Jo, Jaehong Yoon, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Talking head generation creates lifelike avatars from static portraits for virtual communication and content creation. However, current models do not yet convey the feeling of truly interactive communication, often generating one-way responses that lack emotional engagement. We identify two key challenges toward truly interactive avatars: generating motion in real-time under causal constraints and learning expressive, vibrant reactions without additional labeled data. To address these challenges, we propose Avatar Forcing, a new framework for interactive head avatar generation that models real-time user-avatar interactions through diffusion forcing. This design allows the avatar to process real-time multimodal inputs, including the user's audio and motion, with low latency for instant reactions to both verbal and non-verbal cues such as speech, nods, and laughter. Furthermore, we introduce a direct preference optimization method that leverages synthetic losing samples constructed by dropping user conditions, enabling label-free learning of expressive interaction. Experimental results demonstrate that our framework enables real-time interaction with low latency (approximately 500ms), achieving 6.8X speedup compared to the baseline, and produces reactive and expressive avatar motion, which is preferred over 80% against the baseline.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00664</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 11:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast-weight Product Key Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00671</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00671.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Zhao, Llion Jones&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sequence modeling layers in modern language models typically face a trade-off between storage capacity and computational efficiency. While Softmax attention offers unbounded storage at prohibitive quadratic costs, linear variants provide efficiency but suffer from limited, fixed-size storage. We propose Fast-weight Product Key Memory (FwPKM), a novel architecture that resolves this tension by transforming the sparse Product Key Memory (PKM) from a static module into a dynamic, "fast-weight" episodic memory. Unlike PKM, FwPKM updates its parameters dynamically at both training and inference time via local chunk-level gradient descent, allowing the model to rapidly memorize and retrieve new key-value pairs from input sequences. Experiments reveal that FwPKM functions as an effective episodic memory that complements the semantic memory of standard modules, yielding significant perplexity reductions on long-context datasets. Notably, in Needle in a Haystack evaluations, FwPKM generalizes to 128K-token contexts despite being trained on only 4K-token sequences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00671</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 12:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Reasoning-Creativity Trade-off: Toward Creativity-Driven Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00747</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00747.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Max Ruiz Luyten, Mihaela van der Schaar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; State-of-the-art large language model (LLM) pipelines rely on bootstrapped reasoning loops: sampling diverse chains of thought and reinforcing the highest-scoring ones, mainly optimizing correctness. We analyze how this design choice is sensitive to the collapse of the model's distribution over reasoning paths, slashing semantic entropy and undermining creative problem-solving. To analyze this failure, we introduce Distributional Creative Reasoning (DCR), a unified variational objective that casts training as gradient flow through probability measures on solution traces. STaR, GRPO, and DPO, as well as entropy bonuses, and other methods, all constitute special cases of the same loss. The framework delivers three core results: (i) the diversity decay theorem, describing how correctness-based objectives lead to distinct modes of diversity decay for STaR, GRPO, and DPO; (ii) designs that ensure convergence to a stable and diverse policy, effectively preventing collapse; and (iii) simple, actionable recipes to achieve this in practice. DCR thus offers the first principled recipe for LLMs that remain both correct and creative.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00747</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 17:10:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdaGaR: Adaptive Gabor Representation for Dynamic Scene Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00796</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.00796.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiewen Chan, Zhenjun Zhao, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reconstructing dynamic 3D scenes from monocular videos requires simultaneously capturing high-frequency appearance details and temporally continuous motion. Existing methods using single Gaussian primitives are limited by their low-pass filtering nature, while standard Gabor functions introduce energy instability. Moreover, lack of temporal continuity constraints often leads to motion artifacts during interpolation. We propose AdaGaR, a unified framework addressing both frequency adaptivity and temporal continuity in explicit dynamic scene modeling. We introduce Adaptive Gabor Representation, extending Gaussians through learnable frequency weights and adaptive energy compensation to balance detail capture and stability. For temporal continuity, we employ Cubic Hermite Splines with Temporal Curvature Regularization to ensure smooth motion evolution. An Adaptive Initialization mechanism combining depth estimation, point tracking, and foreground masks establishes stable point cloud distributions in early training. Experiments on Tap-Vid DAVIS demonstrate state-of-the-art performance (PSNR 35.49, SSIM 0.9433, LPIPS 0.0723) and strong generalization across frame interpolation, depth consistency, video editing, and stereo view synthesis. Project page: https://jiewenchan.github.io/AdaGaR/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00796</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KV-Embedding: Training-free Text Embedding via Internal KV Re-routing in Decoder-only LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01046</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01046.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yixuan Tang, Yi Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While LLMs are powerful embedding backbones, their application in training-free settings faces two structural challenges: causal attention restricts early tokens from accessing subsequent context, and the next-token prediction objective biases representations toward generation rather than semantic compression. To address these limitations, we propose KV-Embedding, a framework that activates the latent representation power of frozen LLMs. Our method leverages the observation that the key-value (KV) states of the final token at each layer encode a compressed view of the sequence. By re-routing these states as a prepended prefix, we enable all tokens to access sequence-level context within a single forward pass. To ensure model-agnostic applicability, we introduce an automated layer selection strategy based on intrinsic dimensionality. Evaluations on MTEB across Qwen, Mistral, and Llama backbones show that KV-Embedding outperforms existing training-free baselines by up to 10%, while maintaining robust performance on sequences up to 4,096 tokens. These results demonstrate that internal state manipulation offers an efficient alternative to input modification, and we hope this work encourages further exploration of LLM internals for representation learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01046</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 02:55:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Twin AI: Opportunities and Challenges from Large Language Models to World Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01321</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01321.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rong Zhou, Dongping Chen, Zihan Jia, Yao Su, Yixin Liu, Yiwen Lu, Dongwei Shi, Yue Huang, Tianyang Xu, Yi Pan, Xinliang Li, Yohannes Abate, Qingyu Chen, Zhengzhong Tu, Yu Yang, Yu Zhang, Qingsong Wen, Gengchen Mai, Sunyang Fu, Jiachen Li, Xuyu Wang, Ziran Wang, Jing Huang, Tianming Liu, Yong Chen, Lichao Sun, Lifang He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Digital twins, as precise digital representations of physical systems, have evolved from passive simulation tools into intelligent and autonomous entities through the integration of artificial intelligence technologies. This paper presents a unified four-stage framework that systematically characterizes AI integration across the digital twin lifecycle, spanning modeling, mirroring, intervention, and autonomous management. By synthesizing existing technologies and practices, we distill a unified four-stage framework that systematically characterizes how AI methodologies are embedded across the digital twin lifecycle: (1) modeling the physical twin through physics-based and physics-informed AI approaches, (2) mirroring the physical system into a digital twin with real-time synchronization, (3) intervening in the physical twin through predictive modeling, anomaly detection, and optimization strategies, and (4) achieving autonomous management through large language models, foundation models, and intelligent agents. We analyze the synergy between physics-based modeling and data-driven learning, highlighting the shift from traditional numerical solvers to physics-informed and foundation models for physical systems. Furthermore, we examine how generative AI technologies, including large language models and generative world models, transform digital twins into proactive and self-improving cognitive systems capable of reasoning, communication, and creative scenario generation. Through a cross-domain review spanning eleven application domains, including healthcare, aerospace, smart manufacturing, robotics, and smart cities, we identify common challenges related to scalability, explainability, and trustworthiness, and outline directions for responsible AI-driven digital twin systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01321</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 01:17:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEMAS: Large A 150K-Hour Large-scale Extensible Multilingual Audio Suite with Generative Speech Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04233</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04233.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Zhao, Lijian Lin, Ye Zhu, Kai Xie, Yunfei Liu, Yu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present the LEMAS-Dataset, which, to our knowledge, is currently the largest open-source multilingual speech corpus with word-level timestamps. Covering over 150,000 hours across 10 major languages, LEMAS-Dataset is constructed via a efficient data processing pipeline that ensures high-quality data and annotations. To validate the effectiveness of LEMAS-Dataset across diverse generative paradigms, we train two benchmark models with distinct architectures and task specializations on this dataset. LEMAS-TTS, built upon a non-autoregressive flow-matching framework, leverages the dataset's massive scale and linguistic diversity to achieve robust zero-shot multilingual synthesis. Our proposed accent-adversarial training and CTC loss mitigate cross-lingual accent issues, enhancing synthesis stability. Complementarily, LEMAS-Edit employs an autoregressive decoder-only architecture that formulates speech editing as a masked token infilling task. By exploiting precise word-level alignments to construct training masks and adopting adaptive decoding strategies, it achieves seamless, smooth-boundary speech editing with natural transitions. Experimental results demonstrate that models trained on LEMAS-Dataset deliver high-quality synthesis and editing performance, confirming the dataset's quality. We envision that this richly timestamp-annotated, fine-grained multilingual corpus will drive future advances in prompt-based speech generation systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04233</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 03:43:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamID-V:Bridging the Image-to-Video Gap for High-Fidelity Face Swapping via Diffusion Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01425</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01425.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xu Guo, Fulong Ye, Xinghui Li, Pengqi Tu, Pengze Zhang, Qichao Sun, Songtao Zhao, Xiangwang Hou, Qian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video Face Swapping (VFS) requires seamlessly injecting a source identity into a target video while meticulously preserving the original pose, expression, lighting, background, and dynamic information. Existing methods struggle to maintain identity similarity and attribute preservation while preserving temporal consistency. To address the challenge, we propose a comprehensive framework to seamlessly transfer the superiority of Image Face Swapping (IFS) to the video domain. We first introduce a novel data pipeline SyncID-Pipe that pre-trains an Identity-Anchored Video Synthesizer and combines it with IFS models to construct bidirectional ID quadruplets for explicit supervision. Building upon paired data, we propose the first Diffusion Transformer-based framework DreamID-V, employing a core Modality-Aware Conditioning module to discriminatively inject multi-model conditions. Meanwhile, we propose a Synthetic-to-Real Curriculum mechanism and an Identity-Coherence Reinforcement Learning strategy to enhance visual realism and identity consistency under challenging scenarios. To address the issue of limited benchmarks, we introduce IDBench-V, a comprehensive benchmark encompassing diverse scenes. Extensive experiments demonstrate DreamID-V outperforms state-of-the-art methods and further exhibits exceptional versatility, which can be seamlessly adapted to various swap-related tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01425</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 08:07:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-Lego: Pushing the Limits of Supervised Fine-tuning for Software Issue Resolving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01426</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01426.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaofan Tao, Jierun Chen, Yuxin Jiang, Kaiqi Kou, Shaowei Wang, Ruoyu Wang, Xiaohui Li, Sidi Yang, Yiming Du, Jianbo Dai, Zhiming Mao, Xinyu Wang, Lifeng Shang, Haoli Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present SWE-Lego, a supervised fine-tuning (SFT) recipe designed to achieve state-ofthe-art performance in software engineering (SWE) issue resolving. In contrast to prevalent methods that rely on complex training paradigms (e.g., mid-training, SFT, reinforcement learning, and their combinations), we explore how to push the limits of a lightweight SFT-only approach for SWE tasks. SWE-Lego comprises three core building blocks, with key findings summarized as follows: 1) the SWE-Lego dataset, a collection of 32k highquality task instances and 18k validated trajectories, combining real and synthetic data to complement each other in both quality and quantity; 2) a refined SFT procedure with error masking and a difficulty-based curriculum, which demonstrably improves action quality and overall performance. Empirical results show that with these two building bricks alone,the SFT can push SWE-Lego models to state-of-the-art performance among open-source models of comparable size on SWE-bench Verified: SWE-Lego-Qwen3-8B reaches 42.2%, and SWE-Lego-Qwen3-32B attains 52.6%. 3) We further evaluate and improve test-time scaling (TTS) built upon the SFT foundation. Based on a well-trained verifier, SWE-Lego models can be significantly boosted--for example, 42.2% to 49.6% and 52.6% to 58.8% under TTS@16 for the 8B and 32B models, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01426</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 08:07:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOSS Transcribe Diarize: Accurate Transcription with Speaker Diarization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01554</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01554.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; MOSI. AI, Donghua Yu, Zhengyuan Lin, Chen Yang, Yiyang Zhang, Hanfu Chen, Jingqi Chen, Ke Chen, Liwei Fan, Yi Jiang, Jie Zhu, Muchen Li, Wenxuan Wang, Yang Wang, Zhe Xu, Yitian Gong, Yuqian Zhang, Wenbo Zhang, Zhaoye Fei, Qinyuan Cheng, Shimin Li, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Speaker-Attributed, Time-Stamped Transcription (SATS) aims to transcribe what is said and to precisely determine the timing of each speaker, which is particularly valuable for meeting transcription. Existing SATS systems rarely adopt an end-to-end formulation and are further constrained by limited context windows, weak long-range speaker memory, and the inability to output timestamps. To address these limitations, we present MOSS Transcribe Diarize, a unified multimodal large language model that jointly performs Speaker-Attributed, Time-Stamped Transcription in an end-to-end paradigm. Trained on extensive real wild data and equipped with a 128k context window for up to 90-minute inputs, MOSS Transcribe Diarize scales well and generalizes robustly. Across comprehensive evaluations, it outperforms state-of-the-art commercial systems on multiple public and in-house benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01554</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 15:01:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenNovelty: An LLM-powered Agentic System for Verifiable Scholarly Novelty Assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01576</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01576.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Zhang, Kexin Tan, Yueyuan Huang, Yujiong Shen, Chunchun Ma, Li Ju, Xinran Zhang, Yuhui Wang, Wenqing Jing, Jingyi Deng, Huayu Sha, Binze Hu, Jingqi Tong, Changhao Jiang, Yage Geng, Yuankai Ying, Yue Zhang, Zhangyue Yin, Zhiheng Xi, Shihan Dou, Tao Gui, Qi Zhang, Xuanjing Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating novelty is critical yet challenging in peer review, as reviewers must assess submissions against a vast, rapidly evolving literature. This report presents OpenNovelty, an LLM-powered agentic system for transparent, evidence-based novelty analysis. The system operates through four phases: (1) extracting the core task and contribution claims to generate retrieval queries; (2) retrieving relevant prior work based on extracted queries via semantic search engine; (3) constructing a hierarchical taxonomy of core-task-related work and performing contribution-level full-text comparisons against each contribution; and (4) synthesizing all analyses into a structured novelty report with explicit citations and evidence snippets. Unlike naive LLM-based approaches, OpenNovelty grounds all assessments in retrieved real papers, ensuring verifiable judgments. We deploy our system on 500+ ICLR 2026 submissions with all reports publicly available on our website, and preliminary analysis suggests it can identify relevant prior work, including closely related papers that authors may overlook. OpenNovelty aims to empower the research community with a scalable tool that promotes fair, consistent, and evidence-backed peer review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01576</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 15:48:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NitroGen: An Open Foundation Model for Generalist Gaming Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02427</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02427.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Loïc Magne, Anas Awadalla, Guanzhi Wang, Yinzhen Xu, Joshua Belofsky, Fengyuan Hu, Joohwan Kim, Ludwig Schmidt, Georgia Gkioxari, Jan Kautz, Yisong Yue, Yejin Choi, Yuke Zhu, Linxi "Jim" Fan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce NitroGen, a vision-action foundation model for generalist gaming agents that is trained on 40,000 hours of gameplay videos across more than 1,000 games. We incorporate three key ingredients: 1) an internet-scale video-action dataset constructed by automatically extracting player actions from publicly available gameplay videos, 2) a multi-game benchmark environment that can measure cross-game generalization, and 3) a unified vision-action model trained with large-scale behavior cloning. NitroGen exhibits strong competence across diverse domains, including combat encounters in 3D action games, high-precision control in 2D platformers, and exploration in procedurally generated worlds. It transfers effectively to unseen games, achieving up to 52% relative improvement in task success rates over models trained from scratch. We release the dataset, evaluation suite, and model weights to advance research on generalist embodied agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02427</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 16:24:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenRT: An Open-Source Red Teaming Framework for Multimodal LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01592</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01592.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Wang, Yunhao Chen, Juncheng Li, Yixu Wang, Yang Yao, Tianle Gu, Jie Li, Yan Teng, Xingjun Ma, Yingchun Wang, Xia Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid integration of Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) into critical applications is increasingly hindered by persistent safety vulnerabilities. However, existing red-teaming benchmarks are often fragmented, limited to single-turn text interactions, and lack the scalability required for systematic evaluation. To address this, we introduce OpenRT, a unified, modular, and high-throughput red-teaming framework designed for comprehensive MLLM safety evaluation. At its core, OpenRT architects a paradigm shift in automated red-teaming by introducing an adversarial kernel that enables modular separation across five critical dimensions: model integration, dataset management, attack strategies, judging methods, and evaluation metrics. By standardizing attack interfaces, it decouples adversarial logic from a high-throughput asynchronous runtime, enabling systematic scaling across diverse models. Our framework integrates 37 diverse attack methodologies, spanning white-box gradients, multi-modal perturbations, and sophisticated multi-agent evolutionary strategies. Through an extensive empirical study on 20 advanced models (including GPT-5.2, Claude 4.5, and Gemini 3 Pro), we expose critical safety gaps: even frontier models fail to generalize across attack paradigms, with leading models exhibiting average Attack Success Rates as high as 49.14%. Notably, our findings reveal that reasoning models do not inherently possess superior robustness against complex, multi-turn jailbreaks. By open-sourcing OpenRT, we provide a sustainable, extensible, and continuously maintained infrastructure that accelerates the development and standardization of AI safety.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01592</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 16:41:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FFP-300K: Scaling First-Frame Propagation for Generalizable Video Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01720</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01720.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xijie Huang, Chengming Xu, Donghao Luo, Xiaobin Hu, Peng Tang, Xu Peng, Jiangning Zhang, Chengjie Wang, Yanwei Fu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; First-Frame Propagation (FFP) offers a promising paradigm for controllable video editing, but existing methods are hampered by a reliance on cumbersome run-time guidance. We identify the root cause of this limitation as the inadequacy of current training datasets, which are often too short, low-resolution, and lack the task diversity required to teach robust temporal priors. To address this foundational data gap, we first introduce FFP-300K, a new large-scale dataset comprising 300K high-fidelity video pairs at 720p resolution and 81 frames in length, constructed via a principled two-track pipeline for diverse local and global edits. Building on this dataset, we propose a novel framework designed for true guidance-free FFP that resolves the critical tension between maintaining first-frame appearance and preserving source video motion. Architecturally, we introduce Adaptive Spatio-Temporal RoPE (AST-RoPE), which dynamically remaps positional encodings to disentangle appearance and motion references. At the objective level, we employ a self-distillation strategy where an identity propagation task acts as a powerful regularizer, ensuring long-term temporal stability and preventing semantic drift. Comprehensive experiments on the EditVerseBench benchmark demonstrate that our method significantly outperforming existing academic and commercial models by receiving about 0.2 PickScore and 0.3 VLM score improvement against these competitors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01720</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 01:46:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>K-EXAONE Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01739</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01739.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Eunbi Choi, Kibong Choi, Seokhee Hong, Junwon Hwang, Hyojin Jeon, Hyunjik Jo, Joonkee Kim, Seonghwan Kim, Soyeon Kim, Sunkyoung Kim, Yireun Kim, Yongil Kim, Haeju Lee, Jinsik Lee, Kyungmin Lee, Sangha Park, Heuiyeen Yeen, Hwan Chang, Stanley Jungkyu Choi, Yejin Choi, Jiwon Ham, Kijeong Jeon, Geunyeong Jeong, Gerrard Jeongwon Jo, Yonghwan Jo, Jiyeon Jung, Naeun Kang, Dohoon Kim, Euisoon Kim, Hayeon Kim, Hyosang Kim, Hyunseo Kim, Jieun Kim, Minu Kim, Myoungshin Kim, Unsol Kim, Youchul Kim, YoungJin Kim, Chaeeun Lee, Chaeyoon Lee, Changhun Lee, Dahm Lee, Edward Hwayoung Lee, Honglak Lee, Jinsang Lee, Jiyoung Lee, Sangeun Lee, Seungwon Lim, Solji Lim, Woohyung Lim, Chanwoo Moon, Jaewoo Park, Jinho Park, Yongmin Park, Hyerin Seo, Wooseok Seo, Yongwoo Song, Sejong Yang, Sihoon Yang, Chang En Yea, Sihyuk Yi, Chansik Yoon, Dongkeun Yoon, Sangyeon Yoon, Hyeongu Yun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 78&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This technical report presents K-EXAONE, a large-scale multilingual language model developed by LG AI Research. K-EXAONE is built on a Mixture-of-Experts architecture with 236B total parameters, activating 23B parameters during inference. It supports a 256K-token context window and covers six languages: Korean, English, Spanish, German, Japanese, and Vietnamese. We evaluate K-EXAONE on a comprehensive benchmark suite spanning reasoning, agentic, general, Korean, and multilingual abilities. Across these evaluations, K-EXAONE demonstrates performance comparable to open-weight models of similar size. K-EXAONE, designed to advance AI for a better life, is positioned as a powerful proprietary AI foundation model for a wide range of industrial and research applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01739</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 02:30:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>COMPASS: A Framework for Evaluating Organization-Specific Policy Alignment in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01836</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01836.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dasol Choi, DongGeon Lee, Brigitta Jesica Kartono, Helena Berndt, Taeyoun Kwon, Joonwon Jang, Haon Park, Hwanjo Yu, Minsuk Kahng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language models are deployed in high-stakes enterprise applications, from healthcare to finance, ensuring adherence to organization-specific policies has become essential. Yet existing safety evaluations focus exclusively on universal harms. We present COMPASS (Company/Organization Policy Alignment Assessment), the first systematic framework for evaluating whether LLMs comply with organizational allowlist and denylist policies. We apply COMPASS to eight diverse industry scenarios, generating and validating 5,920 queries that test both routine compliance and adversarial robustness through strategically designed edge cases. Evaluating seven state-of-the-art models, we uncover a fundamental asymmetry: models reliably handle legitimate requests (&gt;95% accuracy) but catastrophically fail at enforcing prohibitions, refusing only 13-40% of adversarial denylist violations. These results demonstrate that current LLMs lack the robustness required for policy-critical deployments, establishing COMPASS as an essential evaluation framework for organizational AI safety.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01836</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 06:57:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CogFlow: Bridging Perception and Reasoning through Knowledge Internalization for Visual Mathematical Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01874</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.01874.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuhang Chen, Yunqiu Xu, Junjie Xie, Aojun Lu, Tao Feng, Zeying Huang, Ning Zhang, Yi Sun, Yi Yang, Hangjie Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite significant progress, multimodal large language models continue to struggle with visual mathematical problem solving. Some recent works recognize that visual perception is a bottleneck in visual mathematical reasoning, but their solutions are limited to improving the extraction and interpretation of visual inputs. Notably, they all ignore the key issue of whether the extracted visual cues are faithfully integrated and properly utilized in subsequent reasoning. Motivated by this, we present CogFlow, a novel cognitive-inspired three-stage framework that incorporates a knowledge internalization stage, explicitly simulating the hierarchical flow of human reasoning: perceptionRightarrowinternalizationRightarrowreasoning. Inline with this hierarchical flow, we holistically enhance all its stages. We devise Synergistic Visual Rewards to boost perception capabilities in parametric and semantic spaces, jointly improving visual information extraction from symbols and diagrams. To guarantee faithful integration of extracted visual cues into subsequent reasoning, we introduce a Knowledge Internalization Reward model in the internalization stage, bridging perception and reasoning. Moreover, we design a Visual-Gated Policy Optimization algorithm to further enforce the reasoning is grounded with the visual knowledge, preventing models seeking shortcuts that appear coherent but are visually ungrounded reasoning chains. Moreover, we contribute a new dataset MathCog for model training, which contains samples with over 120K high-quality perception-reasoning aligned annotations. Comprehensive experiments and analysis on commonly used visual mathematical reasoning benchmarks validate the superiority of the proposed CogFlow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01874</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:02:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebGym: Scaling Training Environments for Visual Web Agents with Realistic Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02439</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02439.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Bai, Alexey Taymanov, Tong Zhang, Aviral Kumar, Spencer Whitehead&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present WebGym, the largest-to-date open-source environment for training realistic visual web agents. Real websites are non-stationary and diverse, making artificial or small-scale task sets insufficient for robust policy learning. WebGym contains nearly 300,000 tasks with rubric-based evaluations across diverse, real-world websites and difficulty levels. We train agents with a simple reinforcement learning (RL) recipe, which trains on the agent's own interaction traces (rollouts), using task rewards as feedback to guide learning. To enable scaling RL, we speed up sampling of trajectories in WebGym by developing a high-throughput asynchronous rollout system, designed specifically for web agents. Our system achieves a 4-5x rollout speedup compared to naive implementations. Second, we scale the task set breadth, depth, and size, which results in continued performance improvement. Fine-tuning a strong base vision-language model, Qwen-3-VL-8B-Instruct, on WebGym results in an improvement in success rate on an out-of-distribution test set from 26.2% to 42.9%, significantly outperforming agents based on proprietary models such as GPT-4o and GPT-5-Thinking that achieve 27.1% and 29.8%, respectively. This improvement is substantial because our test set consists only of tasks on websites never seen during training, unlike many other prior works on training visual web agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02439</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 09:35:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MDAgent2: Large Language Model for Code Generation and Knowledge Q&amp;A in Molecular Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02075</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02075.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuofan Shi, Hubao A, Yufei Shao, Mengyan Dai, Yadong Yu, Pan Xiang, Dongliang Huang, Hongxu An, Chunxiao Xin, Haiyang Shen, Zhenyu Wang, Yunshan Na, Gang Huang, Xiang Jing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations are essential for understanding atomic-scale behaviors in materials science, yet writing LAMMPS scripts remains highly specialized and time-consuming tasks. Although LLMs show promise in code generation and domain-specific question answering, their performance in MD scenarios is limited by scarce domain data, the high deployment cost of state-of-the-art LLMs, and low code executability. Building upon our prior MDAgent, we present MDAgent2, the first end-to-end framework capable of performing both knowledge Q&amp;A and code generation within the MD domain. We construct a domain-specific data-construction pipeline that yields three high-quality datasets spanning MD knowledge, question answering, and code generation. Based on these datasets, we adopt a three stage post-training strategy--continued pre-training (CPT), supervised fine-tuning (SFT), and reinforcement learning (RL)--to train two domain-adapted models, MD-Instruct and MD-Code. Furthermore, we introduce MD-GRPO, a closed-loop RL method that leverages simulation outcomes as reward signals and recycles low-reward trajectories for continual refinement. We further build MDAgent2-RUNTIME, a deployable multi-agent system that integrates code generation, execution, evaluation, and self-correction. Together with MD-EvalBench proposed in this work, the first benchmark for LAMMPS code generation and question answering, our models and system achieve performance surpassing several strong baselines.This work systematically demonstrates the adaptability and generalization capability of large language models in industrial simulation tasks, laying a methodological foundation for automatic code generation in AI for Science and industrial-scale simulations. URL: https://github.com/FredericVAN/PKU_MDAgent2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02075</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 12:56:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy-Adaptive Fine-Tuning: Resolving Confident Conflicts to Mitigate Forgetting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02151</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02151.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muxi Diao, Lele Yang, Wuxuan Gong, Yutong Zhang, Zhonghao Yan, Yufei Han, Kongming Liang, Weiran Xu, Zhanyu Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 87&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) is the standard paradigm for domain adaptation, yet it frequently incurs the cost of catastrophic forgetting. In sharp contrast, on-policy Reinforcement Learning (RL) effectively preserves general capabilities. We investigate this discrepancy and identify a fundamental distributional gap: while RL aligns with the model's internal belief, SFT forces the model to fit external supervision. This mismatch often manifests as "Confident Conflicts" tokens characterized by low probability but low entropy. In these instances, the model is highly confident in its own prediction but is forced to learn a divergent ground truth, triggering destructive gradient updates. To address this, we propose Entropy-Adaptive Fine-Tuning (EAFT). Unlike methods relying solely on prediction probability, EAFT utilizes token-level entropy as a gating mechanism to distinguish between epistemic uncertainty and knowledge conflict. This allows the model to learn from uncertain samples while suppressing gradients on conflicting data. Extensive experiments on Qwen and GLM series (ranging from 4B to 32B parameters) across mathematical, medical, and agentic domains confirm our hypothesis. EAFT consistently matches the downstream performance of standard SFT while significantly mitigating the degradation of general capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02151</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:28:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confidence Estimation for LLMs in Multi-turn Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02179</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02179.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Caiqi Zhang, Ruihan Yang, Xiaochen Zhu, Chengzu Li, Tiancheng Hu, Yijiang River Dong, Deqing Yang, Nigel Collier&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While confidence estimation is a promising direction for mitigating hallucinations in Large Language Models (LLMs), current research dominantly focuses on single-turn settings. The dynamics of model confidence in multi-turn conversations, where context accumulates and ambiguity is progressively resolved, remain largely unexplored. Reliable confidence estimation in multi-turn settings is critical for many downstream applications, such as autonomous agents and human-in-the-loop systems. This work presents the first systematic study of confidence estimation in multi-turn interactions, establishing a formal evaluation framework grounded in two key desiderata: per-turn calibration and monotonicity of confidence as more information becomes available. To facilitate this, we introduce novel metrics, including a length-normalized Expected Calibration Error (InfoECE), and a new "Hinter-Guesser" paradigm for generating controlled evaluation datasets. Our experiments reveal that widely-used confidence techniques struggle with calibration and monotonicity in multi-turn dialogues. We propose P(Sufficient), a logit-based probe that achieves comparatively better performance, although the task remains far from solved. Our work provides a foundational methodology for developing more reliable and trustworthy conversational agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02179</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NextFlow: Unified Sequential Modeling Activates Multimodal Understanding and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02204</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02204.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huichao Zhang, Liao Qu, Yiheng Liu, Hang Chen, Yangyang Song, Yongsheng Dong, Shikun Sun, Xian Li, Xu Wang, Yi Jiang, Hu Ye, Bo Chen, Yiming Gao, Peng Liu, Akide Liu, Zhipeng Yang, Qili Deng, Linjie Xing, Jiyang Liu, Zhao Wang, Yang Zhou, Mingcong Liu, Yi Zhang, Qian He, Xiwei Hu, Zhongqi Qi, Jie Shao, Zhiye Fu, Shuai Wang, Fangmin Chen, Xuezhi Chai, Zhihua Wu, Yitong Wang, Zehuan Yuan, Daniel K. Du, Xinglong Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present NextFlow, a unified decoder-only autoregressive transformer trained on 6 trillion interleaved text-image discrete tokens. By leveraging a unified vision representation within a unified autoregressive architecture, NextFlow natively activates multimodal understanding and generation capabilities, unlocking abilities of image editing, interleaved content and video generation. Motivated by the distinct nature of modalities - where text is strictly sequential and images are inherently hierarchical - we retain next-token prediction for text but adopt next-scale prediction for visual generation. This departs from traditional raster-scan methods, enabling the generation of 1024x1024 images in just 5 seconds - orders of magnitude faster than comparable AR models. We address the instabilities of multi-scale generation through a robust training recipe. Furthermore, we introduce a prefix-tuning strategy for reinforcement learning. Experiments demonstrate that NextFlow achieves state-of-the-art performance among unified models and rivals specialized diffusion baselines in visual quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02204</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 15:27:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VAR RL Done Right: Tackling Asynchronous Policy Conflicts in Visual Autoregressive Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02256</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02256.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shikun Sun, Liao Qu, Huichao Zhang, Yiheng Liu, Yangyang Song, Xian Li, Xu Wang, Yi Jiang, Daniel K. Du, Xinglong Wu, Jia Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual generation is dominated by three paradigms: AutoRegressive (AR), diffusion, and Visual AutoRegressive (VAR) models. Unlike AR and diffusion, VARs operate on heterogeneous input structures across their generation steps, which creates severe asynchronous policy conflicts. This issue becomes particularly acute in reinforcement learning (RL) scenarios, leading to unstable training and suboptimal alignment. To resolve this, we propose a novel framework to enhance Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) by explicitly managing these conflicts. Our method integrates three synergistic components: 1) a stabilizing intermediate reward to guide early-stage generation; 2) a dynamic time-step reweighting scheme for precise credit assignment; and 3) a novel mask propagation algorithm, derived from principles of Reward Feedback Learning (ReFL), designed to isolate optimization effects both spatially and temporally. Our approach demonstrates significant improvements in sample quality and objective alignment over the vanilla GRPO baseline, enabling robust and effective optimization for VAR models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02256</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 16:36:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiffProxy: Multi-View Human Mesh Recovery via Diffusion-Generated Dense Proxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02267</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02267.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Renke Wang, Zhenyu Zhang, Ying Tai, Jian Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human mesh recovery from multi-view images faces a fundamental challenge: real-world datasets contain imperfect ground-truth annotations that bias the models' training, while synthetic data with precise supervision suffers from domain gap. In this paper, we propose DiffProxy, a novel framework that generates multi-view consistent human proxies for mesh recovery. Central to DiffProxy is leveraging the diffusion-based generative priors to bridge the synthetic training and real-world generalization. Its key innovations include: (1) a multi-conditional mechanism for generating multi-view consistent, pixel-aligned human proxies; (2) a hand refinement module that incorporates flexible visual prompts to enhance local details; and (3) an uncertainty-aware test-time scaling method that increases robustness to challenging cases during optimization. These designs ensure that the mesh recovery process effectively benefits from the precise synthetic ground truth and generative advantages of the diffusion-based pipeline. Trained entirely on synthetic data, DiffProxy achieves state-of-the-art performance across five real-world benchmarks, demonstrating strong zero-shot generalization particularly on challenging scenarios with occlusions and partial views. Project page: https://wrk226.github.io/DiffProxy.html&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02267</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 16:51:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfiniteVGGT: Visual Geometry Grounded Transformer for Endless Streams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02281</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02281.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuai Yuan, Yantai Yang, Xiaotian Yang, Xupeng Zhang, Zhonghao Zhao, Lingming Zhang, Zhipeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The grand vision of enabling persistent, large-scale 3D visual geometry understanding is shackled by the irreconcilable demands of scalability and long-term stability. While offline models like VGGT achieve inspiring geometry capability, their batch-based nature renders them irrelevant for live systems. Streaming architectures, though the intended solution for live operation, have proven inadequate. Existing methods either fail to support truly infinite-horizon inputs or suffer from catastrophic drift over long sequences. We shatter this long-standing dilemma with InfiniteVGGT, a causal visual geometry transformer that operationalizes the concept of a rolling memory through a bounded yet adaptive and perpetually expressive KV cache. Capitalizing on this, we devise a training-free, attention-agnostic pruning strategy that intelligently discards obsolete information, effectively ``rolling'' the memory forward with each new frame. Fully compatible with FlashAttention, InfiniteVGGT finally alleviates the compromise, enabling infinite-horizon streaming while outperforming existing streaming methods in long-term stability. The ultimate test for such a system is its performance over a truly infinite horizon, a capability that has been impossible to rigorously validate due to the lack of extremely long-term, continuous benchmarks. To address this critical gap, we introduce the Long3D benchmark, which, for the first time, enables a rigorous evaluation of continuous 3D geometry estimation on sequences about 10,000 frames. This provides the definitive evaluation platform for future research in long-term 3D geometry understanding. Code is available at: https://github.com/AutoLab-SAI-SJTU/InfiniteVGGT&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02281</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 17:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Falcon-H1R: Pushing the Reasoning Frontiers with a Hybrid Model for Efficient Test-Time Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02346</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02346.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Falcon LLM Team, Iheb Chaabane, Puneesh Khanna, Suhail Mohmad, Slim Frikha, Shi Hu, Abdalgader Abubaker, Reda Alami, Mikhail Lubinets, Mohamed El Amine Seddik, Hakim Hacid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This work introduces Falcon-H1R, a 7B-parameter reasoning-optimized model that establishes the feasibility of achieving competitive reasoning performance with small language models (SLMs). Falcon-H1R stands out for its parameter efficiency, consistently matching or outperforming SOTA reasoning models that are 2times to 7times larger across a variety of reasoning-intensive benchmarks. These results underscore the importance of careful data curation and targeted training strategies (via both efficient SFT and RL scaling) in delivering significant performance gains without increasing model size. Furthermore, Falcon-H1R advances the 3D limits of reasoning efficiency by combining faster inference (through its hybrid-parallel architecture design), token efficiency, and higher accuracy. This unique blend makes Falcon-H1R-7B a practical backbone for scaling advanced reasoning systems, particularly in scenarios requiring extensive chain-of-thoughts generation and parallel test-time scaling. Leveraging the recently introduced DeepConf approach, Falcon-H1R achieves state-of-the-art test-time scaling efficiency, offering substantial improvements in both accuracy and computational cost. As a result, Falcon-H1R demonstrates that compact models, through targeted model training and architectural choices, can deliver robust and scalable reasoning performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02346</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:44:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talk2Move: Reinforcement Learning for Text-Instructed Object-Level Geometric Transformation in Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02356</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02356.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jing Tan, Zhaoyang Zhang, Yantao Shen, Jiarui Cai, Shuo Yang, Jiajun Wu, Wei Xia, Zhuowen Tu, Stefano Soatto&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Talk2Move, a reinforcement learning (RL) based diffusion framework for text-instructed spatial transformation of objects within scenes. Spatially manipulating objects in a scene through natural language poses a challenge for multimodal generation systems. While existing text-based manipulation methods can adjust appearance or style, they struggle to perform object-level geometric transformations-such as translating, rotating, or resizing objects-due to scarce paired supervision and pixel-level optimization limits. Talk2Move employs Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) to explore geometric actions through diverse rollouts generated from input images and lightweight textual variations, removing the need for costly paired data. A spatial reward guided model aligns geometric transformations with linguistic description, while off-policy step evaluation and active step sampling improve learning efficiency by focusing on informative transformation stages. Furthermore, we design object-centric spatial rewards that evaluate displacement, rotation, and scaling behaviors directly, enabling interpretable and coherent transformations. Experiments on curated benchmarks demonstrate that Talk2Move achieves precise, consistent, and semantically faithful object transformations, outperforming existing text-guided editing approaches in both spatial accuracy and scene coherence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02356</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:55:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VINO: A Unified Visual Generator with Interleaved OmniModal Context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02358</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02358.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyi Chen, Tong He, Zhoujie Fu, Pengfei Wan, Kun Gai, Weicai Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present VINO, a unified visual generator that performs image and video generation and editing within a single framework. Instead of relying on task-specific models or independent modules for each modality, VINO uses a shared diffusion backbone that conditions on text, images and videos, enabling a broad range of visual creation and editing tasks under one model. Specifically, VINO couples a vision-language model (VLM) with a Multimodal Diffusion Transformer (MMDiT), where multimodal inputs are encoded as interleaved conditioning tokens, and then used to guide the diffusion process. This design supports multi-reference grounding, long-form instruction following, and coherent identity preservation across static and dynamic content, while avoiding modality-specific architectural components. To train such a unified system, we introduce a multi-stage training pipeline that progressively expands a video generation base model into a unified, multi-task generator capable of both image and video input and output. Across diverse generation and editing benchmarks, VINO demonstrates strong visual quality, faithful instruction following, improved reference and attribute preservation, and more controllable multi-identity edits. Our results highlight a practical path toward scalable unified visual generation, and the promise of interleaved, in-context computation as a foundation for general-purpose visual creation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02358</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:56:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ExposeAnyone: Personalized Audio-to-Expression Diffusion Models Are Robust Zero-Shot Face Forgery Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02359</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02359.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaede Shiohara, Toshihiko Yamasaki, Vladislav Golyanik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Detecting unknown deepfake manipulations remains one of the most challenging problems in face forgery detection. Current state-of-the-art approaches fail to generalize to unseen manipulations, as they primarily rely on supervised training with existing deepfakes or pseudo-fakes, which leads to overfitting to specific forgery patterns. In contrast, self-supervised methods offer greater potential for generalization, but existing work struggles to learn discriminative representations only from self-supervision. In this paper, we propose ExposeAnyone, a fully self-supervised approach based on a diffusion model that generates expression sequences from audio. The key idea is, once the model is personalized to specific subjects using reference sets, it can compute the identity distances between suspected videos and personalized subjects via diffusion reconstruction errors, enabling person-of-interest face forgery detection. Extensive experiments demonstrate that 1) our method outperforms the previous state-of-the-art method by 4.22 percentage points in the average AUC on DF-TIMIT, DFDCP, KoDF, and IDForge datasets, 2) our model is also capable of detecting Sora2-generated videos, where the previous approaches perform poorly, and 3) our method is highly robust to corruptions such as blur and compression, highlighting the applicability in real-world face forgery detection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02359</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 18:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SimpleMem: Efficient Lifelong Memory for LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02553</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02553.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Liu, Yaofeng Su, Peng Xia, Siwei Han, Zeyu Zheng, Cihang Xie, Mingyu Ding, Huaxiu Yao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; To support reliable long-term interaction in complex environments, LLM agents require memory systems that efficiently manage historical experiences. Existing approaches either retain full interaction histories via passive context extension, leading to substantial redundancy, or rely on iterative reasoning to filter noise, incurring high token costs. To address this challenge, we introduce SimpleMem, an efficient memory framework based on semantic lossless compression. We propose a three-stage pipeline designed to maximize information density and token utilization: (1) Semantic Structured Compression, which applies entropy-aware filtering to distill unstructured interactions into compact, multi-view indexed memory units; (2) Recursive Memory Consolidation, an asynchronous process that integrates related units into higher-level abstract representations to reduce redundancy; and (3) Adaptive Query-Aware Retrieval, which dynamically adjusts retrieval scope based on query complexity to construct precise context efficiently. Experiments on benchmark datasets show that our method consistently outperforms baseline approaches in accuracy, retrieval efficiency, and inference cost, achieving an average F1 improvement of 26.4% while reducing inference-time token consumption by up to 30-fold, demonstrating a superior balance between performance and efficiency. Code is available at https://github.com/aiming-lab/SimpleMem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02553</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 21:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning User Preferences Through Interaction for Long-Term Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02702</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02702.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuhaib Mehri, Priyanka Kargupta, Tal August, Dilek Hakkani-Tür&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As conversational agents accumulate experience collaborating with users, adapting to user preferences is essential for fostering long-term relationships and improving collaboration quality over time. We introduce MultiSessionCollab, a benchmark that evaluates how well agents can learn user preferences and leverage them to improve collaboration quality throughout multiple sessions. To develop agents that succeed in this setting, we present long-term collaborative agents equipped with a memory that persists and refines user preference as interaction experience accumulates. Moreover, we demonstrate that learning signals can be derived from user simulator behavior in MultiSessionCollab to train agents to generate more comprehensive reflections and update their memory more effectively. Extensive experiments show that equipping agents with memory improves long-term collaboration, yielding higher task success rates, more efficient interactions, and reduced user effort. Finally, we conduct a human user study that demonstrates that memory helps improve user experience in real-world settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02702</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 04:26:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiMo-V2-Flash Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02780</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02780.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bangjun Xiao, Bingquan Xia, Bo Yang, Bofei Gao, Bowen Shen, Chen Zhang, Chenhong He, Chiheng Lou, Fuli Luo, Gang Wang, Gang Xie, Hailin Zhang, Hanglong Lv, Hanyu Li, Heyu Chen, Hongshen Xu, Houbin Zhang, Huaqiu Liu, Jiangshan Duo, Jianyu Wei, Jiebao Xiao, Jinhao Dong, Jun Shi, Junhao Hu, Kainan Bao, Kang Zhou, Lei Li, Liang Zhao, Linghao Zhang, Peidian Li, Qianli Chen, Shaohui Liu, Shihua Yu, Shijie Cao, Shimao Chen, Shouqiu Yu, Shuo Liu, Tianling Zhou, Weijiang Su, Weikun Wang, Wenhan Ma, Xiangwei Deng, Bohan Mao, Bowen Ye, Can Cai, Chenghua Wang, Chengxuan Zhu, Chong Ma, Chun Chen, Chunan Li, Dawei Zhu, Deshan Xiao, Dong Zhang, Duo Zhang, Fangyue Liu, Feiyu Yang, Fengyuan Shi, Guoan Wang, Hao Tian, Hao Wu, Heng Qu, Hongfei Yi, Hongxu An, Hongyi Guan, Xing Zhang, Yifan Song, Yihan Yan, Yihao Zhao, Yingchun Lai, Yizhao Gao, Yu Cheng, Yuanyuan Tian, Yudong Wang, Zhen Tang, Zhengju Tang, Zhengtao Wen, Zhichao Song, Zhixian Zheng, Zihan Jiang, Jian Wen, Jiarui Sun, Jiawei Li, Jinlong Xue, Jun Xia, Kai Fang, Menghang Zhu, Nuo Chen, Qian Tu, Qihao Zhang, Qiying Wang, Rang Li, Rui Ma, Shaolei Zhang, Shengfan Wang, Shicheng Li, Shuhao Gu, Shuhuai Ren, Sirui Deng, Tao Guo, Tianyang Lu, Weiji Zhuang, Weikang Zhang, Weimin Xiong, Wenshan Huang, Wenyu Yang, Xin Zhang, Xing Yong, Xu Wang, Xueyang Xie, Yilin Jiang, Yixin Yang, Yongzhe He, Yu Tu, Yuanliang Dong, Yuchen Liu, Yue Ma, Yue Yu, Yuxing Xiang, Zhaojun Huang, Zhenru Lin, Zhipeng Xu, Zhiyang Chen, Zhonghua Deng, Zihan Zhang, Zihao Yue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present MiMo-V2-Flash, a Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) model with 309B total parameters and 15B active parameters, designed for fast, strong reasoning and agentic capabilities. MiMo-V2-Flash adopts a hybrid attention architecture that interleaves Sliding Window Attention (SWA) with global attention, with a 128-token sliding window under a 5:1 hybrid ratio. The model is pre-trained on 27 trillion tokens with Multi-Token Prediction (MTP), employing a native 32k context length and subsequently extended to 256k. To efficiently scale post-training compute, MiMo-V2-Flash introduces a novel Multi-Teacher On-Policy Distillation (MOPD) paradigm. In this framework, domain-specialized teachers (e.g., trained via large-scale reinforcement learning) provide dense and token-level reward, enabling the student model to perfectly master teacher expertise. MiMo-V2-Flash rivals top-tier open-weight models such as DeepSeek-V3.2 and Kimi-K2, despite using only 1/2 and 1/3 of their total parameters, respectively. During inference, by repurposing MTP as a draft model for speculative decoding, MiMo-V2-Flash achieves up to 3.6 acceptance length and 2.6x decoding speedup with three MTP layers. We open-source both the model weights and the three-layer MTP weights to foster open research and community collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02780</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 07:31:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamStyle: A Unified Framework for Video Stylization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02785</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02785.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengtian Li, Jinshu Chen, Songtao Zhao, Wanquan Feng, Pengqi Tu, Qian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video stylization, an important downstream task of video generation models, has not yet been thoroughly explored. Its input style conditions typically include text, style image, and stylized first frame. Each condition has a characteristic advantage: text is more flexible, style image provides a more accurate visual anchor, and stylized first frame makes long-video stylization feasible. However, existing methods are largely confined to a single type of style condition, which limits their scope of application. Additionally, their lack of high-quality datasets leads to style inconsistency and temporal flicker. To address these limitations, we introduce DreamStyle, a unified framework for video stylization, supporting (1) text-guided, (2) style-image-guided, and (3) first-frame-guided video stylization, accompanied by a well-designed data curation pipeline to acquire high-quality paired video data. DreamStyle is built on a vanilla Image-to-Video (I2V) model and trained using a Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) with token-specific up matrices that reduces the confusion among different condition tokens. Both qualitative and quantitative evaluations demonstrate that DreamStyle is competent in all three video stylization tasks, and outperforms the competitors in style consistency and video quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02785</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 07:42:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanistic Interpretability of Large-Scale Counting in LLMs through a System-2 Strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02989</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02989.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hosein Hasani, Mohammadali Banayeeanzade, Ali Nafisi, Sadegh Mohammadian, Fatemeh Askari, Mobin Bagherian, Amirmohammad Izadi, Mahdieh Soleymani Baghshah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs), despite strong performance on complex mathematical problems, exhibit systematic limitations in counting tasks. This issue arises from architectural limits of transformers, where counting is performed across layers, leading to degraded precision for larger counting problems due to depth constraints. To address this limitation, we propose a simple test-time strategy inspired by System-2 cognitive processes that decomposes large counting tasks into smaller, independent sub-problems that the model can reliably solve. We evaluate this approach using observational and causal mediation analyses to understand the underlying mechanism of this System-2-like strategy. Our mechanistic analysis identifies key components: latent counts are computed and stored in the final item representations of each part, transferred to intermediate steps via dedicated attention heads, and aggregated in the final stage to produce the total count. Experimental results demonstrate that this strategy enables LLMs to surpass architectural limitations and achieve high accuracy on large-scale counting tasks. This work provides mechanistic insight into System-2 counting in LLMs and presents a generalizable approach for improving and understanding their reasoning behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02989</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 12:58:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Reasoning Models Are (Not Yet) Multilingual Latent Reasoners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02996</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.02996.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yihong Liu, Raoyuan Zhao, Hinrich Schütze, Michael A. Hedderich&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs) achieve strong performance on mathematical reasoning tasks, often attributed to their capability to generate explicit chain-of-thought (CoT) explanations. However, recent work shows that LRMs often arrive at the correct answer before completing these textual reasoning steps, indicating the presence of latent reasoning -- internal, non-verbal computation encoded in hidden states. While this phenomenon has been explored in English, its multilingual behavior remains largely unknown. In this paper, we conduct a systematic investigation of multilingual latent reasoning in LRMs across 11 languages. Using a truncation-based strategy, we examine how the correct answer emerges as the model is given only partial reasoning traces, allowing us to measure stepwise latent prediction formation. Our results reveal clear evidence of multilingual latent reasoning, though unevenly: strong in resource-rich languages, weaker in low-resource ones, and broadly less observable on harder benchmarks. To understand whether these differences reflect distinct internal mechanisms, we further perform representational analyses. Despite surface-level disparities, we find that the internal evolution of predictions is highly consistent across languages and broadly aligns with English -- a pattern suggesting an English-centered latent reasoning pathway.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02996</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 13:20:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why LLMs Aren't Scientists Yet: Lessons from Four Autonomous Research Attempts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03315</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03315.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dhruv Trehan, Paras Chopra&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We report a case study of four end-to-end attempts to autonomously generate ML research papers using a pipeline of six LLM agents mapped to stages of the scientific workflow. Of these four, three attempts failed during implementation or evaluation. One completed the pipeline and was accepted to Agents4Science 2025, an experimental inaugural venue that required AI systems as first authors, passing both human and multi-AI review. From these attempts, we document six recurring failure modes: bias toward training data defaults, implementation drift under execution pressure, memory and context degradation across long-horizon tasks, overexcitement that declares success despite obvious failures, insufficient domain intelligence, and weak scientific taste in experimental design. We conclude by discussing four design principles for more robust AI-scientist systems, implications for autonomous scientific discovery, and we release all prompts, artifacts, and outputs at https://github.com/Lossfunk/ai-scientist-artefacts-v1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03315</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 13:20:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SOP: A Scalable Online Post-Training System for Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03044</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03044.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingjie Pan, Siyuan Feng, Qinglin Zhang, Xinchen Li, Jianheng Song, Chendi Qu, Yi Wang, Chuankang Li, Ziyu Xiong, Zhi Chen, Yi Liu, Jianlan Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language-action (VLA) models achieve strong generalization through large-scale pre-training, but real-world deployment requires expert-level task proficiency in addition to broad generality. Existing post-training approaches for VLA models are typically offline, single-robot, or task-specific, limiting effective on-policy adaptation and scalable learning from real-world interaction. We introduce a Scalable Online Post-training (SOP) system that enables online, distributed, multi-task post-training of generalist VLA models directly in the physical world. SOP tightly couples execution and learning through a closed-loop architecture in which a fleet of robots continuously streams on-policy experience and human intervention signals to a centralized cloud learner, and asynchronously receives updated policies. This design supports prompt on-policy correction, scales experience collection through parallel deployment, and preserves generality during adaptation. SOP is agnostic to the choice of post-training algorithm; we instantiate it with both interactive imitation learning (HG-DAgger) and reinforcement learning (RECAP). Across a range of real-world manipulation tasks including cloth folding, box assembly, and grocery restocking, we show that SOP substantially improves the performance of large pretrained VLA models while maintaining a single shared policy across tasks. Effective post-training can be achieved within hours of real-world interaction, and performance scales near-linearly with the number of robots in the fleet. These results suggest that tightly coupling online learning with fleet-scale deployment is instrumental to enabling efficient, reliable, and scalable post-training of generalist robot policies in the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03044</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 14:25:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One Sample to Rule Them All: Extreme Data Efficiency in RL Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03111</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03111.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiyuan Li, Zhen Huang, Yanan Wu, Weixun Wang, Xuefeng Li, Yijia Luo, Wenbo Su, Bo Zheng, Pengfei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The reasoning ability of large language models (LLMs) can be unleashed with reinforcement learning (RL) (OpenAI, 2024; DeepSeek-AI et al., 2025a; Zeng et al., 2025). The success of existing RL attempts in LLMs usually relies on high-quality samples of thousands or beyond. In this paper, we challenge fundamental assumptions about data requirements in RL for LLMs by demonstrating the remarkable effectiveness of one-shot learning. Specifically, we introduce polymath learning, a framework for designing one training sample that elicits multidisciplinary impact. We present three key findings: (1) A single, strategically selected math reasoning sample can produce significant performance improvements across multiple domains, including physics, chemistry, and biology with RL; (2) The math skills salient to reasoning suggest the characteristics of the optimal polymath sample; and (3) An engineered synthetic sample that integrates multidiscipline elements outperforms training with individual samples that naturally occur. Our approach achieves superior performance to training with larger datasets across various reasoning benchmarks, demonstrating that sample quality and design, rather than quantity, may be the key to unlock enhanced reasoning capabilities in language models. Our results suggest a shift, dubbed as sample engineering, toward precision engineering of training samples rather than simply increasing data volume.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03111</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 15:41:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Thinker: A General Reasoning Modular Core for Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03127</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03127.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sashuai Zhou, Qiang Zhou, Jijin Hu, Hanqing Yang, Yue Cao, Junpeng Ma, Yinchao Ma, Jun Song, Tiezheng Ge, Cheng Yu, Bo Zheng, Zhou Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite impressive progress in high-fidelity image synthesis, generative models still struggle with logic-intensive instruction following, exposing a persistent reasoning--execution gap. Meanwhile, closed-source systems (e.g., Nano Banana) have demonstrated strong reasoning-driven image generation, highlighting a substantial gap to current open-source models. We argue that closing this gap requires not merely better visual generators, but executable reasoning: decomposing high-level intents into grounded, verifiable plans that directly steer the generative process. To this end, we propose Unified Thinker, a task-agnostic reasoning architecture for general image generation, designed as a unified planning core that can plug into diverse generators and workflows. Unified Thinker decouples a dedicated Thinker from the image Generator, enabling modular upgrades of reasoning without retraining the entire generative model. We further introduce a two-stage training paradigm: we first build a structured planning interface for the Thinker, then apply reinforcement learning to ground its policy in pixel-level feedback, encouraging plans that optimize visual correctness over textual plausibility. Extensive experiments on text-to-image generation and image editing show that Unified Thinker substantially improves image reasoning and generation quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03127</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 15:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel Latent Reasoning for Sequential Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03153</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03153.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiakai Tang, Xu Chen, Wen Chen, Jian Wu, Yuning Jiang, Bo Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Capturing complex user preferences from sparse behavioral sequences remains a fundamental challenge in sequential recommendation. Recent latent reasoning methods have shown promise by extending test-time computation through multi-step reasoning, yet they exclusively rely on depth-level scaling along a single trajectory, suffering from diminishing returns as reasoning depth increases. To address this limitation, we propose Parallel Latent Reasoning (PLR), a novel framework that pioneers width-level computational scaling by exploring multiple diverse reasoning trajectories simultaneously. PLR constructs parallel reasoning streams through learnable trigger tokens in continuous latent space, preserves diversity across streams via global reasoning regularization, and adaptively synthesizes multi-stream outputs through mixture-of-reasoning-streams aggregation. Extensive experiments on three real-world datasets demonstrate that PLR substantially outperforms state-of-the-art baselines while maintaining real-time inference efficiency. Theoretical analysis further validates the effectiveness of parallel reasoning in improving generalization capability. Our work opens new avenues for enhancing reasoning capacity in sequential recommendation beyond existing depth scaling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03153</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 16:25:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniCorn: Towards Self-Improving Unified Multimodal Models through Self-Generated Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03193</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03193.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruiyan Han, Zhen Fang, XinYu Sun, Yuchen Ma, Ziheng Wang, Yu Zeng, Zehui Chen, Lin Chen, Wenxuan Huang, Wei-Jie Xu, Yi Cao, Feng Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Unified Multimodal Models (UMMs) have achieved remarkable success in cross-modal comprehension, a significant gap persists in their ability to leverage such internal knowledge for high-quality generation. We formalize this discrepancy as Conduction Aphasia, a phenomenon where models accurately interpret multimodal inputs but struggle to translate that understanding into faithful and controllable synthesis. To address this, we propose UniCorn, a simple yet elegant self-improvement framework that eliminates the need for external data or teacher supervision. By partitioning a single UMM into three collaborative roles: Proposer, Solver, and Judge, UniCorn generates high-quality interactions via self-play and employs cognitive pattern reconstruction to distill latent understanding into explicit generative signals. To validate the restoration of multimodal coherence, we introduce UniCycle, a cycle-consistency benchmark based on a Text to Image to Text reconstruction loop. Extensive experiments demonstrate that UniCorn achieves comprehensive and substantial improvements over the base model across six general image generation benchmarks. Notably, it achieves SOTA performance on TIIF(73.8), DPG(86.8), CompBench(88.5), and UniCycle while further delivering substantial gains of +5.0 on WISE and +6.5 on OneIG. These results highlight that our method significantly enhances T2I generation while maintaining robust comprehension, demonstrating the scalability of fully self-supervised refinement for unified multimodal intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03193</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 17:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LTX-2: Efficient Joint Audio-Visual Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03233</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03233.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yoav HaCohen, Benny Brazowski, Nisan Chiprut, Yaki Bitterman, Andrew Kvochko, Avishai Berkowitz, Daniel Shalem, Daphna Lifschitz, Dudu Moshe, Eitan Porat, Eitan Richardson, Guy Shiran, Itay Chachy, Jonathan Chetboun, Michael Finkelson, Michael Kupchick, Nir Zabari, Nitzan Guetta, Noa Kotler, Ofir Bibi, Ori Gordon, Poriya Panet, Roi Benita, Shahar Armon, Victor Kulikov, Yaron Inger, Yonatan Shiftan, Zeev Melumian, Zeev Farbman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent text-to-video diffusion models can generate compelling video sequences, yet they remain silent -- missing the semantic, emotional, and atmospheric cues that audio provides. We introduce LTX-2, an open-source foundational model capable of generating high-quality, temporally synchronized audiovisual content in a unified manner. LTX-2 consists of an asymmetric dual-stream transformer with a 14B-parameter video stream and a 5B-parameter audio stream, coupled through bidirectional audio-video cross-attention layers with temporal positional embeddings and cross-modality AdaLN for shared timestep conditioning. This architecture enables efficient training and inference of a unified audiovisual model while allocating more capacity for video generation than audio generation. We employ a multilingual text encoder for broader prompt understanding and introduce a modality-aware classifier-free guidance (modality-CFG) mechanism for improved audiovisual alignment and controllability. Beyond generating speech, LTX-2 produces rich, coherent audio tracks that follow the characters, environment, style, and emotion of each scene -- complete with natural background and foley elements. In our evaluations, the model achieves state-of-the-art audiovisual quality and prompt adherence among open-source systems, while delivering results comparable to proprietary models at a fraction of their computational cost and inference time. All model weights and code are publicly released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03233</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 18:24:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAGMA: A Multi-Graph based Agentic Memory Architecture for AI Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03236</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03236.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dongming Jiang, Yi Li, Guanpeng Li, Bingzhe Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Memory-Augmented Generation (MAG) extends Large Language Models with external memory to support long-context reasoning, but existing approaches largely rely on semantic similarity over monolithic memory stores, entangling temporal, causal, and entity information. This design limits interpretability and alignment between query intent and retrieved evidence, leading to suboptimal reasoning accuracy. In this paper, we propose MAGMA, a multi-graph agentic memory architecture that represents each memory item across orthogonal semantic, temporal, causal, and entity graphs. MAGMA formulates retrieval as policy-guided traversal over these relational views, enabling query-adaptive selection and structured context construction. By decoupling memory representation from retrieval logic, MAGMA provides transparent reasoning paths and fine-grained control over retrieval. Experiments on LoCoMo and LongMemEval demonstrate that MAGMA consistently outperforms state-of-the-art agentic memory systems in long-horizon reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03236</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 18:29:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfiniDepth: Arbitrary-Resolution and Fine-Grained Depth Estimation with Neural Implicit Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03252</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03252.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Yu, Haotong Lin, Jiawei Wang, Jiaxin Li, Yida Wang, Xueyang Zhang, Yue Wang, Xiaowei Zhou, Ruizhen Hu, Sida Peng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 94&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing depth estimation methods are fundamentally limited to predicting depth on discrete image grids. Such representations restrict their scalability to arbitrary output resolutions and hinder the geometric detail recovery. This paper introduces InfiniDepth, which represents depth as neural implicit fields. Through a simple yet effective local implicit decoder, we can query depth at continuous 2D coordinates, enabling arbitrary-resolution and fine-grained depth estimation. To better assess our method's capabilities, we curate a high-quality 4K synthetic benchmark from five different games, spanning diverse scenes with rich geometric and appearance details. Extensive experiments demonstrate that InfiniDepth achieves state-of-the-art performance on both synthetic and real-world benchmarks across relative and metric depth estimation tasks, particularly excelling in fine-detail regions. It also benefits the task of novel view synthesis under large viewpoint shifts, producing high-quality results with fewer holes and artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03252</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 18:57:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muses: Designing, Composing, Generating Nonexistent Fantasy 3D Creatures without Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03256</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03256.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hexiao Lu, Xiaokun Sun, Zeyu Cai, Hao Guo, Ying Tai, Jian Yang, Zhenyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Muses, the first training-free method for fantastic 3D creature generation in a feed-forward paradigm. Previous methods, which rely on part-aware optimization, manual assembly, or 2D image generation, often produce unrealistic or incoherent 3D assets due to the challenges of intricate part-level manipulation and limited out-of-domain generation. In contrast, Muses leverages the 3D skeleton, a fundamental representation of biological forms, to explicitly and rationally compose diverse elements. This skeletal foundation formalizes 3D content creation as a structure-aware pipeline of design, composition, and generation. Muses begins by constructing a creatively composed 3D skeleton with coherent layout and scale through graph-constrained reasoning. This skeleton then guides a voxel-based assembly process within a structured latent space, integrating regions from different objects. Finally, image-guided appearance modeling under skeletal conditions is applied to generate a style-consistent and harmonious texture for the assembled shape. Extensive experiments establish Muses' state-of-the-art performance in terms of visual fidelity and alignment with textual descriptions, and potential on flexible 3D object editing. Project page: https://luhexiao.github.io/Muses.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03256</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guardians of the Hair: Rescuing Soft Boundaries in Depth, Stereo, and Novel Views</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03362</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03362.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiang Zhang, Yang Zhang, Lukas Mehl, Markus Gross, Christopher Schroers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Soft boundaries, like thin hairs, are commonly observed in natural and computer-generated imagery, but they remain challenging for 3D vision due to the ambiguous mixing of foreground and background cues. This paper introduces Guardians of the Hair (HairGuard), a framework designed to recover fine-grained soft boundary details in 3D vision tasks. Specifically, we first propose a novel data curation pipeline that leverages image matting datasets for training and design a depth fixer network to automatically identify soft boundary regions. With a gated residual module, the depth fixer refines depth precisely around soft boundaries while maintaining global depth quality, allowing plug-and-play integration with state-of-the-art depth models. For view synthesis, we perform depth-based forward warping to retain high-fidelity textures, followed by a generative scene painter that fills disoccluded regions and eliminates redundant background artifacts within soft boundaries. Finally, a color fuser adaptively combines warped and inpainted results to produce novel views with consistent geometry and fine-grained details. Extensive experiments demonstrate that HairGuard achieves state-of-the-art performance across monocular depth estimation, stereo image/video conversion, and novel view synthesis, with significant improvements in soft boundary regions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03362</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 19:02:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Illusion of Specialization: Unveiling the Domain-Invariant "Standing Committee" in Mixture-of-Experts Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03425</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03425.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yan Wang, Yitao Xu, Nanhan Shen, Jinyan Su, Jimin Huang, Zining Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Mixture of Experts models are widely assumed to achieve domain specialization through sparse routing. In this work, we question this assumption by introducing COMMITTEEAUDIT, a post hoc framework that analyzes routing behavior at the level of expert groups rather than individual experts. Across three representative models and the MMLU benchmark, we uncover a domain-invariant Standing Committee. This is a compact coalition of routed experts that consistently captures the majority of routing mass across domains, layers, and routing budgets, even when architectures already include shared experts. Qualitative analysis further shows that Standing Committees anchor reasoning structure and syntax, while peripheral experts handle domain-specific knowledge. These findings reveal a strong structural bias toward centralized computation, suggesting that specialization in Mixture of Experts models is far less pervasive than commonly believed. This inherent bias also indicates that current training objectives, such as load-balancing losses that enforce uniform expert utilization, may be working against the model's natural optimization path, thereby limiting training efficiency and performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03425</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 21:29:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Linguistic Competence of Language Models through Pre-training with Language Learning Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03448</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03448.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Atsuki Yamaguchi, Maggie Mi, Nikolaos Aletras&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language models (LMs) are pre-trained on raw text datasets to generate text sequences token-by-token. While this approach facilitates the learning of world knowledge and reasoning, it does not explicitly optimize for linguistic competence. To bridge this gap, we propose L2T, a pre-training framework integrating Language Learning Tasks alongside standard next-token prediction. Inspired by human language acquisition, L2T transforms raw text into structured input-output pairs to provide explicit linguistic stimulation. Pre-training LMs on a mixture of raw text and L2T data not only improves overall performance on linguistic competence benchmarks but accelerates its acquisition, while maintaining competitive performance on general reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03448</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 22:28:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ThinkRL-Edit: Thinking in Reinforcement Learning for Reasoning-Centric Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03467</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03467.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hengjia Li, Liming Jiang, Qing Yan, Yizhi Song, Hao Kang, Zichuan Liu, Xin Lu, Boxi Wu, Deng Cai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-driven image editing with unified multimodal generative models has advanced rapidly, yet their underlying visual reasoning remains limited, leading to suboptimal performance on reasoning-centric edits. Reinforcement learning (RL) has been investigated for improving the quality of image editing, but it faces three key challenges: (1) limited reasoning exploration confined to denoising stochasticity, (2) biased reward fusion, and (3) unstable VLM-based instruction rewards. In this work, we propose ThinkRL-Edit, a reasoning-centric RL framework that decouples visual reasoning from image synthesis and expands reasoning exploration beyond denoising. To the end, we introduce Chain-of-Thought (CoT)-based reasoning sampling with planning and reflection stages prior to generation in online sampling, compelling the model to explore multiple semantic hypotheses and validate their plausibility before committing to a visual outcome. To avoid the failures of weighted aggregation, we propose an unbiased chain preference grouping strategy across multiple reward dimensions. Moreover, we replace interval-based VLM scores with a binary checklist, yielding more precise, lower-variance, and interpretable rewards for complex reasoning. Experiments show our method significantly outperforms prior work on reasoning-centric image editing, producing instruction-faithful, visually coherent, and semantically grounded edits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03467</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 23:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EpiQAL: Benchmarking Large Language Models in Epidemiological Question Answering for Enhanced Alignment and Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03471</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03471.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingyang Wei, Dehai Min, Zewen Liu, Yuzhang Xie, Guanchen Wu, Carl Yang, Max S. Y. Lau, Qi He, Lu Cheng, Wei Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reliable epidemiological reasoning requires synthesizing study evidence to infer disease burden, transmission dynamics, and intervention effects at the population level. Existing medical question answering benchmarks primarily emphasize clinical knowledge or patient-level reasoning, yet few systematically evaluate evidence-grounded epidemiological inference. We present EpiQAL, the first diagnostic benchmark for epidemiological question answering across diverse diseases, comprising three subsets built from open-access literature. The subsets respectively evaluate text-grounded factual recall, multi-step inference linking document evidence with epidemiological principles, and conclusion reconstruction with the Discussion section withheld. Construction combines expert-designed taxonomy guidance, multi-model verification, and retrieval-based difficulty control. Experiments on ten open models reveal that current LLMs show limited performance on epidemiological reasoning, with multi-step inference posing the greatest challenge. Model rankings shift across subsets, and scale alone does not predict success. Chain-of-Thought prompting benefits multi-step inference but yields mixed results elsewhere. EpiQAL provides fine-grained diagnostic signals for evidence grounding, inferential reasoning, and conclusion reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03471</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 23:49:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolving Programmatic Skill Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03509</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03509.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haochen Shi, Xingdi Yuan, Bang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 71&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We study continual skill acquisition in open-ended embodied environments where an agent must construct, refine, and reuse an expanding library of executable skills. We introduce the Programmatic Skill Network (PSN), a framework in which skills are executable symbolic programs forming a compositional network that evolves through experience. PSN defines three core mechanisms instantiated via large language models: (1)REFLECT for structured fault localization over skill compositions, (2) progressive optimization with maturity-aware update gating that stabilizes reliable skills while maintaining plasticity for uncertain ones, and (3) canonical structural refactoring under rollback validation that maintains network compactness. We further show that PSN's learning dynamics exhibit structural parallels to neural network training. Experiments on MineDojo and Crafter demonstrate robust skill reuse, rapid adaptation, and strong generalization across open-ended task distributions.\footnote{We plan to open-source the code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03509</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 01:43:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiffCoT: Diffusion-styled Chain-of-Thought Reasoning in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03559</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03559.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shidong Cao, Hongzhan Lin, Yuxuan Gu, Ziyang Luo, Jing Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning improves multi-step mathematical problem solving in large language models but remains vulnerable to exposure bias and error accumulation, as early mistakes propagate irreversibly through autoregressive decoding. In this work, we propose DiffCoT, a diffusion-styled CoT framework that reformulates CoT reasoning as an iterative denoising process. DiffCoT integrates diffusion principles at the reasoning-step level via a sliding-window mechanism, enabling unified generation and retrospective correction of intermediate steps while preserving token-level autoregression. To maintain causal consistency, we further introduce a causal diffusion noise schedule that respects the temporal structure of reasoning chains. Extensive experiments on three multi-step CoT reasoning benchmarks across diverse model backbones demonstrate that DiffCoT consistently outperforms existing CoT preference optimization methods, yielding improved robustness and error-correction capability in CoT reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03559</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 03:58:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RedBench: A Universal Dataset for Comprehensive Red Teaming of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03699</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03699.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Quy-Anh Dang, Chris Ngo, Truong-Son Hy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As large language models (LLMs) become integral to safety-critical applications, ensuring their robustness against adversarial prompts is paramount. However, existing red teaming datasets suffer from inconsistent risk categorizations, limited domain coverage, and outdated evaluations, hindering systematic vulnerability assessments. To address these challenges, we introduce RedBench, a universal dataset aggregating 37 benchmark datasets from leading conferences and repositories, comprising 29,362 samples across attack and refusal prompts. RedBench employs a standardized taxonomy with 22 risk categories and 19 domains, enabling consistent and comprehensive evaluations of LLM vulnerabilities. We provide a detailed analysis of existing datasets, establish baselines for modern LLMs, and open-source the dataset and evaluation code. Our contributions facilitate robust comparisons, foster future research, and promote the development of secure and reliable LLMs for real-world deployment. Code: https://github.com/knoveleng/redeval&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03699</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 08:34:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ROI-Reasoning: Rational Optimization for Inference via Pre-Computation Meta-Cognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03822</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03822.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muyang Zhao, Qi Qi, Hao Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) can achieve strong reasoning performance with sufficient computation, but they do not inherently know how much computation a task requires. We study budgeted inference-time reasoning for multiple tasks under a strict global token constraint and formalize it as a Ordered Stochastic Multiple-Choice Knapsack Problem(OS-MCKP). This perspective highlights a meta-cognitive requirement -- anticipating task difficulty, estimating return over investment (ROI), and allocating computation strategically. We propose ROI-Reasoning, a two-stage framework that endows LLMs with intrinsic, budget-aware rationality. In the first stage, Meta-Cognitive Fine-Tuning teaches models to predict reasoning cost and expected utility before generation, enabling explicit solve-or-skip decisions. Next, Rationality-Aware Reinforcement Learning optimizes sequential decision making under a hard token budget, allowing models to learn long-horizon allocation strategies. Across budgeted mathematical reasoning benchmarks, ROI-Reasoning consistently improves overall score while substantially reducing regret under tight computation budgets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03822</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 11:30:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atlas: Orchestrating Heterogeneous Models and Tools for Multi-Domain Complex Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03872</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03872.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinyang Wu, Guocheng Zhai, Ruihan Jin, Jiahao Yuan, Yuhao Shen, Shuai Zhang, Zhengqi Wen, Jianhua Tao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The integration of large language models (LLMs) with external tools has significantly expanded the capabilities of AI agents. However, as the diversity of both LLMs and tools increases, selecting the optimal model-tool combination becomes a high-dimensional optimization challenge. Existing approaches often rely on a single model or fixed tool-calling logic, failing to exploit the performance variations across heterogeneous model-tool pairs. In this paper, we present ATLAS (Adaptive Tool-LLM Alignment and Synergistic Invocation), a dual-path framework for dynamic tool usage in cross-domain complex reasoning. ATLAS operates via a dual-path approach: (1) training-free cluster-based routing that exploits empirical priors for domain-specific alignment, and (2) RL-based multi-step routing that explores autonomous trajectories for out-of-distribution generalization. Extensive experiments across 15 benchmarks demonstrate that our method outperforms closed-source models like GPT-4o, surpassing existing routing methods on both in-distribution (+10.1%) and out-of-distribution (+13.1%) tasks. Furthermore, our framework shows significant gains in visual reasoning by orchestrating specialized multi-modal tools.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03872</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 12:38:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ResTok: Learning Hierarchical Residuals in 1D Visual Tokenizers for Autoregressive Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03955</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03955.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xu Zhang, Cheng Da, Huan Yang, Kun Gai, Ming Lu, Zhan Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing 1D visual tokenizers for autoregressive (AR) generation largely follow the design principles of language modeling, as they are built directly upon transformers whose priors originate in language, yielding single-hierarchy latent tokens and treating visual data as flat sequential token streams. However, this language-like formulation overlooks key properties of vision, particularly the hierarchical and residual network designs that have long been essential for convergence and efficiency in visual models. To bring "vision" back to vision, we propose the Residual Tokenizer (ResTok), a 1D visual tokenizer that builds hierarchical residuals for both image tokens and latent tokens. The hierarchical representations obtained through progressively merging enable cross-level feature fusion at each layer, substantially enhancing representational capacity. Meanwhile, the semantic residuals between hierarchies prevent information overlap, yielding more concentrated latent distributions that are easier for AR modeling. Cross-level bindings consequently emerge without any explicit constraints. To accelerate the generation process, we further introduce a hierarchical AR generator that substantially reduces sampling steps by predicting an entire level of latent tokens at once rather than generating them strictly token-by-token. Extensive experiments demonstrate that restoring hierarchical residual priors in visual tokenization significantly improves AR image generation, achieving a gFID of 2.34 on ImageNet-256 with only 9 sampling steps. Code is available at https://github.com/Kwai-Kolors/ResTok.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03955</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 14:09:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmark^2: Systematic Evaluation of LLM Benchmarks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03986</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.03986.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qi Qian, Chengsong Huang, Jingwen Xu, Changze Lv, Muling Wu, Wenhao Liu, Xiaohua Wang, Zhenghua Wang, Zisu Huang, Muzhao Tian, Jianhan Xu, Kun Hu, He-Da Wang, Yao Hu, Xuanjing Huang, Xiaoqing Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid proliferation of benchmarks for evaluating large language models (LLMs) has created an urgent need for systematic methods to assess benchmark quality itself. We propose Benchmark^2, a comprehensive framework comprising three complementary metrics: (1) Cross-Benchmark Ranking Consistency, measuring whether a benchmark produces model rankings aligned with peer benchmarks; (2) Discriminability Score, quantifying a benchmark's ability to differentiate between models; and (3) Capability Alignment Deviation, identifying problematic instances where stronger models fail but weaker models succeed within the same model family. We conduct extensive experiments across 15 benchmarks spanning mathematics, reasoning, and knowledge domains, evaluating 11 LLMs across four model families. Our analysis reveals significant quality variations among existing benchmarks and demonstrates that selective benchmark construction based on our metrics can achieve comparable evaluation performance with substantially reduced test sets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03986</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 14:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Klear: Unified Multi-Task Audio-Video Joint Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04151</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04151.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jun Wang, Chunyu Qiang, Yuxin Guo, Yiran Wang, Xijuan Zeng, Chen Zhang, Pengfei Wan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Audio-video joint generation has progressed rapidly, yet substantial challenges still remain. Non-commercial approaches still suffer audio-visual asynchrony, poor lip-speech alignment, and unimodal degradation, which can be stemmed from weak audio-visual correspondence modeling, limited generalization, and scarce high-quality dense-caption data. To address these issues, we introduce Klear and delve into three axes--model architecture, training strategy, and data curation. Architecturally, we adopt a single-tower design with unified DiT blocks and an Omni-Full Attention mechanism, achieving tight audio-visual alignment and strong scalability. Training-wise, we adopt a progressive multitask regime--random modality masking to joint optimization across tasks, and a multistage curriculum, yielding robust representations, strengthening A-V aligned world knowledge, and preventing unimodal collapse. For datasets, we present the first large-scale audio-video dataset with dense captions, and introduce a novel automated data-construction pipeline which annotates and filters millions of diverse, high-quality, strictly aligned audio-video-caption triplets. Building on this, Klear scales to large datasets, delivering high-fidelity, semantically and temporally aligned, instruction-following generation in both joint and unimodal settings while generalizing robustly to out-of-distribution scenarios. Across tasks, it substantially outperforms prior methods by a large margin and achieves performance comparable to Veo 3, offering a unified, scalable path toward next-generation audio-video synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04151</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Binary Preference: Aligning Diffusion Models to Fine-grained Criteria by Decoupling Attributes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04300</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04300.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenye Meng, Zejian Li, Zhongni Liu, Yize Li, Changle Xie, Kaixin Jia, Ling Yang, Huanghuang Deng, Shiying Ding, Shengyuan Zhang, Jiayi Li, Lingyun Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Post-training alignment of diffusion models relies on simplified signals, such as scalar rewards or binary preferences. This limits alignment with complex human expertise, which is hierarchical and fine-grained. To address this, we first construct a hierarchical, fine-grained evaluation criteria with domain experts, which decomposes image quality into multiple positive and negative attributes organized in a tree structure. Building on this, we propose a two-stage alignment framework. First, we inject domain knowledge to an auxiliary diffusion model via Supervised Fine-Tuning. Second, we introduce Complex Preference Optimization (CPO) that extends DPO to align the target diffusion to our non-binary, hierarchical criteria. Specifically, we reformulate the alignment problem to simultaneously maximize the probability of positive attributes while minimizing the probability of negative attributes with the auxiliary diffusion. We instantiate our approach in the domain of painting generation and conduct CPO training with an annotated dataset of painting with fine-grained attributes based on our criteria. Extensive experiments demonstrate that CPO significantly enhances generation quality and alignment with expertise, opening new avenues for fine-grained criteria alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04300</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:11:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agentic Rubrics as Contextual Verifiers for SWE Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04171</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04171.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohit Raghavendra, Anisha Gunjal, Bing Liu, Yunzhong He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Verification is critical for improving agents: it provides the reward signal for Reinforcement Learning and enables inference-time gains through Test-Time Scaling (TTS). Despite its importance, verification in software engineering (SWE) agent settings often relies on code execution, which can be difficult to scale due to environment setup overhead. Scalable alternatives such as patch classifiers and heuristic methods exist, but they are less grounded in codebase context and harder to interpret. To this end, we explore Agentic Rubrics: an expert agent interacts with the repository to create a context-grounded rubric checklist, and candidate patches are then scored against it without requiring test execution. On SWE-Bench Verified under parallel TTS evaluation, Agentic Rubrics achieve a score of 54.2% on Qwen3-Coder-30B-A3B and 40.6% on Qwen3-32B, with at least a +3.5 percentage-point gain over the strongest baseline in our comparison set. We further analyze rubric behavior, showing that rubric scores are consistent with ground-truth tests while also flagging issues that tests do not capture. Our ablations show that agentic context gathering is essential for producing codebase-specific, unambiguous criteria. Together, these results suggest that Agentic Rubrics provide an efficient, scalable, and granular verification signal for SWE agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04171</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:38:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Choreographing a World of Dynamic Objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04194</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04194.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanzhe Lyu, Chen Geng, Karthik Dharmarajan, Yunzhi Zhang, Hadi Alzayer, Shangzhe Wu, Jiajun Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Dynamic objects in our physical 4D (3D + time) world are constantly evolving, deforming, and interacting with other objects, leading to diverse 4D scene dynamics. In this paper, we present a universal generative pipeline, CHORD, for CHOReographing Dynamic objects and scenes and synthesizing this type of phenomena. Traditional rule-based graphics pipelines to create these dynamics are based on category-specific heuristics, yet are labor-intensive and not scalable. Recent learning-based methods typically demand large-scale datasets, which may not cover all object categories in interest. Our approach instead inherits the universality from the video generative models by proposing a distillation-based pipeline to extract the rich Lagrangian motion information hidden in the Eulerian representations of 2D videos. Our method is universal, versatile, and category-agnostic. We demonstrate its effectiveness by conducting experiments to generate a diverse range of multi-body 4D dynamics, show its advantage compared to existing methods, and demonstrate its applicability in generating robotics manipulation policies. Project page: https://yanzhelyu.github.io/chord&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04194</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:59:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReHyAt: Recurrent Hybrid Attention for Video Diffusion Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04342</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04342.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohsen Ghafoorian, Amirhossein Habibian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in video diffusion models have shifted towards transformer-based architectures, achieving state-of-the-art video generation but at the cost of quadratic attention complexity, which severely limits scalability for longer sequences. We introduce ReHyAt, a Recurrent Hybrid Attention mechanism that combines the fidelity of softmax attention with the efficiency of linear attention, enabling chunk-wise recurrent reformulation and constant memory usage. Unlike the concurrent linear-only SANA Video, ReHyAt's hybrid design allows efficient distillation from existing softmax-based models, reducing the training cost by two orders of magnitude to ~160 GPU hours, while being competitive in the quality. Our light-weight distillation and finetuning pipeline provides a recipe that can be applied to future state-of-the-art bidirectional softmax-based models. Experiments on VBench and VBench-2.0, as well as a human preference study, demonstrate that ReHyAt achieves state-of-the-art video quality while reducing attention cost from quadratic to linear, unlocking practical scalability for long-duration and on-device video generation. Project page is available at https://qualcomm-ai-research.github.io/rehyat.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04342</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 19:26:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Behavior Cloning Improves Causal Reasoning: An Open Model for Real-Time Video Game Playing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04575</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04575.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuguang Yue, Irakli Salia, Samuel Hunt, Chris Green, Wenzhe Shi, Jonathan J Hunt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Behavior cloning is enjoying a resurgence in popularity as scaling both model and data sizes proves to provide a strong starting point for many tasks of interest. In this work, we introduce an open recipe for training a video game playing foundation model designed for inference in realtime on a consumer GPU. We release all data (8300+ hours of high quality human gameplay), training and inference code, and pretrained checkpoints under an open license. We show that our best model is capable of playing a variety of 3D video games at a level competitive with human play. We use this recipe to systematically examine the scaling laws of behavior cloning to understand how the model's performance and causal reasoning varies with model and data scale. We first show in a simple toy problem that, for some types of causal reasoning, increasing both the amount of training data and the depth of the network results in the model learning a more causal policy. We then systematically study how causality varies with the number of parameters (and depth) and training steps in scaled models of up to 1.2 billion parameters, and we find similar scaling results to what we observe in the toy problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04575</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 04:06:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AgentDevel: Reframing Self-Evolving LLM Agents as Release Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04620</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04620.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Di Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in large language model (LLM) agents has largely focused on embedding self-improvement mechanisms inside the agent or searching over many concurrent variants. While these approaches can raise aggregate scores, they often yield unstable and hard-to-audit improvement trajectories, making it difficult to guarantee non-regression or to reason about failures across versions. We reframe agent improvement as release engineering: agents are treated as shippable artifacts, and improvement is externalized into a regression-aware release pipeline. We introduce AgentDevel, a release engineering pipeline that iteratively runs the current agent, produces implementation-blind, symptom-level quality signals from execution traces, synthesizes a single release candidate (RC) via executable diagnosis, and promotes it under flip-centered gating. AgentDevel features three core designs: (i) an implementation-blind LLM critic that characterizes failure appearances without accessing agent internals, (ii) script-based executable diagnosis that aggregates dominant symptom patterns and produces auditable engineering specifications, and (iii) flip-centered gating that prioritizes pass to fail regressions and fail to pass fixes as first-class evidence. Unlike population-based search or in-agent self-refinement, AgentDevel maintains a single canonical version line and emphasizes non-regression as a primary objective. Experiments on execution-heavy benchmarks demonstrate that AgentDevel yields stable improvements with significantly fewer regressions while producing reproducible, auditable artifacts. Overall, AgentDevel provides a practical development discipline for building, debugging, and releasing LLM agents as software development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04620</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 05:49:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ProFuse: Efficient Cross-View Context Fusion for Open-Vocabulary 3D Gaussian Splatting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04754</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04754.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yen-Jen Chiou, Wei-Tse Cheng, Yuan-Fu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present ProFuse, an efficient context-aware framework for open-vocabulary 3D scene understanding with 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS). The pipeline enhances cross-view consistency and intra-mask cohesion within a direct registration setup, adding minimal overhead and requiring no render-supervised fine-tuning. Instead of relying on a pretrained 3DGS scene, we introduce a dense correspondence-guided pre-registration phase that initializes Gaussians with accurate geometry while jointly constructing 3D Context Proposals via cross-view clustering. Each proposal carries a global feature obtained through weighted aggregation of member embeddings, and this feature is fused onto Gaussians during direct registration to maintain per-primitive language coherence across views. With associations established in advance, semantic fusion requires no additional optimization beyond standard reconstruction, and the model retains geometric refinement without densification. ProFuse achieves strong open-vocabulary 3DGS understanding while completing semantic attachment in about five minutes per scene, which is two times faster than SOTA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04754</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 09:20:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AT^2PO: Agentic Turn-based Policy Optimization via Tree Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04767</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04767.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zefang Zong, Dingwei Chen, Yang Li, Qi Yi, Bo Zhou, Chengming Li, Bo Qian, Peng Chen, Jie Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM agents have emerged as powerful systems for tackling multi-turn tasks by interleaving internal reasoning and external tool interactions. Agentic Reinforcement Learning has recently drawn significant research attention as a critical post-training paradigm to further refine these capabilities. In this paper, we present AT^2PO (Agentic Turn-based Policy Optimization via Tree Search), a unified framework for multi-turn agentic RL that addresses three core challenges: limited exploration diversity, sparse credit assignment, and misaligned policy optimization. AT^2PO introduces a turn-level tree structure that jointly enables Entropy-Guided Tree Expansion for strategic exploration and Turn-wise Credit Assignment for fine-grained reward propagation from sparse outcomes. Complementing this, we propose Agentic Turn-based Policy Optimization, a turn-level learning objective that aligns policy updates with the natural decision granularity of agentic interactions. ATPO is orthogonal to tree search and can be readily integrated into any multi-turn RL pipeline. Experiments across seven benchmarks demonstrate consistent improvements over the state-of-the-art baseline by up to 1.84 percentage points in average, with ablation studies validating the effectiveness of each component. Our code is available at https://github.com/zzfoutofspace/ATPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04767</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 09:35:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PyramidalWan: On Making Pretrained Video Model Pyramidal for Efficient Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04792</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04792.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Denis Korzhenkov, Adil Karjauv, Animesh Karnewar, Mohsen Ghafoorian, Amirhossein Habibian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently proposed pyramidal models decompose the conventional forward and backward diffusion processes into multiple stages operating at varying resolutions. These models handle inputs with higher noise levels at lower resolutions, while less noisy inputs are processed at higher resolutions. This hierarchical approach significantly reduces the computational cost of inference in multi-step denoising models. However, existing open-source pyramidal video models have been trained from scratch and tend to underperform compared to state-of-the-art systems in terms of visual plausibility. In this work, we present a pipeline that converts a pretrained diffusion model into a pyramidal one through low-cost finetuning, achieving this transformation without degradation in quality of output videos. Furthermore, we investigate and compare various strategies for step distillation within pyramidal models, aiming to further enhance the inference efficiency. Our results are available at https://qualcomm-ai-research.github.io/PyramidalWan.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04792</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 10:16:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learnable Multipliers: Freeing the Scale of Language Model Matrix Layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04890</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.04890.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Maksim Velikanov, Ilyas Chahed, Jingwei Zuo, Dhia Eddine Rhaiem, Younes Belkada, Hakim Hacid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Applying weight decay (WD) to matrix layers is standard practice in large-language-model pretraining. Prior work suggests that stochastic gradient noise induces a Brownian-like expansion of the weight matrices W, whose growth is counteracted by WD, leading to a WD-noise equilibrium with a certain weight norm ||W||. In this work, we view the equilibrium norm as a harmful artifact of the training procedure, and address it by introducing learnable multipliers to learn the optimal scale. First, we attach a learnable scalar multiplier to W and confirm that the WD-noise equilibrium norm is suboptimal: the learned scale adapts to data and improves performance. We then argue that individual row and column norms are similarly constrained, and free their scale by introducing learnable per-row and per-column multipliers. Our method can be viewed as a learnable, more expressive generalization of muP multipliers. It outperforms a well-tuned muP baseline, reduces the computational overhead of multiplier tuning, and surfaces practical questions such as forward-pass symmetries and the width-scaling of the learned multipliers. Finally, we validate learnable multipliers with both Adam and Muon optimizers, where it shows improvement in downstream evaluations matching the improvement of the switching from Adam to Muon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04890</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 12:41:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Token-Level LLM Collaboration via FusionRoute</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nuoya Xiong, Yuhang Zhou, Hanqing Zeng, Zhaorun Chen, Furong Huang, Shuchao Bi, Lizhu Zhang, Zhuokai Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) exhibit strengths across diverse domains. However, achieving strong performance across these domains with a single general-purpose model typically requires scaling to sizes that are prohibitively expensive to train and deploy. On the other hand, while smaller domain-specialized models are much more efficient, they struggle to generalize beyond their training distributions. To address this dilemma, we propose FusionRoute, a robust and effective token-level multi-LLM collaboration framework in which a lightweight router simultaneously (i) selects the most suitable expert at each decoding step and (ii) contributes a complementary logit that refines or corrects the selected expert's next-token distribution via logit addition. Unlike existing token-level collaboration methods that rely solely on fixed expert outputs, we provide a theoretical analysis showing that pure expert-only routing is fundamentally limited: unless strong global coverage assumptions hold, it cannot in general realize the optimal decoding policy. By augmenting expert selection with a trainable complementary generator, FusionRoute expands the effective policy class and enables recovery of optimal value functions under mild conditions. Empirically, across both Llama-3 and Gemma-2 families and diverse benchmarks spanning mathematical reasoning, code generation, and instruction following, FusionRoute outperforms both sequence- and token-level collaboration, model merging, and direct fine-tuning, while remaining competitive with domain experts on their respective tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05106</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 16:53:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent-as-a-Judge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05111</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05111.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runyang You, Hongru Cai, Caiqi Zhang, Qiancheng Xu, Meng Liu, Tiezheng Yu, Yongqi Li, Wenjie Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM-as-a-Judge has revolutionized AI evaluation by leveraging large language models for scalable assessments. However, as evaluands become increasingly complex, specialized, and multi-step, the reliability of LLM-as-a-Judge has become constrained by inherent biases, shallow single-pass reasoning, and the inability to verify assessments against real-world observations. This has catalyzed the transition to Agent-as-a-Judge, where agentic judges employ planning, tool-augmented verification, multi-agent collaboration, and persistent memory to enable more robust, verifiable, and nuanced evaluations. Despite the rapid proliferation of agentic evaluation systems, the field lacks a unified framework to navigate this shifting landscape. To bridge this gap, we present the first comprehensive survey tracing this evolution. Specifically, we identify key dimensions that characterize this paradigm shift and establish a developmental taxonomy. We organize core methodologies and survey applications across general and professional domains. Furthermore, we analyze frontier challenges and identify promising research directions, ultimately providing a clear roadmap for the next generation of agentic evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05111</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 16:58:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re-Align: Structured Reasoning-guided Alignment for In-Context Image Generation and Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05124</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05124.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runze He, Yiji Cheng, Tiankai Hang, Zhimin Li, Yu Xu, Zijin Yin, Shiyi Zhang, Wenxun Dai, Penghui Du, Ao Ma, Chunyu Wang, Qinglin Lu, Jizhong Han, Jiao Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In-context image generation and editing (ICGE) enables users to specify visual concepts through interleaved image-text prompts, demanding precise understanding and faithful execution of user intent. Although recent unified multimodal models exhibit promising understanding capabilities, these strengths often fail to transfer effectively to image generation. We introduce Re-Align, a unified framework that bridges the gap between understanding and generation through structured reasoning-guided alignment. At its core lies the In-Context Chain-of-Thought (IC-CoT), a structured reasoning paradigm that decouples semantic guidance and reference association, providing clear textual target and mitigating confusion among reference images. Furthermore, Re-Align introduces an effective RL training scheme that leverages a surrogate reward to measure the alignment between structured reasoning text and the generated image, thereby improving the model's overall performance on ICGE tasks. Extensive experiments verify that Re-Align outperforms competitive methods of comparable model scale and resources on both in-context image generation and editing tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05124</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VerseCrafter: Dynamic Realistic Video World Model with 4D Geometric Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05138</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05138.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sixiao Zheng, Minghao Yin, Wenbo Hu, Xiaoyu Li, Ying Shan, Yanwei Fu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video world models aim to simulate dynamic, real-world environments, yet existing methods struggle to provide unified and precise control over camera and multi-object motion, as videos inherently operate dynamics in the projected 2D image plane. To bridge this gap, we introduce VerseCrafter, a 4D-aware video world model that enables explicit and coherent control over both camera and object dynamics within a unified 4D geometric world state. Our approach is centered on a novel 4D Geometric Control representation, which encodes the world state through a static background point cloud and per-object 3D Gaussian trajectories. This representation captures not only an object's path but also its probabilistic 3D occupancy over time, offering a flexible, category-agnostic alternative to rigid bounding boxes or parametric models. These 4D controls are rendered into conditioning signals for a pretrained video diffusion model, enabling the generation of high-fidelity, view-consistent videos that precisely adhere to the specified dynamics. Unfortunately, another major challenge lies in the scarcity of large-scale training data with explicit 4D annotations. We address this by developing an automatic data engine that extracts the required 4D controls from in-the-wild videos, allowing us to train our model on a massive and diverse dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05138</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:28:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Scale Local Speculative Decoding for Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05149</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05149.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Elia Peruzzo, Guillaume Sautière, Amirhossein Habibian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive (AR) models have achieved remarkable success in image synthesis, yet their sequential nature imposes significant latency constraints. Speculative Decoding offers a promising avenue for acceleration, but existing approaches are limited by token-level ambiguity and lack of spatial awareness. In this work, we introduce Multi-Scale Local Speculative Decoding (MuLo-SD), a novel framework that combines multi-resolution drafting with spatially informed verification to accelerate AR image generation. Our method leverages a low-resolution drafter paired with learned up-samplers to propose candidate image tokens, which are then verified in parallel by a high-resolution target model. Crucially, we incorporate a local rejection and resampling mechanism, enabling efficient correction of draft errors by focusing on spatial neighborhoods rather than raster-scan resampling after the first rejection. We demonstrate that MuLo-SD achieves substantial speedups - up to 1.7times - outperforming strong speculative decoding baselines such as EAGLE-2 and LANTERN in terms of acceleration, while maintaining comparable semantic alignment and perceptual quality. These results are validated using GenEval, DPG-Bench, and FID/HPSv2 on the MS-COCO 5k validation split. Extensive ablations highlight the impact of up-sampling design, probability pooling, and local rejection and resampling with neighborhood expansion. Our approach sets a new state-of-the-art in speculative decoding for image synthesis, bridging the gap between efficiency and fidelity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05149</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:39:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DocDancer: Towards Agentic Document-Grounded Information Seeking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05163</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05163.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qintong Zhang, Xinjie Lv, Jialong Wu, Baixuan Li, Zhengwei Tao, Guochen Yan, Huanyao Zhang, Bin Wang, Jiahao Xu, Haitao Mi, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Document Question Answering (DocQA) focuses on answering questions grounded in given documents, yet existing DocQA agents lack effective tool utilization and largely rely on closed-source models. In this work, we introduce DocDancer, an end-to-end trained open-source Doc agent. We formulate DocQA as an information-seeking problem and propose a tool-driven agent framework that explicitly models document exploration and comprehension. To enable end-to-end training of such agents, we introduce an Exploration-then-Synthesis data synthesis pipeline that addresses the scarcity of high-quality training data for DocQA. Training on the synthesized data, the trained models on two long-context document understanding benchmarks, MMLongBench-Doc and DocBench, show their effectiveness. Further analysis provides valuable insights for the agentic tool design and synthetic data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05163</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:54:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RelayLLM: Efficient Reasoning via Collaborative Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05167</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05167.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chengsong Huang, Tong Zheng, Langlin Huang, Jinyuan Li, Haolin Liu, Jiaxin Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) for complex reasoning is often hindered by high computational costs and latency, while resource-efficient Small Language Models (SLMs) typically lack the necessary reasoning capacity. Existing collaborative approaches, such as cascading or routing, operate at a coarse granularity by offloading entire queries to LLMs, resulting in significant computational waste when the SLM is capable of handling the majority of reasoning steps. To address this, we propose RelayLLM, a novel framework for efficient reasoning via token-level collaborative decoding. Unlike routers, RelayLLM empowers the SLM to act as an active controller that dynamically invokes the LLM only for critical tokens via a special command, effectively "relaying" the generation process. We introduce a two-stage training framework, including warm-up and Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) to teach the model to balance independence with strategic help-seeking. Empirical results across six benchmarks demonstrate that RelayLLM achieves an average accuracy of 49.52%, effectively bridging the performance gap between the two models. Notably, this is achieved by invoking the LLM for only 1.07% of the total generated tokens, offering a 98.2% cost reduction compared to performance-matched random routers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05167</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:56:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoV: Chain-of-View Prompting for Spatial Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05172</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05172.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoyu Zhao, Akide Liu, Zeyu Zhang, Weijie Wang, Feng Chen, Ruihan Zhu, Gholamreza Haffari, Bohan Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Embodied question answering (EQA) in 3D environments often requires collecting context that is distributed across multiple viewpoints and partially occluded. However, most recent vision--language models (VLMs) are constrained to a fixed and finite set of input views, which limits their ability to acquire question-relevant context at inference time and hinders complex spatial reasoning. We propose Chain-of-View (CoV) prompting, a training-free, test-time reasoning framework that transforms a VLM into an active viewpoint reasoner through a coarse-to-fine exploration process. CoV first employs a View Selection agent to filter redundant frames and identify question-aligned anchor views. It then performs fine-grained view adjustment by interleaving iterative reasoning with discrete camera actions, obtaining new observations from the underlying 3D scene representation until sufficient context is gathered or a step budget is reached.   We evaluate CoV on OpenEQA across four mainstream VLMs and obtain an average +11.56\% improvement in LLM-Match, with a maximum gain of +13.62\% on Qwen3-VL-Flash. CoV further exhibits test-time scaling: increasing the minimum action budget yields an additional +2.51\% average improvement, peaking at +3.73\% on Gemini-2.5-Flash. On ScanQA and SQA3D, CoV delivers strong performance (e.g., 116 CIDEr / 31.9 EM@1 on ScanQA and 51.1 EM@1 on SQA3D). Overall, these results suggest that question-aligned view selection coupled with open-view search is an effective, model-agnostic strategy for improving spatial reasoning in 3D EQA without additional training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05172</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:59:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoAuto-R1: Video Auto Reasoning via Thinking Once, Answering Twice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05175</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05175.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuming Liu, Mingchen Zhuge, Changsheng Zhao, Jun Chen, Lemeng Wu, Zechun Liu, Chenchen Zhu, Zhipeng Cai, Chong Zhou, Haozhe Liu, Ernie Chang, Saksham Suri, Hongyu Xu, Qi Qian, Wei Wen, Balakrishnan Varadarajan, Zhuang Liu, Hu Xu, Florian Bordes, Raghuraman Krishnamoorthi, Bernard Ghanem, Vikas Chandra, Yunyang Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning has emerged as a powerful tool for multimodal large language models on video understanding tasks. However, its necessity and advantages over direct answering remain underexplored. In this paper, we first demonstrate that for RL-trained video models, direct answering often matches or even surpasses CoT performance, despite CoT producing step-by-step analyses at a higher computational cost. Motivated by this, we propose VideoAuto-R1, a video understanding framework that adopts a reason-when-necessary strategy. During training, our approach follows a Thinking Once, Answering Twice paradigm: the model first generates an initial answer, then performs reasoning, and finally outputs a reviewed answer. Both answers are supervised via verifiable rewards. During inference, the model uses the confidence score of the initial answer to determine whether to proceed with reasoning. Across video QA and grounding benchmarks, VideoAuto-R1 achieves state-of-the-art accuracy with significantly improved efficiency, reducing the average response length by ~3.3x, e.g., from 149 to just 44 tokens. Moreover, we observe a low rate of thinking-mode activation on perception-oriented tasks, but a higher rate on reasoning-intensive tasks. This suggests that explicit language-based reasoning is generally beneficial but not always necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05175</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 18:00:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plenoptic Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05239</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05239.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiao Fu, Shitao Tang, Min Shi, Xian Liu, Jinwei Gu, Ming-Yu Liu, Dahua Lin, Chen-Hsuan Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Camera-controlled generative video re-rendering methods, such as ReCamMaster, have achieved remarkable progress. However, despite their success in single-view setting, these works often struggle to maintain consistency across multi-view scenarios. Ensuring spatio-temporal coherence in hallucinated regions remains challenging due to the inherent stochasticity of generative models. To address it, we introduce PlenopticDreamer, a framework that synchronizes generative hallucinations to maintain spatio-temporal memory. The core idea is to train a multi-in-single-out video-conditioned model in an autoregressive manner, aided by a camera-guided video retrieval strategy that adaptively selects salient videos from previous generations as conditional inputs. In addition, Our training incorporates progressive context-scaling to improve convergence, self-conditioning to enhance robustness against long-range visual degradation caused by error accumulation, and a long-video conditioning mechanism to support extended video generation. Extensive experiments on the Basic and Agibot benchmarks demonstrate that PlenopticDreamer achieves state-of-the-art video re-rendering, delivering superior view synchronization, high-fidelity visuals, accurate camera control, and diverse view transformations (e.g., third-person to third-person, and head-view to gripper-view in robotic manipulation). Project page: https://research.nvidia.com/labs/dir/plenopticdreamer/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05239</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 18:58:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboVIP: Multi-View Video Generation with Visual Identity Prompting Augments Robot Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05241</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05241.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Boyang Wang, Haoran Zhang, Shujie Zhang, Jinkun Hao, Mingda Jia, Qi Lv, Yucheng Mao, Zhaoyang Lyu, Jia Zeng, Xudong Xu, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The diversity, quantity, and quality of manipulation data are critical for training effective robot policies. However, due to hardware and physical setup constraints, collecting large-scale real-world manipulation data remains difficult to scale across diverse environments. Recent work uses text-prompt conditioned image diffusion models to augment manipulation data by altering the backgrounds and tabletop objects in the visual observations. However, these approaches often overlook the practical need for multi-view and temporally coherent observations required by state-of-the-art policy models. Further, text prompts alone cannot reliably specify the scene setup. To provide the diffusion model with explicit visual guidance, we introduce visual identity prompting, which supplies exemplar images as conditioning inputs to guide the generation of the desired scene setup. To this end, we also build a scalable pipeline to curate a visual identity pool from large robotics datasets. Using our augmented manipulation data to train downstream vision-language-action and visuomotor policy models yields consistent performance gains in both simulation and real-robot settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05241</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 18:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GDPO: Group reward-Decoupled Normalization Policy Optimization for Multi-reward RL Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05242</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05242.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shih-Yang Liu, Xin Dong, Ximing Lu, Shizhe Diao, Peter Belcak, Mingjie Liu, Min-Hung Chen, Hongxu Yin, Yu-Chiang Frank Wang, Kwang-Ting Cheng, Yejin Choi, Jan Kautz, Pavlo Molchanov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 137&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As language models become increasingly capable, users expect them to provide not only accurate responses but also behaviors aligned with diverse human preferences across a variety of scenarios. To achieve this, Reinforcement learning (RL) pipelines have begun incorporating multiple rewards, each capturing a distinct preference, to guide models toward these desired behaviors. However, recent work has defaulted to apply Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) under multi-reward setting without examining its suitability. In this paper, we demonstrate that directly applying GRPO to normalize distinct rollout reward combinations causes them to collapse into identical advantage values, reducing the resolution of the training signal and resulting in suboptimal convergence and, in some cases, early training failure. We then introduce Group reward-Decoupled Normalization Policy Optimization (GDPO), a new policy optimization method to resolve these issues by decoupling the normalization of individual rewards, more faithfully preserving their relative differences and enabling more accurate multi-reward optimization, along with substantially improved training stability. We compare GDPO with GRPO across three tasks: tool calling, math reasoning, and coding reasoning, evaluating both correctness metrics (accuracy, bug ratio) and constraint adherence metrics (format, length). Across all settings, GDPO consistently outperforms GRPO, demonstrating its effectiveness and generalizability for multi-reward reinforcement learning optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05242</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 18:59:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RL-AWB: Deep Reinforcement Learning for Auto White Balance Correction in Low-Light Night-time Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05249</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.05249.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuan-Kang Lee, Kuan-Lin Chen, Chia-Che Chang, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Nighttime color constancy remains a challenging problem in computational photography due to low-light noise and complex illumination conditions. We present RL-AWB, a novel framework combining statistical methods with deep reinforcement learning for nighttime white balance. Our method begins with a statistical algorithm tailored for nighttime scenes, integrating salient gray pixel detection with novel illumination estimation. Building on this foundation, we develop the first deep reinforcement learning approach for color constancy that leverages the statistical algorithm as its core, mimicking professional AWB tuning experts by dynamically optimizing parameters for each image. To facilitate cross-sensor evaluation, we introduce the first multi-sensor nighttime dataset. Experiment results demonstrate that our method achieves superior generalization capability across low-light and well-illuminated images. Project page: https://ntuneillee.github.io/research/rl-awb/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05249</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 18:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
