<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:02:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Speed Always Wins: A Survey on Efficient Architectures for Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09834</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09834.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weigao Sun, Jiaxi Hu, Yucheng Zhou, Jusen Du, Disen Lan, Kexin Wang, Tong Zhu, Xiaoye Qu, Yu Zhang, Xiaoyu Mo, Daizong Liu, Yuxuan Liang, Wenliang Chen, Guoqi Li, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have delivered impressive results in language understanding, generation, reasoning, and pushes the ability boundary of multimodal models. Transformer models, as the foundation of modern LLMs, offer a strong baseline with excellent scaling properties. However, the traditional transformer architecture requires substantial computations and poses significant obstacles for large-scale training and practical deployment. In this survey, we offer a systematic examination of innovative LLM architectures that address the inherent limitations of transformers and boost the efficiency. Starting from language modeling, this survey covers the background and technical details of linear and sparse sequence modeling methods, efficient full attention variants, sparse mixture-of-experts, hybrid model architectures incorporating the above techniques, and emerging diffusion LLMs. Additionally, we discuss applications of these techniques to other modalities and consider their wider implications for developing scalable, resource-aware foundation models. By grouping recent studies into the above category, this survey presents a blueprint of modern efficient LLM architectures, and we hope this could help motivate future research toward more efficient, versatile AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09834</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 14:13:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ComoRAG: A Cognitive-Inspired Memory-Organized RAG for Stateful Long   Narrative Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10419</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10419.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Juyuan Wang, Rongchen Zhao, Wei Wei, Yufeng Wang, Mo Yu, Jie Zhou, Jin Xu, Liyan Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Narrative comprehension on long stories and novels has been a challenging domain attributed to their intricate plotlines and entangled, often evolving relations among characters and entities. Given the LLM's diminished reasoning over extended context and high computational cost, retrieval-based approaches remain a pivotal role in practice. However, traditional RAG methods can fall short due to their stateless, single-step retrieval process, which often overlooks the dynamic nature of capturing interconnected relations within long-range context. In this work, we propose ComoRAG, holding the principle that narrative reasoning is not a one-shot process, but a dynamic, evolving interplay between new evidence acquisition and past knowledge consolidation, analogous to human cognition when reasoning with memory-related signals in the brain. Specifically, when encountering a reasoning impasse, ComoRAG undergoes iterative reasoning cycles while interacting with a dynamic memory workspace. In each cycle, it generates probing queries to devise new exploratory paths, then integrates the retrieved evidence of new aspects into a global memory pool, thereby supporting the emergence of a coherent context for the query resolution. Across four challenging long-context narrative benchmarks (200K+ tokens), ComoRAG outperforms strong RAG baselines with consistent relative gains up to 11% compared to the strongest baseline. Further analysis reveals that ComoRAG is particularly advantageous for complex queries requiring global comprehension, offering a principled, cognitively motivated paradigm for retrieval-based long context comprehension towards stateful reasoning. Our code is publicly released at https://github.com/EternityJune25/ComoRAG&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10419</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 07:52:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Solving Math Quiz: Evaluating the Ability of Large Reasoning   Models to Ask for Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11252</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11252.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Youcheng Huang, Bowen Qin, Chen Huang, Duanyu Feng, Xi Yang, Wenqiang Lei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have demonstrated remarkable problem-solving abilities in mathematics, as evaluated by existing benchmarks exclusively on well-defined problems. However, such evaluation setup constitutes a critical gap, since a genuine intelligent agent should not only solve problems (as a math quiz solver), but also be able~to ask for information when the problems lack sufficient information, enabling proactivity in responding users' requests. To bridge such gap, we proposes a new dataset consisting of two types of incomplete problems with diverse contexts. Based on the dataset, our systematical evaluation of LRMs reveals their inability in proactively asking for information. In addition, we uncover the behaviors related to overthinking and hallucination of LRMs, and highlight the potential and challenges of supervised fine-tuning in learning such ability. We hope to provide new insights in developing LRMs with genuine intelligence, rather than just solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11252</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 06:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>G-CUT3R: Guided 3D Reconstruction with Camera and Depth Prior   Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11379</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11379.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ramil Khafizov, Artem Komarichev, Ruslan Rakhimov, Peter Wonka, Evgeny Burnaev&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce G-CUT3R, a novel feed-forward approach for guided 3D scene reconstruction that enhances the CUT3R model by integrating prior information. Unlike existing feed-forward methods that rely solely on input images, our method leverages auxiliary data, such as depth, camera calibrations, or camera positions, commonly available in real-world scenarios. We propose a lightweight modification to CUT3R, incorporating a dedicated encoder for each modality to extract features, which are fused with RGB image tokens via zero convolution. This flexible design enables seamless integration of any combination of prior information during inference. Evaluated across multiple benchmarks, including 3D reconstruction and other multi-view tasks, our approach demonstrates significant performance improvements, showing its ability to effectively utilize available priors while maintaining compatibility with varying input modalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11379</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 10:25:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Punctuation Matters: A Large-Scale Comparison of Prompt Robustness   Methods for LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11383</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11383.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mikhail Seleznyov, Mikhail Chaichuk, Gleb Ershov, Alexander Panchenko, Elena Tutubalina, Oleg Somov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are highly sensitive to subtle, non-semantic variations in prompt phrasing and formatting. In this work, we present the first systematic evaluation of 5 methods for improving prompt robustness within a unified experimental framework. We benchmark these techniques on 8 models from Llama, Qwen and Gemma families across 52 tasks from Natural Instructions dataset. Our evaluation covers robustness methods from both fine-tuned and in-context learning paradigms, and tests their generalization against multiple types of distribution shifts. Finally, we extend our analysis to GPT-4.1 and DeepSeek V3 to assess frontier models' current robustness to format perturbations. Our findings offer actionable insights into the relative effectiveness of these robustness methods, enabling practitioners to make informed decisions when aiming for stable and reliable LLM performance in real-world applications. Code: https://github.com/AIRI-Institute/when-punctuation-matters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11383</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 10:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ovis2.5 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11737</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11737.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiyin Lu, Yang Li, Yu Xia, Yuwei Hu, Shanshan Zhao, Yanqing Ma, Zhichao Wei, Yinglun Li, Lunhao Duan, Jianshan Zhao, Yuxuan Han, Haijun Li, Wanying Chen, Junke Tang, Chengkun Hou, Zhixing Du, Tianli Zhou, Wenjie Zhang, Huping Ding, Jiahe Li, Wen Li, Gui Hu, Yiliang Gu, Siran Yang, Jiamang Wang, Hailong Sun, Yibo Wang, Hui Sun, Jinlong Huang, Yuping He, Shengze Shi, Weihong Zhang, Guodong Zheng, Junpeng Jiang, Sensen Gao, Yi-Feng Wu, Sijia Chen, Yuhui Chen, Qing-Guo Chen, Zhao Xu, Weihua Luo, Kaifu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Ovis2.5, a successor to Ovis2 designed for native-resolution visual perception and strong multimodal reasoning. Ovis2.5 integrates a native-resolution vision transformer that processes images at their native, variable resolutions, avoiding the degradation from fixed-resolution tiling and preserving both fine detail and global layout -- crucial for visually dense content like complex charts. To strengthen reasoning, we train the model to move beyond linear chain-of-thought and perform reflection -- including self-checking and revision. This advanced capability is exposed as an optional "thinking mode" at inference time, allowing users to trade latency for enhanced accuracy on difficult inputs. The model is trained via a comprehensive five-phase curriculum that progressively builds its skills. The process begins with foundational visual and multimodal pretraining, advances through large-scale instruction tuning, and culminates in alignment and reasoning enhancement using DPO and GRPO. To scale these upgrades efficiently, we employ multimodal data packing and hybrid parallelism, yielding a significant end-to-end speedup. We release two open-source models: Ovis2.5-9B and Ovis2.5-2B. The latter continues the "small model, big performance" philosophy of Ovis2, making it ideal for resource-constrained, on-device scenarios. On the OpenCompass multimodal leaderboard, Ovis2.5-9B averages 78.3, marking a substantial improvement over its predecessor, Ovis2-8B, and achieving state-of-the-art results among open-source MLLMs in the sub-40B parameter range; Ovis2.5-2B scores 73.9, establishing SOTA for its size. Beyond aggregate scores, Ovis2.5 achieves leading results on STEM benchmarks, exhibits strong capabilities on grounding and video tasks, and achieves open-source SOTA at its scale for complex chart analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11737</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:01:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representing Speech Through Autoregressive Prediction of Cochlear Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11598</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11598.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Greta Tuckute, Klemen Kotar, Evelina Fedorenko, Daniel L. K. Yamins&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce AuriStream, a biologically inspired model for encoding speech via a two-stage framework inspired by the human auditory processing hierarchy. The first stage transforms raw audio into a time-frequency representation based on the human cochlea, from which we extract discrete cochlear tokens. The second stage applies an autoregressive sequence model over the cochlear tokens. AuriStream learns meaningful phoneme and word representations, and state-of-the-art lexical semantics. AuriStream shows competitive performance on diverse downstream SUPERB speech tasks. Complementing AuriStream's strong representational capabilities, it generates continuations of audio which can be visualized in a spectrogram space and decoded back into audio, providing insights into the model's predictions. In summary, we present a two-stage framework for speech representation learning to advance the development of more human-like models that efficiently handle a range of speech-based tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11598</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:06:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse-LLaVA: Eliminating Alignment Pre-training Through Text-to-Vision   Mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12466</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12466.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuhui Zhan, Tyler Derr&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional multimodal learning approaches require expensive alignment pre-training to bridge vision and language modalities, typically projecting visual features into discrete text token spaces. We challenge both fundamental assumptions underlying this paradigm by proposing Inverse-LLaVA, a novel approach that eliminates alignment pre-training entirely while inverting the conventional mapping direction. Rather than projecting visual features to text space, our method maps text embeddings into continuous visual representation space and performs fusion within transformer intermediate layers. Through selective additive components in attention mechanisms, we enable dynamic integration of visual and textual representations without requiring massive image-text alignment datasets. Comprehensive experiments across nine multimodal benchmarks demonstrate nuanced performance trade-offs: Inverse-LLaVA achieves notable improvements on reasoning-intensive and cognitive tasks (MM-VET: +0.2%, VizWiz: +1.8%, ScienceQA: +0.2%, cognitive reasoning: +27.2%), while showing expected decreases in perception tasks requiring memorized visual-text associations (celebrity recognition: -49.5%, OCR: -21.3%). These results provide the first empirical evidence that alignment pre-training is not necessary for effective multimodal learning, particularly for complex reasoning tasks. Our work establishes the feasibility of a new paradigm that reduces computational requirements by 45%, challenges conventional wisdom about modality fusion, and opens new research directions for efficient multimodal architectures that preserve modality-specific characteristics. Our project website with code and additional resources is available at https://inverse-llava.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12466</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2025 18:36:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlearning Comparator: A Visual Analytics System for Comparative   Evaluation of Machine Unlearning Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12730</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12730.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaeung Lee, Suhyeon Yu, Yurim Jang, Simon S. Woo, Jaemin Jo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Machine Unlearning (MU) aims to remove target training data from a trained model so that the removed data no longer influences the model's behavior, fulfilling "right to be forgotten" obligations under data privacy laws. Yet, we observe that researchers in this rapidly emerging field face challenges in analyzing and understanding the behavior of different MU methods, especially in terms of three fundamental principles in MU: accuracy, efficiency, and privacy. Consequently, they often rely on aggregate metrics and ad-hoc evaluations, making it difficult to accurately assess the trade-offs between methods. To fill this gap, we introduce a visual analytics system, Unlearning Comparator, designed to facilitate the systematic evaluation of MU methods. Our system supports two important tasks in the evaluation process: model comparison and attack simulation. First, it allows the user to compare the behaviors of two models, such as a model generated by a certain method and a retrained baseline, at class-, instance-, and layer-levels to better understand the changes made after unlearning. Second, our system simulates membership inference attacks (MIAs) to evaluate the privacy of a method, where an attacker attempts to determine whether specific data samples were part of the original training set. We evaluate our system through a case study visually analyzing prominent MU methods and demonstrate that it helps the user not only understand model behaviors but also gain insights that can inform the improvement of MU methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12730</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 08:53:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HeroBench: A Benchmark for Long-Horizon Planning and Structured   Reasoning in Virtual Worlds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12782</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12782.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Petr Anokhin, Roman Khalikov, Stefan Rebrikov, Viktor Volkov, Artyom Sorokin, Vincent Bissonnette&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable capabilities in isolated step-by-step reasoning tasks such as mathematics and programming, but their proficiency in long-horizon planning, where solutions require extended, structured sequences of interdependent actions, remains underexplored. Existing benchmarks typically assess LLMs through abstract or low-dimensional algorithmic tasks, failing to capture the complexity of realistic planning environments. We introduce HeroBench, a novel benchmark designed specifically to evaluate long-horizon planning and structured reasoning within complex RPG-inspired virtual worlds. HeroBench provides a rigorously constructed dataset of tasks covering a wide range of difficulties, a simulated environment to execute and validate agent plans, and detailed analytical tools for evaluating model performance. Tasks challenge models to formulate strategic plans, efficiently gather resources, master necessary skills, craft equipment, and defeat adversaries, reflecting practical scenarios' layered dependencies and constraints. Our extensive evaluation of 25 state-of-the-art LLMs, spanning both open-source and proprietary models, including the GPT-5 family, reveals substantial performance disparities rarely observed in conventional reasoning benchmarks. Detailed error analysis further uncovers specific weaknesses in current models' abilities to generate robust high-level plans and reliably execute structured actions. HeroBench thus not only significantly advances the evaluation of LLM reasoning but also provides a flexible, scalable foundation for future research into advanced, autonomous planning in virtual environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12782</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 09:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning with Rubric Anchors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12790</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12790.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zenan Huang, Yihong Zhuang, Guoshan Lu, Zeyu Qin, Haokai Xu, Tianyu Zhao, Ru Peng, Jiaqi Hu, Zhanming Shen, Xiaomeng Hu, Xijun Gu, Peiyi Tu, Jiaxin Liu, Wenyu Chen, Yuzhuo Fu, Zhiting Fan, Yanmei Gu, Yuanyuan Wang, Zhengkai Yang, Jianguo Li, Junbo Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning from Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as a powerful paradigm for enhancing Large Language Models (LLMs), exemplified by the success of OpenAI's o-series. In RLVR, rewards are derived from verifiable signals-such as passing unit tests in code generation or matching correct answers in mathematical reasoning. While effective, this requirement largely confines RLVR to domains with automatically checkable outcomes. To overcome this, we extend the RLVR paradigm to open-ended tasks by integrating rubric-based rewards, where carefully designed rubrics serve as structured, model-interpretable criteria for automatic scoring of subjective outputs. We construct, to our knowledge, the largest rubric reward system to date, with over 10,000 rubrics from humans, LLMs, or a hybrid human-LLM collaboration. Implementing rubric-based RL is challenging; we tackle these issues with a clear framework and present an open-sourced Qwen-30B-A3B model with notable gains: 1) With only 5K+ samples, our system improves by +5.2% on open-ended benchmarks (especially humanities), outperforming a 671B DeepSeek-V3 model by +2.4%, while preserving general and reasoning abilities. 2) Our method provides fine-grained stylistic control, using rubrics as anchors to mitigate the "AI-like" tone and produce more human-like, expressive responses. We share key lessons in rubric construction, data selection, and training, and discuss limitations and future releases.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12790</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 10:06:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next Visual Granularity Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12811</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12811.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yikai Wang, Zhouxia Wang, Zhonghua Wu, Qingyi Tao, Kang Liao, Chen Change Loy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel approach to image generation by decomposing an image into a structured sequence, where each element in the sequence shares the same spatial resolution but differs in the number of unique tokens used, capturing different level of visual granularity. Image generation is carried out through our newly introduced Next Visual Granularity (NVG) generation framework, which generates a visual granularity sequence beginning from an empty image and progressively refines it, from global layout to fine details, in a structured manner. This iterative process encodes a hierarchical, layered representation that offers fine-grained control over the generation process across multiple granularity levels. We train a series of NVG models for class-conditional image generation on the ImageNet dataset and observe clear scaling behavior. Compared to the VAR series, NVG consistently outperforms it in terms of FID scores (3.30 -&gt; 3.03, 2.57 -&gt;2.44, 2.09 -&gt; 2.06). We also conduct extensive analysis to showcase the capability and potential of the NVG framework. Our code and models will be released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12811</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 10:47:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S^2-Guidance: Stochastic Self Guidance for Training-Free Enhancement of   Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12880</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12880.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chubin Chen, Jiashu Zhu, Xiaokun Feng, Nisha Huang, Meiqi Wu, Fangyuan Mao, Jiahong Wu, Xiangxiang Chu, Xiu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Classifier-free Guidance (CFG) is a widely used technique in modern diffusion models for enhancing sample quality and prompt adherence. However, through an empirical analysis on Gaussian mixture modeling with a closed-form solution, we observe a discrepancy between the suboptimal results produced by CFG and the ground truth. The model's excessive reliance on these suboptimal predictions often leads to semantic incoherence and low-quality outputs. To address this issue, we first empirically demonstrate that the model's suboptimal predictions can be effectively refined using sub-networks of the model itself. Building on this insight, we propose S^2-Guidance, a novel method that leverages stochastic block-dropping during the forward process to construct stochastic sub-networks, effectively guiding the model away from potential low-quality predictions and toward high-quality outputs. Extensive qualitative and quantitative experiments on text-to-image and text-to-video generation tasks demonstrate that S^2-Guidance delivers superior performance, consistently surpassing CFG and other advanced guidance strategies. Our code will be released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12880</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 12:31:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lumen: Consistent Video Relighting and Harmonious Background Replacement   with Video Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12945</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12945.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianshu Zeng, Yuxuan Liu, Yutong Feng, Chenxuan Miao, Zixiang Gao, Jiwang Qu, Jianzhang Zhang, Bin Wang, Kun Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video relighting is a challenging yet valuable task, aiming to replace the background in videos while correspondingly adjusting the lighting in the foreground with harmonious blending. During translation, it is essential to preserve the original properties of the foreground, e.g., albedo, and propagate consistent relighting among temporal frames. In this paper, we propose Lumen, an end-to-end video relighting framework developed on large-scale video generative models, receiving flexible textual description for instructing the control of lighting and background. Considering the scarcity of high-qualified paired videos with the same foreground in various lighting conditions, we construct a large-scale dataset with a mixture of realistic and synthetic videos. For the synthetic domain, benefiting from the abundant 3D assets in the community, we leverage advanced 3D rendering engine to curate video pairs in diverse environments. For the realistic domain, we adapt a HDR-based lighting simulation to complement the lack of paired in-the-wild videos. Powered by the aforementioned dataset, we design a joint training curriculum to effectively unleash the strengths of each domain, i.e., the physical consistency in synthetic videos, and the generalized domain distribution in realistic videos. To implement this, we inject a domain-aware adapter into the model to decouple the learning of relighting and domain appearance distribution. We construct a comprehensive benchmark to evaluate Lumen together with existing methods, from the perspectives of foreground preservation and video consistency assessment. Experimental results demonstrate that Lumen effectively edit the input into cinematic relighted videos with consistent lighting and strict foreground preservation. Our project page: https://lumen-relight.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12945</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 14:21:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix-Game 2.0: An Open-Source, Real-Time, and Streaming Interactive   World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13009</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13009.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xianglong He, Chunli Peng, Zexiang Liu, Boyang Wang, Yifan Zhang, Qi Cui, Fei Kang, Biao Jiang, Mengyin An, Yangyang Ren, Baixin Xu, Hao-Xiang Guo, Kaixiong Gong, Cyrus Wu, Wei Li, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Eric Li, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in interactive video generations have demonstrated diffusion model's potential as world models by capturing complex physical dynamics and interactive behaviors. However, existing interactive world models depend on bidirectional attention and lengthy inference steps, severely limiting real-time performance. Consequently, they are hard to simulate real-world dynamics, where outcomes must update instantaneously based on historical context and current actions. To address this, we present Matrix-Game 2.0, an interactive world model generates long videos on-the-fly via few-step auto-regressive diffusion. Our framework consists of three key components: (1) A scalable data production pipeline for Unreal Engine and GTA5 environments to effectively produce massive amounts (about 1200 hours) of video data with diverse interaction annotations; (2) An action injection module that enables frame-level mouse and keyboard inputs as interactive conditions; (3) A few-step distillation based on the casual architecture for real-time and streaming video generation. Matrix Game 2.0 can generate high-quality minute-level videos across diverse scenes at an ultra-fast speed of 25 FPS. We open-source our model weights and codebase to advance research in interactive world modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13009</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 15:28:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise Action-to-Video Generation Through Visual Action Prompts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13104</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13104.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuang Wang, Chao Wen, Haoyu Guo, Sida Peng, Minghan Qin, Hujun Bao, Xiaowei Zhou, Ruizhen Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present visual action prompts, a unified action representation for action-to-video generation of complex high-DoF interactions while maintaining transferable visual dynamics across domains. Action-driven video generation faces a precision-generality trade-off: existing methods using text, primitive actions, or coarse masks offer generality but lack precision, while agent-centric action signals provide precision at the cost of cross-domain transferability. To balance action precision and dynamic transferability, we propose to "render" actions into precise visual prompts as domain-agnostic representations that preserve both geometric precision and cross-domain adaptability for complex actions; specifically, we choose visual skeletons for their generality and accessibility. We propose robust pipelines to construct skeletons from two interaction-rich data sources - human-object interactions (HOI) and dexterous robotic manipulation - enabling cross-domain training of action-driven generative models. By integrating visual skeletons into pretrained video generation models via lightweight fine-tuning, we enable precise action control of complex interaction while preserving the learning of cross-domain dynamics. Experiments on EgoVid, RT-1 and DROID demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed approach. Project page: https://zju3dv.github.io/VAP/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13104</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:12:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Has GPT-5 Achieved Spatial Intelligence? An Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13142</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13142.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongang Cai, Yubo Wang, Qingping Sun, Ruisi Wang, Chenyang Gu, Wanqi Yin, Zhiqian Lin, Zhitao Yang, Chen Wei, Xuanke Shi, Kewang Deng, Xiaoyang Han, Zukai Chen, Jiaqi Li, Xiangyu Fan, Hanming Deng, Lewei Lu, Bo Li, Ziwei Liu, Quan Wang, Dahua Lin, Lei Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-modal models have achieved remarkable progress in recent years. Nevertheless, they continue to exhibit notable limitations in spatial understanding and reasoning, which are fundamental capabilities to achieving artificial general intelligence. With the recent release of GPT-5, allegedly the most powerful AI model to date, it is timely to examine where the leading models stand on the path toward spatial intelligence. First, we propose a comprehensive taxonomy of spatial tasks that unifies existing benchmarks and discuss the challenges in ensuring fair evaluation. We then evaluate state-of-the-art proprietary and open-source models on eight key benchmarks, at a cost exceeding one billion total tokens. Our empirical study reveals that (1) GPT-5 demonstrates unprecedented strength in spatial intelligence, yet (2) still falls short of human performance across a broad spectrum of tasks. Moreover, we (3) identify the more challenging spatial intelligence problems for multi-modal models, and (4) proprietary models do not exhibit a decisive advantage when facing the most difficult problems. In addition, we conduct a qualitative evaluation across a diverse set of scenarios that are intuitive for humans yet fail even the most advanced multi-modal models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13142</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:55:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4DNeX: Feed-Forward 4D Generative Modeling Made Easy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13154</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13154.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoxi Chen, Tianqi Liu, Long Zhuo, Jiawei Ren, Zeng Tao, He Zhu, Fangzhou Hong, Liang Pan, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present 4DNeX, the first feed-forward framework for generating 4D (i.e., dynamic 3D) scene representations from a single image. In contrast to existing methods that rely on computationally intensive optimization or require multi-frame video inputs, 4DNeX enables efficient, end-to-end image-to-4D generation by fine-tuning a pretrained video diffusion model. Specifically, 1) to alleviate the scarcity of 4D data, we construct 4DNeX-10M, a large-scale dataset with high-quality 4D annotations generated using advanced reconstruction approaches. 2) we introduce a unified 6D video representation that jointly models RGB and XYZ sequences, facilitating structured learning of both appearance and geometry. 3) we propose a set of simple yet effective adaptation strategies to repurpose pretrained video diffusion models for 4D modeling. 4DNeX produces high-quality dynamic point clouds that enable novel-view video synthesis. Extensive experiments demonstrate that 4DNeX outperforms existing 4D generation methods in efficiency and generalizability, offering a scalable solution for image-to-4D modeling and laying the foundation for generative 4D world models that simulate dynamic scene evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13154</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
