<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:11:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>The Aloe Family Recipe for Open and Specialized Healthcare LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04388</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.04388.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dario Garcia-Gasulla, Jordi Bayarri-Planas, Ashwin Kumar Gururajan, Enrique Lopez-Cuena, Adrian Tormos, Daniel Hinjos, Pablo Bernabeu-Perez, Anna Arias-Duart, Pablo Agustin Martin-Torres, Marta Gonzalez-Mallo, Sergio Alvarez-Napagao, Eduard Ayguadé-Parra, Ulises Cortés&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Purpose: With advancements in Large Language Models (LLMs) for healthcare, the need arises for competitive open-source models to protect the public interest. This work contributes to the field of open medical LLMs by optimizing key stages of data preprocessing and training, while showing how to improve model safety (through DPO) and efficacy (through RAG). The evaluation methodology used, which includes four different types of tests, defines a new standard for the field. The resultant models, shown to be competitive with the best private alternatives, are released with a permisive license.   Methods: Building on top of strong base models like Llama 3.1 and Qwen 2.5, Aloe Beta uses a custom dataset to enhance public data with synthetic Chain of Thought examples. The models undergo alignment with Direct Preference Optimization, emphasizing ethical and policy-aligned performance in the presence of jailbreaking attacks. Evaluation includes close-ended, open-ended, safety and human assessments, to maximize the reliability of results.   Results: Recommendations are made across the entire pipeline, backed by the solid performance of the Aloe Family. These models deliver competitive performance across healthcare benchmarks and medical fields, and are often preferred by healthcare professionals. On bias and toxicity, the Aloe Beta models significantly improve safety, showing resilience to unseen jailbreaking attacks. For a responsible release, a detailed risk assessment specific to healthcare is attached to the Aloe Family models.   Conclusion: The Aloe Beta models, and the recipe that leads to them, are a significant contribution to the open-source medical LLM field, offering top-of-the-line performance while maintaining high ethical requirements. This work sets a new standard for developing and reporting aligned LLMs in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04388</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 13:13:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple Semi-supervised Knowledge Distillation from Vision-Language   Models via texttt{D}ual-texttt{H}ead   texttt{O}ptimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07675</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.07675.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seongjae Kang, Dong Bok Lee, Hyungjoon Jang, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language models (VLMs) have achieved remarkable success across diverse tasks by leveraging rich textual information with minimal labeled data. However, deploying such large models remains challenging, particularly in resource-constrained environments. Knowledge distillation (KD) offers a well-established solution to this problem; however, recent KD approaches from VLMs often involve multi-stage training or additional tuning, increasing computational overhead and optimization complexity. In this paper, we propose texttt{D}ual-texttt{H}ead texttt{O}ptimization (texttt{DHO}) -- a simple yet effective KD framework that transfers knowledge from VLMs to compact, task-specific models in semi-supervised settings. Specifically, we introduce dual prediction heads that independently learn from labeled data and teacher predictions, and propose to linearly combine their outputs during inference. We observe that DHO mitigates gradient conflicts between supervised and distillation signals, enabling more effective feature learning than single-head KD baselines. As a result, extensive experiments show that DHO consistently outperforms baselines across multiple domains and fine-grained datasets. Notably, on ImageNet, it achieves state-of-the-art performance, improving accuracy by 3% and 0.1% with 1% and 10% labeled data, respectively, while using fewer parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07675</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 15:39:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Through the Looking Glass: Common Sense Consistency Evaluation of Weird   Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07704</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.07704.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Elisei Rykov, Kseniia Petrushina, Kseniia Titova, Anton Razzhigaev, Alexander Panchenko, Vasily Konovalov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Measuring how real images look is a complex task in artificial intelligence research. For example, an image of a boy with a vacuum cleaner in a desert violates common sense. We introduce a novel method, which we call Through the Looking Glass (TLG), to assess image common sense consistency using Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs) and Transformer-based encoder. By leveraging LVLMs to extract atomic facts from these images, we obtain a mix of accurate facts. We proceed by fine-tuning a compact attention-pooling classifier over encoded atomic facts. Our TLG has achieved a new state-of-the-art performance on the WHOOPS! and WEIRD datasets while leveraging a compact fine-tuning component.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07704</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 16:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qwen3 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09388</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.09388.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; An Yang, Anfeng Li, Baosong Yang, Beichen Zhang, Binyuan Hui, Bo Zheng, Bowen Yu, Chang Gao, Chengen Huang, Chenxu Lv, Chujie Zheng, Dayiheng Liu, Fan Zhou, Fei Huang, Feng Hu, Hao Ge, Haoran Wei, Huan Lin, Jialong Tang, Jian Yang, Jianhong Tu, Jianwei Zhang, Jianxin Yang, Jiaxi Yang, Jing Zhou, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin, Kai Dang, Keqin Bao, Kexin Yang, Le Yu, Lianghao Deng, Mei Li, Mingfeng Xue, Mingze Li, Pei Zhang, Peng Wang, Qin Zhu, Rui Men, Ruize Gao, Shixuan Liu, Shuang Luo, Tianhao Li, Tianyi Tang, Wenbiao Yin, Xingzhang Ren, Xinyu Wang, Xinyu Zhang, Xuancheng Ren, Yang Fan, Yang Su, Yichang Zhang, Yinger Zhang, Yu Wan, Yuqiong Liu, Zekun Wang, Zeyu Cui, Zhenru Zhang, Zhipeng Zhou, Zihan Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 148&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we present Qwen3, the latest version of the Qwen model family. Qwen3 comprises a series of large language models (LLMs) designed to advance performance, efficiency, and multilingual capabilities. The Qwen3 series includes models of both dense and Mixture-of-Expert (MoE) architectures, with parameter scales ranging from 0.6 to 235 billion. A key innovation in Qwen3 is the integration of thinking mode (for complex, multi-step reasoning) and non-thinking mode (for rapid, context-driven responses) into a unified framework. This eliminates the need to switch between different models--such as chat-optimized models (e.g., GPT-4o) and dedicated reasoning models (e.g., QwQ-32B)--and enables dynamic mode switching based on user queries or chat templates. Meanwhile, Qwen3 introduces a thinking budget mechanism, allowing users to allocate computational resources adaptively during inference, thereby balancing latency and performance based on task complexity. Moreover, by leveraging the knowledge from the flagship models, we significantly reduce the computational resources required to build smaller-scale models, while ensuring their highly competitive performance. Empirical evaluations demonstrate that Qwen3 achieves state-of-the-art results across diverse benchmarks, including tasks in code generation, mathematical reasoning, agent tasks, etc., competitive against larger MoE models and proprietary models. Compared to its predecessor Qwen2.5, Qwen3 expands multilingual support from 29 to 119 languages and dialects, enhancing global accessibility through improved cross-lingual understanding and generation capabilities. To facilitate reproducibility and community-driven research and development, all Qwen3 models are publicly accessible under Apache 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09388</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 13:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Token Prediction Needs Registers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10518</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.10518.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anastasios Gerontopoulos, Spyros Gidaris, Nikos Komodakis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-token prediction has emerged as a promising objective for improving language model pretraining, but its benefits have not consistently generalized to other settings such as fine-tuning. In this paper, we propose MuToR, a simple and effective approach to multi-token prediction that interleaves learnable register tokens into the input sequence, each tasked with predicting future targets. Compared to existing methods, MuToR offers several key advantages: it introduces only a negligible number of additional parameters, requires no architectural changes--ensuring compatibility with off-the-shelf pretrained language models--and remains aligned with the next-token pretraining objective, making it especially well-suited for supervised fine-tuning. Moreover, it naturally supports scalable prediction horizons. We demonstrate the effectiveness and versatility of MuToR across a range of use cases, including supervised fine-tuning, parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT), and pretraining, on challenging generative tasks in both language and vision domains. Our code will be available at: https://github.com/nasosger/MuToR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10518</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 17:25:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMLongBench: Benchmarking Long-Context Vision-Language Models   Effectively and Thoroughly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10610</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.10610.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaowei Wang, Wenhao Yu, Xiyu Ren, Jipeng Zhang, Yu Zhao, Rohit Saxena, Liang Cheng, Ginny Wong, Simon See, Pasquale Minervini, Yangqiu Song, Mark Steedman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid extension of context windows in large vision-language models has given rise to long-context vision-language models (LCVLMs), which are capable of handling hundreds of images with interleaved text tokens in a single forward pass. In this work, we introduce MMLongBench, the first benchmark covering a diverse set of long-context vision-language tasks, to evaluate LCVLMs effectively and thoroughly. MMLongBench is composed of 13,331 examples spanning five different categories of downstream tasks, such as Visual RAG and Many-Shot ICL. It also provides broad coverage of image types, including various natural and synthetic images. To assess the robustness of the models to different input lengths, all examples are delivered at five standardized input lengths (8K-128K tokens) via a cross-modal tokenization scheme that combines vision patches and text tokens. Through a thorough benchmarking of 46 closed-source and open-source LCVLMs, we provide a comprehensive analysis of the current models' vision-language long-context ability. Our results show that: i) performance on a single task is a weak proxy for overall long-context capability; ii) both closed-source and open-source models face challenges in long-context vision-language tasks, indicating substantial room for future improvement; iii) models with stronger reasoning ability tend to exhibit better long-context performance. By offering wide task coverage, various image types, and rigorous length control, MMLongBench provides the missing foundation for diagnosing and advancing the next generation of LCVLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10610</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 17:52:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GuardReasoner-VL: Safeguarding VLMs via Reinforced Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11049</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11049.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yue Liu, Shengfang Zhai, Mingzhe Du, Yulin Chen, Tri Cao, Hongcheng Gao, Cheng Wang, Xinfeng Li, Kun Wang, Junfeng Fang, Jiaheng Zhang, Bryan Hooi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; To enhance the safety of VLMs, this paper introduces a novel reasoning-based VLM guard model dubbed GuardReasoner-VL. The core idea is to incentivize the guard model to deliberatively reason before making moderation decisions via online RL. First, we construct GuardReasoner-VLTrain, a reasoning corpus with 123K samples and 631K reasoning steps, spanning text, image, and text-image inputs. Then, based on it, we cold-start our model's reasoning ability via SFT. In addition, we further enhance reasoning regarding moderation through online RL. Concretely, to enhance diversity and difficulty of samples, we conduct rejection sampling followed by data augmentation via the proposed safety-aware data concatenation. Besides, we use a dynamic clipping parameter to encourage exploration in early stages and exploitation in later stages. To balance performance and token efficiency, we design a length-aware safety reward that integrates accuracy, format, and token cost. Extensive experiments demonstrate the superiority of our model. Remarkably, it surpasses the runner-up by 19.27% F1 score on average. We release data, code, and models (3B/7B) of GuardReasoner-VL at https://github.com/yueliu1999/GuardReasoner-VL/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11049</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 09:46:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group Think: Multiple Concurrent Reasoning Agents Collaborating at Token   Level Granularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11107</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11107.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chan-Jan Hsu, Davide Buffelli, Jamie McGowan, Feng-Ting Liao, Yi-Chang Chen, Sattar Vakili, Da-shan Shiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated the power of reasoning through self-generated chains of thought. Multiple reasoning agents can collaborate to raise joint reasoning quality above individual outcomes. However, such agents typically interact in a turn-based manner, trading increased latency for improved quality. In this paper, we propose Group Think--a single LLM that acts as multiple concurrent reasoning agents, or thinkers. With shared visibility into each other's partial generation progress, Group Think introduces a new concurrent-reasoning paradigm in which multiple reasoning trajectories adapt dynamically to one another at the token level. For example, a reasoning thread may shift its generation mid-sentence upon detecting that another thread is better positioned to continue. This fine-grained, token-level collaboration enables Group Think to reduce redundant reasoning and improve quality while achieving significantly lower latency. Moreover, its concurrent nature allows for efficient utilization of idle computational resources, making it especially suitable for edge inference, where very small batch size often underutilizes local~GPUs. We give a simple and generalizable modification that enables any existing LLM to perform Group Think on a local GPU. We also present an evaluation strategy to benchmark reasoning latency and empirically demonstrate latency improvements using open-source LLMs that were not explicitly trained for Group Think. We hope this work paves the way for future LLMs to exhibit more sophisticated and more efficient collaborative behavior for higher quality generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11107</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 10:40:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiCo: Revitalizing ConvNets for Scalable and Efficient Diffusion   Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11196</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11196.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuang Ai, Qihang Fan, Xuefeng Hu, Zhenheng Yang, Ran He, Huaibo Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Transformer (DiT), a promising diffusion model for visual generation, demonstrates impressive performance but incurs significant computational overhead. Intriguingly, analysis of pre-trained DiT models reveals that global self-attention is often redundant, predominantly capturing local patterns-highlighting the potential for more efficient alternatives. In this paper, we revisit convolution as an alternative building block for constructing efficient and expressive diffusion models. However, naively replacing self-attention with convolution typically results in degraded performance. Our investigations attribute this performance gap to the higher channel redundancy in ConvNets compared to Transformers. To resolve this, we introduce a compact channel attention mechanism that promotes the activation of more diverse channels, thereby enhancing feature diversity. This leads to Diffusion ConvNet (DiCo), a family of diffusion models built entirely from standard ConvNet modules, offering strong generative performance with significant efficiency gains. On class-conditional ImageNet benchmarks, DiCo outperforms previous diffusion models in both image quality and generation speed. Notably, DiCo-XL achieves an FID of 2.05 at 256x256 resolution and 2.53 at 512x512, with a 2.7x and 3.1x speedup over DiT-XL/2, respectively. Furthermore, our largest model, DiCo-H, scaled to 1B parameters, reaches an FID of 1.90 on ImageNet 256x256-without any additional supervision during training. Code: https://github.com/shallowdream204/DiCo.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11196</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 12:54:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delta Attention: Fast and Accurate Sparse Attention Inference by Delta   Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11254</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11254.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jeffrey Willette, Heejun Lee, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The attention mechanism of a transformer has a quadratic complexity, leading to high inference costs and latency for long sequences. However, attention matrices are mostly sparse, which implies that many entries may be omitted from computation for efficient inference. Sparse attention inference methods aim to reduce this computational burden; however, they also come with a troublesome performance degradation. We discover that one reason for this degradation is that the sparse calculation induces a distributional shift in the attention outputs. The distributional shift causes decoding-time queries to fail to align well with the appropriate keys from the prefill stage, leading to a drop in performance. We propose a simple, novel, and effective procedure for correcting this distributional shift, bringing the distribution of sparse attention outputs closer to that of quadratic attention. Our method can be applied on top of any sparse attention method, and results in an average 36%pt performance increase, recovering 88% of quadratic attention accuracy on the 131K RULER benchmark when applied on top of sliding window attention with sink tokens while only adding a small overhead. Our method can maintain approximately 98.5% sparsity over full quadratic attention, making our model 32 times faster than Flash Attention 2 when processing 1M token prefills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11254</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 13:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Planning: Let's Think Only with Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11409</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11409.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Xu, Chengzu Li, Han Zhou, Xingchen Wan, Caiqi Zhang, Anna Korhonen, Ivan Vulić&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in Large Language Models (LLMs) and their multimodal extensions (MLLMs) have substantially enhanced machine reasoning across diverse tasks. However, these models predominantly rely on pure text as the medium for both expressing and structuring reasoning, even when visual information is present. In this work, we argue that language may not always be the most natural or effective modality for reasoning, particularly in tasks involving spatial and geometrical information. Motivated by this, we propose a new paradigm, Visual Planning, which enables planning through purely visual representations, independent of text. In this paradigm, planning is executed via sequences of images that encode step-by-step inference in the visual domain, akin to how humans sketch or visualize future actions. We introduce a novel reinforcement learning framework, Visual Planning via Reinforcement Learning (VPRL), empowered by GRPO for post-training large vision models, leading to substantial improvements in planning in a selection of representative visual navigation tasks, FrozenLake, Maze, and MiniBehavior. Our visual planning paradigm outperforms all other planning variants that conduct reasoning in the text-only space. Our results establish Visual Planning as a viable and promising alternative to language-based reasoning, opening new avenues for tasks that benefit from intuitive, image-based inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11409</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 16:17:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mergenetic: a Simple Evolutionary Model Merging Library</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11427</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11427.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Adrian Robert Minut, Tommaso Mencattini, Andrea Santilli, Donato Crisostomi, Emanuele Rodolà&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Model merging allows combining the capabilities of existing models into a new one - post hoc, without additional training. This has made it increasingly popular thanks to its low cost and the availability of libraries that support merging on consumer GPUs. Recent work shows that pairing merging with evolutionary algorithms can boost performance, but no framework currently supports flexible experimentation with such strategies in language models. We introduce Mergenetic, an open-source library for evolutionary model merging. Mergenetic enables easy composition of merging methods and evolutionary algorithms while incorporating lightweight fitness estimators to reduce evaluation costs. We describe its design and demonstrate that Mergenetic produces competitive results across tasks and languages using modest hardware.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11427</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 16:43:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SageAttention3: Microscaling FP4 Attention for Inference and An   Exploration of 8-Bit Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11594</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11594.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Jia Wei, Pengle Zhang, Xiaoming Xu, Haofeng Huang, Haoxu Wang, Kai Jiang, Jun Zhu, Jianfei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The efficiency of attention is important due to its quadratic time complexity. We enhance the efficiency of attention through two key contributions: First, we leverage the new FP4 Tensor Cores in Blackwell GPUs to accelerate attention computation. Our implementation achieves 1038 TOPS on RTX5090, which is a 5x speedup over the fastest FlashAttention on RTX5090. Experiments show that our FP4 attention can accelerate inference of various models in a plug-and-play way. Second, we pioneer low-bit attention to training tasks. Existing low-bit attention works like FlashAttention3 and SageAttention focus only on inference. However, the efficiency of training large models is also important. To explore whether low-bit attention can be effectively applied to training tasks, we design an accurate and efficient 8-bit attention for both forward and backward propagation. Experiments indicate that 8-bit attention achieves lossless performance in fine-tuning tasks but exhibits slower convergence in pretraining tasks. The code will be available at https://github.com/thu-ml/SageAttention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11594</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 18:01:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain-of-Model Learning for Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11820</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11820.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaitao Song, Xiaohua Wang, Xu Tan, Huiqiang Jiang, Chengruidong Zhang, Yongliang Shen, Cen LU, Zihao Li, Zifan Song, Caihua Shan, Yansen Wang, Kan Ren, Xiaoqing Zheng, Tao Qin, Yuqing Yang, Dongsheng Li, Lili Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 106&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we propose a novel learning paradigm, termed Chain-of-Model (CoM), which incorporates the causal relationship into the hidden states of each layer as a chain style, thereby introducing great scaling efficiency in model training and inference flexibility in deployment. We introduce the concept of Chain-of-Representation (CoR), which formulates the hidden states at each layer as a combination of multiple sub-representations (i.e., chains) at the hidden dimension level. In each layer, each chain from the output representations can only view all of its preceding chains in the input representations. Consequently, the model built upon CoM framework can progressively scale up the model size by increasing the chains based on the previous models (i.e., chains), and offer multiple sub-models at varying sizes for elastic inference by using different chain numbers. Based on this principle, we devise Chain-of-Language-Model (CoLM), which incorporates the idea of CoM into each layer of Transformer architecture. Based on CoLM, we further introduce CoLM-Air by introducing a KV sharing mechanism, that computes all keys and values within the first chain and then shares across all chains. This design demonstrates additional extensibility, such as enabling seamless LM switching, prefilling acceleration and so on. Experimental results demonstrate our CoLM family can achieve comparable performance to the standard Transformer, while simultaneously enabling greater flexiblity, such as progressive scaling to improve training efficiency and offer multiple varying model sizes for elastic inference, paving a a new way toward building language models. Our code will be released in the future at: https://github.com/microsoft/CoLM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11820</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 04:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When AI Co-Scientists Fail: SPOT-a Benchmark for Automated Verification   of Scientific Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11855</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11855.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guijin Son, Jiwoo Hong, Honglu Fan, Heejeong Nam, Hyunwoo Ko, Seungwon Lim, Jinyeop Song, Jinha Choi, Gonçalo Paulo, Youngjae Yu, Stella Biderman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have fueled the vision of automated scientific discovery, often called AI Co-Scientists. To date, prior work casts these systems as generative co-authors responsible for crafting hypotheses, synthesizing code, or drafting manuscripts. In this work, we explore a complementary application: using LLMs as verifiers to automate the academic verification of scientific manuscripts. To that end, we introduce SPOT, a dataset of 83 published papers paired with 91 errors significant enough to prompt errata or retraction, cross-validated with actual authors and human annotators. Evaluating state-of-the-art LLMs on SPOT, we find that none surpasses 21.1\% recall or 6.1\% precision (o3 achieves the best scores, with all others near zero). Furthermore, confidence estimates are uniformly low, and across eight independent runs, models rarely rediscover the same errors, undermining their reliability. Finally, qualitative analysis with domain experts reveals that even the strongest models make mistakes resembling student-level misconceptions derived from misunderstandings. These findings highlight the substantial gap between current LLM capabilities and the requirements for dependable AI-assisted academic verification.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11855</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 05:45:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdaCoT: Pareto-Optimal Adaptive Chain-of-Thought Triggering via   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11896</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11896.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenwei Lou, Zewei Sun, Xinnian Liang, Meng Qu, Wei Shen, Wenqi Wang, Yuntao Li, Qingping Yang, Shuangzhi Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities but often face challenges with tasks requiring sophisticated reasoning. While Chain-of-Thought (CoT) prompting significantly enhances reasoning, it indiscriminately generates lengthy reasoning steps for all queries, leading to substantial computational costs and inefficiency, especially for simpler inputs. To address this critical issue, we introduce AdaCoT (Adaptive Chain-of-Thought), a novel framework enabling LLMs to adaptively decide when to invoke CoT. AdaCoT framed adaptive reasoning as a Pareto optimization problem that seeks to balance model performance with the costs associated with CoT invocation (both frequency and computational overhead). We propose a reinforcement learning (RL) based method, specifically utilizing Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO), to dynamically control the CoT triggering decision boundary by adjusting penalty coefficients, thereby allowing the model to determine CoT necessity based on implicit query complexity. A key technical contribution is Selective Loss Masking (SLM), designed to counteract decision boundary collapse during multi-stage RL training, ensuring robust and stable adaptive triggering. Experimental results demonstrate that AdaCoT successfully navigates the Pareto frontier, achieving substantial reductions in CoT usage for queries not requiring elaborate reasoning. For instance, on our production traffic testset, AdaCoT reduced CoT triggering rates to as low as 3.18\% and decreased average response tokens by 69.06%, while maintaining high performance on complex tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11896</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 08:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neuro-Symbolic Query Compiler</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11932</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11932.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuyao Zhang, Zhicheng Dou, Xiaoxi Li, Jiajie Jin, Yongkang Wu, Zhonghua Li, Qi Ye, Ji-Rong Wen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Precise recognition of search intent in Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) systems remains a challenging goal, especially under resource constraints and for complex queries with nested structures and dependencies. This paper presents QCompiler, a neuro-symbolic framework inspired by linguistic grammar rules and compiler design, to bridge this gap. It theoretically designs a minimal yet sufficient Backus-Naur Form (BNF) grammar G[q] to formalize complex queries. Unlike previous methods, this grammar maintains completeness while minimizing redundancy. Based on this, QCompiler includes a Query Expression Translator, a Lexical Syntax Parser, and a Recursive Descent Processor to compile queries into Abstract Syntax Trees (ASTs) for execution. The atomicity of the sub-queries in the leaf nodes ensures more precise document retrieval and response generation, significantly improving the RAG system's ability to address complex queries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11932</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 09:36:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VisionReasoner: Unified Visual Perception and Reasoning via   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12081</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.12081.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqi Liu, Tianyuan Qu, Zhisheng Zhong, Bohao Peng, Shu Liu, Bei Yu, Jiaya Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large vision-language models exhibit inherent capabilities to handle diverse visual perception tasks. In this paper, we introduce VisionReasoner, a unified framework capable of reasoning and solving multiple visual perception tasks within a shared model. Specifically, by designing novel multi-object cognitive learning strategies and systematic task reformulation, VisionReasoner enhances its reasoning capabilities to analyze visual inputs, and addresses diverse perception tasks in a unified framework. The model generates a structured reasoning process before delivering the desired outputs responding to user queries. To rigorously assess unified visual perception capabilities, we evaluate VisionReasoner on ten diverse tasks spanning three critical domains: detection, segmentation, and counting. Experimental results show that VisionReasoner achieves superior performance as a unified model, outperforming Qwen2.5VL by relative margins of 29.1% on COCO (detection), 22.1% on ReasonSeg (segmentation), and 15.3% on CountBench (counting).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12081</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 16:51:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Merging in Pre-training of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12082</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.12082.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunshui Li, Yiyuan Ma, Shen Yan, Chaoyi Zhang, Jing Liu, Jianqiao Lu, Ziwen Xu, Mengzhao Chen, Minrui Wang, Shiyi Zhan, Jin Ma, Xunhao Lai, Yao Luo, Xingyan Bin, Hongbin Ren, Mingji Han, Wenhao Hao, Bairen Yi, LingJun Liu, Bole Ma, Xiaoying Jia, Zhou Xun, Liang Xiang, Yonghui Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Model merging has emerged as a promising technique for enhancing large language models, though its application in large-scale pre-training remains relatively unexplored. In this paper, we present a comprehensive investigation of model merging techniques during the pre-training process. Through extensive experiments with both dense and Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architectures ranging from millions to over 100 billion parameters, we demonstrate that merging checkpoints trained with constant learning rates not only achieves significant performance improvements but also enables accurate prediction of annealing behavior. These improvements lead to both more efficient model development and significantly lower training costs. Our detailed ablation studies on merging strategies and hyperparameters provide new insights into the underlying mechanisms while uncovering novel applications. Through comprehensive experimental analysis, we offer the open-source community practical pre-training guidelines for effective model merging.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12082</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 16:53:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BARREL: Boundary-Aware Reasoning for Factual and Reliable LRMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13529</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13529.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junxiao Yang, Jinzhe Tu, Haoran Liu, Xiaoce Wang, Chujie Zheng, Zhexin Zhang, Shiyao Cui, Caishun Chen, Tiantian He, Hongning Wang, Yew-Soon Ong, Minlie Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have shown impressive capabilities in mathematical and logical reasoning. However, current LRMs rarely admit ignorance or respond with "I don't know". Instead, they often produce incorrect answers while showing undue confidence, raising concerns about their factual reliability. In this work, we identify two pathological reasoning patterns characterized by overthinking that contribute to the overconfident and incorrect answers: last-minute guessing and second-thought spiraling. To address these issues, we propose BARREL-a novel framework that promotes concise and boundary-aware factual reasoning. Our experiments show that BARREL-training increases the reliability of DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Llama-8B from 39.33% to 61.48%, while still achieving accuracy comparable to models finetuned on reasoning data generated by R1. These results demonstrate that our pilot study is inspiring to build more reliable and factual System 2 LRMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13529</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 07:27:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSR: Enhancing Depth Perception in Vision-Language Models via   Rationale-Guided Spatial Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12448</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.12448.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Liu, Ming Ma, Xiaomin Yu, Pengxiang Ding, Han Zhao, Mingyang Sun, Siteng Huang, Donglin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite impressive advancements in Visual-Language Models (VLMs) for multi-modal tasks, their reliance on RGB inputs limits precise spatial understanding. Existing methods for integrating spatial cues, such as point clouds or depth, either require specialized sensors or fail to effectively exploit depth information for higher-order reasoning. To this end, we propose a novel Spatial Sense and Reasoning method, dubbed SSR, a novel framework that transforms raw depth data into structured, interpretable textual rationales. These textual rationales serve as meaningful intermediate representations to significantly enhance spatial reasoning capabilities. Additionally, we leverage knowledge distillation to compress the generated rationales into compact latent embeddings, which facilitate resource-efficient and plug-and-play integration into existing VLMs without retraining. To enable comprehensive evaluation, we introduce a new dataset named SSR-CoT, a million-scale visual-language reasoning dataset enriched with intermediate spatial reasoning annotations, and present SSRBench, a comprehensive multi-task benchmark. Extensive experiments on multiple benchmarks demonstrate SSR substantially improves depth utilization and enhances spatial reasoning, thereby advancing VLMs toward more human-like multi-modal understanding. Our project page is at https://yliu-cs.github.io/SSR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12448</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 14:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CPGD: Toward Stable Rule-based Reinforcement Learning for Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12504</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.12504.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zongkai Liu, Fanqing Meng, Lingxiao Du, Zhixiang Zhou, Chao Yu, Wenqi Shao, Qiaosheng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in rule-based reinforcement learning (RL) have significantly improved the reasoning capability of language models (LMs) with rule-based rewards. However, existing RL methods -- such as GRPO, REINFORCE++, and RLOO -- often suffer from training instability, where large policy updates and improper clipping can lead to training collapse. To address this issue, we propose Clipped Policy Gradient Optimization with Policy Drift (CPGD), a novel algorithm designed to stabilize policy learning in LMs. CPGD introduces a policy drift constraint based on KL divergence to dynamically regularize policy updates, and leverages a clip mechanism on the logarithm of the ratio to prevent excessive policy updates. We provide theoretical justification for CPGD and demonstrate through empirical analysis that it mitigates the instability observed in prior approaches. Furthermore, we show that CPGD significantly improves performance while maintaining training stability. Our implementation balances theoretical rigor with practical usability, offering a robust alternative for RL in the post-training of LMs. We release our code at https://github.com/ModalMinds/MM-EUREKA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12504</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 17:44:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Federated Pruning for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13547</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13547.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengxin Guo, Yinong Wang, Wei Li, Mengting Liu, Ming Li, Jinkai Zheng, Liangqiong Qu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM pruning has emerged as a promising technology for compressing LLMs, enabling their deployment on resource-limited devices. However, current methodologies typically require access to public calibration samples, which can be challenging to obtain in privacy-sensitive domains. To address this issue, we introduce FedPrLLM, a comprehensive federated pruning framework designed for the privacy-preserving compression of LLMs. In FedPrLLM, each client only needs to calculate a pruning mask matrix based on its local calibration data and share it with the server to prune the global model. This approach allows for collaborative pruning of the global model with the knowledge of each client while maintaining local data privacy. Additionally, we conduct extensive experiments to explore various possibilities within the FedPrLLM framework, including different comparison groups, pruning strategies, and the decision to scale weights. Our extensive evaluation reveals that one-shot pruning with layer comparison and no weight scaling is the optimal choice within the FedPrLLM framework. We hope our work will help guide future efforts in pruning LLMs in privacy-sensitive fields. Our code is available at https://github.com/Pengxin-Guo/FedPrLLM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13547</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 03:41:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FedSVD: Adaptive Orthogonalization for Private Federated Learning with   LoRA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12805</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.12805.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seanie Lee, Sangwoo Park, Dong Bok Lee, Dominik Wagner, Haebin Seong, Tobias Bocklet, Juho Lee, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), which introduces a product of two trainable low-rank matrices into frozen pre-trained weights, is widely used for efficient fine-tuning of language models in federated learning (FL). However, when combined with differentially private stochastic gradient descent (DP-SGD), LoRA faces substantial noise amplification: DP-SGD perturbs per-sample gradients, and the matrix multiplication of the LoRA update (BA) intensifies this effect. Freezing one matrix (e.g., A) reduces the noise but restricts model expressiveness, often resulting in suboptimal adaptation. To address this, we propose FedSVD, a simple yet effective method that introduces a global reparameterization based on singular value decomposition (SVD). In our approach, each client optimizes only the B matrix and transmits it to the server. The server aggregates the B matrices, computes the product BA using the previous A, and refactorizes the result via SVD. This yields a new adaptive A composed of the orthonormal right singular vectors of BA, and an updated B containing the remaining SVD components. This reparameterization avoids quadratic noise amplification, while allowing A to better capture the principal directions of the aggregate updates. Moreover, the orthonormal structure of A bounds the gradient norms of B and preserves more signal under DP-SGD, as confirmed by our theoretical analysis. As a result, FedSVD consistently improves stability and performance across a variety of privacy settings and benchmarks, outperforming relevant baselines under both private and non-private regimes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12805</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 07:32:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CS-Sum: A Benchmark for Code-Switching Dialogue Summarization and the   Limits of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13559</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13559.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sathya Krishnan Suresh, Tanmay Surana, Lim Zhi Hao, Eng Siong Chng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Code-switching (CS) poses a significant challenge for Large Language Models (LLMs), yet its comprehensibility remains underexplored in LLMs. We introduce CS-Sum, to evaluate the comprehensibility of CS by the LLMs through CS dialogue to English summarization. CS-Sum is the first benchmark for CS dialogue summarization across Mandarin-English (EN-ZH), Tamil-English (EN-TA), and Malay-English (EN-MS), with 900-1300 human-annotated dialogues per language pair. Evaluating ten LLMs, including open and closed-source models, we analyze performance across few-shot, translate-summarize, and fine-tuning (LoRA, QLoRA on synthetic data) approaches. Our findings show that though the scores on automated metrics are high, LLMs make subtle mistakes that alter the complete meaning of the dialogue. To this end, we introduce 3 most common type of errors that LLMs make when handling CS input. Error rates vary across CS pairs and LLMs, with some LLMs showing more frequent errors on certain language pairs, underscoring the need for specialized training on code-switched data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13559</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractured Chain-of-Thought Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12992</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.12992.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baohao Liao, Hanze Dong, Yuhui Xu, Doyen Sahoo, Christof Monz, Junnan Li, Caiming Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Inference-time scaling techniques have significantly bolstered the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs) by harnessing additional computational effort at inference without retraining. Similarly, Chain-of-Thought (CoT) prompting and its extension, Long CoT, improve accuracy by generating rich intermediate reasoning trajectories, but these approaches incur substantial token costs that impede their deployment in latency-sensitive settings. In this work, we first show that truncated CoT, which stops reasoning before completion and directly generates the final answer, often matches full CoT sampling while using dramatically fewer tokens. Building on this insight, we introduce Fractured Sampling, a unified inference-time strategy that interpolates between full CoT and solution-only sampling along three orthogonal axes: (1) the number of reasoning trajectories, (2) the number of final solutions per trajectory, and (3) the depth at which reasoning traces are truncated. Through extensive experiments on five diverse reasoning benchmarks and several model scales, we demonstrate that Fractured Sampling consistently achieves superior accuracy-cost trade-offs, yielding steep log-linear scaling gains in Pass@k versus token budget. Our analysis reveals how to allocate computation across these dimensions to maximize performance, paving the way for more efficient and scalable LLM reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12992</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 11:30:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neurosymbolic Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13138</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13138.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Emile van Krieken, Pasquale Minervini, Edoardo Ponti, Antonio Vergari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Neurosymbolic (NeSy) predictors combine neural perception with symbolic reasoning to solve tasks like visual reasoning. However, standard NeSy predictors assume conditional independence between the symbols they extract, thus limiting their ability to model interactions and uncertainty - often leading to overconfident predictions and poor out-of-distribution generalisation. To overcome the limitations of the independence assumption, we introduce neurosymbolic diffusion models (NeSyDMs), a new class of NeSy predictors that use discrete diffusion to model dependencies between symbols. Our approach reuses the independence assumption from NeSy predictors at each step of the diffusion process, enabling scalable learning while capturing symbol dependencies and uncertainty quantification. Across both synthetic and real-world benchmarks - including high-dimensional visual path planning and rule-based autonomous driving - NeSyDMs achieve state-of-the-art accuracy among NeSy predictors and demonstrate strong calibration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13138</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 14:07:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ViPlan: A Benchmark for Visual Planning with Symbolic Predicates and   Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13180</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13180.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Matteo Merler, Nicola Dainese, Minttu Alakuijala, Giovanni Bonetta, Pietro Ferrazzi, Yu Tian, Bernardo Magnini, Pekka Marttinen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Integrating Large Language Models with symbolic planners is a promising direction for obtaining verifiable and grounded plans compared to planning in natural language, with recent works extending this idea to visual domains using Vision-Language Models (VLMs). However, rigorous comparison between VLM-grounded symbolic approaches and methods that plan directly with a VLM has been hindered by a lack of common environments, evaluation protocols and model coverage. We introduce ViPlan, the first open-source benchmark for Visual Planning with symbolic predicates and VLMs. ViPlan features a series of increasingly challenging tasks in two domains: a visual variant of the classic Blocksworld planning problem and a simulated household robotics environment. We benchmark nine open-source VLM families across multiple sizes, along with selected closed models, evaluating both VLM-grounded symbolic planning and using the models directly to propose actions. We find symbolic planning to outperform direct VLM planning in Blocksworld, where accurate image grounding is crucial, whereas the opposite is true in the household robotics tasks, where commonsense knowledge and the ability to recover from errors are beneficial. Finally, we show that across most models and methods, there is no significant benefit to using Chain-of-Thought prompting, suggesting that current VLMs still struggle with visual reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13180</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 14:38:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid 3D-4D Gaussian Splatting for Fast Dynamic Scene Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13215</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13215.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seungjun Oh, Younggeun Lee, Hyejin Jeon, Eunbyung Park&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in dynamic 3D scene reconstruction have shown promising results, enabling high-fidelity 3D novel view synthesis with improved temporal consistency. Among these, 4D Gaussian Splatting (4DGS) has emerged as an appealing approach due to its ability to model high-fidelity spatial and temporal variations. However, existing methods suffer from substantial computational and memory overhead due to the redundant allocation of 4D Gaussians to static regions, which can also degrade image quality. In this work, we introduce hybrid 3D-4D Gaussian Splatting (3D-4DGS), a novel framework that adaptively represents static regions with 3D Gaussians while reserving 4D Gaussians for dynamic elements. Our method begins with a fully 4D Gaussian representation and iteratively converts temporally invariant Gaussians into 3D, significantly reducing the number of parameters and improving computational efficiency. Meanwhile, dynamic Gaussians retain their full 4D representation, capturing complex motions with high fidelity. Our approach achieves significantly faster training times compared to baseline 4D Gaussian Splatting methods while maintaining or improving the visual quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13215</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 14:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Computer-Use Grounding via User Interface Decomposition and   Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13227</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13227.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianbao Xie, Jiaqi Deng, Xiaochuan Li, Junlin Yang, Haoyuan Wu, Jixuan Chen, Wenjing Hu, Xinyuan Wang, Yuhui Xu, Zekun Wang, Yiheng Xu, Junli Wang, Doyen Sahoo, Tao Yu, Caiming Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graphical user interface (GUI) grounding, the ability to map natural language instructions to specific actions on graphical user interfaces, remains a critical bottleneck in computer use agent development. Current benchmarks oversimplify grounding tasks as short referring expressions, failing to capture the complexity of real-world interactions that require software commonsense, layout understanding, and fine-grained manipulation capabilities. To address these limitations, we introduce OSWorld-G, a comprehensive benchmark comprising 564 finely annotated samples across diverse task types including text matching, element recognition, layout understanding, and precise manipulation. Additionally, we synthesize and release the largest computer use grounding dataset Jedi, which contains 4 million examples through multi-perspective decoupling of tasks. Our multi-scale models trained on Jedi demonstrate its effectiveness by outperforming existing approaches on ScreenSpot-v2, ScreenSpot-Pro, and our OSWorld-G. Furthermore, we demonstrate that improved grounding with Jedi directly enhances agentic capabilities of general foundation models on complex computer tasks, improving from 5% to 27% on OSWorld. Through detailed ablation studies, we identify key factors contributing to grounding performance and verify that combining specialized data for different interface elements enables compositional generalization to novel interfaces. All benchmark, data, checkpoints, and code are open-sourced and available at https://osworld-grounding.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13227</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 15:09:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seek in the Dark: Reasoning via Test-Time Instance-Level Policy Gradient   in Latent Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13308</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13308.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hengli Li, Chenxi Li, Tong Wu, Xuekai Zhu, Yuxuan Wang, Zhaoxin Yu, Eric Hanchen Jiang, Song-Chun Zhu, Zixia Jia, Ying Nian Wu, Zilong Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning ability, a core component of human intelligence, continues to pose a significant challenge for Large Language Models (LLMs) in the pursuit of AGI. Although model performance has improved under the training scaling law, significant challenges remain, particularly with respect to training algorithms, such as catastrophic forgetting, and the limited availability of novel training data. As an alternative, test-time scaling enhances reasoning performance by increasing test-time computation without parameter updating. Unlike prior methods in this paradigm focused on token space, we propose leveraging latent space for more effective reasoning and better adherence to the test-time scaling law. We introduce LatentSeek, a novel framework that enhances LLM reasoning through Test-Time Instance-level Adaptation (TTIA) within the model's latent space. Specifically, LatentSeek leverages policy gradient to iteratively update latent representations, guided by self-generated reward signals. LatentSeek is evaluated on a range of reasoning benchmarks, including GSM8K, MATH-500, and AIME2024, across multiple LLM architectures. Results show that LatentSeek consistently outperforms strong baselines, such as Chain-of-Thought prompting and fine-tuning-based methods. Furthermore, our analysis demonstrates that LatentSeek is highly efficient, typically converging within a few iterations for problems of average complexity, while also benefiting from additional iterations, thereby highlighting the potential of test-time scaling in the latent space. These findings position LatentSeek as a lightweight, scalable, and effective solution for enhancing the reasoning capabilities of LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13308</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 16:26:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinkless: LLM Learns When to Think</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13379</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13379.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gongfan Fang, Xinyin Ma, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning Language Models, capable of extended chain-of-thought reasoning, have demonstrated remarkable performance on tasks requiring complex logical inference. However, applying elaborate reasoning for all queries often results in substantial computational inefficiencies, particularly when many problems admit straightforward solutions. This motivates an open question: Can LLMs learn when to think? To answer this, we propose Thinkless, a learnable framework that empowers an LLM to adaptively select between short-form and long-form reasoning, based on both task complexity and the model's ability. Thinkless is trained under a reinforcement learning paradigm and employs two control tokens, &lt;short&gt; for concise responses and &lt;think&gt; for detailed reasoning. At the core of our method is a Decoupled Group Relative Policy Optimization (DeGRPO) algorithm, which decomposes the learning objective of hybrid reasoning into two components: (1) a control token loss that governs the selection of the reasoning mode, and (2) a response loss that improves the accuracy of the generated answers. This decoupled formulation enables fine-grained control over the contributions of each objective, stabilizing training and effectively preventing collapse observed in vanilla GRPO. Empirically, on several benchmarks such as Minerva Algebra, MATH-500, and GSM8K, Thinkless is able to reduce the usage of long-chain thinking by 50% - 90%, significantly improving the efficiency of Reasoning Language Models. The code is available at https://github.com/VainF/Thinkless&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13379</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:24:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R3: Robust Rubric-Agnostic Reward Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13388</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13388.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; David Anugraha, Zilu Tang, Lester James V. Miranda, Hanyang Zhao, Mohammad Rifqi Farhansyah, Garry Kuwanto, Derry Wijaya, Genta Indra Winata&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward models are essential for aligning language model outputs with human preferences, yet existing approaches often lack both controllability and interpretability. These models are typically optimized for narrow objectives, limiting their generalizability to broader downstream tasks. Moreover, their scalar outputs are difficult to interpret without contextual reasoning. To address these limitations, we introduce R3, a novel reward modeling framework that is rubric-agnostic, generalizable across evaluation dimensions, and provides interpretable, reasoned score assignments. R3 enables more transparent and flexible evaluation of language models, supporting robust alignment with diverse human values and use cases. Our models, data, and code are available as open source at https://github.com/rubricreward/r3&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13388</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:29:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faster Video Diffusion with Trainable Sparse Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13389</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13389.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peiyuan Zhang, Haofeng Huang, Yongqi Chen, Will Lin, Zhengzhong Liu, Ion Stoica, Eric P. Xing, Hao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling video diffusion transformers (DiTs) is limited by their quadratic 3D attention, even though most of the attention mass concentrates on a small subset of positions. We turn this observation into VSA, a trainable, hardware-efficient sparse attention that replaces full attention at both training and inference. In VSA, a lightweight coarse stage pools tokens into tiles and identifies high-weight critical tokens; a fine stage computes token-level attention only inside those tiles subjecting to block computing layout to ensure hard efficiency. This leads to a single differentiable kernel that trains end-to-end, requires no post-hoc profiling, and sustains 85\% of FlashAttention3 MFU. We perform a large sweep of ablation studies and scaling-law experiments by pretraining DiTs from 60M to 1.4B parameters. VSA reaches a Pareto point that cuts training FLOPS by 2.53times with no drop in diffusion loss. Retrofitting the open-source Wan-2.1 model speeds up attention time by 6times and lowers end-to-end generation time from 31s to 18s with comparable quality. These results establish trainable sparse attention as a practical alternative to full attention and a key enabler for further scaling of video diffusion models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13389</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdaptThink: Reasoning Models Can Learn When to Think</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13417</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13417.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiajie Zhang, Nianyi Lin, Lei Hou, Ling Feng, Juanzi Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, large reasoning models have achieved impressive performance on various tasks by employing human-like deep thinking. However, the lengthy thinking process substantially increases inference overhead, making efficiency a critical bottleneck. In this work, we first demonstrate that NoThinking, which prompts the reasoning model to skip thinking and directly generate the final solution, is a better choice for relatively simple tasks in terms of both performance and efficiency. Motivated by this, we propose AdaptThink, a novel RL algorithm to teach reasoning models to choose the optimal thinking mode adaptively based on problem difficulty. Specifically, AdaptThink features two core components: (1) a constrained optimization objective that encourages the model to choose NoThinking while maintaining the overall performance; (2) an importance sampling strategy that balances Thinking and NoThinking samples during on-policy training, thereby enabling cold start and allowing the model to explore and exploit both thinking modes throughout the training process. Our experiments indicate that AdaptThink significantly reduces the inference costs while further enhancing performance. Notably, on three math datasets, AdaptThink reduces the average response length of DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-1.5B by 53% and improves its accuracy by 2.4%, highlighting the promise of adaptive thinking-mode selection for optimizing the balance between reasoning quality and efficiency. Our codes and models are available at https://github.com/THU-KEG/AdaptThink.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13417</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:50:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MM-PRM: Enhancing Multimodal Mathematical Reasoning with Scalable   Step-Level Supervision</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13427</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13427.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lingxiao Du, Fanqing Meng, Zongkai Liu, Zhixiang Zhou, Ping Luo, Qiaosheng Zhang, Wenqi Shao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have achieved impressive progress in vision-language understanding, they still struggle with complex multi-step reasoning, often producing logically inconsistent or partially correct solutions. A key limitation lies in the lack of fine-grained supervision over intermediate reasoning steps. To address this, we propose MM-PRM, a process reward model trained within a fully automated, scalable framework. We first build MM-Policy, a strong multimodal model trained on diverse mathematical reasoning data. Then, we construct MM-K12, a curated dataset of 10,000 multimodal math problems with verifiable answers, which serves as seed data. Leveraging a Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS)-based pipeline, we generate over 700k step-level annotations without human labeling. The resulting PRM is used to score candidate reasoning paths in the Best-of-N inference setup and achieves significant improvements across both in-domain (MM-K12 test set) and out-of-domain (OlympiadBench, MathVista, etc.) benchmarks. Further analysis confirms the effectiveness of soft labels, smaller learning rates, and path diversity in optimizing PRM performance. MM-PRM demonstrates that process supervision is a powerful tool for enhancing the logical robustness of multimodal reasoning systems. We release all our codes and data at https://github.com/ModalMinds/MM-PRM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13427</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:55:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fine-tuning Quantized Neural Networks with Zeroth-order Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13430</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13430.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sifeng Shang, Jiayi Zhou, Chenyu Lin, Minxian Li, Kaiyang Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As the size of large language models grows exponentially, GPU memory has become a bottleneck for adapting these models to downstream tasks. In this paper, we aim to push the limits of memory-efficient training by minimizing memory usage on model weights, gradients, and optimizer states, within a unified framework. Our idea is to eliminate both gradients and optimizer states using zeroth-order optimization, which approximates gradients by perturbing weights during forward passes to identify gradient directions. To minimize memory usage on weights, we employ model quantization, e.g., converting from bfloat16 to int4. However, directly applying zeroth-order optimization to quantized weights is infeasible due to the precision gap between discrete weights and continuous gradients, which would otherwise require de-quantization and re-quantization. To overcome this challenge, we propose Quantized Zeroth-order Optimization (QZO), a novel approach that perturbs the continuous quantization scale for gradient estimation and uses a directional derivative clipping method to stabilize training. QZO is orthogonal to both scalar-based and codebook-based post-training quantization methods. Compared to full-parameter fine-tuning in bfloat16, QZO can reduce the total memory cost by more than 18times for 4-bit LLMs, and enables fine-tuning Llama-2-13B and Stable Diffusion 3.5 Large within a single 24GB GPU.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13430</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:55:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Anytime Reasoning via Budget Relative Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13438</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13438.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Penghui Qi, Zichen Liu, Tianyu Pang, Chao Du, Wee Sun Lee, Min Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling test-time compute is crucial for enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). Existing approaches typically employ reinforcement learning (RL) to maximize a verifiable reward obtained at the end of reasoning traces. However, such methods optimize only the final performance under a large and fixed token budget, which hinders efficiency in both training and deployment. In this work, we present a novel framework, AnytimeReasoner, to optimize anytime reasoning performance, which aims to improve token efficiency and the flexibility of reasoning under varying token budget constraints. To achieve this, we truncate the complete thinking process to fit within sampled token budgets from a prior distribution, compelling the model to summarize the optimal answer for each truncated thinking for verification. This introduces verifiable dense rewards into the reasoning process, facilitating more effective credit assignment in RL optimization. We then optimize the thinking and summary policies in a decoupled manner to maximize the cumulative reward. Additionally, we introduce a novel variance reduction technique, Budget Relative Policy Optimization (BRPO), to enhance the robustness and efficiency of the learning process when reinforcing the thinking policy. Empirical results in mathematical reasoning tasks demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms GRPO across all thinking budgets under various prior distributions, enhancing both training and token efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13438</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChartMuseum: Testing Visual Reasoning Capabilities of Large   Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13444</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13444.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liyan Tang, Grace Kim, Xinyu Zhao, Thom Lake, Wenxuan Ding, Fangcong Yin, Prasann Singhal, Manya Wadhwa, Zeyu Leo Liu, Zayne Sprague, Ramya Namuduri, Bodun Hu, Juan Diego Rodriguez, Puyuan Peng, Greg Durrett&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chart understanding presents a unique challenge for large vision-language models (LVLMs), as it requires the integration of sophisticated textual and visual reasoning capabilities. However, current LVLMs exhibit a notable imbalance between these skills, falling short on visual reasoning that is difficult to perform in text. We conduct a case study using a synthetic dataset solvable only through visual reasoning and show that model performance degrades significantly with increasing visual complexity, while human performance remains robust. We then introduce ChartMuseum, a new Chart Question Answering (QA) benchmark containing 1,162 expert-annotated questions spanning multiple reasoning types, curated from real-world charts across 184 sources, specifically built to evaluate complex visual and textual reasoning. Unlike prior chart understanding benchmarks -- where frontier models perform similarly and near saturation -- our benchmark exposes a substantial gap between model and human performance, while effectively differentiating model capabilities: although humans achieve 93% accuracy, the best-performing model Gemini-2.5-Pro attains only 63.0%, and the leading open-source LVLM Qwen2.5-VL-72B-Instruct achieves only 38.5%. Moreover, on questions requiring primarily visual reasoning, all models experience a 35%-55% performance drop from text-reasoning-heavy question performance. Lastly, our qualitative error analysis reveals specific categories of visual reasoning that are challenging for current LVLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13444</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:59:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EfficientLLM: Efficiency in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13840</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13840.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengqing Yuan, Weixiang Sun, Yixin Liu, Huichi Zhou, Rong Zhou, Yiyang Li, Zheyuan Zhang, Wei Song, Yue Huang, Haolong Jia, Keerthiram Murugesan, Yu Wang, Lifang He, Jianfeng Gao, Lichao Sun, Yanfang Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have driven significant progress, yet their growing parameter counts and context windows incur prohibitive compute, energy, and monetary costs. We introduce EfficientLLM, a novel benchmark and the first comprehensive empirical study evaluating efficiency techniques for LLMs at scale. Conducted on a production-class cluster (48xGH200, 8xH200 GPUs), our study systematically explores three key axes: (1) architecture pretraining (efficient attention variants: MQA, GQA, MLA, NSA; sparse Mixture-of-Experts (MoE)), (2) fine-tuning (parameter-efficient methods: LoRA, RSLoRA, DoRA), and (3) inference (quantization methods: int4, float16). We define six fine-grained metrics (Memory Utilization, Compute Utilization, Latency, Throughput, Energy Consumption, Compression Rate) to capture hardware saturation, latency-throughput balance, and carbon cost. Evaluating over 100 model-technique pairs (0.5B-72B parameters), we derive three core insights: (i) Efficiency involves quantifiable trade-offs: no single method is universally optimal; e.g., MoE reduces FLOPs and improves accuracy but increases VRAM by 40%, while int4 quantization cuts memory/energy by up to 3.9x at a 3-5% accuracy drop. (ii) Optima are task- and scale-dependent: MQA offers optimal memory-latency trade-offs for constrained devices, MLA achieves lowest perplexity for quality-critical tasks, and RSLoRA surpasses LoRA efficiency only beyond 14B parameters. (iii) Techniques generalize across modalities: we extend evaluations to Large Vision Models (Stable Diffusion 3.5, Wan 2.1) and Vision-Language Models (Qwen2.5-VL), confirming effective transferability. By open-sourcing datasets, evaluation pipelines, and leaderboards, EfficientLLM provides essential guidance for researchers and engineers navigating the efficiency-performance landscape of next-generation foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13840</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 02:27:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Path Compression: Compressing Generation Trajectories for   Efficient LLM Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13866</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13866.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiwon Song, Dongwon Jo, Yulhwa Kim, Jae-Joon Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reasoning-focused language models achieve high accuracy by generating lengthy intermediate reasoning paths before producing final answers. While this approach is effective in solving problems that require logical thinking, long reasoning paths significantly increase memory usage and throughput of token generation, limiting the practical deployment of such models. We propose Reasoning Path Compression (RPC), a training-free method that accelerates inference by leveraging the semantic sparsity of reasoning paths. RPC periodically compresses the KV cache by retaining KV cache that receive high importance score, which are computed using a selector window composed of recently generated queries. Experiments show that RPC improves generation throughput of QwQ-32B by up to 1.60times compared to the inference with full KV cache, with an accuracy drop of 1.2% on the AIME 2024 benchmark. Our findings demonstrate that semantic sparsity in reasoning traces can be effectively exploited for compression, offering a practical path toward efficient deployment of reasoning LLMs. Our code is available at https://github.com/jiwonsong-dev/ReasoningPathCompression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13866</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 03:21:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Agent Training for Computer Use</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13909</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13909.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanheng He, Jiahe Jin, Pengfei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling up high-quality trajectory data has long been a critical bottleneck for developing human-like computer use agents. We introduce PC Agent-E, an efficient agent training framework that significantly reduces reliance on large-scale human demonstrations. Starting with just 312 human-annotated computer use trajectories, we further improved data quality by synthesizing diverse action decisions with Claude 3.7 Sonnet. Trained on these enriched trajectories, our PC Agent-E model achieved a remarkable 141% relative improvement, surpassing the strong Claude 3.7 Sonnet with extended thinking on WindowsAgentArena-V2, an improved benchmark we also released. Furthermore, PC Agent-E demonstrates strong generalizability to different operating systems on OSWorld. Our findings suggest that strong computer use capabilities can be stimulated from a small amount of high-quality trajectory data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13909</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 04:20:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLVR-World: Training World Models with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13934</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13934.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jialong Wu, Shaofeng Yin, Ningya Feng, Mingsheng Long&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; World models predict state transitions in response to actions and are increasingly developed across diverse modalities. However, standard training objectives such as maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) often misalign with task-specific goals of world models, i.e., transition prediction metrics like accuracy or perceptual quality. In this paper, we present RLVR-World, a unified framework that leverages reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) to directly optimize world models for such metrics. Despite formulating world modeling as autoregressive prediction of tokenized sequences, RLVR-World evaluates metrics of decoded predictions as verifiable rewards. We demonstrate substantial performance gains on both language- and video-based world models across domains, including text games, web navigation, and robot manipulation. Our work indicates that, beyond recent advances in reasoning language models, RLVR offers a promising post-training paradigm for enhancing the utility of generative models more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13934</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 05:02:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Instruction Bottleneck Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13946</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13946.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Changdae Oh, Jiatong Li, Shawn Im, Yixuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite widespread adoption, multimodal large language models (MLLMs) suffer performance degradation when encountering unfamiliar queries under distribution shifts. Existing methods to improve MLLM generalization typically require either more instruction data or larger advanced model architectures, both of which incur non-trivial human labor or computational costs. In this work, we take an alternative approach to enhance the robustness of MLLMs under distribution shifts, from a representation learning perspective. Inspired by the information bottleneck (IB) principle, we derive a variational lower bound of the IB for MLLMs and devise a practical implementation, Visual Instruction Bottleneck Tuning (Vittle). We then provide a theoretical justification of Vittle by revealing its connection to an information-theoretic robustness metric of MLLM. Empirical validation of three MLLMs on open-ended and closed-form question answering and object hallucination detection tasks over 45 datasets, including 30 shift scenarios, demonstrates that Vittle consistently improves the MLLM's robustness under shifts by pursuing the learning of a minimal sufficient representation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13946</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 05:24:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hunyuan-Game: Industrial-grade Intelligent Game Creation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14135</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14135.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruihuang Li, Caijin Zhou, Shoujian Zheng, Jianxiang Lu, Jiabin Huang, Comi Chen, Junshu Tang, Guangzheng Xu, Jiale Tao, Hongmei Wang, Donghao Li, Wenqing Yu, Senbo Wang, Zhimin Li, Yetshuan Shi, Haoyu Yang, Yukun Wang, Wenxun Dai, Jiaqi Li, Linqing Wang, Qixun Wang, Zhiyong Xu, Yingfang Zhang, Jiangfeng Xiong, Weijie Kong, Chao Zhang, Hongxin Zhang, Qiaoling Zheng, Weiting Guo, Xinchi Deng, Yixuan Li, Renjia Wei, Yulin Jian, Duojun Huang, Xuhua Ren, Sihuan Lin, Yifu Sun, Yuan Zhou, Joey Wang, Qin Lin, Jingmiao Yu, Jihong Zhang, Caesar Zhong, Di Wang, Yuhong Liu, Linus, Jie Jiang, Longhuang Wu, Shuai Shao, Qinglin Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Intelligent game creation represents a transformative advancement in game development, utilizing generative artificial intelligence to dynamically generate and enhance game content. Despite notable progress in generative models, the comprehensive synthesis of high-quality game assets, including both images and videos, remains a challenging frontier. To create high-fidelity game content that simultaneously aligns with player preferences and significantly boosts designer efficiency, we present Hunyuan-Game, an innovative project designed to revolutionize intelligent game production. Hunyuan-Game encompasses two primary branches: image generation and video generation. The image generation component is built upon a vast dataset comprising billions of game images, leading to the development of a group of customized image generation models tailored for game scenarios: (1) General Text-to-Image Generation. (2) Game Visual Effects Generation, involving text-to-effect and reference image-based game visual effect generation. (3) Transparent Image Generation for characters, scenes, and game visual effects. (4) Game Character Generation based on sketches, black-and-white images, and white models. The video generation component is built upon a comprehensive dataset of millions of game and anime videos, leading to the development of five core algorithmic models, each targeting critical pain points in game development and having robust adaptation to diverse game video scenarios: (1) Image-to-Video Generation. (2) 360 A/T Pose Avatar Video Synthesis. (3) Dynamic Illustration Generation. (4) Generative Video Super-Resolution. (5) Interactive Game Video Generation. These image and video generation models not only exhibit high-level aesthetic expression but also deeply integrate domain-specific knowledge, establishing a systematic understanding of diverse game and anime art styles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14135</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 09:39:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniVG-R1: Reasoning Guided Universal Visual Grounding with Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14231</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14231.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sule Bai, Mingxing Li, Yong Liu, Jing Tang, Haoji Zhang, Lei Sun, Xiangxiang Chu, Yansong Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional visual grounding methods primarily focus on single-image scenarios with simple textual references. However, extending these methods to real-world scenarios that involve implicit and complex instructions, particularly in conjunction with multiple images, poses significant challenges, which is mainly due to the lack of advanced reasoning ability across diverse multi-modal contexts. In this work, we aim to address the more practical universal grounding task, and propose UniVG-R1, a reasoning guided multimodal large language model (MLLM) for universal visual grounding, which enhances reasoning capabilities through reinforcement learning (RL) combined with cold-start data. Specifically, we first construct a high-quality Chain-of-Thought (CoT) grounding dataset, annotated with detailed reasoning chains, to guide the model towards correct reasoning paths via supervised fine-tuning. Subsequently, we perform rule-based reinforcement learning to encourage the model to identify correct reasoning chains, thereby incentivizing its reasoning capabilities. In addition, we identify a difficulty bias arising from the prevalence of easy samples as RL training progresses, and we propose a difficulty-aware weight adjustment strategy to further strengthen the performance. Experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of UniVG-R1, which achieves state-of-the-art performance on MIG-Bench with a 9.1% improvement over the previous method. Furthermore, our model exhibits strong generalizability, achieving an average improvement of 23.4% in zero-shot performance across four image and video reasoning grounding benchmarks. The project page can be accessed at https://amap-ml.github.io/UniVG-R1-page/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14231</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 11:40:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Agentic Reinforcement Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14246</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14246.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyu Liu, Yuhang Zang, Yushan Zou, Zijian Liang, Xiaoyi Dong, Yuhang Cao, Haodong Duan, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A key trend in Large Reasoning Models (e.g., OpenAI's o3) is the native agentic ability to use external tools such as web browsers for searching and writing/executing code for image manipulation to think with images. In the open-source research community, while significant progress has been made in language-only agentic abilities such as function calling and tool integration, the development of multi-modal agentic capabilities that involve truly thinking with images, and their corresponding benchmarks, are still less explored. This work highlights the effectiveness of Visual Agentic Reinforcement Fine-Tuning (Visual-ARFT) for enabling flexible and adaptive reasoning abilities for Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs). With Visual-ARFT, open-source LVLMs gain the ability to browse websites for real-time information updates and write code to manipulate and analyze input images through cropping, rotation, and other image processing techniques. We also present a Multi-modal Agentic Tool Bench (MAT) with two settings (MAT-Search and MAT-Coding) designed to evaluate LVLMs' agentic search and coding abilities. Our experimental results demonstrate that Visual-ARFT outperforms its baseline by +18.6% F1 / +13.0% EM on MAT-Coding and +10.3% F1 / +8.7% EM on MAT-Search, ultimately surpassing GPT-4o. Visual-ARFT also achieves +29.3 F1% / +25.9% EM gains on existing multi-hop QA benchmarks such as 2Wiki and HotpotQA, demonstrating strong generalization capabilities. Our findings suggest that Visual-ARFT offers a promising path toward building robust and generalizable multimodal agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14246</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 11:59:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Law for Quantization-Aware Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14302</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14302.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengzhao Chen, Chaoyi Zhang, Jing Liu, Yutao Zeng, Zeyue Xue, Zhiheng Liu, Yunshui Li, Jin Ma, Jie Huang, Xun Zhou, Ping Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) demand substantial computational and memory resources, creating deployment challenges. Quantization-aware training (QAT) addresses these challenges by reducing model precision while maintaining performance. However, the scaling behavior of QAT, especially at 4-bit precision (W4A4), is not well understood. Existing QAT scaling laws often ignore key factors such as the number of training tokens and quantization granularity, which limits their applicability. This paper proposes a unified scaling law for QAT that models quantization error as a function of model size, training data volume, and quantization group size. Through 268 QAT experiments, we show that quantization error decreases as model size increases, but rises with more training tokens and coarser quantization granularity. To identify the sources of W4A4 quantization error, we decompose it into weight and activation components. Both components follow the overall trend of W4A4 quantization error, but with different sensitivities. Specifically, weight quantization error increases more rapidly with more training tokens. Further analysis shows that the activation quantization error in the FC2 layer, caused by outliers, is the primary bottleneck of W4A4 QAT quantization error. By applying mixed-precision quantization to address this bottleneck, we demonstrate that weight and activation quantization errors can converge to similar levels. Additionally, with more training data, weight quantization error eventually exceeds activation quantization error, suggesting that reducing weight quantization error is also important in such scenarios. These findings offer key insights for improving QAT research and development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14302</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 12:54:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vid2World: Crafting Video Diffusion Models to Interactive World Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14357</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14357.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siqiao Huang, Jialong Wu, Qixing Zhou, Shangchen Miao, Mingsheng Long&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; World models, which predict transitions based on history observation and action sequences, have shown great promise in improving data efficiency for sequential decision making. However, existing world models often require extensive domain-specific training and still produce low-fidelity, coarse predictions, limiting their applicability in complex environments. In contrast, video diffusion models trained on large, internet-scale datasets have demonstrated impressive capabilities in generating high-quality videos that capture diverse real-world dynamics. In this work, we present Vid2World, a general approach for leveraging and transferring pre-trained video diffusion models into interactive world models. To bridge the gap, Vid2World performs casualization of a pre-trained video diffusion model by crafting its architecture and training objective to enable autoregressive generation. Furthermore, it introduces a causal action guidance mechanism to enhance action controllability in the resulting interactive world model. Extensive experiments in robot manipulation and game simulation domains show that our method offers a scalable and effective approach for repurposing highly capable video diffusion models to interactive world models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14357</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 13:41:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VisualQuality-R1: Reasoning-Induced Image Quality Assessment via   Reinforcement Learning to Rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14460</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14460.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianhe Wu, Jian Zou, Jie Liang, Lei Zhang, Kede Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; DeepSeek-R1 has demonstrated remarkable effectiveness in incentivizing reasoning and generalization capabilities of large language models (LLMs) through reinforcement learning. Nevertheless, the potential of reasoning-induced computational modeling has not been thoroughly explored in the context of image quality assessment (IQA), a task critically dependent on visual reasoning. In this paper, we introduce VisualQuality-R1, a reasoning-induced no-reference IQA (NR-IQA) model, and we train it with reinforcement learning to rank, a learning algorithm tailored to the intrinsically relative nature of visual quality. Specifically, for a pair of images, we employ group relative policy optimization to generate multiple quality scores for each image. These estimates are then used to compute comparative probabilities of one image having higher quality than the other under the Thurstone model. Rewards for each quality estimate are defined using continuous fidelity measures rather than discretized binary labels. Extensive experiments show that the proposed VisualQuality-R1 consistently outperforms discriminative deep learning-based NR-IQA models as well as a recent reasoning-induced quality regression method. Moreover, VisualQuality-R1 is capable of generating contextually rich, human-aligned quality descriptions, and supports multi-dataset training without requiring perceptual scale realignment. These features make VisualQuality-R1 especially well-suited for reliably measuring progress in a wide range of image processing tasks like super-resolution and image generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14460</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 14:56:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Models Better Express Their Confidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14489</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14489.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dongkeun Yoon, Seungone Kim, Sohee Yang, Sunkyoung Kim, Soyeon Kim, Yongil Kim, Eunbi Choi, Yireun Kim, Minjoon Seo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite their strengths, large language models (LLMs) often fail to communicate their confidence accurately, making it difficult to assess when they might be wrong and limiting their reliability. In this work, we demonstrate that reasoning models-LLMs that engage in extended chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning-exhibit superior performance not only in problem-solving but also in accurately expressing their confidence. Specifically, we benchmark six reasoning models across six datasets and find that they achieve strictly better confidence calibration than their non-reasoning counterparts in 33 out of the 36 settings. Our detailed analysis reveals that these gains in calibration stem from the slow thinking behaviors of reasoning models-such as exploring alternative approaches and backtracking-which enable them to adjust their confidence dynamically throughout their CoT, making it progressively more accurate. In particular, we find that reasoning models become increasingly better calibrated as their CoT unfolds, a trend not observed in non-reasoning models. Moreover, removing slow thinking behaviors from the CoT leads to a significant drop in calibration. Lastly, we show that these gains are not exclusive to reasoning models-non-reasoning models also benefit when guided to perform slow thinking via in-context learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14489</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 15:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Flow Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14513</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14513.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yen-Chen Wu, Feng-Ting Liao, Meng-Hsi Chen, Pei-Chen Ho, Farhang Nabiei, Da-shan Shiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Transformers, the standard implementation for large language models (LLMs), typically consist of tens to hundreds of discrete layers. While more layers can lead to better performance, this approach has been challenged as far from efficient, especially given the superiority of continuous layers demonstrated by diffusion and flow-based models for image generation. We propose the Latent Flow Transformer (LFT), which replaces a block of layers with a single learned transport operator trained via flow matching, offering significant compression while maintaining compatibility with the original architecture. Additionally, we address the limitations of existing flow-based methods in preserving coupling by introducing the Flow Walking (FW) algorithm. On the Pythia-410M model, LFT trained with flow matching compresses 6 of 24 layers and outperforms directly skipping 2 layers (KL Divergence of LM logits at 0.407 vs. 0.529), demonstrating the feasibility of this design. When trained with FW, LFT further distills 12 layers into one while reducing the KL to 0.736 surpassing that from skipping 3 layers (0.932), significantly narrowing the gap between autoregressive and flow-based generation paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14513</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 15:41:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Let LLMs Break Free from Overthinking via Self-Braking Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14604</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14604.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran Zhao, Yuchen Yan, Yongliang Shen, Haolei Xu, Wenqi Zhang, Kaitao Song, Jian Shao, Weiming Lu, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs), such as OpenAI o1 and DeepSeek-R1, have significantly enhanced their reasoning capabilities by generating longer chains of thought, demonstrating outstanding performance across a variety of tasks. However, this performance gain comes at the cost of a substantial increase in redundant reasoning during the generation process, leading to high computational overhead and exacerbating the issue of overthinking. Although numerous existing approaches aim to address the problem of overthinking, they often rely on external interventions. In this paper, we propose a novel framework, Self-Braking Tuning (SBT), which tackles overthinking from the perspective of allowing the model to regulate its own reasoning process, thus eliminating the reliance on external control mechanisms. We construct a set of overthinking identification metrics based on standard answers and design a systematic method to detect redundant reasoning. This method accurately identifies unnecessary steps within the reasoning trajectory and generates training signals for learning self-regulation behaviors. Building on this foundation, we develop a complete strategy for constructing data with adaptive reasoning lengths and introduce an innovative braking prompt mechanism that enables the model to naturally learn when to terminate reasoning at an appropriate point. Experiments across mathematical benchmarks (AIME, AMC, MATH500, GSM8K) demonstrate that our method reduces token consumption by up to 60% while maintaining comparable accuracy to unconstrained models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14604</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 16:53:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TinyV: Reducing False Negatives in Verification Improves RL for LLM   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14625</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14625.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhangchen Xu, Yuetai Li, Fengqing Jiang, Bhaskar Ramasubramanian, Luyao Niu, Bill Yuchen Lin, Radha Poovendran&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning (RL) has become a powerful tool for enhancing the reasoning abilities of large language models (LLMs) by optimizing their policies with reward signals. Yet, RL's success relies on the reliability of rewards, which are provided by verifiers. In this paper, we expose and analyze a widespread problem--false negatives--where verifiers wrongly reject correct model outputs. Our in-depth study of the Big-Math-RL-Verified dataset reveals that over 38% of model-generated responses suffer from false negatives, where the verifier fails to recognize correct answers. We show, both empirically and theoretically, that these false negatives severely impair RL training by depriving the model of informative gradient signals and slowing convergence. To mitigate this, we propose tinyV, a lightweight LLM-based verifier that augments existing rule-based methods, which dynamically identifies potential false negatives and recovers valid responses to produce more accurate reward estimates. Across multiple math-reasoning benchmarks, integrating TinyV boosts pass rates by up to 10% and accelerates convergence relative to the baseline. Our findings highlight the critical importance of addressing verifier false negatives and offer a practical approach to improve RL-based fine-tuning of LLMs. Our code is available at https://github.com/uw-nsl/TinyV.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14625</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:16:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Think Only When You Need with Large Hybrid-Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14631</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14631.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lingjie Jiang, Xun Wu, Shaohan Huang, Qingxiu Dong, Zewen Chi, Li Dong, Xingxing Zhang, Tengchao Lv, Lei Cui, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have shown substantially improved reasoning capabilities over traditional Large Language Models (LLMs) by incorporating extended thinking processes prior to producing final responses. However, excessively lengthy thinking introduces substantial overhead in terms of token consumption and latency, which is particularly unnecessary for simple queries. In this work, we introduce Large Hybrid-Reasoning Models (LHRMs), the first kind of model capable of adaptively determining whether to perform thinking based on the contextual information of user queries. To achieve this, we propose a two-stage training pipeline comprising Hybrid Fine-Tuning (HFT) as a cold start, followed by online reinforcement learning with the proposed Hybrid Group Policy Optimization (HGPO) to implicitly learn to select the appropriate thinking mode. Furthermore, we introduce a metric called Hybrid Accuracy to quantitatively assess the model's capability for hybrid thinking. Extensive experimental results show that LHRMs can adaptively perform hybrid thinking on queries of varying difficulty and type. It outperforms existing LRMs and LLMs in reasoning and general capabilities while significantly improving efficiency. Together, our work advocates for a reconsideration of the appropriate use of extended thinking processes and provides a solid starting point for building hybrid thinking systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14631</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:23:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoEval-Pro: Robust and Realistic Long Video Understanding Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14640</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14640.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wentao Ma, Weiming Ren, Yiming Jia, Zhuofeng Li, Ping Nie, Ge Zhang, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large multimodal models (LMMs) have recently emerged as a powerful tool for long video understanding (LVU), prompting the development of standardized LVU benchmarks to evaluate their performance. However, our investigation reveals a rather sober lesson for existing LVU benchmarks. First, most existing benchmarks rely heavily on multiple-choice questions (MCQs), whose evaluation results are inflated due to the possibility of guessing the correct answer; Second, a significant portion of questions in these benchmarks have strong priors to allow models to answer directly without even reading the input video. For example, Gemini-1.5-Pro can achieve over 50\% accuracy given a random frame from a long video on Video-MME. We also observe that increasing the number of frames does not necessarily lead to improvement on existing benchmarks, which is counterintuitive. As a result, the validity and robustness of current LVU benchmarks are undermined, impeding a faithful assessment of LMMs' long-video understanding capability. To tackle this problem, we propose VideoEval-Pro, a realistic LVU benchmark containing questions with open-ended short-answer, which truly require understanding the entire video. VideoEval-Pro assesses both segment-level and full-video understanding through perception and reasoning tasks. By evaluating 21 proprietary and open-source video LMMs, we conclude the following findings: (1) video LMMs show drastic performance (&gt;25\%) drops on open-ended questions compared with MCQs; (2) surprisingly, higher MCQ scores do not lead to higher open-ended scores on VideoEval-Pro; (3) compared to other MCQ benchmarks, VideoEval-Pro benefits more from increasing the number of input frames. Our results show that VideoEval-Pro offers a more realistic and reliable measure of long video understanding, providing a clearer view of progress in this domain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14640</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:26:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General-Reasoner: Advancing LLM Reasoning Across All Domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14652</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14652.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xueguang Ma, Qian Liu, Dongfu Jiang, Ge Zhang, Zejun Ma, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) has recently demonstrated strong potential in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). Particularly, the "Zero" reinforcement learning introduced by Deepseek-R1-Zero, enables direct RL training of base LLMs without relying on an intermediate supervised fine-tuning stage. Despite these advancements, current works for LLM reasoning mainly focus on mathematical and coding domains, largely due to data abundance and the ease of answer verification. This limits the applicability and generalization of such models to broader domains, where questions often have diverse answer representations, and data is more scarce. In this paper, we propose General-Reasoner, a novel training paradigm designed to enhance LLM reasoning capabilities across diverse domains. Our key contributions include: (1) constructing a large-scale, high-quality dataset of questions with verifiable answers curated by web crawling, covering a wide range of disciplines; and (2) developing a generative model-based answer verifier, which replaces traditional rule-based verification with the capability of chain-of-thought and context-awareness. We train a series of models and evaluate them on a wide range of datasets covering wide domains like physics, chemistry, finance, electronics etc. Our comprehensive evaluation across these 12 benchmarks (e.g. MMLU-Pro, GPQA, SuperGPQA, TheoremQA, BBEH and MATH AMC) demonstrates that General-Reasoner outperforms existing baseline methods, achieving robust and generalizable reasoning performance while maintaining superior effectiveness in mathematical reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14652</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:41:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This Time is Different: An Observability Perspective on Time Series   Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14766</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14766.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ben Cohen, Emaad Khwaja, Youssef Doubli, Salahidine Lemaachi, Chris Lettieri, Charles Masson, Hugo Miccinilli, Elise Ramé, Qiqi Ren, Afshin Rostamizadeh, Jean Ogier du Terrail, Anna-Monica Toon, Kan Wang, Stephan Xie, David Asker, Ameet Talwalkar, Othmane Abou-Amal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Toto, a time series forecasting foundation model with 151 million parameters. Toto uses a modern decoder-only architecture coupled with architectural innovations designed to account for specific challenges found in multivariate observability time series data. Toto's pre-training corpus is a mixture of observability data, open datasets, and synthetic data, and is 4-10times larger than those of leading time series foundation models. Additionally, we introduce BOOM, a large-scale benchmark consisting of 350 million observations across 2,807 real-world time series. For both Toto and BOOM, we source observability data exclusively from Datadog's own telemetry and internal observability metrics. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that Toto achieves state-of-the-art performance on both BOOM and on established general purpose time series forecasting benchmarks. Toto's model weights, inference code, and evaluation scripts, as well as BOOM's data and evaluation code, are all available as open source under the Apache 2.0 License available at https://huggingface.co/Datadog/Toto-Open-Base-1.0 and https://github.com/DataDog/toto.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14766</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:48:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training-Free Watermarking for Autoregressive Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14673</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14673.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Tong, Zihao Pan, Shuai Yang, Kaiyang Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Invisible image watermarking can protect image ownership and prevent malicious misuse of visual generative models. However, existing generative watermarking methods are mainly designed for diffusion models while watermarking for autoregressive image generation models remains largely underexplored. We propose IndexMark, a training-free watermarking framework for autoregressive image generation models. IndexMark is inspired by the redundancy property of the codebook: replacing autoregressively generated indices with similar indices produces negligible visual differences. The core component in IndexMark is a simple yet effective match-then-replace method, which carefully selects watermark tokens from the codebook based on token similarity, and promotes the use of watermark tokens through token replacement, thereby embedding the watermark without affecting the image quality. Watermark verification is achieved by calculating the proportion of watermark tokens in generated images, with precision further improved by an Index Encoder. Furthermore, we introduce an auxiliary validation scheme to enhance robustness against cropping attacks. Experiments demonstrate that IndexMark achieves state-of-the-art performance in terms of image quality and verification accuracy, and exhibits robustness against various perturbations, including cropping, noises, Gaussian blur, random erasing, color jittering, and JPEG compression.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14673</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:58:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reward Reasoning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14674</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14674.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaxin Guo, Zewen Chi, Li Dong, Qingxiu Dong, Xun Wu, Shaohan Huang, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward models play a critical role in guiding large language models toward outputs that align with human expectations. However, an open challenge remains in effectively utilizing test-time compute to enhance reward model performance. In this work, we introduce Reward Reasoning Models (RRMs), which are specifically designed to execute a deliberate reasoning process before generating final rewards. Through chain-of-thought reasoning, RRMs leverage additional test-time compute for complex queries where appropriate rewards are not immediately apparent. To develop RRMs, we implement a reinforcement learning framework that fosters self-evolved reward reasoning capabilities without requiring explicit reasoning traces as training data. Experimental results demonstrate that RRMs achieve superior performance on reward modeling benchmarks across diverse domains. Notably, we show that RRMs can adaptively exploit test-time compute to further improve reward accuracy. The pretrained reward reasoning models are available at https://huggingface.co/Reward-Reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14674</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:58:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visionary-R1: Mitigating Shortcuts in Visual Reasoning with   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14677</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14677.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaer Xia, Yuhang Zang, Peng Gao, Yixuan Li, Kaiyang Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Learning general-purpose reasoning capabilities has long been a challenging problem in AI. Recent research in large language models (LLMs), such as DeepSeek-R1, has shown that reinforcement learning techniques like GRPO can enable pre-trained LLMs to develop reasoning capabilities using simple question-answer pairs. In this paper, we aim to train visual language models (VLMs) to perform reasoning on image data through reinforcement learning and visual question-answer pairs, without any explicit chain-of-thought (CoT) supervision. Our findings indicate that simply applying reinforcement learning to a VLM -- by prompting the model to produce a reasoning chain before providing an answer -- can lead the model to develop shortcuts from easy questions, thereby reducing its ability to generalize across unseen data distributions. We argue that the key to mitigating shortcut learning is to encourage the model to interpret images prior to reasoning. Therefore, we train the model to adhere to a caption-reason-answer output format: initially generating a detailed caption for an image, followed by constructing an extensive reasoning chain. When trained on 273K CoT-free visual question-answer pairs and using only reinforcement learning, our model, named Visionary-R1, outperforms strong multimodal models, such as GPT-4o, Claude3.5-Sonnet, and Gemini-1.5-Pro, on multiple visual reasoning benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14677</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:58:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NExT-Search: Rebuilding User Feedback Ecosystem for Generative AI Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14680</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14680.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sunhao Dai, Wenjie Wang, Liang Pang, Jun Xu, See-Kiong Ng, Ji-Rong Wen, Tat-Seng Chua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative AI search is reshaping information retrieval by offering end-to-end answers to complex queries, reducing users' reliance on manually browsing and summarizing multiple web pages. However, while this paradigm enhances convenience, it disrupts the feedback-driven improvement loop that has historically powered the evolution of traditional Web search. Web search can continuously improve their ranking models by collecting large-scale, fine-grained user feedback (e.g., clicks, dwell time) at the document level. In contrast, generative AI search operates through a much longer search pipeline, spanning query decomposition, document retrieval, and answer generation, yet typically receives only coarse-grained feedback on the final answer. This introduces a feedback loop disconnect, where user feedback for the final output cannot be effectively mapped back to specific system components, making it difficult to improve each intermediate stage and sustain the feedback loop. In this paper, we envision NExT-Search, a next-generation paradigm designed to reintroduce fine-grained, process-level feedback into generative AI search. NExT-Search integrates two complementary modes: User Debug Mode, which allows engaged users to intervene at key stages; and Shadow User Mode, where a personalized user agent simulates user preferences and provides AI-assisted feedback for less interactive users. Furthermore, we envision how these feedback signals can be leveraged through online adaptation, which refines current search outputs in real-time, and offline update, which aggregates interaction logs to periodically fine-tune query decomposition, retrieval, and generation models. By restoring human control over key stages of the generative AI search pipeline, we believe NExT-Search offers a promising direction for building feedback-rich AI search systems that can evolve continuously alongside human feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14680</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:59:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two Experts Are All You Need for Steering Thinking: Reinforcing   Cognitive Effort in MoE Reasoning Models Without Additional Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14681</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14681.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengru Wang, Xingyu Chen, Yue Wang, Zhiwei He, Jiahao Xu, Tian Liang, Qiuzhi Liu, Yunzhi Yao, Wenxuan Wang, Ruotian Ma, Haitao Mi, Ningyu Zhang, Zhaopeng Tu, Xiaolong Li, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architectures within Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have achieved impressive reasoning capabilities by selectively activating experts to facilitate structured cognitive processes. Despite notable advances, existing reasoning models often suffer from cognitive inefficiencies like overthinking and underthinking. To address these limitations, we introduce a novel inference-time steering methodology called Reinforcing Cognitive Experts (RICE), designed to improve reasoning performance without additional training or complex heuristics. Leveraging normalized Pointwise Mutual Information (nPMI), we systematically identify specialized experts, termed ''cognitive experts'' that orchestrate meta-level reasoning operations characterized by tokens like ''&lt;think&gt;''. Empirical evaluations with leading MoE-based LRMs (DeepSeek-R1 and Qwen3-235B) on rigorous quantitative and scientific reasoning benchmarks demonstrate noticeable and consistent improvements in reasoning accuracy, cognitive efficiency, and cross-domain generalization. Crucially, our lightweight approach substantially outperforms prevalent reasoning-steering techniques, such as prompt design and decoding constraints, while preserving the model's general instruction-following skills. These results highlight reinforcing cognitive experts as a promising, practical, and interpretable direction to enhance cognitive efficiency within advanced reasoning models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14681</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emerging Properties in Unified Multimodal Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14683</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14683.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaorui Deng, Deyao Zhu, Kunchang Li, Chenhui Gou, Feng Li, Zeyu Wang, Shu Zhong, Weihao Yu, Xiaonan Nie, Ziang Song, Guang Shi, Haoqi Fan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 117&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unifying multimodal understanding and generation has shown impressive capabilities in cutting-edge proprietary systems. In this work, we introduce BAGEL, an open0source foundational model that natively supports multimodal understanding and generation. BAGEL is a unified, decoder0only model pretrained on trillions of tokens curated from large0scale interleaved text, image, video, and web data. When scaled with such diverse multimodal interleaved data, BAGEL exhibits emerging capabilities in complex multimodal reasoning. As a result, it significantly outperforms open-source unified models in both multimodal generation and understanding across standard benchmarks, while exhibiting advanced multimodal reasoning abilities such as free-form image manipulation, future frame prediction, 3D manipulation, and world navigation. In the hope of facilitating further opportunities for multimodal research, we share the key findings, pretraining details, data creation protocal, and release our code and checkpoints to the community. The project page is at https://bagel-ai.org/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14683</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mind the Gap: Bridging Thought Leap for Improved Chain-of-Thought Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14684</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14684.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haolei Xu, Yuchen Yan, Yongliang Shen, Wenqi Zhang, Guiyang Hou, Shengpei Jiang, Kaitao Song, Weiming Lu, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have achieved remarkable progress on mathematical tasks through Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning. However, existing mathematical CoT datasets often suffer from Thought Leaps due to experts omitting intermediate steps, which negatively impacts model learning and generalization. We propose the CoT Thought Leap Bridge Task, which aims to automatically detect leaps and generate missing intermediate reasoning steps to restore the completeness and coherence of CoT. To facilitate this, we constructed a specialized training dataset called ScaleQM+, based on the structured ScaleQuestMath dataset, and trained CoT-Bridge to bridge thought leaps. Through comprehensive experiments on mathematical reasoning benchmarks, we demonstrate that models fine-tuned on bridged datasets consistently outperform those trained on original datasets, with improvements of up to +5.87% on NuminaMath. Our approach effectively enhances distilled data (+3.02%) and provides better starting points for reinforcement learning (+3.1%), functioning as a plug-and-play module compatible with existing optimization techniques. Furthermore, CoT-Bridge demonstrate improved generalization to out-of-domain logical reasoning tasks, confirming that enhancing reasoning completeness yields broadly applicable benefits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14684</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Reasoning, Losing Control: Evaluating Instruction Following in   Large Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14810</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14810.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tingchen Fu, Jiawei Gu, Yafu Li, Xiaoye Qu, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-following is essential for aligning large language models (LLMs) with user intent. While recent reasoning-oriented models exhibit impressive performance on complex mathematical problems, their ability to adhere to natural language instructions remains underexplored. In this work, we introduce MathIF, a dedicated benchmark for evaluating instruction-following in mathematical reasoning tasks. Our empirical analysis reveals a consistent tension between scaling up reasoning capacity and maintaining controllability, as models that reason more effectively often struggle to comply with user directives. We find that models tuned on distilled long chains-of-thought or trained with reasoning-oriented reinforcement learning often degrade in instruction adherence, especially when generation length increases. Furthermore, we show that even simple interventions can partially recover obedience, though at the cost of reasoning performance. These findings highlight a fundamental tension in current LLM training paradigms and motivate the need for more instruction-aware reasoning models. We release the code and data at https://github.com/TingchenFu/MathIF.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14810</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 18:18:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Text Generation Beyond Discrete Token Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14827</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14827.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yufan Zhuang, Liyuan Liu, Chandan Singh, Jingbo Shang, Jianfeng Gao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In standard autoregressive generation, an LLM predicts the next-token distribution, samples a discrete token, and then discards the distribution, passing only the sampled token as new input. To preserve this distribution's rich information, we propose Mixture of Inputs (MoI), a training-free method for autoregressive generation. After generating a token following the standard paradigm, we construct a new input that blends the generated discrete token with the previously discarded token distribution. Specifically, we employ a Bayesian estimation method that treats the token distribution as the prior, the sampled token as the observation, and replaces the conventional one-hot vector with the continuous posterior expectation as the new model input. MoI allows the model to maintain a richer internal representation throughout the generation process, resulting in improved text quality and reasoning capabilities. On mathematical reasoning, code generation, and PhD-level QA tasks, MoI consistently improves performance across multiple models including QwQ-32B, Nemotron-Super-49B, Gemma-3-27B, and DAPO-Qwen-32B, with no additional training and negligible computational overhead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14827</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 18:41:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion vs. Autoregressive Language Models: A Text Embedding   Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15045</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15045.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyue Zhang, Yilun Zhao, Liyuan Geng, Arman Cohan, Anh Tuan Luu, Chen Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM)-based embedding models, benefiting from large scale pre-training and post-training, have begun to surpass BERT and T5-based models on general-purpose text embedding tasks such as document retrieval. However, a fundamental limitation of LLM embeddings lies in the unidirectional attention used during autoregressive pre-training, which misaligns with the bidirectional nature of text embedding tasks. To this end, We propose adopting diffusion language models for text embeddings, motivated by their inherent bidirectional architecture and recent success in matching or surpassing LLMs especially on reasoning tasks. We present the first systematic study of the diffusion language embedding model, which outperforms the LLM-based embedding model by 20% on long-document retrieval, 8% on reasoning-intensive retrieval, 2% on instruction-following retrieval, and achieve competitive performance on traditional text embedding benchmarks. Our analysis verifies that bidirectional attention is crucial for encoding global context in long and complex text.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15045</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 02:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>lmgame-Bench: How Good are LLMs at Playing Games?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15146</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15146.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lanxiang Hu, Mingjia Huo, Yuxuan Zhang, Haoyang Yu, Eric P. Xing, Ion Stoica, Tajana Rosing, Haojian Jin, Hao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Playing video games requires perception, memory, and planning, exactly the faculties modern large language model (LLM) agents are expected to master. We study the major challenges in using popular video games to evaluate modern LLMs and find that directly dropping LLMs into games cannot make an effective evaluation, for three reasons -- brittle vision perception, prompt sensitivity, and potential data contamination. We introduce lmgame-Bench to turn games into reliable evaluations. lmgame-Bench features a suite of platformer, puzzle, and narrative games delivered through a unified Gym-style API and paired with lightweight perception and memory scaffolds, and is designed to stabilize prompt variance and remove contamination. Across 13 leading models, we show lmgame-Bench is challenging while still separating models well. Correlation analysis shows that every game probes a unique blend of capabilities often tested in isolation elsewhere. More interestingly, performing reinforcement learning on a single game from lmgame-Bench transfers both to unseen games and to external planning tasks. Our evaluation code is available at https://github.com/lmgame-org/GamingAgent/lmgame-bench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15146</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 06:02:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deliberation on Priors: Trustworthy Reasoning of Large Language Models   on Knowledge Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15210</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15210.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jie Ma, Ning Qu, Zhitao Gao, Rui Xing, Jun Liu, Hongbin Pei, Jiang Xie, Linyun Song, Pinghui Wang, Jing Tao, Zhou Su&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Knowledge graph-based retrieval-augmented generation seeks to mitigate hallucinations in Large Language Models (LLMs) caused by insufficient or outdated knowledge. However, existing methods often fail to fully exploit the prior knowledge embedded in knowledge graphs (KGs), particularly their structural information and explicit or implicit constraints. The former can enhance the faithfulness of LLMs' reasoning, while the latter can improve the reliability of response generation. Motivated by these, we propose a trustworthy reasoning framework, termed Deliberation over Priors (DP), which sufficiently utilizes the priors contained in KGs. Specifically, DP adopts a progressive knowledge distillation strategy that integrates structural priors into LLMs through a combination of supervised fine-tuning and Kahneman-Tversky optimization, thereby improving the faithfulness of relation path generation. Furthermore, our framework employs a reasoning-introspection strategy, which guides LLMs to perform refined reasoning verification based on extracted constraint priors, ensuring the reliability of response generation. Extensive experiments on three benchmark datasets demonstrate that DP achieves new state-of-the-art performance, especially a Hit@1 improvement of 13% on the ComplexWebQuestions dataset, and generates highly trustworthy responses. We also conduct various analyses to verify its flexibility and practicality. The code is available at https://github.com/reml-group/Deliberation-on-Priors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15210</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 07:38:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Diffusion Transformers Efficiently via μP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15270</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15270.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenyu Zheng, Xinyu Zhang, Rongzhen Wang, Wei Huang, Zhi Tian, Weilin Huang, Jun Zhu, Chongxuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Transformers have emerged as the foundation for vision generative models, but their scalability is limited by the high cost of hyperparameter (HP) tuning at large scales. Recently, Maximal Update Parametrization (muP) was proposed for vanilla Transformers, which enables stable HP transfer from small to large language models, and dramatically reduces tuning costs. However, it remains unclear whether muP of vanilla Transformers extends to diffusion Transformers, which differ architecturally and objectively. In this work, we generalize standard muP to diffusion Transformers and validate its effectiveness through large-scale experiments. First, we rigorously prove that muP of mainstream diffusion Transformers, including DiT, U-ViT, PixArt-alpha, and MMDiT, aligns with that of the vanilla Transformer, enabling the direct application of existing muP methodologies. Leveraging this result, we systematically demonstrate that DiT-muP enjoys robust HP transferability. Notably, DiT-XL-2-muP with transferred learning rate achieves 2.9 times faster convergence than the original DiT-XL-2. Finally, we validate the effectiveness of muP on text-to-image generation by scaling PixArt-alpha from 0.04B to 0.61B and MMDiT from 0.18B to 18B. In both cases, models under muP outperform their respective baselines while requiring small tuning cost, only 5.5% of one training run for PixArt-alpha and 3% of consumption by human experts for MMDiT-18B. These results establish muP as a principled and efficient framework for scaling diffusion Transformers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15270</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 08:49:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Web-Shepherd: Advancing PRMs for Reinforcing Web Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15277</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15277.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyungjoo Chae, Sunghwan Kim, Junhee Cho, Seungone Kim, Seungjun Moon, Gyeom Hwangbo, Dongha Lim, Minjin Kim, Yeonjun Hwang, Minju Gwak, Dongwook Choi, Minseok Kang, Gwanhoon Im, ByeongUng Cho, Hyojun Kim, Jun Hee Han, Taeyoon Kwon, Minju Kim, Beong-woo Kwak, Dongjin Kang, Jinyoung Yeo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 93&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Web navigation is a unique domain that can automate many repetitive real-life tasks and is challenging as it requires long-horizon sequential decision making beyond typical multimodal large language model (MLLM) tasks. Yet, specialized reward models for web navigation that can be utilized during both training and test-time have been absent until now. Despite the importance of speed and cost-effectiveness, prior works have utilized MLLMs as reward models, which poses significant constraints for real-world deployment. To address this, in this work, we propose the first process reward model (PRM) called Web-Shepherd which could assess web navigation trajectories in a step-level. To achieve this, we first construct the WebPRM Collection, a large-scale dataset with 40K step-level preference pairs and annotated checklists spanning diverse domains and difficulty levels. Next, we also introduce the WebRewardBench, the first meta-evaluation benchmark for evaluating PRMs. In our experiments, we observe that our Web-Shepherd achieves about 30 points better accuracy compared to using GPT-4o on WebRewardBench. Furthermore, when testing on WebArena-lite by using GPT-4o-mini as the policy and Web-Shepherd as the verifier, we achieve 10.9 points better performance, in 10 less cost compared to using GPT-4o-mini as the verifier. Our model, dataset, and code are publicly available at LINK.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15277</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 08:56:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When to Continue Thinking: Adaptive Thinking Mode Switching for   Efficient Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15400</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15400.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoyun Zhang, Jingqing Ruan, Xing Ma, Yawen Zhu, Haodong Zhao, Hao Li, Jiansong Chen, Ke Zeng, Xunliang Cai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs) achieve remarkable performance via long reasoning chains, but often incur excessive computational overhead due to redundant reasoning, especially on simple tasks. In this work, we systematically quantify the upper bounds of LRMs under both Long-Thinking and No-Thinking modes, and uncover the phenomenon of "Internal Self-Recovery Mechanism" where models implicitly supplement reasoning during answer generation. Building on this insight, we propose Adaptive Self-Recovery Reasoning (ASRR), a framework that suppresses unnecessary reasoning and enables implicit recovery. By introducing accuracy-aware length reward regulation, ASRR adaptively allocates reasoning effort according to problem difficulty, achieving high efficiency with negligible performance sacrifice. Experiments across multiple benchmarks and models show that, compared with GRPO, ASRR reduces reasoning budget by up to 32.5% (1.5B) and 25.7% (7B) with minimal accuracy loss (1.2% and 0.6% pass@1), and significantly boosts harmless rates on safety benchmarks (up to +21.7%). Our results highlight the potential of ASRR for enabling efficient, adaptive, and safer reasoning in LRMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15400</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 11:41:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Should We Enhance the Safety of Large Reasoning Models: An Empirical   Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15404</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15404.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhexin Zhang, Xian Qi Loye, Victor Shea-Jay Huang, Junxiao Yang, Qi Zhu, Shiyao Cui, Fei Mi, Lifeng Shang, Yingkang Wang, Hongning Wang, Minlie Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have achieved remarkable success on reasoning-intensive tasks such as mathematics and programming. However, their enhanced reasoning capabilities do not necessarily translate to improved safety performance-and in some cases, may even degrade it. This raises an important research question: how can we enhance the safety of LRMs? In this paper, we present a comprehensive empirical study on how to enhance the safety of LRMs through Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT). Our investigation begins with an unexpected observation: directly distilling safe responses from DeepSeek-R1 fails to significantly enhance safety. We analyze this phenomenon and identify three key failure patterns that contribute to it. We then demonstrate that explicitly addressing these issues during the data distillation process can lead to substantial safety improvements. Next, we explore whether a long and complex reasoning process is necessary for achieving safety. Interestingly, we find that simply using short or template-based reasoning process can attain comparable safety performance-and are significantly easier for models to learn than more intricate reasoning chains. These findings prompt a deeper reflection on the role of reasoning in ensuring safety. Finally, we find that mixing math reasoning data during safety fine-tuning is helpful to balance safety and over-refusal. Overall, we hope our empirical study could provide a more holistic picture on enhancing the safety of LRMs. The code and data used in our experiments are released in https://github.com/thu-coai/LRM-Safety-Study.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15404</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 11:45:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learn to Reason Efficiently with Adaptive Length-based Reward Shaping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15612</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15612.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei Liu, Ruochen Zhou, Yiyun Deng, Yuzhen Huang, Junteng Liu, Yuntian Deng, Yizhe Zhang, Junxian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have shown remarkable capabilities in solving complex problems through reinforcement learning (RL), particularly by generating long reasoning traces. However, these extended outputs often exhibit substantial redundancy, which limits the efficiency of LRMs. In this paper, we investigate RL-based approaches to promote reasoning efficiency. Specifically, we first present a unified framework that formulates various efficient reasoning methods through the lens of length-based reward shaping. Building on this perspective, we propose a novel Length-bAsed StEp Reward shaping method (LASER), which employs a step function as the reward, controlled by a target length. LASER surpasses previous methods, achieving a superior Pareto-optimal balance between performance and efficiency. Next, we further extend LASER based on two key intuitions: (1) The reasoning behavior of the model evolves during training, necessitating reward specifications that are also adaptive and dynamic; (2) Rather than uniformly encouraging shorter or longer chains of thought (CoT), we posit that length-based reward shaping should be difficulty-aware i.e., it should penalize lengthy CoTs more for easy queries. This approach is expected to facilitate a combination of fast and slow thinking, leading to a better overall tradeoff. The resulting method is termed LASER-D (Dynamic and Difficulty-aware). Experiments on DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-1.5B, DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-7B, and DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-32B show that our approach significantly enhances both reasoning performance and response length efficiency. For instance, LASER-D and its variant achieve a +6.1 improvement on AIME2024 while reducing token usage by 63%. Further analysis reveals our RL-based compression produces more concise reasoning patterns with less redundant "self-reflections". Resources are at https://github.com/hkust-nlp/Laser.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15612</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 15:03:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Be Careful When Fine-tuning On Open-Source LLMs: Your Fine-tuning Data   Could Be Secretly Stolen!</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15656</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15656.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhexin Zhang, Yuhao Sun, Junxiao Yang, Shiyao Cui, Hongning Wang, Minlie Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-tuning on open-source Large Language Models (LLMs) with proprietary data is now a standard practice for downstream developers to obtain task-specific LLMs. Surprisingly, we reveal a new and concerning risk along with the practice: the creator of the open-source LLMs can later extract the private downstream fine-tuning data through simple backdoor training, only requiring black-box access to the fine-tuned downstream model. Our comprehensive experiments, across 4 popularly used open-source models with 3B to 32B parameters and 2 downstream datasets, suggest that the extraction performance can be strikingly high: in practical settings, as much as 76.3% downstream fine-tuning data (queries) out of a total 5,000 samples can be perfectly extracted, and the success rate can increase to 94.9% in more ideal settings. We also explore a detection-based defense strategy but find it can be bypassed with improved attack. Overall, we highlight the emergency of this newly identified data breaching risk in fine-tuning, and we hope that more follow-up research could push the progress of addressing this concerning risk. The code and data used in our experiments are released at https://github.com/thu-coai/Backdoor-Data-Extraction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15656</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 15:32:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructing a 3D Town from a Single Image</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15765</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15765.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaizhi Zheng, Ruijian Zhang, Jing Gu, Jie Yang, Xin Eric Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Acquiring detailed 3D scenes typically demands costly equipment, multi-view data, or labor-intensive modeling. Therefore, a lightweight alternative, generating complex 3D scenes from a single top-down image, plays an essential role in real-world applications. While recent 3D generative models have achieved remarkable results at the object level, their extension to full-scene generation often leads to inconsistent geometry, layout hallucinations, and low-quality meshes. In this work, we introduce 3DTown, a training-free framework designed to synthesize realistic and coherent 3D scenes from a single top-down view. Our method is grounded in two principles: region-based generation to improve image-to-3D alignment and resolution, and spatial-aware 3D inpainting to ensure global scene coherence and high-quality geometry generation. Specifically, we decompose the input image into overlapping regions and generate each using a pretrained 3D object generator, followed by a masked rectified flow inpainting process that fills in missing geometry while maintaining structural continuity. This modular design allows us to overcome resolution bottlenecks and preserve spatial structure without requiring 3D supervision or fine-tuning. Extensive experiments across diverse scenes show that 3DTown outperforms state-of-the-art baselines, including Trellis, Hunyuan3D-2, and TripoSG, in terms of geometry quality, spatial coherence, and texture fidelity. Our results demonstrate that high-quality 3D town generation is achievable from a single image using a principled, training-free approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15765</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:10:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft Thinking: Unlocking the Reasoning Potential of LLMs in Continuous   Concept Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15778</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15778.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhen Zhang, Xuehai He, Weixiang Yan, Ao Shen, Chenyang Zhao, Shuohang Wang, Yelong Shen, Xin Eric Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human cognition typically involves thinking through abstract, fluid concepts rather than strictly using discrete linguistic tokens. Current reasoning models, however, are constrained to reasoning within the boundaries of human language, processing discrete token embeddings that represent fixed points in the semantic space. This discrete constraint restricts the expressive power and upper potential of such reasoning models, often causing incomplete exploration of reasoning paths, as standard Chain-of-Thought (CoT) methods rely on sampling one token per step. In this work, we introduce Soft Thinking, a training-free method that emulates human-like "soft" reasoning by generating soft, abstract concept tokens in a continuous concept space. These concept tokens are created by the probability-weighted mixture of token embeddings, which form the continuous concept space, enabling smooth transitions and richer representations that transcend traditional discrete boundaries. In essence, each generated concept token encapsulates multiple meanings from related discrete tokens, implicitly exploring various reasoning paths to converge effectively toward the correct answer. Empirical evaluations on diverse mathematical and coding benchmarks consistently demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of Soft Thinking, improving pass@1 accuracy by up to 2.48 points while simultaneously reducing token usage by up to 22.4% compared to standard CoT. Qualitative analysis further reveals that Soft Thinking outputs remain highly interpretable and readable, highlighting the potential of Soft Thinking to break the inherent bottleneck of discrete language-based reasoning. Code is available at https://github.com/eric-ai-lab/Soft-Thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15778</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:29:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IA-T2I: Internet-Augmented Text-to-Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15779</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15779.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chuanhao Li, Jianwen Sun, Yukang Feng, Mingliang Zhai, Yifan Chang, Kaipeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current text-to-image (T2I) generation models achieve promising results, but they fail on the scenarios where the knowledge implied in the text prompt is uncertain. For example, a T2I model released in February would struggle to generate a suitable poster for a movie premiering in April, because the character designs and styles are uncertain to the model. To solve this problem, we propose an Internet-Augmented text-to-image generation (IA-T2I) framework to compel T2I models clear about such uncertain knowledge by providing them with reference images. Specifically, an active retrieval module is designed to determine whether a reference image is needed based on the given text prompt; a hierarchical image selection module is introduced to find the most suitable image returned by an image search engine to enhance the T2I model; a self-reflection mechanism is presented to continuously evaluate and refine the generated image to ensure faithful alignment with the text prompt. To evaluate the proposed framework's performance, we collect a dataset named Img-Ref-T2I, where text prompts include three types of uncertain knowledge: (1) known but rare. (2) unknown. (3) ambiguous. Moreover, we carefully craft a complex prompt to guide GPT-4o in making preference evaluation, which has been shown to have an evaluation accuracy similar to that of human preference evaluation. Experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of our framework, outperforming GPT-4o by about 30% in human evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15779</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:31:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>dKV-Cache: The Cache for Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15781</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15781.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinyin Ma, Runpeng Yu, Gongfan Fang, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Language Models (DLMs) have been seen as a promising competitor for autoregressive language models. However, diffusion language models have long been constrained by slow inference. A core challenge is that their non-autoregressive architecture and bidirectional attention preclude the key-value cache that accelerates decoding. We address this bottleneck by proposing a KV-cache-like mechanism, delayed KV-Cache, for the denoising process of DLMs. Our approach is motivated by the observation that different tokens have distinct representation dynamics throughout the diffusion process. Accordingly, we propose a delayed and conditioned caching strategy for key and value states. We design two complementary variants to cache key and value step-by-step: (1) dKV-Cache-Decode, which provides almost lossless acceleration, and even improves performance on long sequences, suggesting that existing DLMs may under-utilise contextual information during inference. (2) dKV-Cache-Greedy, which has aggressive caching with reduced lifespan, achieving higher speed-ups with quadratic time complexity at the cost of some performance degradation. dKV-Cache, in final, achieves from 2-10x speedup in inference, largely narrowing the gap between ARs and DLMs. We evaluate our dKV-Cache on several benchmarks, delivering acceleration across general language understanding, mathematical, and code-generation benchmarks. Experiments demonstrate that cache can also be used in DLMs, even in a training-free manner from current DLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15781</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:32:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VerifyBench: Benchmarking Reference-based Reward Systems for Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15801</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15801.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuchen Yan, Jin Jiang, Zhenbang Ren, Yijun Li, Xudong Cai, Yang Liu, Xin Xu, Mengdi Zhang, Jian Shao, Yongliang Shen, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models such as OpenAI o1 and DeepSeek-R1 have achieved remarkable performance in the domain of reasoning. A key component of their training is the incorporation of verifiable rewards within reinforcement learning (RL). However, existing reward benchmarks do not evaluate reference-based reward systems, leaving researchers with limited understanding of the accuracy of verifiers used in RL. In this paper, we introduce two benchmarks, VerifyBench and VerifyBench-Hard, designed to assess the performance of reference-based reward systems. These benchmarks are constructed through meticulous data collection and curation, followed by careful human annotation to ensure high quality. Current models still show considerable room for improvement on both VerifyBench and VerifyBench-Hard, especially smaller-scale models. Furthermore, we conduct a thorough and comprehensive analysis of evaluation results, offering insights for understanding and developing reference-based reward systems. Our proposed benchmarks serve as effective tools for guiding the development of verifier accuracy and the reasoning capabilities of models trained via RL in reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15801</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:54:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRIT: Teaching MLLMs to Think with Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15879</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15879.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yue Fan, Xuehai He, Diji Yang, Kaizhi Zheng, Ching-Chen Kuo, Yuting Zheng, Sravana Jyothi Narayanaraju, Xinze Guan, Xin Eric Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have demonstrated the efficacy of using Reinforcement Learning (RL) in building reasoning models that articulate chains of thoughts prior to producing final answers. However, despite ongoing advances that aim at enabling reasoning for vision-language tasks, existing open-source visual reasoning models typically generate reasoning content with pure natural language, lacking explicit integration of visual information. This limits their ability to produce clearly articulated and visually grounded reasoning chains. To this end, we propose Grounded Reasoning with Images and Texts (GRIT), a novel method for training MLLMs to think with images. GRIT introduces a grounded reasoning paradigm, in which models generate reasoning chains that interleave natural language and explicit bounding box coordinates. These coordinates point to regions of the input image that the model consults during its reasoning process. Additionally, GRIT is equipped with a reinforcement learning approach, GRPO-GR, built upon the GRPO algorithm. GRPO-GR employs robust rewards focused on the final answer accuracy and format of the grounded reasoning output, which eliminates the need for data with reasoning chain annotations or explicit bounding box labels. As a result, GRIT achieves exceptional data efficiency, requiring as few as 20 image-question-answer triplets from existing datasets. Comprehensive evaluations demonstrate that GRIT effectively trains MLLMs to produce coherent and visually grounded reasoning chains, showing a successful unification of reasoning and grounding abilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15879</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:54:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMaDA: Multimodal Large Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15809</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15809.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ling Yang, Ye Tian, Bowen Li, Xinchen Zhang, Ke Shen, Yunhai Tong, Mengdi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce MMaDA, a novel class of multimodal diffusion foundation models designed to achieve superior performance across diverse domains such as textual reasoning, multimodal understanding, and text-to-image generation. The approach is distinguished by three key innovations: (i) MMaDA adopts a unified diffusion architecture with a shared probabilistic formulation and a modality-agnostic design, eliminating the need for modality-specific components. This architecture ensures seamless integration and processing across different data types. (ii) We implement a mixed long chain-of-thought (CoT) fine-tuning strategy that curates a unified CoT format across modalities. By aligning reasoning processes between textual and visual domains, this strategy facilitates cold-start training for the final reinforcement learning (RL) stage, thereby enhancing the model's ability to handle complex tasks from the outset. (iii) We propose UniGRPO, a unified policy-gradient-based RL algorithm specifically tailored for diffusion foundation models. Utilizing diversified reward modeling, UniGRPO unifies post-training across both reasoning and generation tasks, ensuring consistent performance improvements. Experimental results demonstrate that MMaDA-8B exhibits strong generalization capabilities as a unified multimodal foundation model. It surpasses powerful models like LLaMA-3-7B and Qwen2-7B in textual reasoning, outperforms Show-o and SEED-X in multimodal understanding, and excels over SDXL and Janus in text-to-image generation. These achievements highlight MMaDA's effectiveness in bridging the gap between pretraining and post-training within unified diffusion architectures, providing a comprehensive framework for future research and development. We open-source our code and trained models at: https://github.com/Gen-Verse/MMaDA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15809</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:59:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Reason via Mixture-of-Thought for Logical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15817</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15817.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tong Zheng, Lichang Chen, Simeng Han, R. Thomas McCoy, Heng Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human beings naturally utilize multiple reasoning modalities to learn and solve logical problems, i.e., different representational formats such as natural language, code, and symbolic logic. In contrast, most existing LLM-based approaches operate with a single reasoning modality during training, typically natural language. Although some methods explored modality selection or augmentation at inference time, the training process remains modality-blind, limiting synergy among modalities. To fill in this gap, we propose Mixture-of-Thought (MoT), a framework that enables LLMs to reason across three complementary modalities: natural language, code, and a newly introduced symbolic modality, truth-table, which systematically enumerates logical cases and partially mitigates key failure modes in natural language reasoning. MoT adopts a two-phase design: (1) self-evolving MoT training, which jointly learns from filtered, self-generated rationales across modalities; and (2) MoT inference, which fully leverages the synergy of three modalities to produce better predictions. Experiments on logical reasoning benchmarks including FOLIO and ProofWriter demonstrate that our MoT framework consistently and significantly outperforms strong LLM baselines with single-modality chain-of-thought approaches, achieving up to +11.7pp average accuracy gain. Further analyses show that our MoT framework benefits both training and inference stages; that it is particularly effective on harder logical reasoning problems; and that different modalities contribute complementary strengths, with truth-table reasoning helping to overcome key bottlenecks in natural language inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15817</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoGameQA-Bench: Evaluating Vision-Language Models for Video Game   Quality Assurance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15952</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15952.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohammad Reza Taesiri, Abhijay Ghildyal, Saman Zadtootaghaj, Nabajeet Barman, Cor-Paul Bezemer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With video games now generating the highest revenues in the entertainment industry, optimizing game development workflows has become essential for the sector's sustained growth. Recent advancements in Vision-Language Models (VLMs) offer considerable potential to automate and enhance various aspects of game development, particularly Quality Assurance (QA), which remains one of the industry's most labor-intensive processes with limited automation options. To accurately evaluate the performance of VLMs in video game QA tasks and determine their effectiveness in handling real-world scenarios, there is a clear need for standardized benchmarks, as existing benchmarks are insufficient to address the specific requirements of this domain. To bridge this gap, we introduce VideoGameQA-Bench, a comprehensive benchmark that covers a wide array of game QA activities, including visual unit testing, visual regression testing, needle-in-a-haystack tasks, glitch detection, and bug report generation for both images and videos of various games. Code and data are available at: https://asgaardlab.github.io/videogameqa-bench/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15952</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 19:08:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OViP: Online Vision-Language Preference Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15963</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15963.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shujun Liu, Siyuan Wang, Zejun Li, Jianxiang Wang, Cheng Zeng, Zhongyu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large vision-language models (LVLMs) remain vulnerable to hallucination, often generating content misaligned with visual inputs. While recent approaches advance multi-modal Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) to mitigate hallucination, they typically rely on predefined or randomly edited negative samples that fail to reflect actual model errors, limiting training efficacy. In this work, we propose an Online Vision-language Preference Learning (OViP) framework that dynamically constructs contrastive training data based on the model's own hallucinated outputs. By identifying semantic differences between sampled response pairs and synthesizing negative images using a diffusion model, OViP generates more relevant supervision signals in real time. This failure-driven training enables adaptive alignment of both textual and visual preferences. Moreover, we refine existing evaluation protocols to better capture the trade-off between hallucination suppression and expressiveness. Experiments on hallucination and general benchmarks demonstrate that OViP effectively reduces hallucinations while preserving core multi-modal capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15963</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 19:26:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pixel Reasoner: Incentivizing Pixel-Space Reasoning with   Curiosity-Driven Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15966</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15966.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alex Su, Haozhe Wang, Weimin Ren, Fangzhen Lin, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-thought reasoning has significantly improved the performance of Large Language Models (LLMs) across various domains. However, this reasoning process has been confined exclusively to textual space, limiting its effectiveness in visually intensive tasks. To address this limitation, we introduce the concept of reasoning in the pixel-space. Within this novel framework, Vision-Language Models (VLMs) are equipped with a suite of visual reasoning operations, such as zoom-in and select-frame. These operations enable VLMs to directly inspect, interrogate, and infer from visual evidences, thereby enhancing reasoning fidelity for visual tasks. Cultivating such pixel-space reasoning capabilities in VLMs presents notable challenges, including the model's initially imbalanced competence and its reluctance to adopt the newly introduced pixel-space operations. We address these challenges through a two-phase training approach. The first phase employs instruction tuning on synthesized reasoning traces to familiarize the model with the novel visual operations. Following this, a reinforcement learning (RL) phase leverages a curiosity-driven reward scheme to balance exploration between pixel-space reasoning and textual reasoning. With these visual operations, VLMs can interact with complex visual inputs, such as information-rich images or videos to proactively gather necessary information. We demonstrate that this approach significantly improves VLM performance across diverse visual reasoning benchmarks. Our 7B model, \model, achieves 84\% on V* bench, 74\% on TallyQA-Complex, and 84\% on InfographicsVQA, marking the highest accuracy achieved by any open-source model to date. These results highlight the importance of pixel-space reasoning and the effectiveness of our framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15966</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 19:35:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuickVideo: Real-Time Long Video Understanding with System Algorithm   Co-Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16175</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16175.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Benjamin Schneider, Dongfu Jiang, Chao Du, Tianyu Pang, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-video understanding has emerged as a crucial capability in real-world applications such as video surveillance, meeting summarization, educational lecture analysis, and sports broadcasting. However, it remains computationally prohibitive for VideoLLMs, primarily due to two bottlenecks: 1) sequential video decoding, the process of converting the raw bit stream to RGB frames can take up to a minute for hour-long video inputs, and 2) costly prefilling of up to several million tokens for LLM inference, resulting in high latency and memory use. To address these challenges, we propose QuickVideo, a system-algorithm co-design that substantially accelerates long-video understanding to support real-time downstream applications. It comprises three key innovations: QuickDecoder, a parallelized CPU-based video decoder that achieves 2-3 times speedup by splitting videos into keyframe-aligned intervals processed concurrently; QuickPrefill, a memory-efficient prefilling method using KV-cache pruning to support more frames with less GPU memory; and an overlapping scheme that overlaps CPU video decoding with GPU inference. Together, these components infernece time reduce by a minute on long video inputs, enabling scalable, high-quality video understanding even on limited hardware. Experiments show that QuickVideo generalizes across durations and sampling rates, making long video processing feasible in practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16175</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 03:26:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Generative AI Capabilities in Everyday Image Editing Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16181</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16181.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohammad Reza Taesiri, Brandon Collins, Logan Bolton, Viet Dac Lai, Franck Dernoncourt, Trung Bui, Anh Totti Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative AI (GenAI) holds significant promise for automating everyday image editing tasks, especially following the recent release of GPT-4o on March 25, 2025. However, what subjects do people most often want edited? What kinds of editing actions do they want to perform (e.g., removing or stylizing the subject)? Do people prefer precise edits with predictable outcomes or highly creative ones? By understanding the characteristics of real-world requests and the corresponding edits made by freelance photo-editing wizards, can we draw lessons for improving AI-based editors and determine which types of requests can currently be handled successfully by AI editors? In this paper, we present a unique study addressing these questions by analyzing 83k requests from the past 12 years (2013-2025) on the Reddit community, which collected 305k PSR-wizard edits. According to human ratings, approximately only 33% of requests can be fulfilled by the best AI editors (including GPT-4o, Gemini-2.0-Flash, SeedEdit). Interestingly, AI editors perform worse on low-creativity requests that require precise editing than on more open-ended tasks. They often struggle to preserve the identity of people and animals, and frequently make non-requested touch-ups. On the other side of the table, VLM judges (e.g., o1) perform differently from human judges and may prefer AI edits more than human edits. Code and qualitative examples are available at: https://psrdataset.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16181</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 03:35:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AceReason-Nemotron: Advancing Math and Code Reasoning through   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16400</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16400.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Chen, Zhuolin Yang, Zihan Liu, Chankyu Lee, Peng Xu, Mohammad Shoeybi, Bryan Catanzaro, Wei Ping&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite recent progress in large-scale reinforcement learning (RL) for reasoning, the training recipe for building high-performing reasoning models remains elusive. Key implementation details of frontier models, such as DeepSeek-R1, including data curation strategies and RL training recipe, are often omitted. Moreover, recent research indicates distillation remains more effective than RL for smaller models. In this work, we demonstrate that large-scale RL can significantly enhance the reasoning capabilities of strong, small- and mid-sized models, achieving results that surpass those of state-of-the-art distillation-based models. We systematically study the RL training process through extensive ablations and propose a simple yet effective approach: first training on math-only prompts, then on code-only prompts. Notably, we find that math-only RL not only significantly enhances the performance of strong distilled models on math benchmarks (e.g., +14.6% / +17.2% on AIME 2025 for the 7B / 14B models), but also code reasoning tasks (e.g., +6.8% / +5.8% on LiveCodeBench for the 7B / 14B models). In addition, extended code-only RL iterations further improve performance on code benchmarks with minimal or no degradation in math results. We develop a robust data curation pipeline to collect challenging prompts with high-quality, verifiable answers and test cases to enable verification-based RL across both domains. Finally, we identify key experimental insights, including curriculum learning with progressively increasing response lengths and the stabilizing effect of on-policy parameter updates. We find that RL not only elicits the foundational reasoning capabilities acquired during pretraining and supervised fine-tuning (e.g., distillation), but also pushes the limits of the model's reasoning ability, enabling it to solve problems that were previously unsolvable.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16400</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 08:50:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tool-Star: Empowering LLM-Brained Multi-Tool Reasoner via Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16410</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16410.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guanting Dong, Yifei Chen, Xiaoxi Li, Jiajie Jin, Hongjin Qian, Yutao Zhu, Hangyu Mao, Guorui Zhou, Zhicheng Dou, Ji-Rong Wen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable reasoning capabilities via large-scale reinforcement learning (RL). However, leveraging the RL algorithm to empower effective multi-tool collaborative reasoning in LLMs remains an open challenge. In this paper, we introduce Tool-Star, an RL-based framework designed to empower LLMs to autonomously invoke multiple external tools during stepwise reasoning. Tool-Star integrates six types of tools and incorporates systematic designs in both data synthesis and training. To address the scarcity of tool-use data, we propose a general tool-integrated reasoning data synthesis pipeline, which combines tool-integrated prompting with hint-based sampling to automatically and scalably generate tool-use trajectories. A subsequent quality normalization and difficulty-aware classification process filters out low-quality samples and organizes the dataset from easy to hard. Furthermore, we propose a two-stage training framework to enhance multi-tool collaborative reasoning by: (1) cold-start fine-tuning, which guides LLMs to explore reasoning patterns via tool-invocation feedback; and (2) a multi-tool self-critic RL algorithm with hierarchical reward design, which reinforces reward understanding and promotes effective tool collaboration. Experimental analyses on over 10 challenging reasoning benchmarks highlight the effectiveness and efficiency of Tool-Star. The code is available at https://github.com/dongguanting/Tool-Star.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16410</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 09:00:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebAgent-R1: Training Web Agents via End-to-End Multi-Turn Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16421</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16421.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhepei Wei, Wenlin Yao, Yao Liu, Weizhi Zhang, Qin Lu, Liang Qiu, Changlong Yu, Puyang Xu, Chao Zhang, Bing Yin, Hyokun Yun, Lihong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While reinforcement learning (RL) has demonstrated remarkable success in enhancing large language models (LLMs), it has primarily focused on single-turn tasks such as solving math problems. Training effective web agents for multi-turn interactions remains challenging due to the complexity of long-horizon decision-making across dynamic web interfaces. In this work, we present WebAgent-R1, a simple yet effective end-to-end multi-turn RL framework for training web agents. It learns directly from online interactions with web environments by asynchronously generating diverse trajectories, entirely guided by binary rewards depending on task success. Experiments on the WebArena-Lite benchmark demonstrate the effectiveness of WebAgent-R1, boosting the task success rate of Qwen-2.5-3B from 6.1% to 33.9% and Llama-3.1-8B from 8.5% to 44.8%, significantly outperforming existing state-of-the-art methods and strong proprietary models such as OpenAI o3. In-depth analyses reveal the effectiveness of the thinking-based prompting strategy and test-time scaling through increased interactions for web tasks. We further investigate different RL initialization policies by introducing two variants, namely WebAgent-R1-Zero and WebAgent-R1-CoT, which highlight the importance of the warm-up training stage (i.e., behavior cloning) and provide insights on incorporating long chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning in web agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16421</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 09:07:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KRIS-Bench: Benchmarking Next-Level Intelligent Image Editing Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16707</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16707.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yongliang Wu, Zonghui Li, Xinting Hu, Xinyu Ye, Xianfang Zeng, Gang Yu, Wenbo Zhu, Bernt Schiele, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Xu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multi-modal generative models have enabled significant progress in instruction-based image editing. However, while these models produce visually plausible outputs, their capacity for knowledge-based reasoning editing tasks remains under-explored. In this paper, we introduce KRIS-Bench (Knowledge-based Reasoning in Image-editing Systems Benchmark), a diagnostic benchmark designed to assess models through a cognitively informed lens. Drawing from educational theory, KRIS-Bench categorizes editing tasks across three foundational knowledge types: Factual, Conceptual, and Procedural. Based on this taxonomy, we design 22 representative tasks spanning 7 reasoning dimensions and release 1,267 high-quality annotated editing instances. To support fine-grained evaluation, we propose a comprehensive protocol that incorporates a novel Knowledge Plausibility metric, enhanced by knowledge hints and calibrated through human studies. Empirical results on 10 state-of-the-art models reveal significant gaps in reasoning performance, highlighting the need for knowledge-centric benchmarks to advance the development of intelligent image editing systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16707</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 14:08:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LaViDa: A Large Diffusion Language Model for Multimodal Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16839</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16839.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shufan Li, Konstantinos Kallidromitis, Hritik Bansal, Akash Gokul, Yusuke Kato, Kazuki Kozuka, Jason Kuen, Zhe Lin, Kai-Wei Chang, Aditya Grover&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern Vision-Language Models (VLMs) can solve a wide range of tasks requiring visual reasoning. In real-world scenarios, desirable properties for VLMs include fast inference and controllable generation (e.g., constraining outputs to adhere to a desired format). However, existing autoregressive (AR) VLMs like LLaVA struggle in these aspects. Discrete diffusion models (DMs) offer a promising alternative, enabling parallel decoding for faster inference and bidirectional context for controllable generation through text-infilling. While effective in language-only settings, DMs' potential for multimodal tasks is underexplored. We introduce LaViDa, a family of VLMs built on DMs. We build LaViDa by equipping DMs with a vision encoder and jointly fine-tune the combined parts for multimodal instruction following. To address challenges encountered, LaViDa incorporates novel techniques such as complementary masking for effective training, prefix KV cache for efficient inference, and timestep shifting for high-quality sampling. Experiments show that LaViDa achieves competitive or superior performance to AR VLMs on multi-modal benchmarks such as MMMU, while offering unique advantages of DMs, including flexible speed-quality tradeoff, controllability, and bidirectional reasoning. On COCO captioning, LaViDa surpasses Open-LLaVa-Next-8B by +4.1 CIDEr with 1.92x speedup. On bidirectional tasks, it achieves +59% improvement on Constrained Poem Completion. These results demonstrate LaViDa as a strong alternative to AR VLMs. Code and models will be released in the camera-ready version.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16839</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 16:07:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Think or Not? Selective Reasoning via Reinforcement Learning for   Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16854</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16854.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Wang, Kevin Qinghong Lin, James Cheng, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning (RL) has proven to be an effective post-training strategy for enhancing reasoning in vision-language models (VLMs). Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) is a recent prominent method that encourages models to generate complete reasoning traces before answering, leading to increased token usage and computational cost. Inspired by the human-like thinking process-where people skip reasoning for easy questions but think carefully when needed-we explore how to enable VLMs to first decide when reasoning is necessary. To realize this, we propose TON, a two-stage training strategy: (i) a supervised fine-tuning (SFT) stage with a simple yet effective 'thought dropout' operation, where reasoning traces are randomly replaced with empty thoughts. This introduces a think-or-not format that serves as a cold start for selective reasoning; (ii) a GRPO stage that enables the model to freely explore when to think or not, while maximizing task-aware outcome rewards. Experimental results show that TON can reduce the completion length by up to 90% compared to vanilla GRPO, without sacrificing performance or even improving it. Further evaluations across diverse vision-language tasks-covering a range of reasoning difficulties under both 3B and 7B models-consistently reveal that the model progressively learns to bypass unnecessary reasoning steps as training advances. These findings shed light on the path toward human-like reasoning patterns in reinforcement learning approaches. Our code is available at https://github.com/kokolerk/TON.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16854</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 16:13:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training-Free Efficient Video Generation via Dynamic Token Carving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16864</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16864.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuechen Zhang, Jinbo Xing, Bin Xia, Shaoteng Liu, Bohao Peng, Xin Tao, Pengfei Wan, Eric Lo, Jiaya Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the remarkable generation quality of video Diffusion Transformer (DiT) models, their practical deployment is severely hindered by extensive computational requirements. This inefficiency stems from two key challenges: the quadratic complexity of self-attention with respect to token length and the multi-step nature of diffusion models. To address these limitations, we present Jenga, a novel inference pipeline that combines dynamic attention carving with progressive resolution generation. Our approach leverages two key insights: (1) early denoising steps do not require high-resolution latents, and (2) later steps do not require dense attention. Jenga introduces a block-wise attention mechanism that dynamically selects relevant token interactions using 3D space-filling curves, alongside a progressive resolution strategy that gradually increases latent resolution during generation. Experimental results demonstrate that Jenga achieves substantial speedups across multiple state-of-the-art video diffusion models while maintaining comparable generation quality (8.83times speedup with 0.01\% performance drop on VBench). As a plug-and-play solution, Jenga enables practical, high-quality video generation on modern hardware by reducing inference time from minutes to seconds -- without requiring model retraining. Code: https://github.com/dvlab-research/Jenga&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16864</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 16:21:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backdoor Cleaning without External Guidance in MLLM Fine-tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16916</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16916.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuankun Rong, Wenke Huang, Jian Liang, Jinhe Bi, Xun Xiao, Yiming Li, Bo Du, Mang Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) are increasingly deployed in fine-tuning-as-a-service (FTaaS) settings, where user-submitted datasets adapt general-purpose models to downstream tasks. This flexibility, however, introduces serious security risks, as malicious fine-tuning can implant backdoors into MLLMs with minimal effort. In this paper, we observe that backdoor triggers systematically disrupt cross-modal processing by causing abnormal attention concentration on non-semantic regions--a phenomenon we term attention collapse. Based on this insight, we propose Believe Your Eyes (BYE), a data filtering framework that leverages attention entropy patterns as self-supervised signals to identify and filter backdoor samples. BYE operates via a three-stage pipeline: (1) extracting attention maps using the fine-tuned model, (2) computing entropy scores and profiling sensitive layers via bimodal separation, and (3) performing unsupervised clustering to remove suspicious samples. Unlike prior defenses, BYE equires no clean supervision, auxiliary labels, or model modifications. Extensive experiments across various datasets, models, and diverse trigger types validate BYE's effectiveness: it achieves near-zero attack success rates while maintaining clean-task performance, offering a robust and generalizable solution against backdoor threats in MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16916</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:11:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Risk-Averse Reinforcement Learning with Itakura-Saito Loss</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16925</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16925.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Igor Udovichenko, Olivier Croissant, Anita Toleutaeva, Evgeny Burnaev, Alexander Korotin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Risk-averse reinforcement learning finds application in various high-stakes fields. Unlike classical reinforcement learning, which aims to maximize expected returns, risk-averse agents choose policies that minimize risk, occasionally sacrificing expected value. These preferences can be framed through utility theory. We focus on the specific case of the exponential utility function, where we can derive the Bellman equations and employ various reinforcement learning algorithms with few modifications. However, these methods suffer from numerical instability due to the need for exponent computation throughout the process. To address this, we introduce a numerically stable and mathematically sound loss function based on the Itakura-Saito divergence for learning state-value and action-value functions. We evaluate our proposed loss function against established alternatives, both theoretically and empirically. In the experimental section, we explore multiple financial scenarios, some with known analytical solutions, and show that our loss function outperforms the alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16925</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:18:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLaDA-V: Large Language Diffusion Models with Visual Instruction Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16933</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16933.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zebin You, Shen Nie, Xiaolu Zhang, Jun Hu, Jun Zhou, Zhiwu Lu, Ji-Rong Wen, Chongxuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we introduce LLaDA-V, a purely diffusion-based Multimodal Large Language Model (MLLM) that integrates visual instruction tuning with masked diffusion models, representing a departure from the autoregressive paradigms dominant in current multimodal approaches. Built upon LLaDA, a representative large language diffusion model, LLaDA-V incorporates a vision encoder and MLP connector that projects visual features into the language embedding space, enabling effective multimodal alignment. Our empirical investigation reveals several intriguing results: First, LLaDA-V demonstrates promising multimodal performance despite its language model being weaker on purely textual tasks than counterparts like LLaMA3-8B and Qwen2-7B. When trained on the same instruction data, LLaDA-V is highly competitive to LLaMA3-V across multimodal tasks with better data scalability. It also narrows the performance gap to Qwen2-VL, suggesting the effectiveness of its architecture for multimodal tasks. Second, LLaDA-V achieves state-of-the-art performance in multimodal understanding compared to existing hybrid autoregressive-diffusion and purely diffusion-based MLLMs. Our findings suggest that large language diffusion models show promise in multimodal contexts and warrant further investigation in future research. Project page and codes: https://ml-gsai.github.io/LLaDA-V-demo/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16933</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:23:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NovelSeek: When Agent Becomes the Scientist -- Building Closed-Loop   System from Hypothesis to Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16938</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16938.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NovelSeek Team, Bo Zhang, Shiyang Feng, Xiangchao Yan, Jiakang Yuan, Zhiyin Yu, Xiaohan He, Songtao Huang, Shaowei Hou, Zheng Nie, Zhilong Wang, Jinyao Liu, Runmin Ma, Tianshuo Peng, Peng Ye, Dongzhan Zhou, Shufei Zhang, Xiaosong Wang, Yilan Zhang, Meng Li, Zhongying Tu, Xiangyu Yue, Wangli Ouyang, Bowen Zhou, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 106&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Artificial Intelligence (AI) is accelerating the transformation of scientific research paradigms, not only enhancing research efficiency but also driving innovation. We introduce NovelSeek, a unified closed-loop multi-agent framework to conduct Autonomous Scientific Research (ASR) across various scientific research fields, enabling researchers to tackle complicated problems in these fields with unprecedented speed and precision. NovelSeek highlights three key advantages: 1) Scalability: NovelSeek has demonstrated its versatility across 12 scientific research tasks, capable of generating innovative ideas to enhance the performance of baseline code. 2) Interactivity: NovelSeek provides an interface for human expert feedback and multi-agent interaction in automated end-to-end processes, allowing for the seamless integration of domain expert knowledge. 3) Efficiency: NovelSeek has achieved promising performance gains in several scientific fields with significantly less time cost compared to human efforts. For instance, in reaction yield prediction, it increased from 27.6% to 35.4% in just 12 hours; in enhancer activity prediction, accuracy rose from 0.52 to 0.79 with only 4 hours of processing; and in 2D semantic segmentation, precision advanced from 78.8% to 81.0% in a mere 30 hours.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16938</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:27:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fixing Data That Hurts Performance: Cascading LLMs to Relabel Hard   Negatives for Robust Information Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16967</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16967.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nandan Thakur, Crystina Zhang, Xueguang Ma, Jimmy Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training robust retrieval and reranker models typically relies on large-scale retrieval datasets; for example, the BGE collection contains 1.6 million query-passage pairs sourced from various data sources. However, we find that certain datasets can negatively impact model effectiveness -- pruning 8 out of 15 datasets from the BGE collection reduces the training set size by 2.35times and increases nDCG@10 on BEIR by 1.0 point. This motivates a deeper examination of training data quality, with a particular focus on "false negatives", where relevant passages are incorrectly labeled as irrelevant. We propose a simple, cost-effective approach using cascading LLM prompts to identify and relabel hard negatives. Experimental results show that relabeling false negatives with true positives improves both E5 (base) and Qwen2.5-7B retrieval models by 0.7-1.4 nDCG@10 on BEIR and by 1.7-1.8 nDCG@10 on zero-shot AIR-Bench evaluation. Similar gains are observed for rerankers fine-tuned on the relabeled data, such as Qwen2.5-3B on BEIR. The reliability of the cascading design is further supported by human annotation results, where we find judgment by GPT-4o shows much higher agreement with humans than GPT-4o-mini.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16967</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:47:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dimple: Discrete Diffusion Multimodal Large Language Model with Parallel   Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16990</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16990.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runpeng Yu, Xinyin Ma, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we propose Dimple, the first Discrete Diffusion Multimodal Large Language Model (DMLLM). We observe that training with a purely discrete diffusion approach leads to significant training instability, suboptimal performance, and severe length bias issues. To address these challenges, we design a novel training paradigm that combines an initial autoregressive phase with a subsequent diffusion phase. This approach yields the Dimple-7B model, trained on the same dataset and using a similar training pipeline as LLaVA-NEXT. Dimple-7B ultimately surpasses LLaVA-NEXT in performance by 3.9%, demonstrating that DMLLM can achieve performance comparable to that of autoregressive models. To improve inference efficiency, we propose a decoding strategy termed confident decoding, which dynamically adjusts the number of tokens generated at each step, significantly reducing the number of generation iterations. In autoregressive models, the number of forward iterations during generation equals the response length. With confident decoding, however, the number of iterations needed by Dimple is even only text{response length}{3}. We also re-implement the prefilling technique in autoregressive models and demonstrate that it does not significantly impact performance on most benchmark evaluations, while offering a speedup of 1.5x to 7x. Additionally, we explore Dimple's capability to precisely control its response using structure priors. These priors enable structured responses in a manner distinct from instruction-based or chain-of-thought prompting, and allow fine-grained control over response format and length, which is difficult to achieve in autoregressive models. Overall, this work validates the feasibility and advantages of DMLLM and enhances its inference efficiency and controllability. Code and models are available at https://github.com/yu-rp/Dimple.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16990</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:55:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpatialScore: Towards Unified Evaluation for Multimodal Spatial   Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17012</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17012.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoning Wu, Xiao Huang, Yaohui Chen, Ya Zhang, Yanfeng Wang, Weidi Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have achieved impressive success in question-answering tasks, yet their capabilities for spatial understanding are less explored. This work investigates a critical question: do existing MLLMs possess 3D spatial perception and understanding abilities? Concretely, we make the following contributions in this paper: (i) we introduce VGBench, a benchmark specifically designed to assess MLLMs for visual geometry perception, e.g., camera pose and motion estimation; (ii) we propose SpatialScore, the most comprehensive and diverse multimodal spatial understanding benchmark to date, integrating VGBench with relevant data from the other 11 existing datasets. This benchmark comprises 28K samples across various spatial understanding tasks, modalities, and QA formats, along with a carefully curated challenging subset, SpatialScore-Hard; (iii) we develop SpatialAgent, a novel multi-agent system incorporating 9 specialized tools for spatial understanding, supporting both Plan-Execute and ReAct reasoning paradigms; (iv) we conduct extensive evaluations to reveal persistent challenges in spatial reasoning while demonstrating the effectiveness of SpatialAgent. We believe SpatialScore will offer valuable insights and serve as a rigorous benchmark for the next evolution of MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17012</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SophiaVL-R1: Reinforcing MLLMs Reasoning with Thinking Reward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17018</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17018.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaixuan Fan, Kaituo Feng, Haoming Lyu, Dongzhan Zhou, Xiangyu Yue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances have shown success in eliciting strong reasoning abilities in multimodal large language models (MLLMs) through rule-based reinforcement learning (RL) with outcome rewards. However, this paradigm typically lacks supervision over the thinking process leading to the final outcome.As a result, the model may learn sub-optimal reasoning strategies, which can hinder its generalization ability. In light of this, we propose SophiaVL-R1, as an attempt to add reward signals for the thinking process in this paradigm. To achieve this, we first train a thinking reward model that evaluates the quality of the entire thinking process. Given that the thinking reward may be unreliable for certain samples due to reward hacking, we propose the Trust-GRPO method, which assigns a trustworthiness weight to the thinking reward during training. This weight is computed based on the thinking reward comparison of responses leading to correct answers versus incorrect answers, helping to mitigate the impact of potentially unreliable thinking rewards. Moreover, we design an annealing training strategy that gradually reduces the thinking reward over time, allowing the model to rely more on the accurate rule-based outcome reward in later training stages. Experiments show that our SophiaVL-R1 surpasses a series of reasoning MLLMs on various benchmarks (e.g., MathVisita, MMMU), demonstrating strong reasoning and generalization capabilities. Notably, our SophiaVL-R1-7B even outperforms LLaVA-OneVision-72B on most benchmarks, despite the latter having 10 times more parameters. All code, models, and datasets are made publicly available at https://github.com/kxfan2002/SophiaVL-R1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17018</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GoT-R1: Unleashing Reasoning Capability of MLLM for Visual Generation   with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17022</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17022.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chengqi Duan, Rongyao Fang, Yuqing Wang, Kun Wang, Linjiang Huang, Xingyu Zeng, Hongsheng Li, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual generation models have made remarkable progress in creating realistic images from text prompts, yet struggle with complex prompts that specify multiple objects with precise spatial relationships and attributes. Effective handling of such prompts requires explicit reasoning about the semantic content and spatial layout. We present GoT-R1, a framework that applies reinforcement learning to enhance semantic-spatial reasoning in visual generation. Building upon the Generation Chain-of-Thought approach, GoT-R1 enables models to autonomously discover effective reasoning strategies beyond predefined templates through carefully designed reinforcement learning. To achieve this, we propose a dual-stage multi-dimensional reward framework that leverages MLLMs to evaluate both the reasoning process and final output, enabling effective supervision across the entire generation pipeline. The reward system assesses semantic alignment, spatial accuracy, and visual quality in a unified approach. Experimental results demonstrate significant improvements on T2I-CompBench benchmark, particularly in compositional tasks involving precise spatial relationships and attribute binding. GoT-R1 advances the state-of-the-art in image generation by successfully transferring sophisticated reasoning capabilities to the visual generation domain. To facilitate future research, we make our code and pretrained models publicly available at https://github.com/gogoduan/GoT-R1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17022</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
