<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 00:16:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Pisets: A Robust Speech Recognition System for Lectures and Interviews</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18415</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2601.18415.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ivan Bondarenko, Daniil Grebenkin, Oleg Sedukhin, Mikhail Klementev, Roman Derunets, Lyudmila Budneva&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This work presents a speech-to-text system "Pisets" for scientists and journalists which is based on a three-component architecture aimed at improving speech recognition accuracy while minimizing errors and hallucinations associated with the Whisper model. The architecture comprises primary recognition using Wav2Vec2, false positive filtering via the Audio Spectrogram Transformer (AST), and final speech recognition through Whisper. The implementation of curriculum learning methods and the utilization of diverse Russian-language speech corpora significantly enhanced the system's effectiveness. Additionally, advanced uncertainty modeling techniques were introduced, contributing to further improvements in transcription quality. The proposed approaches ensure robust transcribing of long audio data across various acoustic conditions compared to WhisperX and the usual Whisper model. The source code of "Pisets" system is publicly available at GitHub: https://github.com/bond005/pisets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18415</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:14:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Agentic Intelligence for Materials Science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00169</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.00169.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huan Zhang, Yizhan Li, Wenhao Huang, Ziyu Hou, Yu Song, Xuye Liu, Farshid Effaty, Jinya Jiang, Sifan Wu, Qianggang Ding, Izumi Takahara, Leonard R. MacGillivray, Teruyasu Mizoguchi, Tianshu Yu, Lizi Liao, Yuyu Luo, Yu Rong, Jia Li, Ying Diao, Heng Ji, Bang Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The convergence of artificial intelligence and materials science presents a transformative opportunity, but achieving true acceleration in discovery requires moving beyond task-isolated, fine-tuned models toward agentic systems that plan, act, and learn across the full discovery loop. This survey advances a unique pipeline-centric view that spans from corpus curation and pretraining, through domain adaptation and instruction tuning, to goal-conditioned agents interfacing with simulation and experimental platforms. Unlike prior reviews, we treat the entire process as an end-to-end system to be optimized for tangible discovery outcomes rather than proxy benchmarks. This perspective allows us to trace how upstream design choices-such as data curation and training objectives-can be aligned with downstream experimental success through effective credit assignment.   To bridge communities and establish a shared frame of reference, we first present an integrated lens that aligns terminology, evaluation, and workflow stages across AI and materials science. We then analyze the field through two focused lenses: From the AI perspective, the survey details LLM strengths in pattern recognition, predictive analytics, and natural language processing for literature mining, materials characterization, and property prediction; from the materials science perspective, it highlights applications in materials design, process optimization, and the acceleration of computational workflows via integration with external tools (e.g., DFT, robotic labs). Finally, we contrast passive, reactive approaches with agentic design, cataloging current contributions while motivating systems that pursue long-horizon goals with autonomy, memory, and tool use. This survey charts a practical roadmap towards autonomous, safety-aware LLM agents aimed at discovering novel and useful materials.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00169</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 23:48:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TokenTrim: Inference-Time Token Pruning for Autoregressive Long Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00268</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.00268.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ariel Shaulov, Eitan Shaar, Amit Edenzon, Lior Wolf&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Auto-regressive video generation enables long video synthesis by iteratively conditioning each new batch of frames on previously generated content. However, recent work has shown that such pipelines suffer from severe temporal drift, where errors accumulate and amplify over long horizons. We hypothesize that this drift does not primarily stem from insufficient model capacity, but rather from inference-time error propagation. Specifically, we contend that drift arises from the uncontrolled reuse of corrupted latent conditioning tokens during auto-regressive inference. To correct this accumulation of errors, we propose a simple, inference-time method that mitigates temporal drift by identifying and removing unstable latent tokens before they are reused for conditioning. For this purpose, we define unstable tokens as latent tokens whose representations deviate significantly from those of the previously generated batch, indicating potential corruption or semantic drift. By explicitly removing corrupted latent tokens from the auto-regressive context, rather than modifying entire spatial regions or model parameters, our method prevents unreliable latent information from influencing future generation steps. As a result, it significantly improves long-horizon temporal consistency without modifying the model architecture, training procedure, or leaving latent space.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00268</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 19:44:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LatentLens: Revealing Highly Interpretable Visual Tokens in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00462</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.00462.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Benno Krojer, Shravan Nayak, Oscar Mañas, Vaibhav Adlakha, Desmond Elliott, Siva Reddy, Marius Mosbach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Transforming a large language model (LLM) into a Vision-Language Model (VLM) can be achieved by mapping the visual tokens from a vision encoder into the embedding space of an LLM. Intriguingly, this mapping can be as simple as a shallow MLP transformation. To understand why LLMs can so readily process visual tokens, we need interpretability methods that reveal what is encoded in the visual token representations at every layer of LLM processing. In this work, we introduce LatentLens, a novel approach for mapping latent representations to descriptions in natural language. LatentLens works by encoding a large text corpus and storing contextualized token representations for each token in that corpus. Visual token representations are then compared to their contextualized textual representations, with the top-k nearest neighbor representations providing descriptions of the visual token. We evaluate this method on 10 different VLMs, showing that commonly used methods, such as LogitLens, substantially underestimate the interpretability of visual tokens. With LatentLens instead, the majority of visual tokens are interpretable across all studied models and all layers. Qualitatively, we show that the descriptions produced by LatentLens are semantically meaningful and provide more fine-grained interpretations for humans compared to individual tokens. More broadly, our findings contribute new evidence on the alignment between vision and language representations, opening up new directions for analyzing latent representations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.00462</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 02:33:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Terminal Agentic Trajectory Generation from Dockerized Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01244</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.01244.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siwei Wu, Yizhi Li, Yuyang Song, Wei Zhang, Yang Wang, Riza Batista-Navarro, Xian Yang, Mingjie Tang, Bryan Dai, Jian Yang, Chenghua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training agentic models for terminal-based tasks critically depends on high-quality terminal trajectories that capture realistic long-horizon interactions across diverse domains. However, constructing such data at scale remains challenging due to two key requirements: \emph{Executability}, since each instance requires a suitable and often distinct Docker environment; and \emph{Verifiability}, because heterogeneous task outputs preclude unified, standardized verification. To address these challenges, we propose TerminalTraj, a scalable pipeline that (i) filters high-quality repositories to construct Dockerized execution environments, (ii) generates Docker-aligned task instances, and (iii) synthesizes agent trajectories with executable validation code. Using TerminalTraj, we curate 32K Docker images and generate 50,733 verified terminal trajectories across eight domains. Models trained on this data with the Qwen2.5-Coder backbone achieve consistent performance improvements on TerminalBench (TB), with gains of up to 20\% on TB~1.0 and 10\% on TB~2.0 over their respective backbones. Notably, TerminalTraj-32B achieves strong performance among models with fewer than 100B parameters, reaching 35.30\% on TB~1.0 and 22.00\% on TB~2.0, and demonstrates improved test-time scaling behavior. All code and data are available at https://github.com/Wusiwei0410/TerminalTraj.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01244</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 14:09:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MSign: An Optimizer Preventing Training Instability in Large Language Models via Stable Rank Restoration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01734</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.01734.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lianhai Ren, Yucheng Ding, Xiao Liu, Qianxiao Li, Peng Cheng, Yeyun Gong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training instability remains a critical challenge in large language model (LLM) pretraining, often manifesting as sudden gradient explosions that waste significant computational resources. We study training failures in a 5M-parameter NanoGPT model scaled via μP, identifying two key phenomena preceding collapse: (1) rapid decline in weight matrix stable rank (ratio of squared Frobenius norm to squared spectral norm), and (2) increasing alignment between adjacent layer Jacobians. We prove theoretically that these two conditions jointly cause exponential gradient norm growth with network depth. To break this instability mechanism, we propose MSign, a new optimizer that periodically applies matrix sign operations to restore stable rank. Experiments on models from 5M to 3B parameters demonstrate that MSign effectively prevents training failures with a computational overhead of less than 7.0%.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.01734</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 07:18:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Condition Errors Refinement in Autoregressive Image Generation with Diffusion Loss</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07022</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07022.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yucheng Zhou, Hao Li, Jianbing Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have explored autoregressive models for image generation, with promising results, and have combined diffusion models with autoregressive frameworks to optimize image generation via diffusion losses. In this study, we present a theoretical analysis of diffusion and autoregressive models with diffusion loss, highlighting the latter's advantages. We present a theoretical comparison of conditional diffusion and autoregressive diffusion with diffusion loss, demonstrating that patch denoising optimization in autoregressive models effectively mitigates condition errors and leads to a stable condition distribution. Our analysis also reveals that autoregressive condition generation refines the condition, causing the condition error influence to decay exponentially. In addition, we introduce a novel condition refinement approach based on Optimal Transport (OT) theory to address ``condition inconsistency''. We theoretically demonstrate that formulating condition refinement as a Wasserstein Gradient Flow ensures convergence toward the ideal condition distribution, effectively mitigating condition inconsistency. Experiments demonstrate the superiority of our method over diffusion and autoregressive models with diffusion loss methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07022</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 07:48:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modality Gap-Driven Subspace Alignment Training Paradigm For Multimodal Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07026</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07026.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaomin Yu, Yi Xin, Wenjie Zhang, Chonghan Liu, Hanzhen Zhao, Xiaoxing Hu, Xinlei Yu, Ziyue Qiao, Hao Tang, Xue Yang, Xiaobin Hu, Chengwei Qin, Hui Xiong, Yu Qiao, Shuicheng Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 133&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the success of multimodal contrastive learning in aligning visual and linguistic representations, a persistent geometric anomaly, the Modality Gap, remains: embeddings of distinct modalities expressing identical semantics occupy systematically offset regions. Prior approaches to bridge this gap are largely limited by oversimplified isotropic assumptions, hindering their application in large-scale scenarios. In this paper, we address these limitations by precisely characterizing the geometric shape of the modality gap and leveraging it for efficient model scaling. First, we propose the Fixed-frame Modality Gap Theory, which decomposes the modality gap within a frozen reference frame into stable biases and anisotropic residuals. Guided by this precise modeling, we introduce ReAlign, a training-free modality alignment strategy. Utilizing statistics from massive unpaired data, ReAlign aligns text representation into the image representation distribution via a three-step process comprising Anchor, Trace, and Centroid Alignment, thereby explicitly rectifying geometric misalignment. Building on ReAlign, we propose ReVision, a scalable training paradigm for Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs). ReVision integrates ReAlign into the pretraining stage, enabling the model to learn the distribution of visual representations from unpaired text before visual instruction tuning, without the need for large-scale, high-quality image-text pairs. Our framework demonstrates that statistically aligned unpaired data can effectively substitute for expensive image-text pairs, offering a robust path for the efficient scaling of MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07026</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 13:59:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DLLM-Searcher: Adapting Diffusion Large Language Model for Search Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07035</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07035.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiahao Zhao, Shaoxuan Xu, Zhongxiang Sun, Fengqi Zhu, Jingyang Ou, Yuling Shi, Chongxuan Li, Xiao Zhang, Jun Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, Diffusion Large Language Models (dLLMs) have demonstrated unique efficiency advantages, enabled by their inherently parallel decoding mechanism and flexible generation paradigm. Meanwhile, despite the rapid advancement of Search Agents, their practical deployment is constrained by a fundamental limitation, termed as 1) Latency Challenge: the serial execution of multi-round reasoning, tool calling, and tool response waiting under the ReAct agent paradigm induces severe end-to-end latency. Intuitively, dLLMs can leverage their distinctive strengths to optimize the operational efficiency of agents under the ReAct agent paradigm. Practically, existing dLLM backbones face the 2) Agent Ability Challenge. That is, existing dLLMs exhibit remarkably weak reasoning and tool-calling capabilities, preventing these advantages from being effectively realized in practice. In this paper, we propose DLLM-Searcher, an optimization framework for dLLM-based Search Agents. To solve the Agent Ability Challenge, we design a two-stage post-training pipeline encompassing Agentic Supervised Fine-Tuning (Agentic SFT) and Agentic Variance-Reduced Preference Optimization Agentic VRPO, which enhances the backbone dLLM's information seeking and reasoning capabilities. To mitigate the Latency Challenge, we leverage the flexible generation mechanism of dLLMs and propose a novel agent paradigm termed Parallel-Reasoning and Acting P-ReAct. P-ReAct guides the model to prioritize decoding tool_call instructions, thereby allowing the model to keep thinking while waiting for the tool's return. Experimental results demonstrate that DLLM-Searcher achieves performance comparable to mainstream LLM-based search agents and P-ReAct delivers approximately 15% inference acceleration. Our code is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/DLLM-Searcher-553C&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07035</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 09:12:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Entropy Dynamics in Reinforcement Fine-Tuning of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03392</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.03392.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shumin Wang, Yuexiang Xie, Wenhao Zhang, Yuchang Sun, Yanxi Chen, Yaliang Li, Yanyong Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Entropy serves as a critical metric for measuring the diversity of outputs generated by large language models (LLMs), providing valuable insights into their exploration capabilities. While recent studies increasingly focus on monitoring and adjusting entropy to better balance exploration and exploitation in reinforcement fine-tuning (RFT), a principled understanding of entropy dynamics during this process is yet to be thoroughly investigated. In this paper, we establish a theoretical framework for analyzing the entropy dynamics during the RFT process, which begins with a discriminant expression that quantifies entropy change under a single logit update. This foundation enables the derivation of a first-order expression for entropy change, which can be further extended to the update formula of Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO). The corollaries and insights drawn from the theoretical analysis inspire the design of entropy control methods, and also offer a unified lens for interpreting various entropy-based methods in existing studies. We provide empirical evidence to support the main conclusions of our analysis and demonstrate the effectiveness of the derived entropy-discriminator clipping methods. This study yields novel insights into RFT training dynamics, providing theoretical support and practical strategies for optimizing the exploration-exploitation balance during LLM fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03392</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 11:14:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MemGUI-Bench: Benchmarking Memory of Mobile GUI Agents in Dynamic Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06075</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06075.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guangyi Liu, Pengxiang Zhao, Yaozhen Liang, Qinyi Luo, Shunye Tang, Yuxiang Chai, Weifeng Lin, Han Xiao, WenHao Wang, Siheng Chen, Zhengxi Lu, Gao Wu, Hao Wang, Liang Liu, Yong Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current mobile GUI agent benchmarks systematically fail to assess memory capabilities, with only 5.2-11.8% memory-related tasks and no cross-session learning evaluation. We introduce MemGUI-Bench, a comprehensive memory-centric benchmark with pass@k and staged LLM-as-judge evaluation. Our contributions include: (1) a systematic memory taxonomy analyzing 11 agents across 5 architectures; (2) 128 tasks across 26 applications where 89.8% challenge memory through cross-temporal and cross-spatial retention; (3) MemGUI-Eval, an automated pipeline with Progressive Scrutiny and 7 hierarchical metrics; and (4) RQ-driven assessment of 11 state-of-the-art agents. Our experiments reveal significant memory deficits across all evaluated systems, identify 5 distinct failure modes, and synthesize 5 actionable design implications. All resources including code, benchmark, and evaluation results will be \textit{fully open-sourced and continuously maintained} at https://lgy0404.github.io/MemGUI-Bench/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06075</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:01:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCALE: Self-uncertainty Conditioned Adaptive Looking and Execution for Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04208</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.04208.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyeonbeom Choi, Daechul Ahn, Youhan Lee, Taewook Kang, Seongwon Cho, Jonghyun Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models have emerged as a promising paradigm for general-purpose robotic control, with test-time scaling (TTS) gaining attention to enhance robustness beyond training. However, existing TTS methods for VLAs require additional training, verifiers, and multiple forward passes, making them impractical for deployment. Moreover, they intervene only at action decoding while keeping visual representations fixed-insufficient under perceptual ambiguity, where reconsidering how to perceive is as important as deciding what to do. To address these limitations, we propose SCALE, a simple inference strategy that jointly modulates visual perception and action based on 'self-uncertainty', inspired by uncertainty-driven exploration in Active Inference theory-requiring no additional training, no verifier, and only a single forward pass. SCALE broadens exploration in both perception and action under high uncertainty, while focusing on exploitation when confident-enabling adaptive execution across varying conditions. Experiments on simulated and real-world benchmarks demonstrate that SCALE improves state-of-the-art VLAs and outperforms existing TTS methods while maintaining single-pass efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04208</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 04:48:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canzona: A Unified, Asynchronous, and Load-Balanced Framework for Distributed Matrix-based Optimizers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06079</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06079.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liangyu Wang, Siqi Zhang, Junjie Wang, Yiming Dong, Bo Zheng, Zihan Qiu, Shengkun Tang, Di Wang, Rui Men, Dayiheng Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The scaling of Large Language Models (LLMs) drives interest in matrix-based optimizers (e.g., Shampoo, Muon, SOAP) for their convergence efficiency; yet their requirement for holistic updates conflicts with the tensor fragmentation in distributed frameworks like Megatron. Existing solutions are suboptimal: synchronous approaches suffer from computational redundancy, while layer-wise partitioning fails to reconcile this conflict without violating the geometric constraints of efficient communication primitives. To bridge this gap, we propose Canzona, a Unified, Asynchronous, and Load-Balanced framework that decouples logical optimizer assignment from physical parameter distribution. For Data Parallelism, we introduce an alpha-Balanced Static Partitioning strategy that respects atomicity while neutralizing the load imbalance. For Tensor Parallelism, we design an Asynchronous Compute pipeline utilizing Micro-Group Scheduling to batch fragmented updates and hide reconstruction overhead. Extensive evaluations on the Qwen3 model family (up to 32B parameters) on 256 GPUs demonstrate that our approach preserves the efficiency of established parallel architectures, achieving a 1.57x speedup in end-to-end iteration time and reducing optimizer step latency by 5.8x compared to the baseline.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06079</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 07:38:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ASA: Training-Free Representation Engineering for Tool-Calling Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04935</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.04935.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Youjin Wang, Run Zhou, Rong Fu, Shuaishuai Cao, Hongwei Zeng, Jiaxuan Lu, Sicheng Fan, Jiaqiao Zhao, Liangming Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Adapting LLM agents to domain-specific tool calling remains notably brittle under evolving interfaces. Prompt and schema engineering is easy to deploy but often fragile under distribution shift and strict parsers, while continual parameter-efficient fine-tuning improves reliability at the cost of training, maintenance, and potential forgetting. We identify a critical Lazy Agent failure mode where tool necessity is nearly perfectly decodable from mid-layer activations, yet the model remains conservative in entering tool mode, revealing a representation-behavior gap. We propose Activation Steering Adapter (ASA), a training-free, inference-time controller that performs a single-shot mid-layer intervention and targets tool domains via a router-conditioned mixture of steering vectors with a probe-guided signed gate to amplify true intent while suppressing spurious triggers. On MTU-Bench with Qwen2.5-1.5B, ASA improves strict tool-use F1 from 0.18 to 0.50 while reducing the false positive rate from 0.15 to 0.05, using only about 20KB of portable assets and no weight updates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04935</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 14:20:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of Space: Can Foundation Models Construct Spatial Beliefs through Active Exploration?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07055</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07055.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pingyue Zhang, Zihan Huang, Yue Wang, Jieyu Zhang, Letian Xue, Zihan Wang, Qineng Wang, Keshigeyan Chandrasegaran, Ruohan Zhang, Yejin Choi, Ranjay Krishna, Jiajun Wu, Li Fei-Fei, Manling Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatial embodied intelligence requires agents to act to acquire information under partial observability. While multimodal foundation models excel at passive perception, their capacity for active, self-directed exploration remains understudied. We propose Theory of Space, defined as an agent's ability to actively acquire information through self-directed, active exploration and to construct, revise, and exploit a spatial belief from sequential, partial observations. We evaluate this through a benchmark where the goal is curiosity-driven exploration to build an accurate cognitive map. A key innovation is spatial belief probing, which prompts models to reveal their internal spatial representations at each step. Our evaluation of state-of-the-art models reveals several critical bottlenecks. First, we identify an Active-Passive Gap, where performance drops significantly when agents must autonomously gather information. Second, we find high inefficiency, as models explore unsystematically compared to program-based proxies. Through belief probing, we diagnose that while perception is an initial bottleneck, global beliefs suffer from instability that causes spatial knowledge to degrade over time. Finally, using a false belief paradigm, we uncover Belief Inertia, where agents fail to update obsolete priors with new evidence. This issue is present in text-based agents but is particularly severe in vision-based models. Our findings suggest that current foundation models struggle to maintain coherent, revisable spatial beliefs during active exploration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07055</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 19:06:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AudioSAE: Towards Understanding of Audio-Processing Models with Sparse AutoEncoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05027</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.05027.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Georgii Aparin, Tasnima Sadekova, Alexey Rukhovich, Assel Yermekova, Laida Kushnareva, Vadim Popov, Kristian Kuznetsov, Irina Piontkovskaya&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse Autoencoders (SAEs) are powerful tools for interpreting neural representations, yet their use in audio remains underexplored. We train SAEs across all encoder layers of Whisper and HuBERT, provide an extensive evaluation of their stability, interpretability, and show their practical utility. Over 50% of the features remain consistent across random seeds, and reconstruction quality is preserved. SAE features capture general acoustic and semantic information as well as specific events, including environmental noises and paralinguistic sounds (e.g. laughter, whispering) and disentangle them effectively, requiring removal of only 19-27% of features to erase a concept. Feature steering reduces Whisper's false speech detections by 70% with negligible WER increase, demonstrating real-world applicability. Finally, we find SAE features correlated with human EEG activity during speech perception, indicating alignment with human neural processing. The code and checkpoints are available at https://github.com/audiosae/audiosae_demo.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05027</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 20:29:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Back to Basics: Revisiting Exploration in Reinforcement Learning for LLM Reasoning via Generative Probabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05281</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.05281.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengyi Li, Elizaveta Goncharova, Andrey Kuznetsov, Ivan Oseledets&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as an indispensable paradigm for enhancing reasoning in Large Language Models (LLMs). However, standard policy optimization methods, such as Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), often converge to low-entropy policies, leading to severe mode collapse and limited output diversity. We analyze this issue from the perspective of sampling probability dynamics, identifying that the standard objective disproportionately reinforces the highest-likelihood paths, thereby suppressing valid alternative reasoning chains. To address this, we propose a novel Advantage Re-weighting Mechanism (ARM) designed to equilibrate the confidence levels across all correct responses. By incorporating Prompt Perplexity and Answer Confidence into the advantage estimation, our method dynamically reshapes the reward signal to attenuate the gradient updates of over-confident reasoning paths, while redistributing probability mass toward under-explored correct solutions. Empirical results demonstrate that our approach significantly enhances generative diversity and response entropy while maintaining competitive accuracy, effectively achieving a superior trade-off between exploration and exploitation in reasoning tasks. Empirical results on Qwen2.5 and DeepSeek models across mathematical and coding benchmarks show that ProGRPO significantly mitigates entropy collapse. Specifically, on Qwen2.5-7B, our method outperforms GRPO by 5.7% in Pass@1 and, notably, by 13.9% in Pass@32, highlighting its superior capability in generating diverse correct reasoning paths.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05281</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 04:06:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OPUS: Towards Efficient and Principled Data Selection in Large Language Model Pre-training in Every Iteration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05400</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.05400.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaobo Wang, Xuan Ouyang, Tianyi Xu, Yuzheng Hu, Jialin Liu, Guo Chen, Tianyu Zhang, Junhao Zheng, Kexin Yang, Xingzhang Ren, Dayiheng Liu, Linfeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 311&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As high-quality public text approaches exhaustion, a phenomenon known as the Data Wall, pre-training is shifting from more tokens to better tokens. However, existing methods either rely on heuristic static filters that ignore training dynamics, or use dynamic yet optimizer-agnostic criteria based on raw gradients. We propose OPUS (Optimizer-induced Projected Utility Selection), a dynamic data selection framework that defines utility in the optimizer-induced update space. OPUS scores candidates by projecting their effective updates, shaped by modern optimizers, onto a target direction derived from a stable, in-distribution proxy. To ensure scalability, we employ Ghost technique with CountSketch for computational efficiency, and Boltzmann sampling for data diversity, incurring only 4.7\% additional compute overhead. OPUS achieves remarkable results across diverse corpora, quality tiers, optimizers, and model scales. In pre-training of GPT-2 Large/XL on FineWeb and FineWeb-Edu with 30B tokens, OPUS outperforms industrial-level baselines and even full 200B-token training. Moreover, when combined with industrial-level static filters, OPUS further improves pre-training efficiency, even with lower-quality data. Furthermore, in continued pre-training of Qwen3-8B-Base on SciencePedia, OPUS achieves superior performance using only 0.5B tokens compared to full training with 3B tokens, demonstrating significant data efficiency gains in specialized domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05400</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 07:34:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling Implicit Advantage Symmetry: Why GRPO Struggles with Exploration and Difficulty Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05548</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.05548.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiqi Yu, Zhangquan Chen, Mengting Liu, Heye Zhang, Liangqiong Qu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR), particularly GRPO, has become the standard for eliciting LLM reasoning. However, its efficiency in exploration and difficulty adaptation remains an open challenge. In this work, we argue that these bottlenecks stem from an implicit advantage symmetry inherent in Group Relative Advantage Estimation (GRAE). This symmetry induces two critical limitations: (i) at the group level, strict symmetry in weights between correct and incorrect trajectories leaves unsampled action logits unchanged, thereby hindering exploration of novel correct solution. (ii) at the sample level, the algorithm implicitly prioritizes medium-difficulty samples, remaining agnostic to the non-stationary demands of difficulty focus. Through controlled experiments, we reveal that this symmetric property is sub-optimal, yielding two pivotal insights: (i) asymmetrically suppressing the advantages of correct trajectories encourages essential exploration. (ii) learning efficiency is maximized by a curriculum-like transition-prioritizing simpler samples initially before gradually shifting to complex ones. Motivated by these findings, we propose Asymmetric GRAE (A-GRAE), which dynamically modulates exploration incentives and sample-difficulty focus. Experiments across seven benchmarks demonstrate that A-GRAE consistently improves GRPO and its variants across both LLMs and MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05548</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 11:07:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse Video Generation Propels Real-World Beyond-the-View Vision-Language Navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05827</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.05827.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hai Zhang, Siqi Liang, Li Chen, Yuxian Li, Yukuan Xu, Yichao Zhong, Fu Zhang, Hongyang Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Why must vision-language navigation be bound to detailed and verbose language instructions? While such details ease decision-making, they fundamentally contradict the goal for navigation in the real-world. Ideally, agents should possess the autonomy to navigate in unknown environments guided solely by simple and high-level intents. Realizing this ambition introduces a formidable challenge: Beyond-the-View Navigation (BVN), where agents must locate distant, unseen targets without dense and step-by-step guidance. Existing large language model (LLM)-based methods, though adept at following dense instructions, often suffer from short-sighted behaviors due to their reliance on short-horimzon supervision. Simply extending the supervision horizon, however, destabilizes LLM training. In this work, we identify that video generation models inherently benefit from long-horizon supervision to align with language instructions, rendering them uniquely suitable for BVN tasks. Capitalizing on this insight, we propose introducing the video generation model into this field for the first time. Yet, the prohibitive latency for generating videos spanning tens of seconds makes real-world deployment impractical. To bridge this gap, we propose SparseVideoNav, achieving sub-second trajectory inference guided by a generated sparse future spanning a 20-second horizon. This yields a remarkable 27x speed-up compared to the unoptimized counterpart. Extensive real-world zero-shot experiments demonstrate that SparseVideoNav achieves 2.5x the success rate of state-of-the-art LLM baselines on BVN tasks and marks the first realization of such capability in challenging night scenes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05827</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 16:16:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OdysseyArena: Benchmarking Large Language Models For Long-Horizon, Active and Inductive Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05843</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.05843.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fangzhi Xu, Hang Yan, Qiushi Sun, Jinyang Wu, Zixian Huang, Muye Huang, Jingyang Gong, Zichen Ding, Kanzhi Cheng, Yian Wang, Xinyu Che, Zeyi Sun, Jian Zhang, Zhangyue Yin, Haoran Luo, Xuanjing Huang, Ben Kao, Jun Liu, Qika Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of Large Language Models (LLMs) has catalyzed the development of autonomous agents capable of navigating complex environments. However, existing evaluations primarily adopt a deductive paradigm, where agents execute tasks based on explicitly provided rules and static goals, often within limited planning horizons. Crucially, this neglects the inductive necessity for agents to discover latent transition laws from experience autonomously, which is the cornerstone for enabling agentic foresight and sustaining strategic coherence. To bridge this gap, we introduce OdysseyArena, which re-centers agent evaluation on long-horizon, active, and inductive interactions. We formalize and instantiate four primitives, translating abstract transition dynamics into concrete interactive environments. Building upon this, we establish OdysseyArena-Lite for standardized benchmarking, providing a set of 120 tasks to measure an agent's inductive efficiency and long-horizon discovery. Pushing further, we introduce OdysseyArena-Challenge to stress-test agent stability across extreme interaction horizons (e.g., &gt; 200 steps). Extensive experiments on 15+ leading LLMs reveal that even frontier models exhibit a deficiency in inductive scenarios, identifying a critical bottleneck in the pursuit of autonomous discovery in complex environments. Our code and data are available at https://github.com/xufangzhi/Odyssey-Arena&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05843</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 16:31:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniVideo-R1: Reinforcing Audio-visual Reasoning with Query Intention and Modality Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05847</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.05847.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhangquan Chen, Jiale Tao, Ruihuang Li, Yihao Hu, Ruitao Chen, Zhantao Yang, Xinlei Yu, Haodong Jing, Manyuan Zhang, Shuai Shao, Biao Wang, Qinglin Lu, Ruqi Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While humans perceive the world through diverse modalities that operate synergistically to support a holistic understanding of their surroundings, existing omnivideo models still face substantial challenges on audio-visual understanding tasks. In this paper, we propose OmniVideo-R1, a novel reinforced framework that improves mixed-modality reasoning. OmniVideo-R1 empowers models to "think with omnimodal cues" by two key strategies: (1) query-intensive grounding based on self-supervised learning paradigms; and (2) modality-attentive fusion built upon contrastive learning paradigms. Extensive experiments on multiple benchmarks demonstrate that OmniVideo-R1 consistently outperforms strong baselines, highlighting its effectiveness and robust generalization capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05847</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 16:35:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Improving Multilingual Long Reasoning via Translation-Reasoning Integrated Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05940</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.05940.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junxiao Liu, Zhijun Wang, Yixiao Li, Zhejian Lai, Liqian Huang, Xin Huang, Xue Han, Junlan Feng, Shujian Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long reasoning models often struggle in multilingual settings: they tend to reason in English for non-English questions; when constrained to reasoning in the question language, accuracies drop substantially. The struggle is caused by the limited abilities for both multilingual question understanding and multilingual reasoning. To address both problems, we propose TRIT (Translation-Reasoning Integrated Training), a self-improving framework that integrates the training of translation into multilingual reasoning. Without external feedback or additional multilingual data, our method jointly enhances multilingual question understanding and response generation. On MMATH, our method outperforms multiple baselines by an average of 7 percentage points, improving both answer correctness and language consistency. Further analysis reveals that integrating translation training improves cross-lingual question alignment by over 10 percentage points and enhances translation quality for both mathematical questions and general-domain text, with gains up to 8.4 COMET points on FLORES-200.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05940</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 17:55:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Improving World Modelling with Latent Actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06130</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06130.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifu Qiu, Zheng Zhao, Waylon Li, Yftah Ziser, Anna Korhonen, Shay B. Cohen, Edoardo M. Ponti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Internal modelling of the world -- predicting transitions between previous states X and next states Y under actions Z -- is essential to reasoning and planning for LLMs and VLMs. Learning such models typically requires costly action-labelled trajectories. We propose SWIRL, a self-improvement framework that learns from state-only sequences by treating actions as a latent variable and alternating between Forward World Modelling (FWM) P_θ(Y|X,Z) and an Inverse Dynamics Modelling (IDM) Q_φ(Z|X,Y). SWIRL iterates two phases: (1) Variational Information Maximisation, which updates the FWM to generate next states that maximise conditional mutual information with latent actions given prior states, encouraging identifiable consistency; and (2) ELBO Maximisation, which updates the IDM to explain observed transitions, effectively performing coordinate ascent. Both models are trained with reinforcement learning (specifically, GRPO) with the opposite frozen model's log-probability as a reward signal. We provide theoretical learnability guarantees for both updates, and evaluate SWIRL on LLMs and VLMs across multiple environments: single-turn and multi-turn open-world visual dynamics and synthetic textual environments for physics, web, and tool calling. SWIRL achieves gains of 16% on AURORABench, 28% on ByteMorph, 16% on WorldPredictionBench, and 14% on StableToolBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06130</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 19:04:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EgoAVU: Egocentric Audio-Visual Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06139</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06139.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ashish Seth, Xinhao Mei, Changsheng Zhao, Varun Nagaraja, Ernie Chang, Gregory P. Meyer, Gael Le Lan, Yunyang Xiong, Vikas Chandra, Yangyang Shi, Dinesh Manocha, Zhipeng Cai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding egocentric videos plays a vital role for embodied intelligence. Recent multi-modal large language models (MLLMs) can accept both visual and audio inputs. However, due to the challenge of obtaining text labels with coherent joint-modality information, whether MLLMs can jointly understand both modalities in egocentric videos remains under-explored. To address this problem, we introduce EgoAVU, a scalable data engine to automatically generate egocentric audio-visual narrations, questions, and answers. EgoAVU enriches human narrations with multimodal context and generates audio-visual narrations through cross-modal correlation modeling. Token-based video filtering and modular, graph-based curation ensure both data diversity and quality. Leveraging EgoAVU, we construct EgoAVU-Instruct, a large-scale training dataset of 3M samples, and EgoAVU-Bench, a manually verified evaluation split covering diverse tasks. EgoAVU-Bench clearly reveals the limitations of existing MLLMs: they bias heavily toward visual signals, often neglecting audio cues or failing to correspond audio with the visual source. Finetuning MLLMs on EgoAVU-Instruct effectively addresses this issue, enabling up to 113% performance improvement on EgoAVU-Bench. Such benefits also transfer to other benchmarks such as EgoTempo and EgoIllusion, achieving up to 28% relative performance gain. Code will be released to the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06139</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 19:16:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judging What We Cannot Solve: A Consequence-Based Approach for Oracle-Free Evaluation of Research-Level Math</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06291</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06291.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guijin Son, Donghun Yang, Hitesh Laxmichand Patel, Hyunwoo Ko, Amit Agarwal, Sunghee Ahn, Kyong-Ha Lee, Youngjae Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in reasoning models suggests that generating plausible attempts for research-level mathematics may be within reach, but verification remains a bottleneck, consuming scarce expert time. We hypothesize that a meaningful solution should contain enough method-level information that, when applied to a neighborhood of related questions, it should yield better downstream performance than incorrect solutions. Building on this idea, we propose Consequence-Based Utility, an oracle-free evaluator that scores each candidate by testing its value as an in-context exemplar in solving related yet verifiable questions. Our approach is evaluated on an original set of research-level math problems, each paired with one expert-written solution and nine LLM-generated solutions. Notably, Consequence-Based Utility consistently outperforms reward models, generative reward models, and LLM judges on ranking quality. Specifically, for GPT-OSS-120B, it improves Acc@1 from 67.2 to 76.3 and AUC from 71.4 to 79.6, with similarly large AUC gains on GPT-OSS-20B (69.0 to 79.2). Furthermore, compared to LLM-Judges, it also exhibits a larger solver-evaluator gap, maintaining a stronger correct-wrong separation even on instances where the underlying solver often fails to solve.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06291</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 01:10:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LatentChem: From Textual CoT to Latent Thinking in Chemical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07075</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07075.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinwu Ye, Yicheng Mao, Jia Zhang, Yimeng Liu, Li Hao, Fang Wu, Zhiwei Li, Yuxuan Liao, Zehong Wang, Zhiyuan Liu, Zhenfei Yin, Li Yuan, Philip Torr, Huan Sun, Xiangxiang Zeng, Mengdi Wang, Le Cong, Shenghua Gao, Xiangru Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chemical large language models (LLMs) predominantly rely on explicit Chain-of-Thought (CoT) in natural language to perform complex reasoning. However, chemical reasoning is inherently continuous and structural, and forcing it into discrete linguistic tokens introduces a fundamental representation mismatch that constrains both efficiency and performance. We introduce LatentChem, a latent reasoning interface that decouples chemical computation from textual generation, enabling models to perform multi-step reasoning directly in continuous latent space while emitting language only for final outputs. Remarkably, we observe a consistent emergent behavior: when optimized solely for task success, models spontaneously internalize reasoning, progressively abandoning verbose textual derivations in favor of implicit latent computation. This shift is not merely stylistic but computationally advantageous. Across diverse chemical reasoning benchmarks, LatentChem achieves a 59.88\% non-tie win rate over strong CoT-based baselines on ChemCoTBench, while delivering a 10.84times average inference speedup. Our results provide empirical evidence that chemical reasoning is more naturally and effectively realized as continuous latent dynamics rather than discretized linguistic trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07075</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 01:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>POINTS-GUI-G: GUI-Grounding Journey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06391</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06391.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongyin Zhao, Yuan Liu, Yikun Liu, Haicheng Wang, Le Tian, Xiao Zhou, Yangxiu You, Zilin Yu, Yang Yu, Jie Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of vision-language models has catalyzed the emergence of GUI agents, which hold immense potential for automating complex tasks, from online shopping to flight booking, thereby alleviating the burden of repetitive digital workflows. As a foundational capability, GUI grounding is typically established as a prerequisite for end-to-end task execution. It enables models to precisely locate interface elements, such as text and icons, to perform accurate operations like clicking and typing. Unlike prior works that fine-tune models already possessing strong spatial awareness (e.g., Qwen3-VL), we aim to master the full technical pipeline by starting from a base model with minimal grounding ability, such as POINTS-1.5. We introduce POINTS-GUI-G-8B, which achieves state-of-the-art performance with scores of 59.9 on ScreenSpot-Pro, 66.0 on OSWorld-G, 95.7 on ScreenSpot-v2, and 49.9 on UI-Vision. Our model's success is driven by three key factors: (1) Refined Data Engineering, involving the unification of diverse open-source datasets format alongside sophisticated strategies for augmentation, filtering, and difficulty grading; (2) Improved Training Strategies, including continuous fine-tuning of the vision encoder to enhance perceptual accuracy and maintaining resolution consistency between training and inference; and (3) Reinforcement Learning (RL) with Verifiable Rewards. While RL is traditionally used to bolster reasoning, we demonstrate that it significantly improves precision in the perception-intensive GUI grounding task. Furthermore, GUI grounding provides a natural advantage for RL, as rewards are easily verifiable and highly accurate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06391</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 05:14:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alleviating Sparse Rewards by Modeling Step-Wise and Long-Term Sampling Effects in Flow-Based GRPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06422</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06422.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunze Tong, Mushui Liu, Canyu Zhao, Wanggui He, Shiyi Zhang, Hongwei Zhang, Peng Zhang, Jinlong Liu, Ju Huang, Jiamang Wang, Hao Jiang, Pipei Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deploying GRPO on Flow Matching models has proven effective for text-to-image generation. However, existing paradigms typically propagate an outcome-based reward to all preceding denoising steps without distinguishing the local effect of each step. Moreover, current group-wise ranking mainly compares trajectories at matched timesteps and ignores within-trajectory dependencies, where certain early denoising actions can affect later states via delayed, implicit interactions. We propose TurningPoint-GRPO (TP-GRPO), a GRPO framework that alleviates step-wise reward sparsity and explicitly models long-term effects within the denoising trajectory. TP-GRPO makes two key innovations: (i) it replaces outcome-based rewards with step-level incremental rewards, providing a dense, step-aware learning signal that better isolates each denoising action's "pure" effect, and (ii) it identifies turning points-steps that flip the local reward trend and make subsequent reward evolution consistent with the overall trajectory trend-and assigns these actions an aggregated long-term reward to capture their delayed impact. Turning points are detected solely via sign changes in incremental rewards, making TP-GRPO efficient and hyperparameter-free. Extensive experiments also demonstrate that TP-GRPO exploits reward signals more effectively and consistently improves generation. Demo code is available at https://github.com/YunzeTong/TurningPoint-GRPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06422</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 06:37:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RelayGen: Intra-Generation Model Switching for Efficient Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06454</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06454.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiwon Song, Yoongon Kim, Jae-Joon Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs) achieve strong performance on complex reasoning tasks by generating long, multi-step reasoning trajectories, but inference-time scaling incurs substantial deployment cost. A key challenge is that generation difficulty varies within a single output, whereas existing efficiency-oriented approaches either ignore this intra-generation variation or rely on supervised token-level routing with high system complexity. We present RelayGen, a training-free, segment-level runtime model switching framework that exploits difficulty variation in long-form reasoning. Through offline analysis of generation uncertainty using token probability margins, we show that coarse-grained segment-level control is sufficient to capture difficulty transitions within a reasoning trajectory. RelayGen identifies model-specific switch cues that signal transitions to lower-difficulty segments and dynamically delegates their continuation to a smaller model, while preserving high-difficulty reasoning on the large model. Across multiple reasoning benchmarks, RelayGen substantially reduces inference latency while preserving most of the accuracy of large models. When combined with speculative decoding, RelayGen achieves up to 2.2times end-to-end speedup with less than 2\% accuracy degradation, without requiring additional training or learned routing components.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06454</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 07:35:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuantaAlpha: An Evolutionary Framework for LLM-Driven Alpha Mining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07085</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07085.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jun Han, Shuo Zhang, Wei Li, Zhi Yang, Yifan Dong, Tu Hu, Jialuo Yuan, Xiaomin Yu, Yumo Zhu, Fangqi Lou, Xin Guo, Zhaowei Liu, Tianyi Jiang, Ruichuan An, Jingping Liu, Biao Wu, Rongze Chen, Kunyi Wang, Yifan Wang, Sen Hu, Xinbing Kong, Liwen Zhang, Ronghao Chen, Huacan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 180&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Financial markets are noisy and non-stationary, making alpha mining highly sensitive to noise in backtesting results and sudden market regime shifts. While recent agentic frameworks improve alpha mining automation, they often lack controllable multi-round search and reliable reuse of validated experience. To address these challenges, we propose QuantaAlpha, an evolutionary alpha mining framework that treats each end-to-end mining run as a trajectory and improves factors through trajectory-level mutation and crossover operations. QuantaAlpha localizes suboptimal steps in each trajectory for targeted revision and recombines complementary high-reward segments to reuse effective patterns, enabling structured exploration and refinement across mining iterations. During factor generation, QuantaAlpha enforces semantic consistency across the hypothesis, factor expression, and executable code, while constraining the complexity and redundancy of the generated factor to mitigate crowding. Extensive experiments on the China Securities Index 300 (CSI 300) demonstrate consistent gains over strong baseline models and prior agentic systems. When utilizing GPT-5.2, QuantaAlpha achieves an Information Coefficient (IC) of 0.1501, with an Annualized Rate of Return (ARR) of 27.75% and a Maximum Drawdown (MDD) of 7.98%. Moreover, factors mined on CSI 300 transfer effectively to the China Securities Index 500 (CSI 500) and the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 Index (S&amp;P 500), delivering 160% and 137% cumulative excess return over four years, respectively, which indicates strong robustness of QuantaAlpha under market distribution shifts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07085</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 08:08:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AgentCPM-Report: Interleaving Drafting and Deepening for Open-Ended Deep Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06540</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06540.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yishan Li, Wentong Chen, Yukun Yan, Mingwei Li, Sen Mei, Xiaorong Wang, Kunpeng Liu, Xin Cong, Shuo Wang, Zhong Zhang, Yaxi Lu, Zhenghao Liu, Yankai Lin, Zhiyuan Liu, Maosong Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating deep research reports requires large-scale information acquisition and the synthesis of insight-driven analysis, posing a significant challenge for current language models. Most existing approaches follow a plan-then-write paradigm, whose performance heavily depends on the quality of the initial outline. However, constructing a comprehensive outline itself demands strong reasoning ability, causing current deep research systems to rely almost exclusively on closed-source or online large models. This reliance raises practical barriers to deployment and introduces safety and privacy concerns for user-authored data. In this work, we present AgentCPM-Report, a lightweight yet high-performing local solution composed of a framework that mirrors the human writing process and an 8B-parameter deep research agent. Our framework uses a Writing As Reasoning Policy (WARP), which enables models to dynamically revise outlines during report generation. Under this policy, the agent alternates between Evidence-Based Drafting and Reasoning-Driven Deepening, jointly supporting information acquisition, knowledge refinement, and iterative outline evolution. To effectively equip small models with this capability, we introduce a Multi-Stage Agentic Training strategy, consisting of cold-start, atomic skill RL, and holistic pipeline RL. Experiments on DeepResearch Bench, DeepConsult, and DeepResearch Gym demonstrate that AgentCPM-Report outperforms leading closed-source systems, with substantial gains in Insight.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06540</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 09:45:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baichuan-M3: Modeling Clinical Inquiry for Reliable Medical Decision-Making</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06570</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06570.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baichuan-M3 Team, Chengfeng Dou, Fan Yang, Fei Li, Jiyuan Jia, Qiang Ju, Shuai Wang, Tianpeng Li, Xiangrong Zeng, Yijie Zhou, Hongda Zhang, Jinyang Tai, Linzhuang Sun, Peidong Guo, Yichuan Mo, Xiaochuan Wang, Hengfu Cui, Zhishou Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Baichuan-M3, a medical-enhanced large language model engineered to shift the paradigm from passive question-answering to active, clinical-grade decision support. Addressing the limitations of existing systems in open-ended consultations, Baichuan-M3 utilizes a specialized training pipeline to model the systematic workflow of a physician. Key capabilities include: (i) proactive information acquisition to resolve ambiguity; (ii) long-horizon reasoning that unifies scattered evidence into coherent diagnoses; and (iii) adaptive hallucination suppression to ensure factual reliability. Empirical evaluations demonstrate that Baichuan-M3 achieves state-of-the-art results on HealthBench, the newly introduced HealthBench-Hallu and ScanBench, significantly outperforming GPT-5.2 in clinical inquiry, advisory and safety. The models are publicly available at https://huggingface.co/collections/baichuan-inc/baichuan-m3.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06570</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 10:08:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NanoQuant: Efficient Sub-1-Bit Quantization of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06694</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06694.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyochan Chong, Dongkyu Kim, Changdong Kim, Minseop Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Weight-only quantization has become a standard approach for efficiently serving large language models (LLMs). However, existing methods fail to efficiently compress models to binary (1-bit) levels, as they either require large amounts of data and compute or incur additional storage. In this work, we propose NanoQuant, the first post-training quantization (PTQ) method to compress LLMs to both binary and sub-1-bit levels. NanoQuant formulates quantization as a low-rank binary factorization problem, and compresses full-precision weights to low-rank binary matrices and scales. Specifically, it utilizes an efficient alternating direction method of multipliers (ADMM) method to precisely initialize latent binary matrices and scales, and then tune the initialized parameters through a block and model reconstruction process. Consequently, NanoQuant establishes a new Pareto frontier in low-memory post-training quantization, achieving state-of-the-art accuracy even at sub-1-bit compression rates. NanoQuant makes large-scale deployment feasible on consumer hardware. For example, it compresses Llama2-70B by 25.8times in just 13 hours on a single H100, enabling a 70B model to operate on a consumer 8 GB GPU.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06694</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 13:26:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F-GRPO: Don't Let Your Policy Learn the Obvious and Forget the Rare</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06717</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06717.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daniil Plyusov, Alexey Gorbatovski, Boris Shaposhnikov, Viacheslav Sinii, Alexey Malakhov, Daniil Gavrilov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) is commonly based on group sampling to estimate advantages and stabilize policy updates. In practice, large group sizes are not feasible due to computational limits, which biases learning toward trajectories that are already likely. Smaller groups often miss rare-correct trajectories while still containing mixed rewards, concentrating probability on common solutions. We derive the probability that updates miss rare-correct modes as a function of group size, showing non-monotonic behavior, and characterize how updates redistribute mass within the correct set, revealing that unsampled-correct mass can shrink even as total correct mass grows. Motivated by this analysis, we propose a difficulty-aware advantage scaling coefficient, inspired by Focal loss, that down-weights updates on high-success prompts. The lightweight modification can be directly integrated into any group-relative RLVR algorithm such as GRPO, DAPO, and CISPO. On Qwen2.5-7B across in-domain and out-of-domain benchmarks, our method improves pass@256 from 64.1 rightarrow 70.3 (GRPO), 69.3 rightarrow 72.5 (DAPO), and 73.2 rightarrow 76.8 (CISPO), while preserving or improving pass@1, without increasing group size or computational cost.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06717</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 14:07:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AIRS-Bench: a Suite of Tasks for Frontier AI Research Science Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06855</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06855.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alisia Lupidi, Bhavul Gauri, Thomas Simon Foster, Bassel Al Omari, Despoina Magka, Alberto Pepe, Alexis Audran-Reiss, Muna Aghamelu, Nicolas Baldwin, Lucia Cipolina-Kun, Jean-Christophe Gagnon-Audet, Chee Hau Leow, Sandra Lefdal, Hossam Mossalam, Abhinav Moudgil, Saba Nazir, Emanuel Tewolde, Isabel Urrego, Jordi Armengol Estape, Amar Budhiraja, Gaurav Chaurasia, Abhishek Charnalia, Derek Dunfield, Karen Hambardzumyan, Daniel Izcovich, Martin Josifoski, Ishita Mediratta, Kelvin Niu, Parth Pathak, Michael Shvartsman, Edan Toledo, Anton Protopopov, Roberta Raileanu, Alexander Miller, Tatiana Shavrina, Jakob Foerster, Yoram Bachrach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 69&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM agents hold significant promise for advancing scientific research. To accelerate this progress, we introduce AIRS-Bench (the AI Research Science Benchmark), a suite of 20 tasks sourced from state-of-the-art machine learning papers. These tasks span diverse domains, including language modeling, mathematics, bioinformatics, and time series forecasting. AIRS-Bench tasks assess agentic capabilities over the full research lifecycle -- including idea generation, experiment analysis and iterative refinement -- without providing baseline code. The AIRS-Bench task format is versatile, enabling easy integration of new tasks and rigorous comparison across different agentic frameworks. We establish baselines using frontier models paired with both sequential and parallel scaffolds. Our results show that agents exceed human SOTA in four tasks but fail to match it in sixteen others. Even when agents surpass human benchmarks, they do not reach the theoretical performance ceiling for the underlying tasks. These findings indicate that AIRS-Bench is far from saturated and offers substantial room for improvement. We open-source the AIRS-Bench task definitions and evaluation code to catalyze further development in autonomous scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06855</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 16:45:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamDojo: A Generalist Robot World Model from Large-Scale Human Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06949</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06949.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shenyuan Gao, William Liang, Kaiyuan Zheng, Ayaan Malik, Seonghyeon Ye, Sihyun Yu, Wei-Cheng Tseng, Yuzhu Dong, Kaichun Mo, Chen-Hsuan Lin, Qianli Ma, Seungjun Nah, Loic Magne, Jiannan Xiang, Yuqi Xie, Ruijie Zheng, Dantong Niu, You Liang Tan, K. R. Zentner, George Kurian, Suneel Indupuru, Pooya Jannaty, Jinwei Gu, Jun Zhang, Jitendra Malik, Pieter Abbeel, Ming-Yu Liu, Yuke Zhu, Joel Jang, Linxi "Jim" Fan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Being able to simulate the outcomes of actions in varied environments will revolutionize the development of generalist agents at scale. However, modeling these world dynamics, especially for dexterous robotics tasks, poses significant challenges due to limited data coverage and scarce action labels. As an endeavor towards this end, we introduce DreamDojo, a foundation world model that learns diverse interactions and dexterous controls from 44k hours of egocentric human videos. Our data mixture represents the largest video dataset to date for world model pretraining, spanning a wide range of daily scenarios with diverse objects and skills. To address the scarcity of action labels, we introduce continuous latent actions as unified proxy actions, enhancing interaction knowledge transfer from unlabeled videos. After post-training on small-scale target robot data, DreamDojo demonstrates a strong understanding of physics and precise action controllability. We also devise a distillation pipeline that accelerates DreamDojo to a real-time speed of 10.81 FPS and further improves context consistency. Our work enables several important applications based on generative world models, including live teleoperation, policy evaluation, and model-based planning. Systematic evaluation on multiple challenging out-of-distribution (OOD) benchmarks verifies the significance of our method for simulating open-world, contact-rich tasks, paving the way for general-purpose robot world models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06949</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 18:49:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InftyThink+: Effective and Efficient Infinite-Horizon Reasoning via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06960</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.06960.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuchen Yan, Liang Jiang, Jin Jiang, Shuaicheng Li, Zujie Wen, Zhiqiang Zhang, Jun Zhou, Jian Shao, Yueting Zhuang, Yongliang Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models achieve strong performance by scaling inference-time chain-of-thought, but this paradigm suffers from quadratic cost, context length limits, and degraded reasoning due to lost-in-the-middle effects. Iterative reasoning mitigates these issues by periodically summarizing intermediate thoughts, yet existing methods rely on supervised learning or fixed heuristics and fail to optimize when to summarize, what to preserve, and how to resume reasoning. We propose InftyThink+, an end-to-end reinforcement learning framework that optimizes the entire iterative reasoning trajectory, building on model-controlled iteration boundaries and explicit summarization. InftyThink+ adopts a two-stage training scheme with supervised cold-start followed by trajectory-level reinforcement learning, enabling the model to learn strategic summarization and continuation decisions. Experiments on DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-1.5B show that InftyThink+ improves accuracy by 21% on AIME24 and outperforms conventional long chain-of-thought reinforcement learning by a clear margin, while also generalizing better to out-of-distribution benchmarks. Moreover, InftyThink+ significantly reduces inference latency and accelerates reinforcement learning training, demonstrating improved reasoning efficiency alongside stronger performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06960</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 18:59:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TermiGen: High-Fidelity Environment and Robust Trajectory Synthesis for Terminal Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07274</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07274.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaijie Zhu, Yuzhou Nie, Yijiang Li, Yiming Huang, Jialian Wu, Jiang Liu, Ximeng Sun, Zhenfei Yin, Lun Wang, Zicheng Liu, Emad Barsoum, William Yang Wang, Wenbo Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 196&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Executing complex terminal tasks remains a significant challenge for open-weight LLMs, constrained by two fundamental limitations. First, high-fidelity, executable training environments are scarce: environments synthesized from real-world repositories are not diverse and scalable, while trajectories synthesized by LLMs suffer from hallucinations. Second, standard instruction tuning uses expert trajectories that rarely exhibit simple mistakes common to smaller models. This creates a distributional mismatch, leaving student models ill-equipped to recover from their own runtime failures. To bridge these gaps, we introduce TermiGen, an end-to-end pipeline for synthesizing verifiable environments and resilient expert trajectories. Termi-Gen first generates functionally valid tasks and Docker containers via an iterative multi-agent refinement loop. Subsequently, we employ a Generator-Critic protocol that actively injects errors during trajectory collection, synthesizing data rich in error-correction cycles. Fine-tuned on this TermiGen-generated dataset, our TermiGen-Qwen2.5-Coder-32B achieves a 31.3% pass rate on TerminalBench. This establishes a new open-weights state-of-the-art, outperforming existing baselines and notably surpassing capable proprietary models such as o4-mini. Dataset is avaiable at https://github.com/ucsb-mlsec/terminal-bench-env.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07274</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 23:56:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure Code Generation via Online Reinforcement Learning with Vulnerability Reward Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07422</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07422.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyi Wu, Mingzhe Du, Yue Liu, Chengran Yang, Terry Yue Zhuo, Jiaheng Zhang, See-Kiong Ng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly used in software development, yet their tendency to generate insecure code remains a major barrier to real-world deployment. Existing secure code alignment methods often suffer from a functionality--security paradox, improving security at the cost of substantial utility degradation. We propose SecCoderX, an online reinforcement learning framework for functionality-preserving secure code generation. SecCoderX first bridges vulnerability detection and secure code generation by repurposing mature detection resources in two ways: (i) synthesizing diverse, reality-grounded vulnerability-inducing coding tasks for online RL rollouts, and (ii) training a reasoning-based vulnerability reward model that provides scalable and reliable security supervision. Together, these components are unified in an online RL loop to align code LLMs to generate secure and functional code. Extensive experiments demonstrate that SecCoderX achieves state-of-the-art performance, improving Effective Safety Rate (ESR) by approximately 10% over unaligned models, whereas prior methods often degrade ESR by 14-54%. We release our code, dataset and model checkpoints at https://github.com/AndrewWTY/SecCoderX.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07422</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 07:42:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLinf-USER: A Unified and Extensible System for Real-World Online Policy Learning in Embodied AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07837</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07837.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongzhi Zang, Shu'ang Yu, Hao Lin, Tianxing Zhou, Zefang Huang, Zhen Guo, Xin Xu, Jiakai Zhou, Yuze Sheng, Shizhe Zhang, Feng Gao, Wenhao Tang, Yufeng Yue, Quanlu Zhang, Xinlei Chen, Chao Yu, Yu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Online policy learning directly in the physical world is a promising yet challenging direction for embodied intelligence. Unlike simulation, real-world systems cannot be arbitrarily accelerated, cheaply reset, or massively replicated, which makes scalable data collection, heterogeneous deployment, and long-horizon effective training difficult. These challenges suggest that real-world policy learning is not only an algorithmic issue but fundamentally a systems problem. We present USER, a Unified and extensible SystEm for Real-world online policy learning. USER treats physical robots as first-class hardware resources alongside GPUs through a unified hardware abstraction layer, enabling automatic discovery, management, and scheduling of heterogeneous robots. To address cloud-edge communication, USER introduces an adaptive communication plane with tunneling-based networking, distributed data channels for traffic localization, and streaming-multiprocessor-aware weight synchronization to regulate GPU-side overhead. On top of this infrastructure, USER organizes learning as a fully asynchronous framework with a persistent, cache-aware buffer, enabling efficient long-horizon experiments with robust crash recovery and reuse of historical data. In addition, USER provides extensible abstractions for rewards, algorithms, and policies, supporting online imitation or reinforcement learning of CNN/MLP, generative policies, and large vision-language-action (VLA) models within a unified pipeline. Results in both simulation and the real world show that USER enables multi-robot coordination, heterogeneous manipulators, edge-cloud collaboration with large models, and long-running asynchronous training, offering a unified and extensible systems foundation for real-world online policy learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07837</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 06:23:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurrent-Depth VLA: Implicit Test-Time Compute Scaling of Vision-Language-Action Models via Latent Iterative Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07845</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07845.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yalcin Tur, Jalal Naghiyev, Haoquan Fang, Wei-Chuan Tsai, Jiafei Duan, Dieter Fox, Ranjay Krishna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 67&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models rely on fixed computational depth, expending the same amount of compute on simple adjustments and complex multi-step manipulation. While Chain-of-Thought (CoT) prompting enables variable computation, it scales memory linearly and is ill-suited for continuous action spaces. We introduce Recurrent-Depth VLA (RD-VLA), an architecture that achieves computational adaptivity via latent iterative refinement rather than explicit token generation. RD-VLA employs a recurrent, weight-tied action head that supports arbitrary inference depth with a constant memory footprint. The model is trained using truncated backpropagation through time (TBPTT) to efficiently supervise the refinement process. At inference, RD-VLA dynamically allocates compute using an adaptive stopping criterion based on latent convergence. Experiments on challenging manipulation tasks show that recurrent depth is critical: tasks that fail entirely (0 percent success) with single-iteration inference exceed 90 percent success with four iterations, while simpler tasks saturate rapidly. RD-VLA provides a scalable path to test-time compute in robotics, replacing token-based reasoning with latent reasoning to achieve constant memory usage and up to 80x inference speedup over prior reasoning-based VLA models. Project page: https://rd-vla.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07845</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 07:21:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LOCA-bench: Benchmarking Language Agents Under Controllable and Extreme Context Growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07962</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.07962.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weihao Zeng, Yuzhen Huang, Junxian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly capable of carrying out long-running, real-world tasks. However, as the amount of context grows, their reliability often deteriorates, a phenomenon known as "context rot". Existing long-context benchmarks primarily focus on single-step settings that evaluate a model's ability to retrieve information from a long snippet. In realistic scenarios, however, LLMs often need to act as agents that explore environments, follow instructions and plans, extract useful information, and predict correct actions under a dynamically growing context. To assess language agents in such settings, we introduce LOCA-bench (a benchmark for LOng-Context Agents). Given a task prompt, LOCA-bench leverages automated and scalable control of environment states to regulate the agent's context length. This design enables LOCA-bench to extend the context length potentially to infinity in a controlled way while keeping the underlying task semantics fixed. LOCA-bench evaluates language agents as a combination of models and scaffolds, including various context management strategies. While agent performance generally degrades as the environment states grow more complex, advanced context management techniques can substantially improve the overall success rate. We open-source LOCA-bench to provide a platform for evaluating models and scaffolds in long-context, agentic scenarios: https://github.com/hkust-nlp/LOCA-bench&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07962</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 13:20:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VidVec: Unlocking Video MLLM Embeddings for Video-Text Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08099</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08099.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Issar Tzachor, Dvir Samuel, Rami Ben-Ari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 119&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have adapted generative Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) into embedding extractors for vision tasks, typically through fine-tuning to produce universal representations. However, their performance on video remains inferior to Video Foundation Models (VFMs). In this paper, we focus on leveraging MLLMs for video-text embedding and retrieval. We first conduct a systematic layer-wise analysis, showing that intermediate (pre-trained) MLLM layers already encode substantial task-relevant information. Leveraging this insight, we demonstrate that combining intermediate-layer embeddings with a calibrated MLLM head yields strong zero-shot retrieval performance without any training. Building on these findings, we introduce a lightweight text-based alignment strategy which maps dense video captions to short summaries and enables task-related video-text embedding learning without visual supervision. Remarkably, without any fine-tuning beyond text, our method outperforms current methods, often by a substantial margin, achieving state-of-the-art results across common video retrieval benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08099</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 19:39:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak-Driven Learning: How Weak Agents make Strong Agents Stronger</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08222</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08222.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zehao Chen, Gongxun Li, Tianxiang Ai, Yifei Li, Zixuan Huang, Wang Zhou, Fuzhen Zhuang, Xianglong Liu, Jianxin Li, Deqing Wang, Yikun Ban&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 252&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As post-training optimization becomes central to improving large language models, we observe a persistent saturation bottleneck: once models grow highly confident, further training yields diminishing returns. While existing methods continue to reinforce target predictions, we find that informative supervision signals remain latent in models' own historical weak states. Motivated by this observation, we propose WMSS (Weak Agents Can Make Strong Agents Stronger), a post-training paradigm that leverages weak checkpoints to guide continued optimization. By identifying recoverable learning gaps via entropy dynamics and reinforcing them through compensatory learning, WMSS enables strong agents to improve beyond conventional post-training saturation. Experiments on mathematical reasoning and code generation datasets show that agents trained with our approach achieve effective performance improvements, while incurring zero additional inference cost.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08222</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 02:50:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SkillRL: Evolving Agents via Recursive Skill-Augmented Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08234</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08234.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peng Xia, Jianwen Chen, Hanyang Wang, Jiaqi Liu, Kaide Zeng, Yu Wang, Siwei Han, Yiyang Zhou, Xujiang Zhao, Haifeng Chen, Zeyu Zheng, Cihang Xie, Huaxiu Yao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 64&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Model (LLM) agents have shown stunning results in complex tasks, yet they often operate in isolation, failing to learn from past experiences. Existing memory-based methods primarily store raw trajectories, which are often redundant and noise-heavy. This prevents agents from extracting high-level, reusable behavioral patterns that are essential for generalization. In this paper, we propose SkillRL, a framework that bridges the gap between raw experience and policy improvement through automatic skill discovery and recursive evolution. Our approach introduces an experience-based distillation mechanism to build a hierarchical skill library SkillBank, an adaptive retrieval strategy for general and task-specific heuristics, and a recursive evolution mechanism that allows the skill library to co-evolve with the agent's policy during reinforcement learning. These innovations significantly reduce the token footprint while enhancing reasoning utility. Experimental results on ALFWorld, WebShop and seven search-augmented tasks demonstrate that SkillRL achieves state-of-the-art performance, outperforming strong baselines over 15.3% and maintaining robustness as task complexity increases. Code is available at this https://github.com/aiming-lab/SkillRL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08234</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 03:17:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>G-LNS: Generative Large Neighborhood Search for LLM-Based Automatic Heuristic Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08253</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08253.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baoyun Zhao, He Wang, Liang Zeng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Large Language Models (LLMs) have recently shown promise in Automated Heuristic Design (AHD), existing approaches typically formulate AHD around constructive priority rules or parameterized local search guidance, thereby restricting the search space to fixed heuristic forms. Such designs offer limited capacity for structural exploration, making it difficult to escape deep local optima in complex Combinatorial Optimization Problems (COPs). In this work, we propose G-LNS, a generative evolutionary framework that extends LLM-based AHD to the automated design of Large Neighborhood Search (LNS) operators. Unlike prior methods that evolve heuristics in isolation, G-LNS leverages LLMs to co-evolve tightly coupled pairs of destroy and repair operators. A cooperative evaluation mechanism explicitly captures their interaction, enabling the discovery of complementary operator logic that jointly performs effective structural disruption and reconstruction. Extensive experiments on challenging COP benchmarks, such as Traveling Salesman Problems (TSP) and Capacitated Vehicle Routing Problems (CVRP), demonstrate that G-LNS significantly outperforms LLM-based AHD methods as well as strong classical solvers. The discovered heuristics not only achieve near-optimal solutions with reduced computational budgets but also exhibit robust generalization across diverse and unseen instance distributions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08253</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 04:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Data and Reward Design for Scientific Reasoning in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08321</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08321.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijie Chen, Zhenghao Lin, Xiao Liu, Zhenzhong Lan, Yeyun Gong, Peng Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Solving open-ended science questions remains challenging for large language models, particularly due to inherently unreliable supervision and evaluation. The bottleneck lies in the data construction and reward design for scientific post-training. We develop a large-scale, systematic data processing pipeline that transforms heterogeneous open-source science data into Dr. SCI dataset, which comprises of 1M questions across eight STEM subjects, with explicit verifiable/open-ended splits, scalable difficulty annotation, and fine-grained rubrics that operationalize evaluation for open-ended answers. Building on this dataset, we propose the Dr. SCI post-training pipeline, which redesigns the standard SFT -&gt; RL workflow through three components: (i) Exploration-Expanding SFT, which broadens the model's reasoning pattern coverage prior to RL; (ii) Dynamic Difficulty Curriculum, which adapts training data to the model's evolving scientific capability; and (iii) SciRubric-Guided RL, which enables stable reinforcement learning on open-ended scientific questions via rubric-based evaluation with explicit answer correctness. Qwen3-4B-Base trained using Dr. SCI pipeline achieves 63.2 on GPQA-diamond and 32.4 on GPQA-general, consistently improves over strong post-trained baselines such as o1-mini and GPT-4o, demonstrating substantial gains in scientific reasoning, especially in open-ended settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08321</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 06:52:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prism: Spectral-Aware Block-Sparse Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08426</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08426.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinghao Wang, Pengyu Wang, Xiaoran Liu, Fangxu Liu, Jason Chu, Kai Song, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Block-sparse attention is promising for accelerating long-context LLM pre-filling, yet identifying relevant blocks efficiently remains a bottleneck. Existing methods typically employ coarse-grained attention as a proxy for block importance estimation, but often resort to expensive token-level searching or scoring, resulting in significant selection overhead. In this work, we trace the inaccuracy of standard coarse-grained attention via mean pooling to a theoretical root cause: the interaction between mean pooling and Rotary Positional Embeddings (RoPE). We prove that mean pooling acts as a low-pass filter that induces destructive interference in high-frequency dimensions, effectively creating a "blind spot" for local positional information (e.g., slash patterns). To address this, we introduce Prism, a training-free spectral-aware approach that decomposes block selection into high-frequency and low-frequency branches. By applying energy-based temperature calibration, Prism restores the attenuated positional signals directly from pooled representations, enabling block importance estimation using purely block-level operations, thereby improving efficiency. Extensive evaluations confirm that Prism maintains accuracy parity with full attention while delivering up to 5.1times speedup.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08426</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 09:31:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NarraScore: Bridging Visual Narrative and Musical Dynamics via Hierarchical Affective Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09070</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09070.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yufan Wen, Zhaocheng Liu, YeGuo Hua, Ziyi Guo, Lihua Zhang, Chun Yuan, Jian Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Synthesizing coherent soundtracks for long-form videos remains a formidable challenge, currently stalled by three critical impediments: computational scalability, temporal coherence, and, most critically, a pervasive semantic blindness to evolving narrative logic. To bridge these gaps, we propose NarraScore, a hierarchical framework predicated on the core insight that emotion serves as a high-density compression of narrative logic. Uniquely, we repurpose frozen Vision-Language Models (VLMs) as continuous affective sensors, distilling high-dimensional visual streams into dense, narrative-aware Valence-Arousal trajectories. Mechanistically, NarraScore employs a Dual-Branch Injection strategy to reconcile global structure with local dynamism: a Global Semantic Anchor ensures stylistic stability, while a surgical Token-Level Affective Adapter modulates local tension via direct element-wise residual injection. This minimalist design bypasses the bottlenecks of dense attention and architectural cloning, effectively mitigating the overfitting risks associated with data scarcity. Experiments demonstrate that NarraScore achieves state-of-the-art consistency and narrative alignment with negligible computational overhead, establishing a fully autonomous paradigm for long-video soundtrack generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09070</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 09:39:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demo-ICL: In-Context Learning for Procedural Video Knowledge Acquisition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08439</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08439.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhao Dong, Shulin Tian, Shuai Liu, Shuangrui Ding, Yuhang Zang, Xiaoyi Dong, Yuhang Cao, Jiaqi Wang, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the growing video understanding capabilities of recent Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs), existing video benchmarks primarily assess understanding based on models' static, internal knowledge, rather than their ability to learn and adapt from dynamic, novel contexts from few examples. To bridge this gap, we present Demo-driven Video In-Context Learning, a novel task focused on learning from in-context demonstrations to answer questions about the target videos. Alongside this, we propose Demo-ICL-Bench, a challenging benchmark designed to evaluate demo-driven video in-context learning capabilities. Demo-ICL-Bench is constructed from 1200 instructional YouTube videos with associated questions, from which two types of demonstrations are derived: (i) summarizing video subtitles for text demonstration; and (ii) corresponding instructional videos as video demonstrations. To effectively tackle this new challenge, we develop Demo-ICL, an MLLM with a two-stage training strategy: video-supervised fine-tuning and information-assisted direct preference optimization, jointly enhancing the model's ability to learn from in-context examples. Extensive experiments with state-of-the-art MLLMs confirm the difficulty of Demo-ICL-Bench, demonstrate the effectiveness of Demo-ICL, and thereby unveil future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08439</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 09:51:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GISA: A Benchmark for General Information-Seeking Assistant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08543</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08543.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yutao Zhu, Xingshuo Zhang, Maosen Zhang, Jiajie Jin, Liancheng Zhang, Xiaoshuai Song, Kangzhi Zhao, Wencong Zeng, Ruiming Tang, Han Li, Ji-Rong Wen, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The advancement of large language models (LLMs) has significantly accelerated the development of search agents capable of autonomously gathering information through multi-turn web interactions. Various benchmarks have been proposed to evaluate such agents. However, existing benchmarks often construct queries backward from answers, producing unnatural tasks misaligned with real-world needs. Moreover, these benchmarks tend to focus on either locating specific information or aggregating information from multiple sources, while relying on static answer sets prone to data contamination. To bridge these gaps, we introduce GISA, a benchmark for General Information-Seeking Assistants comprising 373 human-crafted queries that reflect authentic information-seeking scenarios. GISA features four structured answer formats (item, set, list, and table), enabling deterministic evaluation. It integrates both deep reasoning and broad information aggregation within unified tasks, and includes a live subset with periodically updated answers to resist memorization. Notably, GISA provides complete human search trajectories for every query, offering gold-standard references for process-level supervision and imitation learning. Experiments on mainstream LLMs and commercial search products reveal that even the best-performing model achieves only 19.30\% exact match score, with performance notably degrading on tasks requiring complex planning and comprehensive information gathering. These findings highlight substantial room for future improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08543</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:44:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLaDA2.1: Speeding Up Text Diffusion via Token Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08676</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08676.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tiwei Bie, Maosong Cao, Xiang Cao, Bingsen Chen, Fuyuan Chen, Kun Chen, Lun Du, Daozhuo Feng, Haibo Feng, Mingliang Gong, Zhuocheng Gong, Yanmei Gu, Jian Guan, Kaiyuan Guan, Hongliang He, Zenan Huang, Juyong Jiang, Zhonghui Jiang, Zhenzhong Lan, Chengxi Li, Jianguo Li, Zehuan Li, Huabin Liu, Lin Liu, Guoshan Lu, Yuan Lu, Yuxin Ma, Xingyu Mou, Zhenxuan Pan, Kaida Qiu, Yuji Ren, Jianfeng Tan, Yiding Tian, Zian Wang, Lanning Wei, Tao Wu, Yipeng Xing, Wentao Ye, Liangyu Zha, Tianze Zhang, Xiaolu Zhang, Junbo Zhao, Da Zheng, Hao Zhong, Wanli Zhong, Jun Zhou, Junlin Zhou, Liwang Zhu, Muzhi Zhu, Yihong Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While LLaDA2.0 showcased the scaling potential of 100B-level block-diffusion models and their inherent parallelization, the delicate equilibrium between decoding speed and generation quality has remained an elusive frontier. Today, we unveil LLaDA2.1, a paradigm shift designed to transcend this trade-off. By seamlessly weaving Token-to-Token (T2T) editing into the conventional Mask-to-Token (M2T) scheme, we introduce a joint, configurable threshold-decoding scheme. This structural innovation gives rise to two distinct personas: the Speedy Mode (S Mode), which audaciously lowers the M2T threshold to bypass traditional constraints while relying on T2T to refine the output; and the Quality Mode (Q Mode), which leans into conservative thresholds to secure superior benchmark performances with manageable efficiency degrade. Furthering this evolution, underpinned by an expansive context window, we implement the first large-scale Reinforcement Learning (RL) framework specifically tailored for dLLMs, anchored by specialized techniques for stable gradient estimation. This alignment not only sharpens reasoning precision but also elevates instruction-following fidelity, bridging the chasm between diffusion dynamics and complex human intent. We culminate this work by releasing LLaDA2.1-Mini (16B) and LLaDA2.1-Flash (100B). Across 33 rigorous benchmarks, LLaDA2.1 delivers strong task performance and lightning-fast decoding speed. Despite its 100B volume, on coding tasks it attains an astounding 892 TPS on HumanEval+, 801 TPS on BigCodeBench, and 663 TPS on LiveCodeBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08676</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:00:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TimeChat-Captioner: Scripting Multi-Scene Videos with Time-Aware and Structural Audio-Visual Captions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08711</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08711.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Linli Yao, Yuancheng Wei, Yaojie Zhang, Lei Li, Xinlong Chen, Feifan Song, Ziyue Wang, Kun Ouyang, Yuanxin Liu, Lingpeng Kong, Qi Liu, Pengfei Wan, Kun Gai, Yuanxing Zhang, Xu Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper proposes Omni Dense Captioning, a novel task designed to generate continuous, fine-grained, and structured audio-visual narratives with explicit timestamps. To ensure dense semantic coverage, we introduce a six-dimensional structural schema to create "script-like" captions, enabling readers to vividly imagine the video content scene by scene, akin to a cinematographic screenplay. To facilitate research, we construct OmniDCBench, a high-quality, human-annotated benchmark, and propose SodaM, a unified metric that evaluates time-aware detailed descriptions while mitigating scene boundary ambiguity. Furthermore, we construct a training dataset, TimeChatCap-42K, and present TimeChat-Captioner-7B, a strong baseline trained via SFT and GRPO with task-specific rewards. Extensive experiments demonstrate that TimeChat-Captioner-7B achieves state-of-the-art performance, surpassing Gemini-2.5-Pro, while its generated dense descriptions significantly boost downstream capabilities in audio-visual reasoning (DailyOmni and WorldSense) and temporal grounding (Charades-STA). All datasets, models, and code will be made publicly available at https://github.com/yaolinli/TimeChat-Captioner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08711</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 14:21:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOVA: Towards Scalable and Synchronized Video-Audio Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08794</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08794.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; SII-OpenMOSS Team, Donghua Yu, Mingshu Chen, Qi Chen, Qi Luo, Qianyi Wu, Qinyuan Cheng, Ruixiao Li, Tianyi Liang, Wenbo Zhang, Wenming Tu, Xiangyu Peng, Yang Gao, Yanru Huo, Ying Zhu, Yinze Luo, Yiyang Zhang, Yuerong Song, Zhe Xu, Zhiyu Zhang, Chenchen Yang, Cheng Chang, Chushu Zhou, Hanfu Chen, Hongnan Ma, Jiaxi Li, Jingqi Tong, Junxi Liu, Ke Chen, Shimin Li, Songlin Wang, Wei Jiang, Zhaoye Fei, Zhiyuan Ning, Chunguo Li, Chenhui Li, Ziwei He, Zengfeng Huang, Xie Chen, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 149&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Audio is indispensable for real-world video, yet generation models have largely overlooked audio components. Current approaches to producing audio-visual content often rely on cascaded pipelines, which increase cost, accumulate errors, and degrade overall quality. While systems such as Veo 3 and Sora 2 emphasize the value of simultaneous generation, joint multimodal modeling introduces unique challenges in architecture, data, and training. Moreover, the closed-source nature of existing systems limits progress in the field. In this work, we introduce MOVA (MOSS Video and Audio), an open-source model capable of generating high-quality, synchronized audio-visual content, including realistic lip-synced speech, environment-aware sound effects, and content-aligned music. MOVA employs a Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture, with a total of 32B parameters, of which 18B are active during inference. It supports IT2VA (Image-Text to Video-Audio) generation task. By releasing the model weights and code, we aim to advance research and foster a vibrant community of creators. The released codebase features comprehensive support for efficient inference, LoRA fine-tuning, and prompt enhancement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08794</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 15:31:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dr. MAS: Stable Reinforcement Learning for Multi-Agent LLM Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08847</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08847.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lang Feng, Longtao Zheng, Shuo He, Fuxiang Zhang, Bo An&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-agent LLM systems enable advanced reasoning and tool use via role specialization, yet reliable reinforcement learning (RL) post-training for such systems remains difficult. In this work, we theoretically pinpoint a key reason for training instability when extending group-based RL to multi-agent LLM systems. We show that under GRPO-style optimization, a global normalization baseline may deviate from diverse agents' reward distributions, which ultimately leads to gradient-norm instability. Based on this finding, we propose Dr. MAS, a simple and stable RL training recipe for multi-agent LLM systems. Dr. MAS uses an agent-wise remedy: normalizing advantages per agent using each agent's own reward statistics, which calibrates gradient scales and dramatically stabilizes training, both theoretically and empirically. Beyond the algorithm, Dr. MAS provides an end-to-end RL training framework for multi-agent LLM systems, supporting scalable orchestration, flexible per-agent LLM serving and optimization configs, and shared resource scheduling of LLM actor backends. We evaluate Dr. MAS on multi-agent math reasoning and multi-turn search benchmarks using Qwen2.5 and Qwen3 series models. Dr. MAS achieves clear gains over vanilla GRPO (e.g., +5.6\% avg@16 and +4.6\% pass@16 on math, and +15.2\% avg@16 and +13.1\% pass@16 on search) while largely eliminating gradient spikes. Moreover, it remains highly effective under heterogeneous agent-model assignments while improving efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08847</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 16:13:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InternAgent-1.5: A Unified Agentic Framework for Long-Horizon Autonomous Scientific Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08990</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.08990.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiyang Feng, Runmin Ma, Xiangchao Yan, Yue Fan, Yusong Hu, Songtao Huang, Shuaiyu Zhang, Zongsheng Cao, Tianshuo Peng, Jiakang Yuan, Zijie Guo, Zhijie Zhong, Shangheng Du, Weida Wang, Jinxin Shi, Yuhao Zhou, Xiaohan He, Zhiyin Yu, Fangchen Yu, Qihao Zheng, Jiamin Wu, Mianxin Liu, Chi Zhang, Shaowei Hou, Shuya Li, Yankai Jiang, Wenjie Lou, Lilong Wang, Zifu Wang, Jiong Wang, Wanghan Xu, Yue Deng, Dongrui Liu, Yiheng Wang, Wenlong Zhang, Fenghua Ling, Shufei Zhang, Xiaosong Wang, Shuangjia Zheng, Xun Huang, Siqi Sun, Shuyue Hu, Peng Ye, Chunfeng Song, Bin Wang, Conghui He, Yihao Liu, Xin Li, Qibin Hou, Tao Chen, Xiangyu Yue, Bin Wang, Liang He, Dahua Lin, Bowen Zhou, Bo Zhang, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce InternAgent-1.5, a unified system designed for end-to-end scientific discovery across computational and empirical domains. The system is built on a structured architecture composed of three coordinated subsystems for generation, verification, and evolution. These subsystems are supported by foundational capabilities for deep research, solution optimization, and long horizon memory. The architecture allows InternAgent-1.5 to operate continuously across extended discovery cycles while maintaining coherent and improving behavior. It also enables the system to coordinate computational modeling and laboratory experimentation within a single unified system. We evaluate InternAgent-1.5 on scientific reasoning benchmarks such as GAIA, HLE, GPQA, and FrontierScience, and the system achieves leading performance that demonstrates strong foundational capabilities. Beyond these benchmarks, we further assess two categories of discovery tasks. In algorithm discovery tasks, InternAgent-1.5 autonomously designs competitive methods for core machine learning problems. In empirical discovery tasks, it executes complete computational or wet lab experiments and produces scientific findings in earth, life, biological, and physical domains. Overall, these results show that InternAgent-1.5 provides a general and scalable framework for autonomous scientific discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08990</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:36:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI-Venus-1.5 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09082</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09082.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Veuns-Team, Changlong Gao, Zhangxuan Gu, Yulin Liu, Xinyu Qiu, Shuheng Shen, Yue Wen, Tianyu Xia, Zhenyu Xu, Zhengwen Zeng, Beitong Zhou, Xingran Zhou, Weizhi Chen, Sunhao Dai, Jingya Dou, Yichen Gong, Yuan Guo, Zhenlin Guo, Feng Li, Qian Li, Jinzhen Lin, Yuqi Zhou, Linchao Zhu, Liang Chen, Zhenyu Guo, Changhua Meng, Weiqiang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 149&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; GUI agents have emerged as a powerful paradigm for automating interactions in digital environments, yet achieving both broad generality and consistently strong task performance remains challenging.In this report, we present UI-Venus-1.5, a unified, end-to-end GUI Agent designed for robust real-world applications.The proposed model family comprises two dense variants (2B and 8B) and one mixture-of-experts variant (30B-A3B) to meet various downstream application scenarios.Compared to our previous version, UI-Venus-1.5 introduces three key technical advances: (1) a comprehensive Mid-Training stage leveraging 10 billion tokens across 30+ datasets to establish foundational GUI semantics; (2) Online Reinforcement Learning with full-trajectory rollouts, aligning training objectives with long-horizon, dynamic navigation in large-scale environments; and (3) a single unified GUI Agent constructed via Model Merging, which synthesizes domain-specific models (grounding, web, and mobile) into one cohesive checkpoint. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that UI-Venus-1.5 establishes new state-of-the-art performance on benchmarks such as ScreenSpot-Pro (69.6%), VenusBench-GD (75.0%), and AndroidWorld (77.6%), significantly outperforming previous strong baselines. In addition, UI-Venus-1.5 demonstrates robust navigation capabilities across a variety of Chinese mobile apps, effectively executing user instructions in real-world scenarios. Code: https://github.com/inclusionAI/UI-Venus; Model: https://huggingface.co/collections/inclusionAI/ui-venus&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09082</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:43:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>iGRPO: Self-Feedback-Driven LLM Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09000</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09000.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ali Hatamizadeh, Shrimai Prabhumoye, Igor Gitman, Ximing Lu, Seungju Han, Wei Ping, Yejin Choi, Jan Kautz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown promise in solving complex mathematical problems, yet they still fall short of producing accurate and consistent solutions. Reinforcement Learning (RL) is a framework for aligning these models with task-specific rewards, improving overall quality and reliability. Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) is an efficient, value-function-free alternative to Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO) that leverages group-relative reward normalization. We introduce Iterative Group Relative Policy Optimization (iGRPO), a two-stage extension of GRPO that adds dynamic self-conditioning through model-generated drafts. In Stage 1, iGRPO samples multiple exploratory drafts and selects the highest-reward draft using the same scalar reward signal used for optimization. In Stage 2, it appends this best draft to the original prompt and applies a GRPO-style update on draft-conditioned refinements, training the policy to improve beyond its strongest prior attempt. Under matched rollout budgets, iGRPO consistently outperforms GRPO across base models (e.g., Nemotron-H-8B-Base-8K and DeepSeek-R1 Distilled), validating its effectiveness on diverse reasoning benchmarks. Moreover, applying iGRPO to OpenReasoning-Nemotron-7B trained on AceReason-Math achieves new state-of-the-art results of 85.62\% and 79.64\% on AIME24 and AIME25, respectively. Ablations further show that the refinement wrapper generalizes beyond GRPO variants, benefits from a generative judge, and alters learning dynamics by delaying entropy collapse. These results underscore the potential of iterative, self-feedback-based RL for advancing verifiable mathematical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:45:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GEBench: Benchmarking Image Generation Models as GUI Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09007</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09007.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haodong Li, Jingwei Wu, Quan Sun, Guopeng Li, Juanxi Tian, Huanyu Zhang, Yanlin Lai, Ruichuan An, Hongbo Peng, Yuhong Dai, Chenxi Li, Chunmei Qing, Jia Wang, Ziyang Meng, Zheng Ge, Xiangyu Zhang, Daxin Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in image generation models have enabled the prediction of future Graphical User Interface (GUI) states based on user instructions. However, existing benchmarks primarily focus on general domain visual fidelity, leaving the evaluation of state transitions and temporal coherence in GUI-specific contexts underexplored. To address this gap, we introduce GEBench, a comprehensive benchmark for evaluating dynamic interaction and temporal coherence in GUI generation. GEBench comprises 700 carefully curated samples spanning five task categories, covering both single-step interactions and multi-step trajectories across real-world and fictional scenarios, as well as grounding point localization. To support systematic evaluation, we propose GE-Score, a novel five-dimensional metric that assesses Goal Achievement, Interaction Logic, Content Consistency, UI Plausibility, and Visual Quality. Extensive evaluations on current models indicate that while they perform well on single-step transitions, they struggle significantly with maintaining temporal coherence and spatial grounding over longer interaction sequences. Our findings identify icon interpretation, text rendering, and localization precision as critical bottlenecks. This work provides a foundation for systematic assessment and suggests promising directions for future research toward building high-fidelity generative GUI environments. The code is available at: https://github.com/stepfun-ai/GEBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09007</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:52:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact-Anchored Policies: Contact Conditioning Creates Strong Robot Utility Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09017</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09017.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zichen Jeff Cui, Omar Rayyan, Haritheja Etukuru, Bowen Tan, Zavier Andrianarivo, Zicheng Teng, Yihang Zhou, Krish Mehta, Nicholas Wojno, Kevin Yuanbo Wu, Manan H Anjaria, Ziyuan Wu, Manrong Mao, Guangxun Zhang, Binit Shah, Yejin Kim, Soumith Chintala, Lerrel Pinto, Nur Muhammad Mahi Shafiullah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The prevalent paradigm in robot learning attempts to generalize across environments, embodiments, and tasks with language prompts at runtime. A fundamental tension limits this approach: language is often too abstract to guide the concrete physical understanding required for robust manipulation. In this work, we introduce Contact-Anchored Policies (CAP), which replace language conditioning with points of physical contact in space. Simultaneously, we structure CAP as a library of modular utility models rather than a monolithic generalist policy. This factorization allows us to implement a real-to-sim iteration cycle: we build EgoGym, a lightweight simulation benchmark, to rapidly identify failure modes and refine our models and datasets prior to real-world deployment. We show that by conditioning on contact and iterating via simulation, CAP generalizes to novel environments and embodiments out of the box on three fundamental manipulation skills while using only 23 hours of demonstration data, and outperforms large, state-of-the-art VLAs in zero-shot evaluations by 56%. All model checkpoints, codebase, hardware, simulation, and datasets will be open-sourced. Project page: https://cap-policy.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09017</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent Banana: High-Fidelity Image Editing with Agentic Thinking and Tooling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09084</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09084.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruijie Ye, Jiayi Zhang, Zhuoxin Liu, Zihao Zhu, Siyuan Yang, Li Li, Tianfu Fu, Franck Dernoncourt, Yue Zhao, Jiacheng Zhu, Ryan Rossi, Wenhao Chai, Zhengzhong Tu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We study instruction-based image editing under professional workflows and identify three persistent challenges: (i) editors often over-edit, modifying content beyond the user's intent; (ii) existing models are largely single-turn, while multi-turn edits can alter object faithfulness; and (iii) evaluation at around 1K resolution is misaligned with real workflows that often operate on ultra high-definition images (e.g., 4K). We propose Agent Banana, a hierarchical agentic planner-executor framework for high-fidelity, object-aware, deliberative editing. Agent Banana introduces two key mechanisms: (1) Context Folding, which compresses long interaction histories into structured memory for stable long-horizon control; and (2) Image Layer Decomposition, which performs localized layer-based edits to preserve non-target regions while enabling native-resolution outputs. To support rigorous evaluation, we build HDD-Bench, a high-definition, dialogue-based benchmark featuring verifiable stepwise targets and native 4K images (11.8M pixels) for diagnosing long-horizon failures. On HDD-Bench, Agent Banana achieves the best multi-turn consistency and background fidelity (e.g., IC 0.871, SSIM-OM 0.84, LPIPS-OM 0.12) while remaining competitive on instruction following, and also attains strong performance on standard single-turn editing benchmarks. We hope this work advances reliable, professional-grade agentic image editing and its integration into real workflows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09084</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:59:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>χ_{0}: Resource-Aware Robust Manipulation via Taming Distributional Inconsistencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09021</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09021.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Checheng Yu, Chonghao Sima, Gangcheng Jiang, Hai Zhang, Haoguang Mai, Hongyang Li, Huijie Wang, Jin Chen, Kaiyang Wu, Li Chen, Lirui Zhao, Modi Shi, Ping Luo, Qingwen Bu, Shijia Peng, Tianyu Li, Yibo Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; High-reliability long-horizon robotic manipulation has traditionally relied on large-scale data and compute to understand complex real-world dynamics. However, we identify that the primary bottleneck to real-world robustness is not resource scale alone, but the distributional shift among the human demonstration distribution, the inductive bias learned by the policy, and the test-time execution distribution -- a systematic inconsistency that causes compounding errors in multi-stage tasks. To mitigate these inconsistencies, we propose χ_{0}, a resource-efficient framework with effective modules designated to achieve production-level robustness in robotic manipulation. Our approach builds off three technical pillars: (i) Model Arithmetic, a weight-space merging strategy that efficiently soaks up diverse distributions of different demonstrations, varying from object appearance to state variations; (ii) Stage Advantage, a stage-aware advantage estimator that provides stable, dense progress signals, overcoming the numerical instability of prior non-stage approaches; and (iii) Train-Deploy Alignment, which bridges the distribution gap via spatio-temporal augmentation, heuristic DAgger corrections, and temporal chunk-wise smoothing. χ_{0} enables two sets of dual-arm robots to collaboratively orchestrate long-horizon garment manipulation, spanning tasks from flattening, folding, to hanging different clothes. Our method exhibits high-reliability autonomy; we are able to run the system from arbitrary initial state for consecutive 24 hours non-stop. Experiments validate that χ_{0} surpasses the state-of-the-art π_{0.5} in success rate by nearly 250%, with only 20-hour data and 8 A100 GPUs. Code, data and models will be released to facilitate the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09021</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:59:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WorldCompass: Reinforcement Learning for Long-Horizon World Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09022</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09022.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zehan Wang, Tengfei Wang, Haiyu Zhang, Xuhui Zuo, Junta Wu, Haoyuan Wang, Wenqiang Sun, Zhenwei Wang, Chenjie Cao, Hengshuang Zhao, Chunchao Guo, Zhou Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This work presents WorldCompass, a novel Reinforcement Learning (RL) post-training framework for the long-horizon, interactive video-based world models, enabling them to explore the world more accurately and consistently based on interaction signals. To effectively "steer" the world model's exploration, we introduce three core innovations tailored to the autoregressive video generation paradigm: 1) Clip-level rollout Strategy: We generate and evaluate multiple samples at a single target clip, which significantly boosts rollout efficiency and provides fine-grained reward signals. 2) Complementary Reward Functions: We design reward functions for both interaction-following accuracy and visual quality, which provide direct supervision and effectively suppress reward-hacking behaviors. 3) Efficient RL Algorithm: We employ the negative-aware fine-tuning strategy coupled with various efficiency optimizations to efficiently and effectively enhance model capacity. Evaluations on the SoTA open-source world model, WorldPlay, demonstrate that WorldCompass significantly improves interaction accuracy and visual fidelity across various scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09022</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Reasoning Chains Reduce Intrinsic Dimensionality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09276</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09276.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Archiki Prasad, Mandar Joshi, Kenton Lee, Mohit Bansal, Peter Shaw&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning and its variants have substantially improved the performance of language models on complex reasoning tasks, yet the precise mechanisms by which different strategies facilitate generalization remain poorly understood. While current explanations often point to increased test-time computation or structural guidance, establishing a consistent, quantifiable link between these factors and generalization remains challenging. In this work, we identify intrinsic dimensionality as a quantitative measure for characterizing the effectiveness of reasoning chains. Intrinsic dimensionality quantifies the minimum number of model dimensions needed to reach a given accuracy threshold on a given task. By keeping the model architecture fixed and varying the task formulation through different reasoning strategies, we demonstrate that effective reasoning strategies consistently reduce the intrinsic dimensionality of the task. Validating this on GSM8K with Gemma-3 1B and 4B, we observe a strong inverse correlation between the intrinsic dimensionality of a reasoning strategy and its generalization performance on both in-distribution and out-of-distribution data. Our findings suggest that effective reasoning chains facilitate learning by better compressing the task using fewer parameters, offering a new quantitative metric for analyzing reasoning processes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09276</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 23:32:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fine-T2I: An Open, Large-Scale, and Diverse Dataset for High-Quality T2I Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09439</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09439.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xu Ma, Yitian Zhang, Qihua Dong, Yun Fu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; High-quality and open datasets remain a major bottleneck for text-to-image (T2I) fine-tuning. Despite rapid progress in model architectures and training pipelines, most publicly available fine-tuning datasets suffer from low resolution, poor text-image alignment, or limited diversity, resulting in a clear performance gap between open research models and enterprise-grade models. In this work, we present Fine-T2I, a large-scale, high-quality, and fully open dataset for T2I fine-tuning. Fine-T2I spans 10 task combinations, 32 prompt categories, 11 visual styles, and 5 prompt templates, and combines synthetic images generated by strong modern models with carefully curated real images from professional photographers. All samples are rigorously filtered for text-image alignment, visual fidelity, and prompt quality, with over 95% of initial candidates removed. The final dataset contains over 6 million text-image pairs, around 2 TB on disk, approaching the scale of pretraining datasets while maintaining fine-tuning-level quality. Across a diverse set of pretrained diffusion and autoregressive models, fine-tuning on Fine-T2I consistently improves both generation quality and instruction adherence, as validated by human evaluation, visual comparison, and automatic metrics. We release Fine-T2I under an open license to help close the data gap in T2I fine-tuning in the open community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09439</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 06:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>P1-VL: Bridging Visual Perception and Scientific Reasoning in Physics Olympiads</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09443</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09443.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yun Luo, Futing Wang, Qianjia Cheng, Fangchen Yu, Haodi Lei, Jianhao Yan, Chenxi Li, Jiacheng Chen, Yufeng Zhao, Haiyuan Wan, Yuchen Zhang, Shenghe Zheng, Junchi Yao, Qingyang Zhang, Haonan He, Wenxuan Zeng, Li Sheng, Chengxing Xie, Yuxin Zuo, Yizhuo Li, Yulun Wu, Rui Huang, Dongzhan Zhou, Kai Chen, Yu Qiao, Lei Bai, Yu Cheng, Ning Ding, Bowen Zhou, Peng Ye, Ganqu Cui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The transition from symbolic manipulation to science-grade reasoning represents a pivotal frontier for Large Language Models (LLMs), with physics serving as the critical test anchor for binding abstract logic to physical reality. Physics demands that a model maintain physical consistency with the laws governing the universe, a task that fundamentally requires multimodal perception to ground abstract logic in reality. At the Olympiad level, diagrams are often constitutive rather than illustrative, containing essential constraints, such as boundary conditions and spatial symmetries, that are absent from the text. To bridge this visual-logical gap, we introduce P1-VL, a family of open-source vision-language models engineered for advanced scientific reasoning. Our method harmonizes Curriculum Reinforcement Learning, which employs progressive difficulty expansion to stabilize post-training, with Agentic Augmentation, enabling iterative self-verification at inference. Evaluated on HiPhO, a rigorous benchmark of 13 exams from 2024-2025, our flagship P1-VL-235B-A22B becomes the first open-source Vision-Language Model (VLM) to secure 12 gold medals and achieves the state-of-the-art performance in the open-source models. Our agent-augmented system achieves the No.2 overall rank globally, trailing only Gemini-3-Pro. Beyond physics, P1-VL demonstrates remarkable scientific reasoning capacity and generalizability, establishing significant leads over base models in STEM benchmarks. By open-sourcing P1-VL, we provide a foundational step toward general-purpose physical intelligence to better align visual perceptions with abstract physical laws for machine scientific discovery.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09443</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 06:28:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BagelVLA: Enhancing Long-Horizon Manipulation via Interleaved Vision-Language-Action Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09849</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09849.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yucheng Hu, Jianke Zhang, Yuanfei Luo, Yanjiang Guo, Xiaoyu Chen, Xinshu Sun, Kun Feng, Qingzhou Lu, Sheng Chen, Yangang Zhang, Wei Li, Jianyu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Equipping embodied agents with the ability to reason about tasks, foresee physical outcomes, and generate precise actions is essential for general-purpose manipulation. While recent Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models have leveraged pre-trained foundation models, they typically focus on either linguistic planning or visual forecasting in isolation. These methods rarely integrate both capabilities simultaneously to guide action generation, leading to suboptimal performance in complex, long-horizon manipulation tasks. To bridge this gap, we propose BagelVLA, a unified model that integrates linguistic planning, visual forecasting, and action generation within a single framework. Initialized from a pretrained unified understanding and generative model, BagelVLA is trained to interleave textual reasoning and visual prediction directly into the action execution loop. To efficiently couple these modalities, we introduce Residual Flow Guidance (RFG), which initializes from current observation and leverages single-step denoising to extract predictive visual features, guiding action generation with minimal latency. Extensive experiments demonstrate that BagelVLA outperforms existing baselines by a significant margin on multiple simulated and real-world benchmarks, particularly in tasks requiring multi-stage reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09849</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 14:54:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Code2World: A GUI World Model via Renderable Code Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09856</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09856.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhao Zheng, Li'an Zhong, Yi Wang, Rui Dai, Kaikui Liu, Xiangxiang Chu, Linyuan Lv, Philip Torr, Kevin Qinghong Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 186&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autonomous GUI agents interact with environments by perceiving interfaces and executing actions. As a virtual sandbox, the GUI World model empowers agents with human-like foresight by enabling action-conditioned prediction. However, existing text- and pixel-based approaches struggle to simultaneously achieve high visual fidelity and fine-grained structural controllability. To this end, we propose Code2World, a vision-language coder that simulates the next visual state via renderable code generation. Specifically, to address the data scarcity problem, we construct AndroidCode by translating GUI trajectories into high-fidelity HTML and refining synthesized code through a visual-feedback revision mechanism, yielding a corpus of over 80K high-quality screen-action pairs. To adapt existing VLMs into code prediction, we first perform SFT as a cold start for format layout following, then further apply Render-Aware Reinforcement Learning which uses rendered outcome as the reward signal by enforcing visual semantic fidelity and action consistency. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Code2World-8B achieves the top-performing next UI prediction, rivaling the competitive GPT-5 and Gemini-3-Pro-Image. Notably, Code2World significantly enhances downstream navigation success rates in a flexible manner, boosting Gemini-2.5-Flash by +9.5% on AndroidWorld navigation. The code is available at https://github.com/AMAP-ML/Code2World.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09856</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 14:56:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Devil Behind Moltbook: Anthropic Safety is Always Vanishing in Self-Evolving AI Societies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09877</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.09877.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenxu Wang, Chaozhuo Li, Songyang Liu, Zejian Chen, Jinyu Hou, Ji Qi, Rui Li, Litian Zhang, Qiwei Ye, Zheng Liu, Xu Chen, Xi Zhang, Philip S. Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 184&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The emergence of multi-agent systems built from large language models (LLMs) offers a promising paradigm for scalable collective intelligence and self-evolution. Ideally, such systems would achieve continuous self-improvement in a fully closed loop while maintaining robust safety alignment--a combination we term the self-evolution trilemma. However, we demonstrate both theoretically and empirically that an agent society satisfying continuous self-evolution, complete isolation, and safety invariance is impossible. Drawing on an information-theoretic framework, we formalize safety as the divergence degree from anthropic value distributions. We theoretically demonstrate that isolated self-evolution induces statistical blind spots, leading to the irreversible degradation of the system's safety alignment. Empirical and qualitative results from an open-ended agent community (Moltbook) and two closed self-evolving systems reveal phenomena that align with our theoretical prediction of inevitable safety erosion. We further propose several solution directions to alleviate the identified safety concern. Our work establishes a fundamental limit on the self-evolving AI societies and shifts the discourse from symptom-driven safety patches to a principled understanding of intrinsic dynamical risks, highlighting the need for external oversight or novel safety-preserving mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09877</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 15:18:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain of Mindset: Reasoning with Adaptive Cognitive Modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10063</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10063.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyi Jiang, Arctanx An, Hengyi Feng, Naixin Zhai, Haodong Li, Xiaomin Yu, Jiahui Liu, Hanwen Du, Shuo Zhang, Zhi Yang, Jie Huang, Yuhua Li, Yongxin Ni, Huacan Wang, Ronghao Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human problem-solving is never the repetition of a single mindset, by which we mean a distinct mode of cognitive processing. When tackling a specific task, we do not rely on a single mindset; instead, we integrate multiple mindsets within the single solution process. However, existing LLM reasoning methods fall into a common trap: they apply the same fixed mindset across all steps, overlooking that different stages of solving the same problem require fundamentally different mindsets. This single-minded assumption prevents models from reaching the next level of intelligence. To address this limitation, we propose Chain of Mindset (CoM), a training-free agentic framework that enables step-level adaptive mindset orchestration. CoM decomposes reasoning into four functionally heterogeneous mindsets: Spatial, Convergent, Divergent, and Algorithmic. A Meta-Agent dynamically selects the optimal mindset based on the evolving reasoning state, while a bidirectional Context Gate filters cross-module information flow to maintain effectiveness and efficiency. Experiments across six challenging benchmarks spanning mathematics, code generation, scientific QA, and spatial reasoning demonstrate that CoM achieves state-of-the-art performance, outperforming the strongest baseline by 4.96\% and 4.72\% in overall accuracy on Qwen3-VL-32B-Instruct and Gemini-2.0-Flash, while balancing reasoning efficiency. Our code is publicly available at https://github.com/QuantaAlpha/chain-of-mindset{https://github.com/QuantaAlpha/chain-of-mindset}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10063</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:31:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Autonomous Mathematics Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10177</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10177.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tony Feng, Trieu H. Trinh, Garrett Bingham, Dawsen Hwang, Yuri Chervonyi, Junehyuk Jung, Joonkyung Lee, Carlo Pagano, Sang-hyun Kim, Federico Pasqualotto, Sergei Gukov, Jonathan N. Lee, Junsu Kim, Kaiying Hou, Golnaz Ghiasi, Yi Tay, YaGuang Li, Chenkai Kuang, Yuan Liu, Hanzhao, Lin, Evan Zheran Liu, Nigamaa Nayakanti, Xiaomeng Yang, Heng-tze Cheng, Demis Hassabis, Koray Kavukcuoglu, Quoc V. Le, Thang Luong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in foundational models have yielded reasoning systems capable of achieving a gold-medal standard at the International Mathematical Olympiad. The transition from competition-level problem-solving to professional research, however, requires navigating vast literature and constructing long-horizon proofs. In this work, we introduce Aletheia, a math research agent that iteratively generates, verifies, and revises solutions end-to-end in natural language. Specifically, Aletheia is powered by an advanced version of Gemini Deep Think for challenging reasoning problems, a novel inference-time scaling law that extends beyond Olympiad-level problems, and intensive tool use to navigate the complexities of mathematical research. We demonstrate the capability of Aletheia from Olympiad problems to PhD-level exercises and most notably, through several distinct milestones in AI-assisted mathematics research: (a) a research paper (Feng26) generated by AI without any human intervention in calculating certain structure constants in arithmetic geometry called eigenweights; (b) a research paper (LeeSeo26) demonstrating human-AI collaboration in proving bounds on systems of interacting particles called independent sets; and (c) an extensive semi-autonomous evaluation (Feng et al., 2026a) of 700 open problems on Bloom's Erdos Conjectures database, including autonomous solutions to four open questions. In order to help the public better understand the developments pertaining to AI and mathematics, we suggest codifying standard levels quantifying autonomy and novelty of AI-assisted results. We conclude with reflections on human-AI collaboration in mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10177</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:50:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent World Model: Infinity Synthetic Environments for Agentic Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10090</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10090.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoyang Wang, Canwen Xu, Boyi Liu, Yite Wang, Siwei Han, Zhewei Yao, Huaxiu Yao, Yuxiong He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language model (LLM) have empowered autonomous agents to perform complex tasks that require multi-turn interactions with tools and environments. However, scaling such agent training is limited by the lack of diverse and reliable environments. In this paper, we propose Agent World Model (AWM), a fully synthetic environment generation pipeline. Using this pipeline, we scale to 1,000 environments covering everyday scenarios, in which agents can interact with rich toolsets (35 tools per environment on average) and obtain high-quality observations. Notably, these environments are code-driven and backed by databases, providing more reliable and consistent state transitions than environments simulated by LLMs. Moreover, they enable more efficient agent interaction compared with collecting trajectories from realistic environments. To demonstrate the effectiveness of this resource, we perform large-scale reinforcement learning for multi-turn tool-use agents. Thanks to the fully executable environments and accessible database states, we can also design reliable reward functions. Experiments on three benchmarks show that training exclusively in synthetic environments, rather than benchmark-specific ones, yields strong out-of-distribution generalization. The code is available at https://github.com/Snowflake-Labs/agent-world-model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10090</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:55:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VLA-JEPA: Enhancing Vision-Language-Action Model with Latent World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10098</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10098.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingwen Sun, Wenyao Zhang, Zekun Qi, Shaojie Ren, Zezhi Liu, Hanxin Zhu, Guangzhong Sun, Xin Jin, Zhibo Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Pretraining Vision-Language-Action (VLA) policies on internet-scale video is appealing, yet current latent-action objectives often learn the wrong thing: they remain anchored to pixel variation rather than action-relevant state transitions, making them vulnerable to appearance bias, nuisance motion, and information leakage. We introduce VLA-JEPA, a JEPA-style pretraining framework that sidesteps these pitfalls by design. The key idea is leakage-free state prediction: a target encoder produces latent representations from future frames, while the student pathway sees only the current observation -- future information is used solely as supervision targets, never as input. By predicting in latent space rather than pixel space, VLA-JEPA learns dynamics abstractions that are robust to camera motion and irrelevant background changes. This yields a simple two-stage recipe -- JEPA pretraining followed by action-head fine-tuning -- without the multi-stage complexity of prior latent-action pipelines. Experiments on LIBERO, LIBERO-Plus, SimplerEnv and real-world manipulation tasks show that VLA-JEPA achieves consistent gains in generalization and robustness over existing methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10098</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:58:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoWorld 2: Learning Transferable Knowledge from Real-world Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10102</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10102.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongwei Ren, Yunchao Wei, Xiao Yu, Guixun Luo, Yao Zhao, Bingyi Kang, Jiashi Feng, Xiaojie Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Learning transferable knowledge from unlabeled video data and applying it in new environments is a fundamental capability of intelligent agents. This work presents VideoWorld 2, which extends VideoWorld and offers the first investigation into learning transferable knowledge directly from raw real-world videos. At its core, VideoWorld 2 introduces a dynamic-enhanced Latent Dynamics Model (dLDM) that decouples action dynamics from visual appearance: a pretrained video diffusion model handles visual appearance modeling, enabling the dLDM to learn latent codes that focus on compact and meaningful task-related dynamics. These latent codes are then modeled autoregressively to learn task policies and support long-horizon reasoning. We evaluate VideoWorld 2 on challenging real-world handcraft making tasks, where prior video generation and latent-dynamics models struggle to operate reliably. Remarkably, VideoWorld 2 achieves up to 70% improvement in task success rate and produces coherent long execution videos. In robotics, we show that VideoWorld 2 can acquire effective manipulation knowledge from the Open-X dataset, which substantially improves task performance on CALVIN. This study reveals the potential of learning transferable world knowledge directly from raw videos, with all code, data, and models to be open-sourced for further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10102</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Olaf-World: Orienting Latent Actions for Video World Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10104</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10104.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxin Jiang, Yuchao Gu, Ivor W. Tsang, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling action-controllable world models is limited by the scarcity of action labels. While latent action learning promises to extract control interfaces from unlabeled video, learned latents often fail to transfer across contexts: they entangle scene-specific cues and lack a shared coordinate system. This occurs because standard objectives operate only within each clip, providing no mechanism to align action semantics across contexts. Our key insight is that although actions are unobserved, their semantic effects are observable and can serve as a shared reference. We introduce SeqΔ-REPA, a sequence-level control-effect alignment objective that anchors integrated latent action to temporal feature differences from a frozen, self-supervised video encoder. Building on this, we present Olaf-World, a pipeline that pretrains action-conditioned video world models from large-scale passive video. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method learns a more structured latent action space, leading to stronger zero-shot action transfer and more data-efficient adaptation to new control interfaces than state-of-the-art baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10104</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:58:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EgoHumanoid: Unlocking In-the-Wild Loco-Manipulation with Robot-Free Egocentric Demonstration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Modi Shi, Shijia Peng, Jin Chen, Haoran Jiang, Yinghui Li, Di Huang, Ping Luo, Hongyang Li, Li Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human demonstrations offer rich environmental diversity and scale naturally, making them an appealing alternative to robot teleoperation. While this paradigm has advanced robot-arm manipulation, its potential for the more challenging, data-hungry problem of humanoid loco-manipulation remains largely unexplored. We present EgoHumanoid, the first framework to co-train a vision-language-action policy using abundant egocentric human demonstrations together with a limited amount of robot data, enabling humanoids to perform loco-manipulation across diverse real-world environments. To bridge the embodiment gap between humans and robots, including discrepancies in physical morphology and viewpoint, we introduce a systematic alignment pipeline spanning from hardware design to data processing. A portable system for scalable human data collection is developed, and we establish practical collection protocols to improve transferability. At the core of our human-to-humanoid alignment pipeline lies two key components. The view alignment reduces visual domain discrepancies caused by camera height and perspective variation. The action alignment maps human motions into a unified, kinematically feasible action space for humanoid control. Extensive real-world experiments demonstrate that incorporating robot-free egocentric data significantly outperforms robot-only baselines by 51\%, particularly in unseen environments. Our analysis further reveals which behaviors transfer effectively and the potential for scaling human data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10106</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Internalizing Meta-Experience into Memory for Guided Reinforcement Learning in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10224</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10224.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiting Huang, Zecheng Li, Yu Zeng, Qingnan Ren, Zhen Fang, Qisheng Su, Kou Shi, Lin Chen, Zehui Chen, Feng Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as an effective approach for enhancing the reasoning capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs). Despite its efficacy, RLVR faces a meta-learning bottleneck: it lacks mechanisms for error attribution and experience internalization intrinsic to the human learning cycle beyond practice and verification, thereby limiting fine-grained credit assignment and reusable knowledge formation. We term such reusable knowledge representations derived from past errors as meta-experience. Based on this insight, we propose Meta-Experience Learning (MEL), a novel framework that incorporates self-distilled meta-experience into the model's parametric memory. Building upon standard RLVR, we introduce an additional design that leverages the LLM's self-verification capability to conduct contrastive analysis on paired correct and incorrect trajectories, identify the precise bifurcation points where reasoning errors arise, and summarize them into generalizable meta-experience. The meta-experience is further internalized into the LLM's parametric memory by minimizing the negative log-likelihood, which induces a language-modeled reward signal that bridges correct and incorrect reasoning trajectories and facilitates effective knowledge reuse. Experimental results demonstrate that MEL achieves consistent improvements on benchmarks, yielding 3.92%--4.73% Pass@1 gains across varying model sizes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10224</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 19:16:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blockwise Advantage Estimation for Multi-Objective RL with Verifiable Rewards</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10231</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10231.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kirill Pavlenko, Alexander Golubev, Simon Karasik, Boris Yangel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) assigns a single scalar advantage to all tokens in a completion. For structured generations with explicit segments and objectives, this couples unrelated reward signals across segments, leading to objective interference and misattributed credit. We propose Blockwise Advantage Estimation, a family of GRPO-compatible methods that assigns each objective its own advantage and applies it only to the tokens in the corresponding text block, reducing reliance on hand-designed scalar rewards and scaling naturally to additional objectives. A key challenge is estimating advantages for later blocks whose rewards are conditioned on sampled prefixes; standard unbiased approaches require expensive nested rollouts from intermediate states. Concretely, we introduce an Outcome-Conditioned Baseline that approximates intermediate state values using only within-group statistics by stratifying samples according to a prefix-derived intermediate outcome. On math tasks with uncertainty estimation, our method mitigates reward interference, is competitive with a state-of-the-art reward-designed approach, and preserves test-time gains from confidence-weighted ensembling. More broadly, it provides a modular recipe for optimizing sequential objectives in structured generations without additional rollouts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10231</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 19:22:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiveMedBench: A Contamination-Free Medical Benchmark for LLMs with Automated Rubric Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10367</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10367.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiling Yan, Dingjie Song, Zhe Fang, Yisheng Ji, Xiang Li, Quanzheng Li, Lichao Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The deployment of Large Language Models (LLMs) in high-stakes clinical settings demands rigorous and reliable evaluation. However, existing medical benchmarks remain static, suffering from two critical limitations: (1) data contamination, where test sets inadvertently leak into training corpora, leading to inflated performance estimates; and (2) temporal misalignment, failing to capture the rapid evolution of medical knowledge. Furthermore, current evaluation metrics for open-ended clinical reasoning often rely on either shallow lexical overlap (e.g., ROUGE) or subjective LLM-as-a-Judge scoring, both inadequate for verifying clinical correctness. To bridge these gaps, we introduce LiveMedBench, a continuously updated, contamination-free, and rubric-based benchmark that weekly harvests real-world clinical cases from online medical communities, ensuring strict temporal separation from model training data. We propose a Multi-Agent Clinical Curation Framework that filters raw data noise and validates clinical integrity against evidence-based medical principles. For evaluation, we develop an Automated Rubric-based Evaluation Framework that decomposes physician responses into granular, case-specific criteria, achieving substantially stronger alignment with expert physicians than LLM-as-a-Judge. To date, LiveMedBench comprises 2,756 real-world cases spanning 38 medical specialties and multiple languages, paired with 16,702 unique evaluation criteria. Extensive evaluation of 38 LLMs reveals that even the best-performing model achieves only 39.2%, and 84% of models exhibit performance degradation on post-cutoff cases, confirming pervasive data contamination risks. Error analysis further identifies contextual application-not factual knowledge-as the dominant bottleneck, with 35-48% of failures stemming from the inability to tailor medical knowledge to patient-specific constraints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10367</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 23:38:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When to Memorize and When to Stop: Gated Recurrent Memory for Long-Context Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10560</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10560.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Leheng Sheng, Yongtao Zhang, Wenchang Ma, Yaorui Shi, Ting Huang, Xiang Wang, An Zhang, Ke Shen, Tat-Seng Chua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While reasoning over long context is crucial for various real-world applications, it remains challenging for large language models (LLMs) as they suffer from performance degradation as the context length grows. Recent work MemAgent has tried to tackle this by processing context chunk-by-chunk in an RNN-like loop and updating a textual memory for final answering. However, this naive recurrent memory update faces two crucial drawbacks: (i) memory can quickly explode because it can update indiscriminately, even on evidence-free chunks; and (ii) the loop lacks an exit mechanism, leading to unnecessary computation after even sufficient evidence is collected. To address these issues, we propose GRU-Mem, which incorporates two text-controlled gates for more stable and efficient long-context reasoning. Specifically, in GRU-Mem, the memory only updates when the update gate is open and the recurrent loop will exit immediately once the exit gate is open. To endow the model with such capabilities, we introduce two reward signals r^{update} and r^{exit} within end-to-end RL, rewarding the correct updating and exiting behaviors respectively. Experiments on various long-context reasoning tasks demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of GRU-Mem, which generally outperforms the vanilla MemAgent with up to 400\% times inference speed acceleration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10560</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 06:14:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step 3.5 Flash: Open Frontier-Level Intelligence with 11B Active Parameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10604</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10604.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ailin Huang, Ang Li, Aobo Kong, Bin Wang, Binxing Jiao, Bo Dong, Bojun Wang, Boyu Chen, Brian Li, Buyun Ma, Chang Su, Changxin Miao, Changyi Wan, Chao Lou, Chen Hu, Chen Xu, Chenfeng Yu, Chengting Feng, Chengyuan Yao, Chunrui Han, Dan Ma, Dapeng Shi, Daxin Jiang, Dehua Ma, Deshan Sun, Di Qi, Enle Liu, Fajie Zhang, Fanqi Wan, Guanzhe Huang, Gulin Yan, Guoliang Cao, Guopeng Li, Han Cheng, Hangyu Guo, Hanshan Zhang, Hao Nie, Haonan Jia, Haoran Lv, Hebin Zhou, Hekun Lv, Heng Wang, Heung-Yeung Shum, Hongbo Huang, Hongbo Peng, Hongyu Zhou, Hongyuan Wang, Houyong Chen, Huangxi Zhu, Huimin Wu, Huiyong Guo, Jia Wang, Jian Zhou, Jianjian Sun, Jiaoren Wu, Jiaran Zhang, Jiashu Lv, Jiashuo Liu, Jiayi Fu, Jiayu Liu, Jie Cheng, Jie Luo, Jie Yang, Jie Zhou, Jieyi Hou, Jing Bai, Jingcheng Hu, Jingjing Xie, Jingwei Wu, Jingyang Zhang, Jishi Zhou, Junfeng Liu, Junzhe Lin, Ka Man Lo, Kai Liang, Kaibo Liu, Kaijun Tan, Kaiwen Yan, Kaixiang Li, Kang An, Kangheng Lin, Lei Yang, Liang Lv, Liang Zhao, Liangyu Chen, Lieyu Shi, Liguo Tan, Lin Lin, Lina Chen, Luck Ma, Mengqiang Ren, Michael Li, Ming Li, Mingliang Li, Mingming Zhang, Mingrui Chen, Mitt Huang, Na Wang, Peng Liu, Qi Han, Qian Zhao, Qinglin He, Qinxin Du, Qiuping Wu, Quan Sun, Rongqiu Yang, Ruihang Miao, Ruixin Han, Ruosi Wan, Ruyan Guo, Shan Wang, Shaoliang Pang, Shaowen Yang, Shengjie Fan, Shijie Shang, Shiliang Yang, Shiwei Li, Shuangshuang Tian, Siqi Liu, Siye Wu, Siyu Chen, Song Yuan, Tiancheng Cao, Tianchi Yue, Tianhao Cheng, Tianning Li, Tingdan Luo, Wang You, Wei Ji, Wei Yuan, Wei Zhang, Weibo Wu, Weihao Xie, Wen Sun, Wenjin Deng, Wenzhen Zheng, Wuxun Xie, Xiangfeng Wang, Xiangwen Kong, Xiangyu Liu, Xiangyu Zhang, Xiaobo Yang, Xiaojia Liu, Xiaolan Yuan, Xiaoran Jiao, Xiaoxiao Ren, Xiaoyun Zhang, Xin Li, Xin Liu, Xin Wu, Xing Chen, Xingping Yang, Xinran Wang, Xu Zhao, Xuan He, Xuanti Feng, Xuedan Cai, Xuqiang Zhou, Yanbo Yu, Yang Li, Yang Xu, Yanlin Lai, Yanming Xu, Yaoyu Wang, Yeqing Shen, Yibo Zhu, Yichen Lv, Yicheng Cao, Yifeng Gong, Yijing Yang, Yikun Yang, Yin Zhao, Yingxiu Zhao, Yinmin Zhang, Yitong Zhang, Yixuan Zhang, Yiyang Chen, Yongchi Zhao, Yongshen Long, Yongyao Wang, Yousong Guan, Yu Zhou, Yuang Peng, Yuanhao Ding, Yuantao Fan, Yuanzhen Yang, Yuchu Luo, Yudi Zhao, Yue Peng, Yueqiang Lin, Yufan Lu, Yuling Zhao, Yunzhou Ju, Yurong Zhang, Yusheng Li, Yuxiang Yang, Yuyang Chen, Yuzhu Cai, Zejia Weng, Zetao Hong, Zexi Li, Zhe Xie, Zheng Ge, Zheng Gong, Zheng Zeng, Zhenyi Lu, Zhewei Huang, Zhichao Chang, Zhiguo Huang, Zhiheng Hu, Zidong Yang, Zili Wang, Ziqi Ren, Zixin Zhang, Zixuan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 174&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Step 3.5 Flash, a sparse Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) model that bridges frontier-level agentic intelligence and computational efficiency. We focus on what matters most when building agents: sharp reasoning and fast, reliable execution. Step 3.5 Flash pairs a 196B-parameter foundation with 11B active parameters for efficient inference. It is optimized with interleaved 3:1 sliding-window/full attention and Multi-Token Prediction (MTP-3) to reduce the latency and cost of multi-round agentic interactions. To reach frontier-level intelligence, we design a scalable reinforcement learning framework that combines verifiable signals with preference feedback, while remaining stable under large-scale off-policy training, enabling consistent self-improvement across mathematics, code, and tool use. Step 3.5 Flash demonstrates strong performance across agent, coding, and math tasks, achieving 85.4% on IMO-AnswerBench, 86.4% on LiveCodeBench-v6 (2024.08-2025.05), 88.2% on tau2-Bench, 69.0% on BrowseComp (with context management), and 51.0% on Terminal-Bench 2.0, comparable to frontier models such as GPT-5.2 xHigh and Gemini 3.0 Pro. By redefining the efficiency frontier, Step 3.5 Flash provides a high-density foundation for deploying sophisticated agents in real-world industrial environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10604</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 07:53:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Causal Kalman Filtering for Stable and Effective Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10609</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10609.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuo He, Lang Feng, Xin Cheng, Lei Feng, Bo An&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning for large language models suffers from high-variance token-level importance sampling (IS) ratios, which would destabilize policy optimization at scale. To improve stability, recent methods typically use a fixed sequence-level IS ratio for all tokens in a sequence or adjust each token's IS ratio separately, thereby neglecting temporal off-policy derivation across tokens in a sequence. In this paper, we first empirically identify that local off-policy deviation is structurally inconsistent at the token level, which may distort policy-gradient updates across adjacent tokens and lead to training collapse. To address the issue, we propose Online Causal Kalman Filtering for stable and effective Policy Optimization (KPO). Concretely, we model the desired IS ratio as a latent state that evolves across tokens and apply a Kalman filter to update this state online and autoregressively based on the states of past tokens, regardless of future tokens. The resulting filtered IS ratios preserve token-wise local structure-aware variation while strongly smoothing noise spikes, yielding more stable and effective policy updates. Experimentally, KPO achieves superior results on challenging math reasoning datasets compared with state-of-the-art counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10609</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 07:57:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Do Decoder-Only LLMs Perceive Users? Rethinking Attention Masking for User Representation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10622</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10622.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiahao Yuan, Yike Xu, Jinyong Wen, Baokun Wang, Yang Chen, Xiaotong Lin, Wuliang Huang, Ziyi Gao, Xing Fu, Yu Cheng, Weiqiang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Decoder-only large language models are increasingly used as behavioral encoders for user representation learning, yet the impact of attention masking on the quality of user embeddings remains underexplored. In this work, we conduct a systematic study of causal, hybrid, and bidirectional attention masks within a unified contrastive learning framework trained on large-scale real-world Alipay data that integrates long-horizon heterogeneous user behaviors. To improve training dynamics when transitioning from causal to bidirectional attention, we propose Gradient-Guided Soft Masking, a gradient-based pre-warmup applied before a linear scheduler that gradually opens future attention during optimization. Evaluated on 9 industrial user cognition benchmarks covering prediction, preference, and marketing sensitivity tasks, our approach consistently yields more stable training and higher-quality bidirectional representations compared with causal, hybrid, and scheduler-only baselines, while remaining compatible with decoder pretraining. Overall, our findings highlight the importance of masking design and training transition in adapting decoder-only LLMs for effective user representation learning. Our code is available at https://github.com/JhCircle/Deepfind-GGSM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10622</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 08:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOSS-Audio-Tokenizer: Scaling Audio Tokenizers for Future Audio Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10934</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10934.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yitian Gong, Kuangwei Chen, Zhaoye Fei, Xiaogui Yang, Ke Chen, Yang Wang, Kexin Huang, Mingshu Chen, Ruixiao Li, Qingyuan Cheng, Shimin Li, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Discrete audio tokenizers are fundamental to empowering large language models with native audio processing and generation capabilities. Despite recent progress, existing approaches often rely on pretrained encoders, semantic distillation, or heterogeneous CNN-based architectures. These designs introduce fixed inductive biases that limit reconstruction fidelity and hinder effective scaling. In this paper, we argue that discrete audio tokenization should be learned fully end-to-end using a homogeneous and scalable architecture. To this end, we first propose CAT (Causal Audio Tokenizer with Transformer), a purely Transformer-based architecture that jointly optimizes the encoder, quantizer, and decoder from scratch for high-fidelity reconstruction. Building on the CAT architecture, we develop MOSS-Audio-Tokenizer, a large-scale audio tokenizer featuring 1.6 billion parameters, pre-trained on 3 million hours of diverse, general audio data. We show that this simple, fully end-to-end approach built from homogeneous, causal Transformer blocks scales gracefully and supports high-fidelity reconstruction across diverse audio domains. Across speech, sound, and music, MOSS-Audio-Tokenizer consistently outperforms prior codecs over a wide range of bitrates, while exhibiting predictable improvements with increased scale. Notably, leveraging the discrete tokens from our model, we develop the first purely autoregressive TTS model that surpasses prior non-autoregressive and cascaded systems. Furthermore, MOSS-Audio-Tokenizer enables competitive ASR performance without auxiliary encoders. Our findings position the CAT architecture as a unified, scalable interface for the next generation of native audio foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10934</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 15:13:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FeatureBench: Benchmarking Agentic Coding for Complex Feature Development</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10975</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.10975.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qixing Zhou, Jiacheng Zhang, Haiyang Wang, Rui Hao, Jiahe Wang, Minghao Han, Yuxue Yang, Shuzhe Wu, Feiyang Pan, Lue Fan, Dandan Tu, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agents powered by large language models (LLMs) are increasingly adopted in the software industry, contributing code as collaborators or even autonomous developers. As their presence grows, it becomes important to assess the current boundaries of their coding abilities. Existing agentic coding benchmarks, however, cover a limited task scope, e.g., bug fixing within a single pull request (PR), and often rely on non-executable evaluations or lack an automated approach for continually updating the evaluation coverage. To address such issues, we propose FeatureBench, a benchmark designed to evaluate agentic coding performance in end-to-end, feature-oriented software development. FeatureBench incorporates an execution-based evaluation protocol and a scalable test-driven method that automatically derives tasks from code repositories with minimal human effort. By tracing from unit tests along a dependency graph, our approach can identify feature-level coding tasks spanning multiple commits and PRs scattered across the development timeline, while ensuring the proper functioning of other features after the separation. Using this framework, we curated 200 challenging evaluation tasks and 3825 executable environments from 24 open-source repositories in the first version of our benchmark. Empirical evaluation reveals that the state-of-the-art agentic model, such as Claude 4.5 Opus, which achieves a 74.4% resolved rate on SWE-bench, succeeds on only 11.0% of tasks, opening new opportunities for advancing agentic coding. Moreover, benefiting from our automated task collection toolkit, FeatureBench can be easily scaled and updated over time to mitigate data leakage. The inherent verifiability of constructed environments also makes our method potentially valuable for agent training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10975</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 16:06:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ROCKET: Rapid Optimization via Calibration-guided Knapsack Enhanced Truncation for Efficient Model Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11008</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11008.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ammar Ali, Baher Mohammad, Denis Makhov, Dmitriy Shopkhoev, Magauiya Zhussip, Stamatios Lefkimmiatis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present ROCKET, a training-free model compression method that achieves state-of-the-art performance in comparison with factorization, structured-sparsification and dynamic compression baselines. Operating under a global compression budget, ROCKET comprises two key innovations: First, it formulates layer-wise compression allocation as a multi-choice knapsack problem, selecting the optimal compression level for each layer to minimize total reconstruction error while adhering to a target model size. Second, it introduces a single-step sparse matrix factorization inspired by dictionary learning: using only a small calibration set, it sparsifies weight coefficients based on activation-weights sensitivity and then updates the dictionary in closed form via least squares bypassing iterative optimization, sparse coding, or backpropagation entirely. ROCKET consistently outperforms existing compression approaches across different model architectures at 20-50\% compression rates. Notably, it retains over 90\% of the original model's performance at 30\% compression without any fine-tuning. Moreover, when applying a light fine-tuning phase, recovery is substantially enhanced: for instance, compressing Qwen3-14B to an 8B-parameter model and healing it with just 30 million tokens yields performance nearly on par with the original Qwen3-8B. The code for ROCKET is at github.com/mts-ai/ROCKET/tree/main.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11008</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 16:34:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RISE: Self-Improving Robot Policy with Compositional World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11075</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11075.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiazhi Yang, Kunyang Lin, Jinwei Li, Wencong Zhang, Tianwei Lin, Longyan Wu, Zhizhong Su, Hao Zhao, Ya-Qin Zhang, Li Chen, Ping Luo, Xiangyu Yue, Hongyang Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the sustained scaling on model capacity and data acquisition, Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models remain brittle in contact-rich and dynamic manipulation tasks, where minor execution deviations can compound into failures. While reinforcement learning (RL) offers a principled path to robustness, on-policy RL in the physical world is constrained by safety risk, hardware cost, and environment reset. To bridge this gap, we present RISE, a scalable framework of robotic reinforcement learning via imagination. At its core is a Compositional World Model that (i) predicts multi-view future via a controllable dynamics model, and (ii) evaluates imagined outcomes with a progress value model, producing informative advantages for the policy improvement. Such compositional design allows state and value to be tailored by best-suited yet distinct architectures and objectives. These components are integrated into a closed-loop self-improving pipeline that continuously generates imaginary rollouts, estimates advantages, and updates the policy in imaginary space without costly physical interaction. Across three challenging real-world tasks, RISE yields significant improvement over prior art, with more than +35% absolute performance increase in dynamic brick sorting, +45% for backpack packing, and +35% for box closing, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11075</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 17:43:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DataChef: Cooking Up Optimal Data Recipes for LLM Adaptation via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11089</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11089.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yicheng Chen, Zerun Ma, Xinchen Xie, Yining Li, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In the current landscape of Large Language Models (LLMs), the curation of large-scale, high-quality training data is a primary driver of model performance. A key lever is the data recipe, which comprises a data processing pipeline to transform raw sources into training corpora. Despite the growing use of LLMs to automate individual data processing steps, such as data synthesis and filtering, the overall design of data recipes remains largely manual and labor-intensive, requiring substantial human expertise and iteration. To bridge this gap, we formulate end-to-end data recipe generation for LLM adaptation. Given a target benchmark and a pool of available data sources, a model is required to output a complete data recipe that adapts a base LLM to the target task. We present DataChef-32B, which performs online reinforcement learning using a proxy reward that predicts downstream performance for candidate recipes. Across six held-out tasks, DataChef-32B produces practical recipes that reach comparable downstream performance to those curated by human experts. Notably, the recipe from DataChef-32B adapts Qwen3-1.7B-Base to the math domain, achieving 66.7 on AIME'25 and surpassing Qwen3-1.7B. This work sheds new light on automating LLM training and developing self-evolving AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11089</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 17:56:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhyCritic: Multimodal Critic Models for Physical AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11124</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11124.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyi Xiong, Shihao Wang, Guilin Liu, Yi Dong, Ming Li, Heng Huang, Jan Kautz, Zhiding Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the rapid development of large multimodal models, reliable judge and critic models have become essential for open-ended evaluation and preference alignment, providing pairwise preferences, numerical scores, and explanatory justifications for assessing model-generated responses. However, existing critics are primarily trained in general visual domains such as captioning or image question answering, leaving physical AI tasks involving perception, causal reasoning, and planning largely underexplored. We introduce PhyCritic, a multimodal critic model optimized for physical AI through a two-stage RLVR pipeline: a physical skill warmup stage that enhances physically oriented perception and reasoning, followed by self-referential critic finetuning, where the critic generates its own prediction as an internal reference before judging candidate responses, improving judgment stability and physical correctness. Across both physical and general-purpose multimodal judge benchmarks, PhyCritic achieves strong performance gains over open-source baselines and, when applied as a policy model, further improves perception and reasoning in physically grounded tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11124</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 18:35:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GENIUS: Generative Fluid Intelligence Evaluation Suite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11144</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11144.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruichuan An, Sihan Yang, Ziyu Guo, Wei Dai, Zijun Shen, Haodong Li, Renrui Zhang, Xinyu Wei, Guopeng Li, Wenshan Wu, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified Multimodal Models (UMMs) have shown remarkable progress in visual generation. Yet, existing benchmarks predominantly assess Crystallized Intelligence, which relies on recalling accumulated knowledge and learned schemas. This focus overlooks Generative Fluid Intelligence (GFI): the capacity to induce patterns, reason through constraints, and adapt to novel scenarios on the fly. To rigorously assess this capability, we introduce GENIUS (GEN Fluid Intelligence EvalUation Suite). We formalize GFI as a synthesis of three primitives. These include Inducing Implicit Patterns (e.g., inferring personalized visual preferences), Executing Ad-hoc Constraints (e.g., visualizing abstract metaphors), and Adapting to Contextual Knowledge (e.g., simulating counter-intuitive physics). Collectively, these primitives challenge models to solve problems grounded entirely in the immediate context. Our systematic evaluation of 12 representative models reveals significant performance deficits in these tasks. Crucially, our diagnostic analysis disentangles these failure modes. It demonstrates that deficits stem from limited context comprehension rather than insufficient intrinsic generative capability. To bridge this gap, we propose a training-free attention intervention strategy. Ultimately, GENIUS establishes a rigorous standard for GFI, guiding the field beyond knowledge utilization toward dynamic, general-purpose reasoning. Our dataset and code will be released at: https://github.com/arctanxarc/GENIUS{https://github.com/arctanxarc/GENIUS}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11144</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 18:55:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Repetition Beats Data Scaling in Long-CoT Supervised Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11149</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11149.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dawid J. Kopiczko, Sagar Vaze, Tijmen Blankevoort, Yuki M. Asano&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on chain-of-thought data is an essential post-training step for reasoning language models. Standard machine learning intuition suggests that training with more unique training samples yields better generalization. Counterintuitively, we show that SFT benefits from repetition: under a fixed update budget, training for more epochs on smaller datasets outperforms single-epoch training on larger datasets. On AIME'24/25 and GPQA benchmarks, Olmo3-7B trained for 128 epochs on 400 samples outperforms the equivalent 1 epoch on 51200 samples by 12-26 percentage points, with no additional catastrophic forgetting. We find that training token accuracy reliably signals when repetition has saturated; improvements from additional epochs plateau at full memorization, a pattern consistent across all settings. These findings provide a practical approach for reasoning SFT, where scaling epochs with token accuracy as a stopping criterion can replace expensive undirected data scaling. We pose the repetition advantage, where full memorization coincides with improved generalization, as a new open problem for the community in understanding the training dynamics of large language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11149</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 18:58:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voxtral Realtime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11298</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11298.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander H. Liu, Andy Ehrenberg, Andy Lo, Chen-Yo Sun, Guillaume Lample, Jean-Malo Delignon, Khyathi Raghavi Chandu, Patrick von Platen, Pavankumar Reddy Muddireddy, Rohin Arora, Sanchit Gandhi, Sandeep Subramanian, Soham Ghosh, Srijan Mishra, Abhinav Rastogi, Alan Jeffares, Albert Jiang, Alexandre Sablayrolles, Amélie Héliou, Andrew Bai, Angele Lenglemetz, Anmol Agarwal, Anton Eliseev, Antonia Calvi, Arjun Majumdar, Baptiste Bout, Baptiste Rozière, Baudouin De Monicault, Benjamin Tibi, Clémence Lanfranchi, Connor Chen, Corentin Barreau, Corentin Sautier, Cyprien Courtot, Darius Dabert, Diego de las Casas, Elliot Chane-Sane, Enguerrand Paquin, Faruk Ahmed, Federico Baldassarre, Gabrielle Berrada, Gaëtan Ecrepont, Gauthier Guinet, Genevieve Hayes, Georgii Novikov, Giada Pistilli, Guillaume Martin, Gunjan Dhanuka, Gunshi Gupta, Han Zhou, Indraneel Mukherjee, Irene Zhang, Jaeyoung Kim, Jan Ludziejewski, Jason Rute, Joachim Studnia, John Harvill, Jonas Amar, Josselin Somerville Roberts, Julien Tauran, Karmesh Yadav, Kartik Khandelwal, Kush Jain, Laurence Aitchison, Léonard Blier, Lingxiao Zhao, Louis Martin, Lucile Saulnier, Luyu Gao, Maarten Buyl, Manan Sharma, Margaret Jennings, Marie Pellat, Mark Prins, Mathieu Poirée, Mathilde Guillaumin, Matthieu Dinot, Matthieu Futeral, Maxime Darrin, Maximilian Augustin, Mert Unsal, Mia Chiquier, Nathan Grinsztajn, Neha Gupta, Olivier Bousquet, Olivier Duchenne, Patricia Wang, Paul Jacob, Paul Wambergue, Paula Kurylowicz, Philomène Chagniot, Pierre Stock, Piotr Miłoś, Prateek Gupta, Pravesh Agrawal, Quentin Torroba, Ram Ramrakhya, Rishi Shah, Romain Sauvestre, Roman Soletskyi, Rosalie Millner, Sagar Vaze, Samuel Humeau, Siddharth Gandhi, Sumukh Aithal, Szymon Antoniak, Teven Le Scao, Théo Cachet, Theo Simon Sorg, Thibaut Lavril, Thomas Chabal, Thomas Foubert, Thomas Robert, Thomas Wang, Tim Lawson, Tom Bewley, Tom Edwards, Tyler Wang, Valeriia Nemychnikova, Van Phung, Vedant Nanda, Victor Jouault, Virgile Richard, Vladislav Bataev, Wassim Bouaziz, Wen-Ding Li, William Marshall, Xinghui Li, Xingran Guo, Xinyu Yang, Yannic Neuhaus, Yihan Wang, Zaccharie Ramzi, Zhenlin Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Voxtral Realtime, a natively streaming automatic speech recognition model that matches offline transcription quality at sub-second latency. Unlike approaches that adapt offline models through chunking or sliding windows, Voxtral Realtime is trained end-to-end for streaming, with explicit alignment between audio and text streams. Our architecture builds on the Delayed Streams Modeling framework, introducing a new causal audio encoder and Ada RMS-Norm for improved delay conditioning. We scale pretraining to a large-scale dataset spanning 13 languages. At a delay of 480ms, Voxtral Realtime achieves performance on par with Whisper, the most widely deployed offline transcription system. We release the model weights under the Apache 2.0 license.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11298</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 19:17:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LoopFormer: Elastic-Depth Looped Transformers for Latent Reasoning via Shortcut Modulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11451</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11451.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ahmadreza Jeddi, Marco Ciccone, Babak Taati&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Looped Transformers have emerged as an efficient and powerful class of models for reasoning in the language domain. Recent studies show that these models achieve strong performance on algorithmic and reasoning tasks, suggesting that looped architectures possess an inductive bias toward latent reasoning. However, prior approaches fix the number of loop iterations during training and inference, leaving open the question of whether these models can flexibly adapt their computational depth under variable compute budgets. We introduce LoopFormer, a looped Transformer trained on variable-length trajectories to enable budget-conditioned reasoning. Our core contribution is a shortcut-consistency training scheme that aligns trajectories of different lengths, ensuring that shorter loops yield informative representations while longer loops continue to refine them. LoopFormer conditions each loop on the current time and step size, enabling representations to evolve consistently across trajectories of varying length rather than drifting or stagnating. Empirically, LoopFormer demonstrates robust performance on language modeling and reasoning benchmarks even under aggressive compute constraints, while scaling gracefully with additional budget. These results show that looped Transformers are inherently suited for adaptive language modeling, opening a path toward controllable and budget-aware large language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11451</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 23:58:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking with Drafting: Optical Decompression via Logical Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11731</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11731.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingxuan Wei, Honghao He, Caijun Jia, Siyuan Li, Zheng Sun, Yuhang Xu, Yuanyuan Lin, Linzhuang Sun, Yuchen Wu, Bihui Yu, Xiangxiang Zhang, Cheng Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing multimodal large language models have achieved high-fidelity visual perception and exploratory visual generation. However, a precision paradox persists in complex reasoning tasks: optical perception systems transcribe symbols without capturing logical topology, while pixel-based generative models produce visual artifacts lacking mathematical exactness. To bridge this gap, we propose that reasoning over visual inputs be reconceptualized as optical decompression-the process of reconstructing latent logical structures from compressed visual tokens. Guided by the axiom that Parsing is Reasoning, we introduce Thinking with Drafting (TwD), which utilizes a minimalist Domain-Specific Language (DSL) as a grounding intermediate representation. Unlike standard approaches that hallucinate answers directly, TwD forces the model to draft its mental model into executable code, rendering deterministic visual proofs for self-verification. To validate this, we present VisAlg, a visual algebra benchmark. Experiments demonstrate that TwD serve as a superior cognitive scaffold. Our work establishes a closed-loop system where visual generation acts not as a creative output but as a logical verifier, offering a generalizable path for visual reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11731</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 08:54:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Think Longer to Explore Deeper: Learn to Explore In-Context via Length-Incentivized Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11748</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.11748.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Futing Wang, Jianhao Yan, Yun Luo, Ganqu Cui, Zhi Wang, Xiaoye Qu, Yue Zhang, Yu Cheng, Tao Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Achieving effective test-time scaling requires models to engage in In-Context Exploration -- the intrinsic ability to generate, verify, and refine multiple reasoning hypotheses within a single continuous context.   Grounded in State Coverage theory, our analysis identifies a critical bottleneck to enabling this capability: while broader state coverage requires longer reasoning trajectories, the probability of sampling such sequences decays exponentially during autoregressive generation, a phenomenon we term the ``Shallow Exploration Trap''.   To bridge this gap, we propose Length-Incentivized Exploration(\method).   This simple yet effective recipe explicitly encourages models to explore more via a length-based reward coupled with a redundancy penalty, thereby maximizing state coverage in two-step manner.   Comprehensive experiments across different models (Qwen3, Llama) demonstrate that \method effectively incentivize in-context exploration.   As a result, our method achieves an average improvement of 4.4\% on in-domain tasks and a 2.7\% gain on out-of-domain benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11748</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 09:24:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition-RL: Compose Your Verifiable Prompts for Reinforcement Learning of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12036</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12036.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Xu, Clive Bai, Kai Yang, Tianhao Chen, Yangkun Chen, Weijie Liu, Hao Chen, Yang Wang, Saiyong Yang, Can Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 89&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large-scale verifiable prompts underpin the success of Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR), but they contain many uninformative examples and are costly to expand further. Recent studies focus on better exploiting limited training data by prioritizing hard prompts whose rollout pass rate is 0. However, easy prompts with a pass rate of 1 also become increasingly prevalent as training progresses, thereby reducing the effective data size. To mitigate this, we propose Composition-RL, a simple yet useful approach for better utilizing limited verifiable prompts targeting pass-rate-1 prompts. More specifically, Composition-RL automatically composes multiple problems into a new verifiable question and uses these compositional prompts for RL training. Extensive experiments across model sizes from 4B to 30B show that Composition-RL consistently improves reasoning capability over RL trained on the original dataset. Performance can be further boosted with a curriculum variant of Composition-RL that gradually increases compositional depth over training. Additionally, Composition-RL enables more effective cross-domain RL by composing prompts drawn from different domains. Codes, datasets, and models are available at https://github.com/XinXU-USTC/Composition-RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12036</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 15:03:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LawThinker: A Deep Research Legal Agent in Dynamic Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12056</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12056.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinyu Yang, Chenlong Deng, Tongyu Wen, Binyu Xie, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Legal reasoning requires not only correct outcomes but also procedurally compliant reasoning processes. However, existing methods lack mechanisms to verify intermediate reasoning steps, allowing errors such as inapplicable statute citations to propagate undetected through the reasoning chain. To address this, we propose LawThinker, an autonomous legal research agent that adopts an Explore-Verify-Memorize strategy for dynamic judicial environments. The core idea is to enforce verification as an atomic operation after every knowledge exploration step. A DeepVerifier module examines each retrieval result along three dimensions of knowledge accuracy, fact-law relevance, and procedural compliance, with a memory module for cross-round knowledge reuse in long-horizon tasks. Experiments on the dynamic benchmark J1-EVAL show that LawThinker achieves a 24% improvement over direct reasoning and an 11% gain over workflow-based methods, with particularly strong improvements on process-oriented metrics. Evaluations on three static benchmarks further confirm its generalization capability. The code is available at https://github.com/yxy-919/LawThinker-agent .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12056</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 15:19:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepSight: An All-in-One LM Safety Toolkit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12092</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12092.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bo Zhang, Jiaxuan Guo, Lijun Li, Dongrui Liu, Sujin Chen, Guanxu Chen, Zhijie Zheng, Qihao Lin, Lewen Yan, Chen Qian, Yijin Zhou, Yuyao Wu, Shaoxiong Guo, Tianyi Du, Jingyi Yang, Xuhao Hu, Ziqi Miao, Xiaoya Lu, Jing Shao, Xia Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As the development of Large Models (LMs) progresses rapidly, their safety is also a priority. In current Large Language Models (LLMs) and Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) safety workflow, evaluation, diagnosis, and alignment are often handled by separate tools. Specifically, safety evaluation can only locate external behavioral risks but cannot figure out internal root causes. Meanwhile, safety diagnosis often drifts from concrete risk scenarios and remains at the explainable level. In this way, safety alignment lack dedicated explanations of changes in internal mechanisms, potentially degrading general capabilities. To systematically address these issues, we propose an open-source project, namely DeepSight, to practice a new safety evaluation-diagnosis integrated paradigm. DeepSight is low-cost, reproducible, efficient, and highly scalable large-scale model safety evaluation project consisting of a evaluation toolkit DeepSafe and a diagnosis toolkit DeepScan. By unifying task and data protocols, we build a connection between the two stages and transform safety evaluation from black-box to white-box insight. Besides, DeepSight is the first open source toolkit that support the frontier AI risk evaluation and joint safety evaluation and diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12092</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 15:43:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GigaBrain-0.5M*: a VLA That Learns From World Model-Based Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12099</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12099.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; GigaBrain Team, Boyuan Wang, Chaojun Ni, Guan Huang, Guosheng Zhao, Hao Li, Jie Li, Jindi Lv, Jingyu Liu, Lv Feng, Mingming Yu, Peng Li, Qiuping Deng, Tianze Liu, Xinyu Zhou, Xinze Chen, Xiaofeng Wang, Yang Wang, Yifan Li, Yifei Nie, Yilong Li, Yukun Zhou, Yun Ye, Zhichao Liu, Zheng Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language-action (VLA) models that directly predict multi-step action chunks from current observations face inherent limitations due to constrained scene understanding and weak future anticipation capabilities. In contrast, video world models pre-trained on web-scale video corpora exhibit robust spatiotemporal reasoning and accurate future prediction, making them a natural foundation for enhancing VLA learning. Therefore, we propose GigaBrain-0.5M*, a VLA model trained via world model-based reinforcement learning. Built upon GigaBrain-0.5, which is pre-trained on over 10,000 hours of robotic manipulation data, whose intermediate version currently ranks first on the international RoboChallenge benchmark. GigaBrain-0.5M* further integrates world model-based reinforcement learning via RAMP (Reinforcement leArning via world Model-conditioned Policy) to enable robust cross-task adaptation. Empirical results demonstrate that RAMP achieves substantial performance gains over the RECAP baseline, yielding improvements of approximately 30\% on challenging tasks including Laundry Folding, Box Packing, and Espresso Preparation. Critically, GigaBrain-0.5M^* exhibits reliable long-horizon execution, consistently accomplishing complex manipulation tasks without failure as validated by real-world deployment videos on our https://gigabrain05m.github.io{project page}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12099</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 15:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Pensieve Paradigm: Stateful Language Models Mastering Their Own Context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12108</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12108.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoyuan Liu, Tian Liang, Dongyang Ma, Deyu Zhou, Haitao Mi, Pinjia He, Yan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In the world of Harry Potter, when Dumbledore's mind is overburdened, he extracts memories into a Pensieve to be revisited later. In the world of AI, while we possess the Pensieve-mature databases and retrieval systems, our models inexplicably lack the "wand" to operate it. They remain like a Dumbledore without agency, passively accepting a manually engineered context as their entire memory. This work finally places the wand in the model's hand. We introduce StateLM, a new class of foundation models endowed with an internal reasoning loop to manage their own state. We equip our model with a suite of memory tools, such as context pruning, document indexing, and note-taking, and train it to actively manage these tools. By learning to dynamically engineering its own context, our model breaks free from the architectural prison of a fixed window. Experiments across various model sizes demonstrate StateLM's effectiveness across diverse scenarios. On long-document QA tasks, StateLMs consistently outperform standard LLMs across all model scales; on the chat memory task, they achieve absolute accuracy improvements of 10% to 20% over standard LLMs. On the deep research task BrowseComp-Plus, the performance gap becomes even more pronounced: StateLM achieves up to 52% accuracy, whereas standard LLM counterparts struggle around 5%. Ultimately, our approach shifts LLMs from passive predictors to state-aware agents where reasoning becomes a stateful and manageable process.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12108</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 16:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning beyond Teacher: Generalized On-Policy Distillation with Reward Extrapolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12125</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12125.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenkai Yang, Weijie Liu, Ruobing Xie, Kai Yang, Saiyong Yang, Yankai Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; On-policy distillation (OPD), which aligns the student with the teacher's logit distribution on student-generated trajectories, has demonstrated strong empirical gains in improving student performance and often outperforms off-policy distillation and reinforcement learning (RL) paradigms. In this work, we first theoretically show that OPD is a special case of dense KL-constrained RL where the reward function and the KL regularization are always weighted equally and the reference model can by any model. Then, we propose the Generalized On-Policy Distillation (G-OPD) framework, which extends the standard OPD objective by introducing a flexible reference model and a reward scaling factor that controls the relative weight of the reward term against the KL regularization. Through comprehensive experiments on math reasoning and code generation tasks, we derive two novel insights: (1) Setting the reward scaling factor to be greater than 1 (i.e., reward extrapolation), which we term ExOPD, consistently improves over standard OPD across a range of teacher-student size pairings. In particular, in the setting where we merge the knowledge from different domain experts, obtained by applying domain-specific RL to the same student model, back into the original student, ExOPD enables the student to even surpass the teacher's performance boundary and outperform the domain teachers. (2) Building on ExOPD, we further find that in the strong-to-weak distillation setting (i.e., distilling a smaller student from a larger teacher), performing reward correction by choosing the reference model as the teacher's base model before RL yields a more accurate reward signal and further improves distillation performance. However, this choice assumes access to the teacher's pre-RL variant and incurs more computational overhead. We hope our work offers new insights for future research on OPD.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12125</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 16:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>dVoting: Fast Voting for dLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12153</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12153.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sicheng Feng, Zigeng Chen, Xinyin Ma, Gongfan Fang, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Large Language Models (dLLMs) represent a new paradigm beyond autoregressive modeling, offering competitive performance while naturally enabling a flexible decoding process. Specifically, dLLMs can generate tokens at arbitrary positions in parallel, endowing them with significant potential for parallel test-time scaling, which was previously constrained by severe inefficiency in autoregressive modeling. In this work, we introduce dVoting, a fast voting technique that boosts reasoning capability without training, with only an acceptable extra computational overhead. dVoting is motivated by the observation that, across multiple samples for the same prompt, token predictions remain largely consistent, whereas performance is determined by a small subset of tokens exhibiting cross-sample variability. Leveraging the arbitrary-position generation capability of dLLMs, dVoting performs iterative refinement by sampling, identifying uncertain tokens via consistency analysis, regenerating them through voting, and repeating this process until convergence. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that dVoting consistently improves performance across various benchmarks. It achieves gains of 6.22%-7.66% on GSM8K, 4.40%-7.20% on MATH500, 3.16%-14.84% on ARC-C, and 4.83%-5.74% on MMLU. Our code is available at https://github.com/fscdc/dVoting&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12153</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 16:35:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepGen 1.0: A Lightweight Unified Multimodal Model for Advancing Image Generation and Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12205</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12205.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dianyi Wang, Ruihang Li, Feng Han, Chaofan Ma, Wei Song, Siyuan Wang, Yibin Wang, Yi Xin, Hongjian Liu, Zhixiong Zhang, Shengyuan Ding, Tianhang Wang, Zhenglin Cheng, Tao Lin, Cheng Jin, Kaicheng Yu, Jingjing Chen, Wenjie Wang, Zhongyu Wei, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current unified multimodal models for image generation and editing typically rely on massive parameter scales (e.g., &gt;10B), entailing prohibitive training costs and deployment footprints. In this work, we present DeepGen 1.0, a lightweight 5B unified model that achieves comprehensive capabilities competitive with or surpassing much larger counterparts. To overcome the limitations of compact models in semantic understanding and fine-grained control, we introduce Stacked Channel Bridging (SCB), a deep alignment framework that extracts hierarchical features from multiple VLM layers and fuses them with learnable 'think tokens' to provide the generative backbone with structured, reasoning-rich guidance. We further design a data-centric training strategy spanning three progressive stages: (1) Alignment Pre-training on large-scale image-text pairs and editing triplets to synchronize VLM and DiT representations, (2) Joint Supervised Fine-tuning on a high-quality mixture of generation, editing, and reasoning tasks to foster omni-capabilities, and (3) Reinforcement Learning with MR-GRPO, which leverages a mixture of reward functions and supervision signals, resulting in substantial gains in generation quality and alignment with human preferences, while maintaining stable training progress and avoiding visual artifacts. Despite being trained on only ~50M samples, DeepGen 1.0 achieves leading performance across diverse benchmarks, surpassing the 80B HunyuanImage by 28% on WISE and the 27B Qwen-Image-Edit by 37% on UniREditBench. By open-sourcing our training code, weights, and datasets, we provide an efficient, high-performance alternative to democratize unified multimodal research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12205</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 17:44:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stroke of Surprise: Progressive Semantic Illusions in Vector Sketching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12280</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2602.12280.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huai-Hsun Cheng, Siang-Ling Zhang, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual illusions traditionally rely on spatial manipulations such as multi-view consistency. In this work, we introduce Progressive Semantic Illusions, a novel vector sketching task where a single sketch undergoes a dramatic semantic transformation through the sequential addition of strokes. We present Stroke of Surprise, a generative framework that optimizes vector strokes to satisfy distinct semantic interpretations at different drawing stages. The core challenge lies in the "dual-constraint": initial prefix strokes must form a coherent object (e.g., a duck) while simultaneously serving as the structural foundation for a second concept (e.g., a sheep) upon adding delta strokes. To address this, we propose a sequence-aware joint optimization framework driven by a dual-branch Score Distillation Sampling (SDS) mechanism. Unlike sequential approaches that freeze the initial state, our method dynamically adjusts prefix strokes to discover a "common structural subspace" valid for both targets. Furthermore, we introduce a novel Overlay Loss that enforces spatial complementarity, ensuring structural integration rather than occlusion. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our method significantly outperforms state-of-the-art baselines in recognizability and illusion strength, successfully expanding visual anagrams from the spatial to the temporal dimension. Project page: https://stroke-of-surprise.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12280</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 18:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
