<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:14:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Agents: Building Effective Agents While Reducing Cost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02694</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02694.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ningning Wang, Xavier Hu, Pai Liu, He Zhu, Yue Hou, Heyuan Huang, Shengyu Zhang, Jian Yang, Jiaheng Liu, Ge Zhang, Changwang Zhang, Jun Wang, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 84&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The remarkable capabilities of Large Language Model (LLM)-driven agents have enabled sophisticated systems to tackle complex, multi-step tasks, but their escalating costs threaten scalability and accessibility. This work presents the first systematic study of the efficiency-effectiveness trade-off in modern agent systems, addressing the critical need for cost-effective designs without sacrificing performance. We investigate three key questions: (1) How much complexity do agentic tasks inherently require? (2) When do additional modules yield diminishing returns? (3) How much efficiency can be gained through the design of efficient agent frameworks? Through an empirical analysis on the GAIA benchmark, we evaluate the impact of LLM backbone selection, agent framework designs, and test-time scaling strategies. Using the cost-of-pass metric, we quantify the efficiency-performance trade-off across these dimensions. Our findings inform the development of Efficient Agents , a novel agent framework that has an optimal complexity to task requirements. Efficient Agents retains 96.7% of the performance of OWL, one leading open-source agent framework, while reducing operational costs from 0.398 to 0.228, resulting in a 28.4% improvement in cost-of-pass. Our work provides actionable insights for designing efficient, high-performing agent systems, advancing the accessibility and sustainability of AI-driven solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02694</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 17:56:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RecGPT Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22879</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.22879.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chao Yi, Dian Chen, Gaoyang Guo, Jiakai Tang, Jian Wu, Jing Yu, Sunhao Dai, Wen Chen, Wenjun Yang, Yuning Jiang, Zhujin Gao, Bo Zheng, Chi Li, Dimin Wang, Dixuan Wang, Fan Li, Fan Zhang, Haibin Chen, Haozhuang Liu, Jialin Zhu, Jiamang Wang, Jiawei Wu, Jin Cui, Ju Huang, Kai Zhang, Kan Liu, Lang Tian, Liang Rao, Longbin Li, Lulu Zhao, Mao Zhang, Na He, Peiyang Wang, Qiqi Huang, Tao Luo, Wenbo Su, Xiaoxiao He, Xin Tong, Xu Chen, Xunke Xi, Yang Li, Yaxuan Wu, Yeqiu Yang, Yi Hu, Yinnan Song, Yuchen Li, Yujie Luo, Yujin Yuan, Yuliang Yan, Zhengyang Wang, Zhibo Xiao, Zhixin Ma, Zile Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recommender systems are among the most impactful applications of artificial intelligence, serving as critical infrastructure connecting users, merchants, and platforms. However, most current industrial systems remain heavily reliant on historical co-occurrence patterns and log-fitting objectives, i.e., optimizing for past user interactions without explicitly modeling user intent. This log-fitting approach often leads to overfitting to narrow historical preferences, failing to capture users' evolving and latent interests. As a result, it reinforces filter bubbles and long-tail phenomena, ultimately harming user experience and threatening the sustainability of the whole recommendation ecosystem.   To address these challenges, we rethink the overall design paradigm of recommender systems and propose RecGPT, a next-generation framework that places user intent at the center of the recommendation pipeline. By integrating large language models (LLMs) into key stages of user interest mining, item retrieval, and explanation generation, RecGPT transforms log-fitting recommendation into an intent-centric process. To effectively align general-purpose LLMs to the above domain-specific recommendation tasks at scale, RecGPT incorporates a multi-stage training paradigm, which integrates reasoning-enhanced pre-alignment and self-training evolution, guided by a Human-LLM cooperative judge system. Currently, RecGPT has been fully deployed on the Taobao App. Online experiments demonstrate that RecGPT achieves consistent performance gains across stakeholders: users benefit from increased content diversity and satisfaction, merchants and the platform gain greater exposure and conversions. These comprehensive improvement results across all stakeholders validates that LLM-driven, intent-centric design can foster a more sustainable and mutually beneficial recommendation ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22879</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 17:55:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PixNerd: Pixel Neural Field Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23268</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23268.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuai Wang, Ziteng Gao, Chenhui Zhu, Weilin Huang, Limin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The current success of diffusion transformers heavily depends on the compressed latent space shaped by the pre-trained variational autoencoder(VAE). However, this two-stage training paradigm inevitably introduces accumulated errors and decoding artifacts. To address the aforementioned problems, researchers return to pixel space at the cost of complicated cascade pipelines and increased token complexity. In contrast to their efforts, we propose to model the patch-wise decoding with neural field and present a single-scale, single-stage, efficient, end-to-end solution, coined as pixel neural field diffusion~(PixelNerd). Thanks to the efficient neural field representation in PixNerd, we directly achieved 2.15 FID on ImageNet 256times256 and 2.84 FID on ImageNet 512times512 without any complex cascade pipeline or VAE. We also extend our PixNerd framework to text-to-image applications. Our PixNerd-XXL/16 achieved a competitive 0.73 overall score on the GenEval benchmark and 80.9 overall score on the DPG benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23268</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 06:07:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>iLRM: An Iterative Large 3D Reconstruction Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23277</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23277.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gyeongjin Kang, Seungtae Nam, Xiangyu Sun, Sameh Khamis, Abdelrahman Mohamed, Eunbyung Park&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Feed-forward 3D modeling has emerged as a promising approach for rapid and high-quality 3D reconstruction. In particular, directly generating explicit 3D representations, such as 3D Gaussian splatting, has attracted significant attention due to its fast and high-quality rendering, as well as numerous applications. However, many state-of-the-art methods, primarily based on transformer architectures, suffer from severe scalability issues because they rely on full attention across image tokens from multiple input views, resulting in prohibitive computational costs as the number of views or image resolution increases. Toward a scalable and efficient feed-forward 3D reconstruction, we introduce an iterative Large 3D Reconstruction Model (iLRM) that generates 3D Gaussian representations through an iterative refinement mechanism, guided by three core principles: (1) decoupling the scene representation from input-view images to enable compact 3D representations; (2) decomposing fully-attentional multi-view interactions into a two-stage attention scheme to reduce computational costs; and (3) injecting high-resolution information at every layer to achieve high-fidelity reconstruction. Experimental results on widely used datasets, such as RE10K and DL3DV, demonstrate that iLRM outperforms existing methods in both reconstruction quality and speed. Notably, iLRM exhibits superior scalability, delivering significantly higher reconstruction quality under comparable computational cost by efficiently leveraging a larger number of input views.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23277</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 06:33:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seed-Prover: Deep and Broad Reasoning for Automated Theorem Proving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23726</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23726.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Luoxin Chen, Jinming Gu, Liankai Huang, Wenhao Huang, Zhicheng Jiang, Allan Jie, Xiaoran Jin, Xing Jin, Chenggang Li, Kaijing Ma, Cheng Ren, Jiawei Shen, Wenlei Shi, Tong Sun, He Sun, Jiahui Wang, Siran Wang, Zhihong Wang, Chenrui Wei, Shufa Wei, Yonghui Wu, Yuchen Wu, Yihang Xia, Huajian Xin, Fan Yang, Huaiyuan Ying, Hongyi Yuan, Zheng Yuan, Tianyang Zhan, Chi Zhang, Yue Zhang, Ge Zhang, Tianyun Zhao, Jianqiu Zhao, Yichi Zhou, Thomas Hanwen Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 112&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLMs have demonstrated strong mathematical reasoning abilities by leveraging reinforcement learning with long chain-of-thought, yet they continue to struggle with theorem proving due to the lack of clear supervision signals when solely using natural language. Dedicated domain-specific languages like Lean provide clear supervision via formal verification of proofs, enabling effective training through reinforcement learning. In this work, we propose Seed-Prover, a lemma-style whole-proof reasoning model. Seed-Prover can iteratively refine its proof based on Lean feedback, proved lemmas, and self-summarization. To solve IMO-level contest problems, we design three test-time inference strategies that enable both deep and broad reasoning. Seed-Prover proves 78.1% of formalized past IMO problems, saturates MiniF2F, and achieves over 50\% on PutnamBench, outperforming the previous state-of-the-art by a large margin. To address the lack of geometry support in Lean, we introduce a geometry reasoning engine Seed-Geometry, which outperforms previous formal geometry engines. We use these two systems to participate in IMO 2025 and fully prove 5 out of 6 problems. This work represents a significant advancement in automated mathematical reasoning, demonstrating the effectiveness of formal verification with long chain-of-thought reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23726</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 17:00:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phi-Ground Tech Report: Advancing Perception in GUI Grounding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23779</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.23779.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Miaosen Zhang, Ziqiang Xu, Jialiang Zhu, Qi Dai, Kai Qiu, Yifan Yang, Chong Luo, Tianyi Chen, Justin Wagle, Tim Franklin, Baining Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the development of multimodal reasoning models, Computer Use Agents (CUAs), akin to Jarvis from "Iron Man", are becoming a reality. GUI grounding is a core component for CUAs to execute actual actions, similar to mechanical control in robotics, and it directly leads to the success or failure of the system. It determines actions such as clicking and typing, as well as related parameters like the coordinates for clicks. Current end-to-end grounding models still achieve less than 65\% accuracy on challenging benchmarks like ScreenSpot-pro and UI-Vision, indicating they are far from being ready for deployment. % , as a single misclick can result in unacceptable consequences. In this work, we conduct an empirical study on the training of grounding models, examining details from data collection to model training. Ultimately, we developed the Phi-Ground model family, which achieves state-of-the-art performance across all five grounding benchmarks for models under 10B parameters in agent settings. In the end-to-end model setting, our model still achieves SOTA results with scores of \textbf{43.2} on ScreenSpot-pro and \textbf{27.2} on UI-Vision. We believe that the various details discussed in this paper, along with our successes and failures, not only clarify the construction of grounding models but also benefit other perception tasks. Project homepage: https://zhangmiaosen2000.github.io/Phi-Ground/{https://zhangmiaosen2000.github.io/Phi-Ground/}&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23779</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 17:59:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive Kernel-Pro: A Framework for Deep Research Agents and Agent   Foundation Models Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00414</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00414.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianqing Fang, Zhisong Zhang, Xiaoyang Wang, Rui Wang, Can Qin, Yuxuan Wan, Jun-Yu Ma, Ce Zhang, Jiaqi Chen, Xiyun Li, Hongming Zhang, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 89&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; General AI Agents are increasingly recognized as foundational frameworks for the next generation of artificial intelligence, enabling complex reasoning, web interaction, coding, and autonomous research capabilities. However, current agent systems are either closed-source or heavily reliant on a variety of paid APIs and proprietary tools, limiting accessibility and reproducibility for the research community. In this work, we present Cognitive Kernel-Pro, a fully open-source and (to the maximum extent) free multi-module agent framework designed to democratize the development and evaluation of advanced AI agents. Within Cognitive Kernel-Pro, we systematically investigate the curation of high-quality training data for Agent Foundation Models, focusing on the construction of queries, trajectories, and verifiable answers across four key domains: web, file, code, and general reasoning. Furthermore, we explore novel strategies for agent test-time reflection and voting to enhance agent robustness and performance. We evaluate Cognitive Kernel-Pro on GAIA, achieving state-of-the-art results among open-source and free agents. Notably, our 8B-parameter open-source model surpasses previous leading systems such as WebDancer and WebSailor, establishing a new performance standard for accessible, high-capability AI agents. Code is available at https://github.com/Tencent/CognitiveKernel-Pro&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00414</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 08:11:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Fixed: Variable-Length Denoising for Diffusion Large Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00819</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.00819.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinsong Li, Xiaoyi Dong, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Jiaqi Wang, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Large Language Models (DLLMs) are emerging as a powerful alternative to the dominant Autoregressive Large Language Models, offering efficient parallel generation and capable global context modeling. However, the practical application of DLLMs is hindered by a critical architectural constraint: the need for a statically predefined generation length. This static length allocation leads to a problematic trade-off: insufficient lengths cripple performance on complex tasks, while excessive lengths incur significant computational overhead and sometimes result in performance degradation. While the inference framework is rigid, we observe that the model itself possesses internal signals that correlate with the optimal response length for a given task. To bridge this gap, we leverage these latent signals and introduce DAEDAL, a novel training-free denoising strategy that enables Dynamic Adaptive Length Expansion for Diffusion Large Language Models. DAEDAL operates in two phases: 1) Before the denoising process, DAEDAL starts from a short initial length and iteratively expands it to a coarse task-appropriate length, guided by a sequence completion metric. 2) During the denoising process, DAEDAL dynamically intervenes by pinpointing and expanding insufficient generation regions through mask token insertion, ensuring the final output is fully developed. Extensive experiments on DLLMs demonstrate that DAEDAL achieves performance comparable, and in some cases superior, to meticulously tuned fixed-length baselines, while simultaneously enhancing computational efficiency by achieving a higher effective token ratio. By resolving the static length constraint, DAEDAL unlocks new potential for DLLMs, bridging a critical gap with their Autoregressive counterparts and paving the way for more efficient and capable generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00819</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 17:56:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Llama-3.1-FoundationAI-SecurityLLM-8B-Instruct Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01059</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01059.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sajana Weerawardhena, Paul Kassianik, Blaine Nelson, Baturay Saglam, Anu Vellore, Aman Priyanshu, Supriti Vijay, Massimo Aufiero, Arthur Goldblatt, Fraser Burch, Ed Li, Jianliang He, Dhruv Kedia, Kojin Oshiba, Zhouran Yang, Yaron Singer, Amin Karbasi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable success across many domains, yet their integration into cybersecurity applications remains limited due to a lack of general-purpose cybersecurity data, representational complexity, and safety and regulatory concerns. To address this gap, we previously introduced Foundation-Sec-8B, a cybersecurity-focused LLM suitable for fine-tuning on downstream tasks. That model, however, was not designed for chat-style interactions or instruction-following. In this report, we release Foundation-Sec-8B-Instruct: a model specifically trained for general-purpose cybersecurity dialogue. Built on Foundation-Sec-8B, it combines domain-specific knowledge with instruction-following, conversational capabilities, and alignment with human preferences to produce high-quality, relevant responses. Comprehensive evaluations show that Foundation-Sec-8B-Instruct outperforms Llama 3.1-8B-Instruct on a range of cybersecurity tasks while matching its instruction-following performance. It is also competitive with GPT-4o-mini on cyber threat intelligence and instruction-following tasks. We envision Foundation-Sec-8B-Instruct becoming an indispensable assistant in the daily workflows of cybersecurity professionals. We release the model publicly at https://huggingface.co/fdtn-ai/Foundation-Sec-8B-Instruct.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01059</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 20:25:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Chain-of-Thought Reasoning of LLMs a Mirage? A Data Distribution Lens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01191</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01191.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chengshuai Zhao, Zhen Tan, Pingchuan Ma, Dawei Li, Bohan Jiang, Yancheng Wang, Yingzhen Yang, Huan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 228&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-Thought (CoT) prompting has been shown to improve Large Language Model (LLM) performance on various tasks. With this approach, LLMs appear to produce human-like reasoning steps before providing answers (a.k.a., CoT reasoning), which often leads to the perception that they engage in deliberate inferential processes. However, some initial findings suggest that CoT reasoning may be more superficial than it appears, motivating us to explore further. In this paper, we study CoT reasoning via a data distribution lens and investigate if CoT reasoning reflects a structured inductive bias learned from in-distribution data, allowing the model to conditionally generate reasoning paths that approximate those seen during training. Thus, its effectiveness is fundamentally bounded by the degree of distribution discrepancy between the training data and the test queries. With this lens, we dissect CoT reasoning via three dimensions: task, length, and format. To investigate each dimension, we design DataAlchemy, an isolated and controlled environment to train LLMs from scratch and systematically probe them under various distribution conditions. Our results reveal that CoT reasoning is a brittle mirage that vanishes when it is pushed beyond training distributions. This work offers a deeper understanding of why and when CoT reasoning fails, emphasizing the ongoing challenge of achieving genuine and generalizable reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01191</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 04:37:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SitEmb-v1.5: Improved Context-Aware Dense Retrieval for Semantic   Association and Long Story Comprehension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01959</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.01959.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junjie Wu, Jiangnan Li, Yuqing Li, Lemao Liu, Liyan Xu, Jiwei Li, Dit-Yan Yeung, Jie Zhou, Mo Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) over long documents typically involves splitting the text into smaller chunks, which serve as the basic units for retrieval. However, due to dependencies across the original document, contextual information is often essential for accurately interpreting each chunk. To address this, prior work has explored encoding longer context windows to produce embeddings for longer chunks. Despite these efforts, gains in retrieval and downstream tasks remain limited. This is because (1) longer chunks strain the capacity of embedding models due to the increased amount of information they must encode, and (2) many real-world applications still require returning localized evidence due to constraints on model or human bandwidth.   We propose an alternative approach to this challenge by representing short chunks in a way that is conditioned on a broader context window to enhance retrieval performance -- i.e., situating a chunk's meaning within its context. We further show that existing embedding models are not well-equipped to encode such situated context effectively, and thus introduce a new training paradigm and develop the situated embedding models (SitEmb). To evaluate our method, we curate a book-plot retrieval dataset specifically designed to assess situated retrieval capabilities. On this benchmark, our SitEmb-v1 model based on BGE-M3 substantially outperforms state-of-the-art embedding models, including several with up to 7-8B parameters, with only 1B parameters. Our 8B SitEmb-v1.5 model further improves performance by over 10% and shows strong results across different languages and several downstream applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01959</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 23:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Trade-off: Self-Supervised Reinforcement Learning for   Reasoning Models' Instruction Following</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02150</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02150.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qingyu Ren, Qianyu He, Bowei Zhang, Jie Zeng, Jiaqing Liang, Yanghua Xiao, Weikang Zhou, Zeye Sun, Fei Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning models excel in complex problem solving but exhibit a concerning trade off between reasoning capabilities and instruction following abilities. Existing approaches for improving instruction following rely on stronger external models, creating methodological bottlenecks and practical limitations including increased costs and accessibility constraints. We propose a self-supervised RL framework that leverages reasoning models' own internal signals to improve instruction following capabilities without external supervision. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our framework significantly improves instruction following capabilities while maintaining reasoning performance, offering a scalable and cost-effective approach to enhance instruction following in reasoning models. The data and code are publicly available at https://github.com/Rainier-rq/verl-if.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02150</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 07:48:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seed Diffusion: A Large-Scale Diffusion Language Model with High-Speed   Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02193</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02193.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxuan Song, Zheng Zhang, Cheng Luo, Pengyang Gao, Fan Xia, Hao Luo, Zheng Li, Yuehang Yang, Hongli Yu, Xingwei Qu, Yuwei Fu, Jing Su, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Mingxuan Wang, Lin Yan, Xiaoying Jia, Jingjing Liu, Wei-Ying Ma, Ya-Qin Zhang, Yonghui Wu, Hao Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 128&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Seed Diffusion Preview, a large-scale language model based on discrete-state diffusion, offering remarkably fast inference speed. Thanks to non-sequential, parallel generation, discrete diffusion models provide a notable speedup to mitigate the inherent latency of token-by-token decoding, as demonstrated recently (e.g., Mercury Coder, Gemini Diffusion). Seed Diffusion Preview achieves an inference speed of 2,146 token/s over H20 GPUs while maintaining competitive performance across a sweep of standard code evaluation benchmarks, significantly faster than contemporary Mercury and Gemini Diffusion, establishing new state of the art on the speed-quality Pareto frontier for code models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02193</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 08:43:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CellForge: Agentic Design of Virtual Cell Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02276</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02276.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangru Tang, Zhuoyun Yu, Jiapeng Chen, Yan Cui, Daniel Shao, Weixu Wang, Fang Wu, Yuchen Zhuang, Wenqi Shi, Zhi Huang, Arman Cohan, Xihong Lin, Fabian Theis, Smita Krishnaswamy, Mark Gerstein&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Virtual cell modeling represents an emerging frontier at the intersection of artificial intelligence and biology, aiming to predict quantities such as responses to diverse perturbations quantitatively. However, autonomously building computational models for virtual cells is challenging due to the complexity of biological systems, the heterogeneity of data modalities, and the need for domain-specific expertise across multiple disciplines. Here, we introduce CellForge, an agentic system that leverages a multi-agent framework that transforms presented biological datasets and research objectives directly into optimized computational models for virtual cells. More specifically, given only raw single-cell multi-omics data and task descriptions as input, CellForge outputs both an optimized model architecture and executable code for training virtual cell models and inference. The framework integrates three core modules: Task Analysis for presented dataset characterization and relevant literature retrieval, Method Design, where specialized agents collaboratively develop optimized modeling strategies, and Experiment Execution for automated generation of code. The agents in the Design module are separated into experts with differing perspectives and a central moderator, and have to collaboratively exchange solutions until they achieve a reasonable consensus. We demonstrate CellForge's capabilities in single-cell perturbation prediction, using six diverse datasets that encompass gene knockouts, drug treatments, and cytokine stimulations across multiple modalities. CellForge consistently outperforms task-specific state-of-the-art methods. Overall, CellForge demonstrates how iterative interaction between LLM agents with differing perspectives provides better solutions than directly addressing a modeling challenge. Our code is publicly available at https://github.com/gersteinlab/CellForge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02276</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:43:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qwen-Image Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02324</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.02324.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenfei Wu, Jiahao Li, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin, Kaiyuan Gao, Kun Yan, Sheng-ming Yin, Shuai Bai, Xiao Xu, Yilei Chen, Yuxiang Chen, Zecheng Tang, Zekai Zhang, Zhengyi Wang, An Yang, Bowen Yu, Chen Cheng, Dayiheng Liu, Deqing Li, Hang Zhang, Hao Meng, Hu Wei, Jingyuan Ni, Kai Chen, Kuan Cao, Liang Peng, Lin Qu, Minggang Wu, Peng Wang, Shuting Yu, Tingkun Wen, Wensen Feng, Xiaoxiao Xu, Yi Wang, Yichang Zhang, Yongqiang Zhu, Yujia Wu, Yuxuan Cai, Zenan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 239&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Qwen-Image, an image generation foundation model in the Qwen series that achieves significant advances in complex text rendering and precise image editing. To address the challenges of complex text rendering, we design a comprehensive data pipeline that includes large-scale data collection, filtering, annotation, synthesis, and balancing. Moreover, we adopt a progressive training strategy that starts with non-text-to-text rendering, evolves from simple to complex textual inputs, and gradually scales up to paragraph-level descriptions. This curriculum learning approach substantially enhances the model's native text rendering capabilities. As a result, Qwen-Image not only performs exceptionally well in alphabetic languages such as English, but also achieves remarkable progress on more challenging logographic languages like Chinese. To enhance image editing consistency, we introduce an improved multi-task training paradigm that incorporates not only traditional text-to-image (T2I) and text-image-to-image (TI2I) tasks but also image-to-image (I2I) reconstruction, effectively aligning the latent representations between Qwen2.5-VL and MMDiT. Furthermore, we separately feed the original image into Qwen2.5-VL and the VAE encoder to obtain semantic and reconstructive representations, respectively. This dual-encoding mechanism enables the editing module to strike a balance between preserving semantic consistency and maintaining visual fidelity. Qwen-Image achieves state-of-the-art performance, demonstrating its strong capabilities in both image generation and editing across multiple benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02324</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 11:49:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork UniPic: Unified Autoregressive Modeling for Visual Understanding   and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03320</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03320.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peiyu Wang, Yi Peng, Yimeng Gan, Liang Hu, Tianyidan Xie, Xiaokun Wang, Yichen Wei, Chuanxin Tang, Bo Zhu, Changshi Li, Hongyang Wei, Eric Li, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Skywork UniPic, a 1.5 billion-parameter autoregressive model that unifies image understanding, text-to-image generation, and image editing within a single architecture-eliminating the need for task-specific adapters or inter-module connectors-and demonstrate that compact multimodal systems can achieve state-of-the-art performance on commodity hardware. Skywork UniPic achieves a GenEval score of 0.86, surpassing most existing unified models; sets a new DPG-Bench complex-generation record of 85.5; attains 5.83 on GEditBench-EN and 3.49 on ImgEdit-Bench for image editing; and generates 1024 x 1024 images with under 15 GB of GPU memory (e.g., RTX 4090). (1) a decoupled encoding strategy that leverages a masked autoregressive encoder for synthesis and a SigLIP2 encoder for understanding, all feeding a shared autoregressive decoder; (2) a progressive, resolution-aware training schedule scaling from 256 x 256 to 1024 x 1024 while dynamically unfreezing parameters to balance capacity and stability; and (3) meticulously curated, 100 million-scale datasets augmented with task-specific reward models to refine generation and editing objectives. By demonstrating that high-fidelity multimodal integration need not incur prohibitive resource demands, Skywork UniPic establishes a practical paradigm for deployable, high-fidelity multimodal AI. Code and weights are publicly available at https://huggingface.co/Skywork/Skywork-UniPic-1.5B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03320</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 10:59:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training Long-Context, Multi-Turn Software Engineering Agents with   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03501</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03501.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Golubev, Maria Trofimova, Sergei Polezhaev, Ibragim Badertdinov, Maksim Nekrashevich, Anton Shevtsov, Simon Karasik, Sergey Abramov, Andrei Andriushchenko, Filipp Fisin, Sergei Skvortsov, Boris Yangel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Research on applications of Reinforcement Learning (RL) to Large Language Models (LLMs) has mostly been focused on single-turn problems, such as mathematical reasoning or single-shot code generation. While these problems can be viewed as token-level multi-turn MDPs, this view corresponds to a degenerate case of multi-turn interaction where the environment provides no feedback. This contrasts with many real-world domains, such as software engineering (SWE), which require rich multi-turn interactions with a stateful environment that responds to each action with a non-trivial observation.   To bridge this gap, we demonstrate the successful application of RL to this general regime. Using a modified Decoupled Advantage Policy Optimization (DAPO) algorithm, we train an agent based on Qwen2.5-72B-Instruct to solve real-world software engineering tasks. Our approach increases the agent's success rate on the SWE-bench Verified benchmark from a 20% rejection fine-tuned baseline to 39%, without relying on any teacher models. On SWE-rebench, our agent matches or outperforms leading open-weight models such as DeepSeek-V3-0324 and Qwen3-235B-A22B using an identical scaffolding, offering a viable path toward building more capable autonomous agents for complex real-world problems based on open models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03501</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 14:30:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent Lightning: Train ANY AI Agents with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03680</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03680.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xufang Luo, Yuge Zhang, Zhiyuan He, Zilong Wang, Siyun Zhao, Dongsheng Li, Luna K. Qiu, Yuqing Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 65&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Agent Lightning, a flexible and extensible framework that enables Reinforcement Learning (RL)-based training of Large Language Models (LLMs) for any AI agent. Unlike existing methods that tightly couple RL training with agent or rely on sequence concatenation with masking, Agent Lightning achieves complete decoupling between agent execution and training, allowing seamless integration with existing agents developed via diverse ways (e.g., using frameworks like LangChain, OpenAI Agents SDK, AutoGen, and building from scratch) with almost ZERO code modifications. By formulating agent execution as Markov decision process, we define an unified data interface and propose a hierarchical RL algorithm, LightningRL, which contains a credit assignment module, allowing us to decompose trajectories generated by ANY agents into training transition. This enables RL to handle complex interaction logic, such as multi-agent scenarios and dynamic workflows. For the system design, we introduce a Training-Agent Disaggregation architecture, and brings agent observability frameworks into agent runtime, providing a standardized agent finetuning interface. Experiments across text-to-SQL, retrieval-augmented generation, and math tool-use tasks demonstrate stable, continuous improvements, showcasing the framework's potential for real-world agent training and deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03680</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 17:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CompassVerifier: A Unified and Robust Verifier for LLMs Evaluation and   Outcome Reward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03686</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03686.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shudong Liu, Hongwei Liu, Junnan Liu, Linchen Xiao, Songyang Gao, Chengqi Lyu, Yuzhe Gu, Wenwei Zhang, Derek F. Wong, Songyang Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Answer verification is crucial not only for evaluating large language models (LLMs) by matching their unstructured outputs against standard answers, but also serves as the reward model to guide LLM optimization. Most evaluation frameworks rely on regularized matching or employ general LLMs for answer verification, which demands extensive, repetitive customization for regex rules or evaluation prompts. Two fundamental limitations persist in current methodologies: 1) the absence of comprehensive benchmarks that systematically evaluate verification capabilities across different LLMs; and 2) the nascent stage of verifier development, where existing approaches lack both the robustness to handle complex edge cases and the generalizability across different domains. In this work, we develop CompassVerifier, an accurate and robust lightweight verifier model for evaluation and outcome reward. It demonstrates multi-domain competency spanning math, knowledge, and diverse reasoning tasks, with the capability to process various answer types, including multi-subproblems, formulas, and sequence answers, while effectively identifying abnormal/invalid responses. We introduce VerifierBench benchmark comprising model outputs collected from multiple data sources, augmented through manual analysis of metaerror patterns to enhance CompassVerifier. We anticipate that CompassVerifier and VerifierBench will facilitate answer verification, evaluation protocols, and reinforcement learning research. Code and dataset are available at https://github.com/open-compass/CompassVerifier.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03686</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 17:55:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongVie: Multimodal-Guided Controllable Ultra-Long Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03694</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.03694.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianxiong Gao, Zhaoxi Chen, Xian Liu, Jianfeng Feng, Chenyang Si, Yanwei Fu, Yu Qiao, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Controllable ultra-long video generation is a fundamental yet challenging task. Although existing methods are effective for short clips, they struggle to scale due to issues such as temporal inconsistency and visual degradation. In this paper, we initially investigate and identify three key factors: separate noise initialization, independent control signal normalization, and the limitations of single-modality guidance. To address these issues, we propose LongVie, an end-to-end autoregressive framework for controllable long video generation. LongVie introduces two core designs to ensure temporal consistency: 1) a unified noise initialization strategy that maintains consistent generation across clips, and 2) global control signal normalization that enforces alignment in the control space throughout the entire video. To mitigate visual degradation, LongVie employs 3) a multi-modal control framework that integrates both dense (e.g., depth maps) and sparse (e.g., keypoints) control signals, complemented by 4) a degradation-aware training strategy that adaptively balances modality contributions over time to preserve visual quality. We also introduce LongVGenBench, a comprehensive benchmark consisting of 100 high-resolution videos spanning diverse real-world and synthetic environments, each lasting over one minute. Extensive experiments show that LongVie achieves state-of-the-art performance in long-range controllability, consistency, and quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03694</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VeriGUI: Verifiable Long-Chain GUI Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04026</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04026.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shunyu Liu, Minghao Liu, Huichi Zhou, Zhenyu Cui, Yang Zhou, Yuhao Zhou, Wendong Fan, Ge Zhang, Jiajun Shi, Weihao Xuan, Jiaxing Huang, Shuang Luo, Fang Wu, Heli Qi, Qingcheng Zeng, Ziqi Ren, Jialiang Gao, Jindi Lv, Junjie Wang, Aosong Feng, Heng Zhou, Wangchunshu Zhou, Zhenfei Yin, Wenlong Zhang, Guohao Li, Wenhao Yu, Irene Li, Lei Ma, Lei Bai, Qunshu Lin, Mingli Song, Dacheng Tao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 156&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies have delved into constructing autonomous agents capable of performing complex Graphical User Interface (GUI)-based computer tasks, with the potential to revolutionize human-computer interaction. Despite encouraging results, existing efforts mainly focus on short-term interactions and rely on outcome-only verification, thereby limiting their scalability in real-world GUI applications that demand long-horizon task decomposition and execution. In this work, we introduce VeriGUI, a novel verifiable long-chain GUI dataset designed to facilitate the development and evaluation of generalist GUI agents operating in realistic computer environments. Our dataset emphasizes two critical dimensions: (1) long-chain complexity, with tasks decomposed into a sequence of interdependent subtasks spanning hundreds of steps, explicitly designed to allow any subtask to serve as a valid starting point; and (2) subtask-level verifiability, which enables diverse exploration strategies within each subtask, while ensuring that each subtask-level goal remains verifiable and consistent. The dataset consists of GUI task trajectories across both desktop and web, annotated by human experts. Extensive experiments on VeriGUI using various agents with different foundation models reveal significant performance gaps in handling long-horizon tasks, highlighting the need for more robust planning and decision-making capabilities in GUI agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04026</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 02:38:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Vision-Language Model Training with Reinforcement Learning in   Synthetic Worlds for Real-World Success</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04280</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04280.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; George Bredis, Stanislav Dereka, Viacheslav Sinii, Ruslan Rakhimov, Daniil Gavrilov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Interactive multimodal agents must convert raw visual observations into coherent sequences of language-conditioned actions -- a capability that current vision-language models (VLMs) still lack. Earlier reinforcement-learning (RL) efforts could, in principle, endow VLMs with such skills, but they have seldom tested whether the learned behaviours generalize beyond their training simulators, and they depend either on brittle hyperparameter tuning or on dense-reward environments with low state variability. We introduce Vision-Language Decoupled Actor-Critic (VL-DAC), a lightweight, hyperparameter-free RL algorithm. VL-DAC applies PPO updates to action tokens while learning value only at the environment-step level: an arrangement, to our knowledge, not previously explored for large VLMs or LLMs. This simple decoupling removes unstable weighting terms and yields faster, more reliable convergence. Training a single VLM with VL-DAC in one inexpensive simulator at a time (MiniWorld, Gym-Cards, ALFWorld, or WebShop) already produces policies that generalize widely: +50\% relative on BALROG (game-centric agentic control), +5\% relative on the hardest part of VSI-Bench (spatial planning), and +2\% on VisualWebBench (web navigation), all without degrading general image understanding accuracy. These results provide the first evidence that a simple RL algorithm can train VLMs entirely in cheap synthetic worlds while delivering measurable gains on real-image agentic, spatial-reasoning, and web-navigation benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04280</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 10:08:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain-of-Agents: End-to-End Agent Foundation Models via Multi-Agent   Distillation and Agentic RL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13167</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13167.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weizhen Li, Jianbo Lin, Zhuosong Jiang, Jingyi Cao, Xinpeng Liu, Jiayu Zhang, Zhenqiang Huang, Qianben Chen, Weichen Sun, Qiexiang Wang, Hongxuan Lu, Tianrui Qin, Chenghao Zhu, Yi Yao, Shuying Fan, Xiaowan Li, Tiannan Wang, Pai Liu, King Zhu, He Zhu, Dingfeng Shi, Piaohong Wang, Yeyi Guan, Xiangru Tang, Minghao Liu, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Jian Yang, Jiaheng Liu, Ge Zhang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 119&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) and multi-agent systems have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in complex problem-solving tasks such as deep research, vibe coding, and mathematical reasoning. However, most existing multi-agent systems are built upon manual prompt/workflow engineering with sophisticated agent frameworks, making them computationally inefficient, less capable, and can not benefit from data-centric learning. In this work, we introduce Chain-of-Agents (CoA), a novel paradigm of LLM reasoning that enables native end-to-end complex problem-solving in the same way as a multi-agent system (i.e., multi-turn problem solving with multiple tools and multiple agents) within one model. In chain-of-agents problem-solving, the model dynamically activates different tool agents and role-playing agents to simulate multi-agent collaboration in an end-to-end fashion. To elicit end-to-end chain-of-agents problem-solving abilities in LLMs, we introduce a multi-agent distillation framework to distill state-of-the-art multi-agent systems into chain-of-agents trajectories for agentic supervised fine-tuning. We then use agentic reinforcement learning on verifiable agentic tasks to further improve the models' capabilities on chain-of-agents problem solving. We call the resulting models Agent Foundation Models (AFMs). Our empirical studies demonstrate that AFM establishes new state-of-the-art performance across diverse benchmarks in both web agent and code agent settings. We make the entire research, including the model weights, code for training and evaluation, and the training data, fully open-sourced, which offers a solid starting point for future research on agent models and agentic RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13167</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 17:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SEAgent: Self-Evolving Computer Use Agent with Autonomous Learning from   Experience</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04700</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04700.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeyi Sun, Ziyu Liu, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Xiaoyi Dong, Tong Wu, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Repurposing large vision-language models (LVLMs) as computer use agents (CUAs) has led to substantial breakthroughs, primarily driven by human-labeled data. However, these models often struggle with novel and specialized software, particularly in scenarios lacking human annotations. To address this challenge, we propose SEAgent, an agentic self-evolving framework enabling CUAs to autonomously evolve through interactions with unfamiliar software. Specifically, SEAgent empowers computer-use agents to autonomously master novel software environments via experiential learning, where agents explore new software, learn through iterative trial-and-error, and progressively tackle auto-generated tasks organized from simple to complex. To achieve this goal, we design a World State Model for step-wise trajectory assessment, along with a Curriculum Generator that generates increasingly diverse and challenging tasks. The agent's policy is updated through experiential learning, comprised of adversarial imitation of failure actions and Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) on successful ones. Furthermore, we introduce a specialist-to-generalist training strategy that integrates individual experiential insights from specialist agents, facilitating the development of a stronger generalist CUA capable of continuous autonomous evolution. This unified agent ultimately achieves performance surpassing ensembles of individual specialist agents on their specialized software. We validate the effectiveness of SEAgent across five novel software environments within OS-World. Our approach achieves a significant improvement of 23.2% in success rate, from 11.3% to 34.5%, over a competitive open-source CUA, i.e., UI-TARS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04700</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 17:58:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voost: A Unified and Scalable Diffusion Transformer for Bidirectional   Virtual Try-On and Try-Off</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04825</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04825.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seungyong Lee, Jeong-gi Kwak&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Virtual try-on aims to synthesize a realistic image of a person wearing a target garment, but accurately modeling garment-body correspondence remains a persistent challenge, especially under pose and appearance variation. In this paper, we propose Voost - a unified and scalable framework that jointly learns virtual try-on and try-off with a single diffusion transformer. By modeling both tasks jointly, Voost enables each garment-person pair to supervise both directions and supports flexible conditioning over generation direction and garment category, enhancing garment-body relational reasoning without task-specific networks, auxiliary losses, or additional labels. In addition, we introduce two inference-time techniques: attention temperature scaling for robustness to resolution or mask variation, and self-corrective sampling that leverages bidirectional consistency between tasks. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Voost achieves state-of-the-art results on both try-on and try-off benchmarks, consistently outperforming strong baselines in alignment accuracy, visual fidelity, and generalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04825</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 19:10:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R-Zero: Self-Evolving Reasoning LLM from Zero Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05004</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05004.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chengsong Huang, Wenhao Yu, Xiaoyang Wang, Hongming Zhang, Zongxia Li, Ruosen Li, Jiaxin Huang, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 123&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-evolving Large Language Models (LLMs) offer a scalable path toward super-intelligence by autonomously generating, refining, and learning from their own experiences. However, existing methods for training such models still rely heavily on vast human-curated tasks and labels, typically via fine-tuning or reinforcement learning, which poses a fundamental bottleneck to advancing AI systems toward capabilities beyond human intelligence. To overcome this limitation, we introduce R-Zero, a fully autonomous framework that generates its own training data from scratch. Starting from a single base LLM, R-Zero initializes two independent models with distinct roles, a Challenger and a Solver. These models are optimized separately and co-evolve through interaction: the Challenger is rewarded for proposing tasks near the edge of the Solver capability, and the Solver is rewarded for solving increasingly challenging tasks posed by the Challenger. This process yields a targeted, self-improving curriculum without any pre-existing tasks and labels. Empirically, R-Zero substantially improves reasoning capability across different backbone LLMs, e.g., boosting the Qwen3-4B-Base by +6.49 on math-reasoning benchmarks and +7.54 on general-domain reasoning benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05004</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 03:38:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SONAR-LLM: Autoregressive Transformer that Thinks in Sentence Embeddings   and Speaks in Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05305</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05305.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nikita Dragunov, Temurbek Rahmatullaev, Elizaveta Goncharova, Andrey Kuznetsov, Anton Razzhigaev&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The recently proposed Large Concept Model (LCM) generates text by predicting a sequence of sentence-level embeddings and training with either mean-squared error or diffusion objectives. We present SONAR-LLM, a decoder-only transformer that "thinks" in the same continuous SONAR embedding space, yet is supervised through token-level cross-entropy propagated via the frozen SONAR decoder. This hybrid objective retains the semantic abstraction of LCM while eliminating its diffusion sampler and restoring a likelihood-based training signal. Across model sizes from 39M to 1.3B parameters, SONAR-LLM attains competitive generation quality. We report scaling trends, ablations, benchmark results, and release the complete training code and all pretrained checkpoints to foster reproducibility and future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05305</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 12:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepPHY: Benchmarking Agentic VLMs on Physical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05405</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05405.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinrun Xu, Pi Bu, Ye Wang, Brje F. Karlsson, Ziming Wang, Tengtao Song, Qi Zhu, Jun Song, Zhiming Ding, Bo Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although Vision Language Models (VLMs) exhibit strong perceptual abilities and impressive visual reasoning, they struggle with attention to detail and precise action planning in complex, dynamic environments, leading to subpar performance. Real-world tasks typically require complex interactions, advanced spatial reasoning, long-term planning, and continuous strategy refinement, usually necessitating understanding the physics rules of the target scenario. However, evaluating these capabilities in real-world scenarios is often prohibitively expensive. To bridge this gap, we introduce DeepPHY, a novel benchmark framework designed to systematically evaluate VLMs' understanding and reasoning about fundamental physical principles through a series of challenging simulated environments. DeepPHY integrates multiple physical reasoning environments of varying difficulty levels and incorporates fine-grained evaluation metrics. Our evaluation finds that even state-of-the-art VLMs struggle to translate descriptive physical knowledge into precise, predictive control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05405</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 13:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Generalization of SFT: A Reinforcement Learning Perspective with   Reward Rectification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05629</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05629.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yongliang Wu, Yizhou Zhou, Zhou Ziheng, Yingzhe Peng, Xinyu Ye, Xinting Hu, Wenbo Zhu, Lu Qi, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Xu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 167&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present a simple yet theoretically motivated improvement to Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) for the Large Language Model (LLM), addressing its limited generalization compared to reinforcement learning (RL). Through mathematical analysis, we reveal that standard SFT gradients implicitly encode a problematic reward structure that may severely restrict the generalization capabilities of model. To rectify this, we propose Dynamic Fine-Tuning (DFT), stabilizing gradient updates for each token by dynamically rescaling the objective function with the probability of this token. Remarkably, this single-line code change significantly outperforms standard SFT across multiple challenging benchmarks and base models, demonstrating greatly improved generalization. Additionally, our approach shows competitive results in offline RL settings, offering an effective yet simpler alternative. This work bridges theoretical insight and practical solutions, substantially advancing SFT performance. The code will be available at https://github.com/yongliang-wu/DFT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05629</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 17:59:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genie Envisioner: A Unified World Foundation Platform for Robotic   Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05635</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05635.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yue Liao, Pengfei Zhou, Siyuan Huang, Donglin Yang, Shengcong Chen, Yuxin Jiang, Yue Hu, Jingbin Cai, Si Liu, Jianlan Luo, Liliang Chen, Shuicheng Yan, Maoqing Yao, Guanghui Ren&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Genie Envisioner (GE), a unified world foundation platform for robotic manipulation that integrates policy learning, evaluation, and simulation within a single video-generative framework. At its core, GE-Base is a large-scale, instruction-conditioned video diffusion model that captures the spatial, temporal, and semantic dynamics of real-world robotic interactions in a structured latent space. Built upon this foundation, GE-Act maps latent representations to executable action trajectories through a lightweight, flow-matching decoder, enabling precise and generalizable policy inference across diverse embodiments with minimal supervision. To support scalable evaluation and training, GE-Sim serves as an action-conditioned neural simulator, producing high-fidelity rollouts for closed-loop policy development. The platform is further equipped with EWMBench, a standardized benchmark suite measuring visual fidelity, physical consistency, and instruction-action alignment. Together, these components establish Genie Envisioner as a scalable and practical foundation for instruction-driven, general-purpose embodied intelligence. All code, models, and benchmarks will be released publicly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05635</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 17:59:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebWatcher: Breaking New Frontier of Vision-Language Deep Research Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05748</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.05748.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinyu Geng, Peng Xia, Zhen Zhang, Xinyu Wang, Qiuchen Wang, Ruixue Ding, Chenxi Wang, Jialong Wu, Yida Zhao, Kuan Li, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 121&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Web agents such as Deep Research have demonstrated superhuman cognitive abilities, capable of solving highly challenging information-seeking problems. However, most research remains primarily text-centric, overlooking visual information in the real world. This makes multimodal Deep Research highly challenging, as such agents require much stronger reasoning abilities in perception, logic, knowledge, and the use of more sophisticated tools compared to text-based agents. To address this limitation, we introduce WebWatcher, a multi-modal Agent for Deep Research equipped with enhanced visual-language reasoning capabilities. It leverages high-quality synthetic multimodal trajectories for efficient cold start training, utilizes various tools for deep reasoning, and further enhances generalization through reinforcement learning. To better evaluate the capabilities of multimodal agents, we propose BrowseComp-VL, a benchmark with BrowseComp-style that requires complex information retrieval involving both visual and textual information. Experimental results show that WebWatcher significantly outperforms proprietary baseline, RAG workflow and open-source agents in four challenging VQA benchmarks, which paves the way for solving complex multimodal information-seeking tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05748</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2025 18:03:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memp: Exploring Agent Procedural Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06433</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.06433.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runnan Fang, Yuan Liang, Xiaobin Wang, Jialong Wu, Shuofei Qiao, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) based agents excel at diverse tasks, yet they suffer from brittle procedural memory that is manually engineered or entangled in static parameters. In this work, we investigate strategies to endow agents with a learnable, updatable, and lifelong procedural memory. We propose Memp that distills past agent trajectories into both fine-grained, step-by-step instructions and higher-level, script-like abstractions, and explore the impact of different strategies for Build, Retrieval, and Update of procedural memory. Coupled with a dynamic regimen that continuously updates, corrects, and deprecates its contents, this repository evolves in lockstep with new experience. Empirical evaluation on TravelPlanner and ALFWorld shows that as the memory repository is refined, agents achieve steadily higher success rates and greater efficiency on analogous tasks. Moreover, procedural memory built from a stronger model retains its value: migrating the procedural memory to a weaker model yields substantial performance gains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06433</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 16:20:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GLM-4.5: Agentic, Reasoning, and Coding (ARC) Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06471</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.06471.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; GLM-4. 5 Team, Aohan Zeng, Xin Lv, Qinkai Zheng, Zhenyu Hou, Bin Chen, Chengxing Xie, Cunxiang Wang, Da Yin, Hao Zeng, Jiajie Zhang, Kedong Wang, Lucen Zhong, Mingdao Liu, Rui Lu, Shulin Cao, Xiaohan Zhang, Xuancheng Huang, Yao Wei, Yean Cheng, Yifan An, Yilin Niu, Yuanhao Wen, Yushi Bai, Zhengxiao Du, Zihan Wang, Zilin Zhu, Bohan Zhang, Bosi Wen, Bowen Wu, Bowen Xu, Can Huang, Casey Zhao, Changpeng Cai, Chao Yu, Chen Li, Chendi Ge, Chenghua Huang, Chenhui Zhang, Chenxi Xu, Chenzheng Zhu, Chuang Li, Congfeng Yin, Daoyan Lin, Dayong Yang, Dazhi Jiang, Ding Ai, Erle Zhu, Fei Wang, Gengzheng Pan, Guo Wang, Hailong Sun, Haitao Li, Haiyang Li, Haiyi Hu, Hanyu Zhang, Hao Peng, Hao Tai, Haoke Zhang, Haoran Wang, Haoyu Yang, He Liu, He Zhao, Hongwei Liu, Hongxi Yan, Huan Liu, Huilong Chen, Ji Li, Jiajing Zhao, Jiamin Ren, Jian Jiao, Jiani Zhao, Jianyang Yan, Jiaqi Wang, Jiayi Gui, Jiayue Zhao, Jie Liu, Jijie Li, Jing Li, Jing Lu, Jingsen Wang, Jingwei Yuan, Jingxuan Li, Jingzhao Du, Jinhua Du, Jinxin Liu, Junkai Zhi, Junli Gao, Ke Wang, Lekang Yang, Liang Xu, Lin Fan, Lindong Wu, Lintao Ding, Lu Wang, Man Zhang, Minghao Li, Minghuan Xu, Mingming Zhao, Mingshu Zhai, Pengfan Du, Qian Dong, Shangde Lei, Shangqing Tu, Shangtong Yang, Shaoyou Lu, Shijie Li, Shuang Li, Shuang-Li, Shuxun Yang, Sibo Yi, Tianshu Yu, Wei Tian, Weihan Wang, Wenbo Yu, Weng Lam Tam, Wenjie Liang, Wentao Liu, Xiao Wang, Xiaohan Jia, Xiaotao Gu, Xiaoying Ling, Xin Wang, Xing Fan, Xingru Pan, Xinyuan Zhang, Xinze Zhang, Xiuqing Fu, Xunkai Zhang, Yabo Xu, Yandong Wu, Yida Lu, Yidong Wang, Yilin Zhou, Yiming Pan, Ying Zhang, Yingli Wang, Yingru Li, Yinpei Su, Yipeng Geng, Yitong Zhu, Yongkun Yang, Yuhang Li, Yuhao Wu, Yujiang Li, Yunan Liu, Yunqing Wang, Yuntao Li, Yuxuan Zhang, Zezhen Liu, Zhen Yang, Zhengda Zhou, Zhongpei Qiao, Zhuoer Feng, Zhuorui Liu, Zichen Zhang, Zihan Wang, Zijun Yao, Zikang Wang, Ziqiang Liu, Ziwei Chai, Zixuan Li, Zuodong Zhao, Wenguang Chen, Jidong Zhai, Bin Xu, Minlie Huang, Hongning Wang, Juanzi Li, Yuxiao Dong, Jie Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 168&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present GLM-4.5, an open-source Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) large language model with 355B total parameters and 32B activated parameters, featuring a hybrid reasoning method that supports both thinking and direct response modes. Through multi-stage training on 23T tokens and comprehensive post-training with expert model iteration and reinforcement learning, GLM-4.5 achieves strong performance across agentic, reasoning, and coding (ARC) tasks, scoring 70.1% on TAU-Bench, 91.0% on AIME 24, and 64.2% on SWE-bench Verified. With much fewer parameters than several competitors, GLM-4.5 ranks 3rd overall among all evaluated models and 2nd on agentic benchmarks. We release both GLM-4.5 (355B parameters) and a compact version, GLM-4.5-Air (106B parameters), to advance research in reasoning and agentic AI systems. Code, models, and more information are available at https://github.com/zai-org/GLM-4.5.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06471</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 17:21:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BrowseComp-Plus: A More Fair and Transparent Evaluation Benchmark of   Deep-Research Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06600</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.06600.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zijian Chen, Xueguang Ma, Shengyao Zhuang, Ping Nie, Kai Zou, Andrew Liu, Joshua Green, Kshama Patel, Ruoxi Meng, Mingyi Su, Sahel Sharifymoghaddam, Yanxi Li, Haoran Hong, Xinyu Shi, Xuye Liu, Nandan Thakur, Crystina Zhang, Luyu Gao, Wenhu Chen, Jimmy Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep-Research agents, which integrate large language models (LLMs) with search tools, have shown success in improving the effectiveness of handling complex queries that require iterative search planning and reasoning over search results. Evaluations on current benchmarks like BrowseComp relies on black-box live web search APIs, have notable limitations in (1) fairness: dynamic and opaque web APIs hinder fair comparisons and reproducibility of deep research methods; (2) transparency: lack of control over the document corpus makes it difficult to isolate retriever contributions. In other words, the current evaluations may compare a complete deep research system at a given time, but they do not foster well-controlled experiments to provide insights into the capability of underlying deep research LLMs. To address these challenges, we introduce BrowseComp-Plus, a benchmark derived from BrowseComp, employing a fixed, carefully curated corpus. Each query in BrowseComp-Plus includes human-verified supporting documents and mined challenging negatives, enabling controlled experimentation. The benchmark is shown to be effective in distinguishing the performance of deep research systems. For instance, the open-source model Search-R1, when paired with the BM25 retriever, achieves 3.86% accuracy, whereas the GPT-5 achieves 55.9%. Integrating the GPT-5 with the Qwen3-Embedding-8B retriever further enhances its accuracy to 70.1% with fewer search calls. This benchmark allows comprehensive evaluation and disentangled analysis of deep research agents and retrieval methods, fostering insights into retrieval effectiveness, citation accuracy, and context engineering in Deep-Research system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06600</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 17:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReasonRank: Empowering Passage Ranking with Strong Reasoning Ability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07050</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07050.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenhan Liu, Xinyu Ma, Weiwei Sun, Yutao Zhu, Yuchen Li, Dawei Yin, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 114&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Model (LLM) based listwise ranking has shown superior performance in many passage ranking tasks. With the development of Large Reasoning Models, many studies have demonstrated that step-by-step reasoning during test-time helps improve listwise ranking performance. However, due to the scarcity of reasoning-intensive training data, existing rerankers perform poorly in many complex ranking scenarios and the ranking ability of reasoning-intensive rerankers remains largely underdeveloped. In this paper, we first propose an automated reasoning-intensive training data synthesis framework, which sources training queries and passages from diverse domains and applies DeepSeek-R1 to generate high-quality training labels. A self-consistency data filtering mechanism is designed to ensure the data quality. To empower the listwise reranker with strong reasoning ability, we further propose a two-stage post-training approach, which includes a cold-start supervised fine-tuning (SFT) stage for reasoning pattern learning and a reinforcement learning (RL) stage for further ranking ability enhancement. During the RL stage, based on the nature of listwise ranking, we design a multi-view ranking reward, which is more effective than a ranking metric-based reward. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our trained reasoning-intensive reranker ReasonRank outperforms existing baselines significantly and also achieves much lower latency than pointwise reranker Rank1. Through further experiments, our ReasonRank has achieved state-of-the-art (SOTA) performance 40.6 on the BRIGHT leaderboard\footnote{https://brightbenchmark.github.io/.} Our codes are available at https://github.com/8421BCD/ReasonRank.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07050</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 17:26:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Survey of Self-Evolving AI Agents: A New Paradigm   Bridging Foundation Models and Lifelong Agentic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07407</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07407.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinyuan Fang, Yanwen Peng, Xi Zhang, Yingxu Wang, Xinhao Yi, Guibin Zhang, Yi Xu, Bin Wu, Siwei Liu, Zihao Li, Zhaochun Ren, Nikos Aletras, Xi Wang, Han Zhou, Zaiqiao Meng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models have sparked growing interest in AI agents capable of solving complex, real-world tasks. However, most existing agent systems rely on manually crafted configurations that remain static after deployment, limiting their ability to adapt to dynamic and evolving environments. To this end, recent research has explored agent evolution techniques that aim to automatically enhance agent systems based on interaction data and environmental feedback. This emerging direction lays the foundation for self-evolving AI agents, which bridge the static capabilities of foundation models with the continuous adaptability required by lifelong agentic systems. In this survey, we provide a comprehensive review of existing techniques for self-evolving agentic systems. Specifically, we first introduce a unified conceptual framework that abstracts the feedback loop underlying the design of self-evolving agentic systems. The framework highlights four key components: System Inputs, Agent System, Environment, and Optimisers, serving as a foundation for understanding and comparing different strategies. Based on this framework, we systematically review a wide range of self-evolving techniques that target different components of the agent system. We also investigate domain-specific evolution strategies developed for specialised fields such as biomedicine, programming, and finance, where optimisation objectives are tightly coupled with domain constraints. In addition, we provide a dedicated discussion on the evaluation, safety, and ethical considerations for self-evolving agentic systems, which are critical to ensuring their effectiveness and reliability. This survey aims to provide researchers and practitioners with a systematic understanding of self-evolving AI agents, laying the foundation for the development of more adaptive, autonomous, and lifelong agentic systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07407</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 16:07:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CharacterShot: Controllable and Consistent 4D Character Animation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07409</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07409.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyao Gao, Jiaxing Li, Wenran Liu, Yanhong Zeng, Fei Shen, Kai Chen, Yanan Sun, Cairong Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we propose CharacterShot, a controllable and consistent 4D character animation framework that enables any individual designer to create dynamic 3D characters (i.e., 4D character animation) from a single reference character image and a 2D pose sequence. We begin by pretraining a powerful 2D character animation model based on a cutting-edge DiT-based image-to-video model, which allows for any 2D pose sequnce as controllable signal. We then lift the animation model from 2D to 3D through introducing dual-attention module together with camera prior to generate multi-view videos with spatial-temporal and spatial-view consistency. Finally, we employ a novel neighbor-constrained 4D gaussian splatting optimization on these multi-view videos, resulting in continuous and stable 4D character representations. Moreover, to improve character-centric performance, we construct a large-scale dataset Character4D, containing 13,115 unique characters with diverse appearances and motions, rendered from multiple viewpoints. Extensive experiments on our newly constructed benchmark, CharacterBench, demonstrate that our approach outperforms current state-of-the-art methods. Code, models, and datasets will be publicly available at https://github.com/Jeoyal/CharacterShot.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07409</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Aug 2025 16:15:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Klear-Reasoner: Advancing Reasoning Capability via Gradient-Preserving   Clipping Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07629</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07629.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenpeng Su, Leiyu Pan, Xue Bai, Dening Liu, Guanting Dong, Jiaming Huang, Wenping Hu, Guorui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Klear-Reasoner, a model with long reasoning capabilities that demonstrates careful deliberation during problem solving, achieving outstanding performance across multiple benchmarks. Although there are already many excellent works related to inference models in the current community, there are still many problems with reproducing high-performance inference models due to incomplete disclosure of training details. This report provides an in-depth analysis of the reasoning model, covering the entire post-training workflow from data preparation and long Chain-of-Thought supervised fine-tuning (long CoT SFT) to reinforcement learning (RL), along with detailed ablation studies for each experimental component. For SFT data, our experiments show that a small number of high-quality data sources are more effective than a large number of diverse data sources, and that difficult samples can achieve better results without accuracy filtering. In addition, we investigate two key issues with current clipping mechanisms in RL: Clipping suppresses critical exploration signals and ignores suboptimal trajectories. To address these challenges, we propose Gradient-Preserving clipping Policy Optimization (GPPO) that gently backpropagates gradients from clipped tokens. GPPO not only enhances the model's exploration capacity but also improves its efficiency in learning from negative samples. Klear-Reasoner exhibits exceptional reasoning abilities in mathematics and programming, scoring 90.5\% on AIME 2024, 83.2\% on AIME 2025, 66.0\% on LiveCodeBench V5 and 58.1\% on LiveCodeBench V6.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07629</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 05:17:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stand-In: A Lightweight and Plug-and-Play Identity Control for Video   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07901</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07901.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bowen Xue, Qixin Yan, Wenjing Wang, Hao Liu, Chen Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating high-fidelity human videos that match user-specified identities is important yet challenging in the field of generative AI. Existing methods often rely on an excessive number of training parameters and lack compatibility with other AIGC tools. In this paper, we propose Stand-In, a lightweight and plug-and-play framework for identity preservation in video generation. Specifically, we introduce a conditional image branch into the pre-trained video generation model. Identity control is achieved through restricted self-attentions with conditional position mapping, and can be learned quickly with only 2000 pairs. Despite incorporating and training just sim1\% additional parameters, our framework achieves excellent results in video quality and identity preservation, outperforming other full-parameter training methods. Moreover, our framework can be seamlessly integrated for other tasks, such as subject-driven video generation, pose-referenced video generation, stylization, and face swapping.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07901</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 12:17:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MolmoAct: Action Reasoning Models that can Reason in Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07917</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07917.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jason Lee, Jiafei Duan, Haoquan Fang, Yuquan Deng, Shuo Liu, Boyang Li, Bohan Fang, Jieyu Zhang, Yi Ru Wang, Sangho Lee, Winson Han, Wilbert Pumacay, Angelica Wu, Rose Hendrix, Karen Farley, Eli VanderBilt, Ali Farhadi, Dieter Fox, Ranjay Krishna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning is central to purposeful action, yet most robotic foundation models map perception and instructions directly to control, which limits adaptability, generalization, and semantic grounding. We introduce Action Reasoning Models (ARMs), a class of vision-language-action models that integrate perception, planning, and control through a structured three-stage pipeline. Our model, MolmoAct, encodes observations and instructions into depth-aware perception tokens, generates mid-level spatial plans as editable trajectory traces, and predicts precise low-level actions, enabling explainable and steerable behavior. MolmoAct-7B-D achieves strong performance across simulation and real-world settings: 70.5% zero-shot accuracy on SimplerEnv Visual Matching tasks, surpassing closed-source Pi-0 and GR00T N1; 86.6% average success on LIBERO, including an additional 6.3% gain over ThinkAct on long-horizon tasks; and in real-world fine-tuning, an additional 10% (single-arm) and an additional 22.7% (bimanual) task progression over Pi-0-FAST. It also outperforms baselines by an additional 23.3% on out-of-distribution generalization and achieves top human-preference scores for open-ended instruction following and trajectory steering. Furthermore, we release, for the first time, the MolmoAct Dataset -- a mid-training robot dataset comprising over 10,000 high quality robot trajectories across diverse scenarios and tasks. Training with this dataset yields an average 5.5% improvement in general performance over the base model. We release all model weights, training code, our collected dataset, and our action reasoning dataset, establishing MolmoAct as both a state-of-the-art robotics foundation model and an open blueprint for building ARMs that transform perception into purposeful action through structured reasoning. Blogpost: https://allenai.org/blog/molmoact&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07917</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 12:32:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Ten Turns: Unlocking Long-Horizon Agentic Search with Large-Scale   Asynchronous RL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07976</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07976.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaxuan Gao, Wei Fu, Minyang Xie, Shusheng Xu, Chuyi He, Zhiyu Mei, Banghua Zhu, Yi Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in LLM-based agents have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in handling complex, knowledge-intensive tasks by integrating external tools. Among diverse choices of tools, search tools play a pivotal role in accessing vast external knowledge. However, open-source agents still fall short of achieving expert-level Search Intelligence, the ability to resolve ambiguous queries, generate precise searches, analyze results, and conduct thorough exploration. Existing approaches fall short in scalability, efficiency, and data quality. For example, small turn limits in existing online RL methods, e.g. &lt;=10, restrict complex strategy learning. This paper introduces ASearcher, an open-source project for large-scale RL training of search agents. Our key contributions include: (1) Scalable fully asynchronous RL training that enables long-horizon search while maintaining high training efficiency. (2) A prompt-based LLM agent that autonomously synthesizes high-quality and challenging QAs, creating a large-scale QA dataset. Through RL training, our prompt-based QwQ-32B agent achieves substantial improvements, with 46.7% and 20.8% Avg@4 gains on xBench and GAIA, respectively. Notably, our agent exhibits extreme long-horizon search, with tool calls exceeding 40 turns and output tokens exceeding 150k during training time. With a simple agent design and no external LLMs, ASearcher-Web-QwQ achieves Avg@4 scores of 42.1 on xBench and 52.8 on GAIA, surpassing existing open-source 32B agents. We open-source our models, training data, and codes in https://github.com/inclusionAI/ASearcher.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07976</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:36:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Omni-Effects: Unified and Spatially-Controllable Visual Effects   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07981</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07981.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fangyuan Mao, Aiming Hao, Jintao Chen, Dongxia Liu, Xiaokun Feng, Jiashu Zhu, Meiqi Wu, Chubin Chen, Jiahong Wu, Xiangxiang Chu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual effects (VFX) are essential visual enhancements fundamental to modern cinematic production. Although video generation models offer cost-efficient solutions for VFX production, current methods are constrained by per-effect LoRA training, which limits generation to single effects. This fundamental limitation impedes applications that require spatially controllable composite effects, i.e., the concurrent generation of multiple effects at designated locations. However, integrating diverse effects into a unified framework faces major challenges: interference from effect variations and spatial uncontrollability during multi-VFX joint training. To tackle these challenges, we propose Omni-Effects, a first unified framework capable of generating prompt-guided effects and spatially controllable composite effects. The core of our framework comprises two key innovations: (1) LoRA-based Mixture of Experts (LoRA-MoE), which employs a group of expert LoRAs, integrating diverse effects within a unified model while effectively mitigating cross-task interference. (2) Spatial-Aware Prompt (SAP) incorporates spatial mask information into the text token, enabling precise spatial control. Furthermore, we introduce an Independent-Information Flow (IIF) module integrated within the SAP, isolating the control signals corresponding to individual effects to prevent any unwanted blending. To facilitate this research, we construct a comprehensive VFX dataset Omni-VFX via a novel data collection pipeline combining image editing and First-Last Frame-to-Video (FLF2V) synthesis, and introduce a dedicated VFX evaluation framework for validating model performance. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Omni-Effects achieves precise spatial control and diverse effect generation, enabling users to specify both the category and location of desired effects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07981</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 13:41:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WideSearch: Benchmarking Agentic Broad Info-Seeking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07999</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.07999.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ryan Wong, Jiawei Wang, Junjie Zhao, Li Chen, Yan Gao, Long Zhang, Xuan Zhou, Zuo Wang, Kai Xiang, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Yang Wang, Ke Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 105&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; From professional research to everyday planning, many tasks are bottlenecked by wide-scale information seeking, which is more repetitive than cognitively complex. With the rapid development of Large Language Models (LLMs), automated search agents powered by LLMs offer a promising solution to liberate humans from this tedious work. However, the capability of these agents to perform such "wide-context" collection reliably and completely remains largely unevaluated due to a lack of suitable benchmarks. To bridge this gap, we introduce WideSearch, a new benchmark engineered to evaluate agent reliability on these large-scale collection tasks. The benchmark features 200 manually curated questions (100 in English, 100 in Chinese) from over 15 diverse domains, grounded in real user queries. Each task requires agents to collect large-scale atomic information, which could be verified one by one objectively, and arrange it into a well-organized output. A rigorous five-stage quality control pipeline ensures the difficulty, completeness, and verifiability of the dataset. We benchmark over 10 state-of-the-art agentic search systems, including single-agent, multi-agent frameworks, and end-to-end commercial systems. Most systems achieve overall success rates near 0\%, with the best performer reaching just 5\%. However, given sufficient time, cross-validation by multiple human testers can achieve a near 100\% success rate. These results demonstrate that present search agents have critical deficiencies in large-scale information seeking, underscoring urgent areas for future research and development in agentic search. Our dataset, evaluation pipeline, and benchmark results have been publicly released at https://widesearch-seed.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07999</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 14:03:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix-3D: Omnidirectional Explorable 3D World Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08086</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.08086.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongqi Yang, Wenhang Ge, Yuqi Li, Jiaqi Chen, Haoyuan Li, Mengyin An, Fei Kang, Hua Xue, Baixin Xu, Yuyang Yin, Eric Li, Yang Liu, Yikai Wang, Hao-Xiang Guo, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Explorable 3D world generation from a single image or text prompt forms a cornerstone of spatial intelligence. Recent works utilize video model to achieve wide-scope and generalizable 3D world generation. However, existing approaches often suffer from a limited scope in the generated scenes. In this work, we propose Matrix-3D, a framework that utilize panoramic representation for wide-coverage omnidirectional explorable 3D world generation that combines conditional video generation and panoramic 3D reconstruction. We first train a trajectory-guided panoramic video diffusion model that employs scene mesh renders as condition, to enable high-quality and geometrically consistent scene video generation. To lift the panorama scene video to 3D world, we propose two separate methods: (1) a feed-forward large panorama reconstruction model for rapid 3D scene reconstruction and (2) an optimization-based pipeline for accurate and detailed 3D scene reconstruction. To facilitate effective training, we also introduce the Matrix-Pano dataset, the first large-scale synthetic collection comprising 116K high-quality static panoramic video sequences with depth and trajectory annotations. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our proposed framework achieves state-of-the-art performance in panoramic video generation and 3D world generation. See more in https://matrix-3d.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08086</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 15:29:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Part I: Tricks or Traps? A Deep Dive into RL for LLM Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08221</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.08221.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihe Liu, Jiashun Liu, Yancheng He, Weixun Wang, Jiaheng Liu, Ling Pan, Xinyu Hu, Shaopan Xiong, Ju Huang, Jian Hu, Shengyi Huang, Siran Yang, Jiamang Wang, Wenbo Su, Bo Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning for LLM reasoning has rapidly emerged as a prominent research area, marked by a significant surge in related studies on both algorithmic innovations and practical applications. Despite this progress, several critical challenges remain, including the absence of standardized guidelines for employing RL techniques and a fragmented understanding of their underlying mechanisms. Additionally, inconsistent experimental settings, variations in training data, and differences in model initialization have led to conflicting conclusions, obscuring the key characteristics of these techniques and creating confusion among practitioners when selecting appropriate techniques. This paper systematically reviews widely adopted RL techniques through rigorous reproductions and isolated evaluations within a unified open-source framework. We analyze the internal mechanisms, applicable scenarios, and core principles of each technique through fine-grained experiments, including datasets of varying difficulty, model sizes, and architectures. Based on these insights, we present clear guidelines for selecting RL techniques tailored to specific setups, and provide a reliable roadmap for practitioners navigating the RL for the LLM domain. Finally, we reveal that a minimalist combination of two techniques can unlock the learning capability of critic-free policies using vanilla PPO loss. The results demonstrate that our simple combination consistently improves performance, surpassing strategies like GRPO and DAPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08221</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 17:39:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ODYSSEY: Open-World Quadrupeds Exploration and Manipulation for   Long-Horizon Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08240</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.08240.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaijun Wang, Liqin Lu, Mingyu Liu, Jianuo Jiang, Zeju Li, Bolin Zhang, Wancai Zheng, Xinyi Yu, Hao Chen, Chunhua Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language-guided long-horizon mobile manipulation has long been a grand challenge in embodied semantic reasoning, generalizable manipulation, and adaptive locomotion. Three fundamental limitations hinder progress: First, although large language models have improved spatial reasoning and task planning through semantic priors, existing implementations remain confined to tabletop scenarios, failing to address the constrained perception and limited actuation ranges of mobile platforms. Second, current manipulation strategies exhibit insufficient generalization when confronted with the diverse object configurations encountered in open-world environments. Third, while crucial for practical deployment, the dual requirement of maintaining high platform maneuverability alongside precise end-effector control in unstructured settings remains understudied.   In this work, we present ODYSSEY, a unified mobile manipulation framework for agile quadruped robots equipped with manipulators, which seamlessly integrates high-level task planning with low-level whole-body control. To address the challenge of egocentric perception in language-conditioned tasks, we introduce a hierarchical planner powered by a vision-language model, enabling long-horizon instruction decomposition and precise action execution. At the control level, our novel whole-body policy achieves robust coordination across challenging terrains. We further present the first benchmark for long-horizon mobile manipulation, evaluating diverse indoor and outdoor scenarios. Through successful sim-to-real transfer, we demonstrate the system's generalization and robustness in real-world deployments, underscoring the practicality of legged manipulators in unstructured environments. Our work advances the feasibility of generalized robotic assistants capable of complex, dynamic tasks. Our project page: https://kaijwang.github.io/odyssey.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08240</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 17:54:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mol-R1: Towards Explicit Long-CoT Reasoning in Molecule Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08401</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.08401.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiatong Li, Weida Wang, Qinggang Zhang, Junxian Li, Di Zhang, Changmeng Zheng, Shufei Zhang, Xiaoyong Wei, Qing Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs), especially Explicit Long Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning models like DeepSeek-R1 and QWQ, have demonstrated powerful reasoning capabilities, achieving impressive performance in commonsense reasoning and mathematical inference. Despite their effectiveness, Long-CoT reasoning models are often criticized for their limited ability and low efficiency in knowledge-intensive domains such as molecule discovery. Success in this field requires a precise understanding of domain knowledge, including molecular structures and chemical principles, which is challenging due to the inherent complexity of molecular data and the scarcity of high-quality expert annotations. To bridge this gap, we introduce Mol-R1, a novel framework designed to improve explainability and reasoning performance of R1-like Explicit Long-CoT reasoning LLMs in text-based molecule generation. Our approach begins with a high-quality reasoning dataset curated through Prior Regulation via In-context Distillation (PRID), a dedicated distillation strategy to effectively generate paired reasoning traces guided by prior regulations. Building upon this, we introduce MoIA, Molecular Iterative Adaptation, a sophisticated training strategy that iteratively combines Supervised Fine-tuning (SFT) with Reinforced Policy Optimization (RPO), tailored to boost the reasoning performance of R1-like reasoning models for molecule discovery. Finally, we examine the performance of Mol-R1 in the text-based molecule reasoning generation task, showing superior performance against existing baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08401</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 18:50:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VertexRegen: Mesh Generation with Continuous Level of Detail</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09062</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09062.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiang Zhang, Yawar Siddiqui, Armen Avetisyan, Chris Xie, Jakob Engel, Henry Howard-Jenkins&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce VertexRegen, a novel mesh generation framework that enables generation at a continuous level of detail. Existing autoregressive methods generate meshes in a partial-to-complete manner and thus intermediate steps of generation represent incomplete structures. VertexRegen takes inspiration from progressive meshes and reformulates the process as the reversal of edge collapse, i.e. vertex split, learned through a generative model. Experimental results demonstrate that VertexRegen produces meshes of comparable quality to state-of-the-art methods while uniquely offering anytime generation with the flexibility to halt at any step to yield valid meshes with varying levels of detail.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09062</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 16:25:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex Logical Instruction Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09125</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09125.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mian Zhang, Shujian Liu, Sixun Dong, Ming Yin, Yebowen Hu, Xun Wang, Steven Ma, Song Wang, Sathish Reddy Indurthi, Haoyun Deng, Zhiyu Zoey Chen, Kaiqiang Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction following has catalyzed the recent era of Large Language Models (LLMs) and is the foundational skill underpinning more advanced capabilities such as reasoning and agentic behaviors. As tasks grow more challenging, the logic structures embedded in natural language instructions becomes increasingly intricate. However, how well LLMs perform on such logic-rich instructions remains under-explored. We propose LogicIFGen and LogicIFEval. LogicIFGen is a scalable, automated framework for generating verifiable instructions from code functions, which can naturally express rich logic such as conditionals, nesting, recursion, and function calls. We further curate a collection of complex code functions and use LogicIFGen to construct LogicIFEval, a benchmark comprising 426 verifiable logic-rich instructions. Our experiments demonstrate that current state-of-the-art LLMs still struggle to correctly follow the instructions in LogicIFEval. Most LLMs can only follow fewer than 60% of the instructions, revealing significant deficiencies in the instruction-following ability. Code and Benchmark: https://github.com/mianzhang/LogicIF&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09125</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 17:54:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Is a Feature: Exploiting Temporal Dynamics in Diffusion Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09138</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09138.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wen Wang, Bozhen Fang, Chenchen Jing, Yongliang Shen, Yangyi Shen, Qiuyu Wang, Hao Ouyang, Hao Chen, Chunhua Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion large language models (dLLMs) generate text through iterative denoising, yet current decoding strategies discard rich intermediate predictions in favor of the final output. Our work here reveals a critical phenomenon, temporal oscillation, where correct answers often emerge in the middle process, but are overwritten in later denoising steps. To address this issue, we introduce two complementary methods that exploit temporal consistency: 1) Temporal Self-Consistency Voting, a training-free, test-time decoding strategy that aggregates predictions across denoising steps to select the most consistent output; and 2) a post-training method termed Temporal Consistency Reinforcement, which uses Temporal Semantic Entropy (TSE), a measure of semantic stability across intermediate predictions, as a reward signal to encourage stable generations. Empirical results across multiple benchmarks demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach. Using the negative TSE reward alone, we observe a remarkable average improvement of 24.7% on the Countdown dataset over an existing dLLM. Combined with the accuracy reward, we achieve absolute gains of 2.0% on GSM8K, 4.3% on MATH500, 6.6% on SVAMP, and 25.3% on Countdown, respectively. Our findings underscore the untapped potential of temporal dynamics in dLLMs and offer two simple yet effective tools to harness them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09138</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeing, Listening, Remembering, and Reasoning: A Multimodal Agent with   Long-Term Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09736</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09736.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lin Long, Yichen He, Wentao Ye, Yiyuan Pan, Yuan Lin, Hang Li, Junbo Zhao, Wei Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce M3-Agent, a novel multimodal agent framework equipped with long-term memory. Like humans, M3-Agent can process real-time visual and auditory inputs to build and update its long-term memory. Beyond episodic memory, it also develops semantic memory, enabling it to accumulate world knowledge over time. Its memory is organized in an entity-centric, multimodal format, allowing deeper and more consistent understanding of the environment. Given an instruction, M3-Agent autonomously performs multi-turn, iterative reasoning and retrieves relevant information from memory to accomplish the task. To evaluate memory effectiveness and memory-based reasoning in multimodal agents, we develop M3-Bench, a new long-video question answering benchmark. M3-Bench comprises 100 newly recorded real-world videos captured from a robot's perspective (M3-Bench-robot) and 929 web-sourced videos across diverse scenarios (M3-Bench-web). We annotate question-answer pairs designed to test key capabilities essential for agent applications, such as human understanding, general knowledge extraction, and cross-modal reasoning. Experimental results show that M3-Agent, trained via reinforcement learning, outperforms the strongest baseline, a prompting agent using Gemini-1.5-pro and GPT-4o, achieving 6.7%, 7.7%, and 5.3% higher accuracy on M3-Bench-robot, M3-Bench-web and VideoMME-long, respectively. Our work advances the multimodal agents toward more human-like long-term memory and provides insights into their practical design. Model, code and data are available at https://github.com/bytedance-seed/m3-agent&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09736</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 12:03:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speed Always Wins: A Survey on Efficient Architectures for Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09834</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09834.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weigao Sun, Jiaxi Hu, Yucheng Zhou, Jusen Du, Disen Lan, Kexin Wang, Tong Zhu, Xiaoye Qu, Yu Zhang, Xiaoyu Mo, Daizong Liu, Yuxuan Liang, Wenliang Chen, Guoqi Li, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have delivered impressive results in language understanding, generation, reasoning, and pushes the ability boundary of multimodal models. Transformer models, as the foundation of modern LLMs, offer a strong baseline with excellent scaling properties. However, the traditional transformer architecture requires substantial computations and poses significant obstacles for large-scale training and practical deployment. In this survey, we offer a systematic examination of innovative LLM architectures that address the inherent limitations of transformers and boost the efficiency. Starting from language modeling, this survey covers the background and technical details of linear and sparse sequence modeling methods, efficient full attention variants, sparse mixture-of-experts, hybrid model architectures incorporating the above techniques, and emerging diffusion LLMs. Additionally, we discuss applications of these techniques to other modalities and consider their wider implications for developing scalable, resource-aware foundation models. By grouping recent studies into the above category, this survey presents a blueprint of modern efficient LLM architectures, and we hope this could help motivate future research toward more efficient, versatile AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09834</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 14:13:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRELUDE: A Benchmark Designed to Require Global Comprehension and   Reasoning over Long Contexts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09848</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09848.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mo Yu, Tsz Ting Chung, Chulun Zhou, Tong Li, Rui Lu, Jiangnan Li, Liyan Xu, Haoshu Lu, Ning Zhang, Jing Li, Jie Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 66&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce PRELUDE, a benchmark for evaluating long-context understanding through the task of determining whether a character's prequel story is consistent with the canonical narrative of the original book. Our task poses a stronger demand for global comprehension and deep reasoning than existing benchmarks -- as the prequels are not part of the original story, assessing their plausibility typically requires searching and integrating information that is only indirectly related. Empirically, 88% of instances require evidence from multiple parts of the narrative. Experimental results highlight the challenge of our task: in-context learning, RAG and in-domain training with state-of-the-art LLMs, and commercial DeepResearch services, lag behind humans by &gt;15%. A further human study reveals that models often produce correct answers with flawed reasoning, leading to an over 30% gap in reasoning accuracy compared to humans. These findings underscore the substantial room for improvement in long-context understanding and reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09848</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 14:28:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AWorld: Dynamic Multi-Agent System with Stable Maneuvering for Robust   GAIA Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09889</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09889.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhitian Xie, Qintong Wu, Chengyue Yu, Chenyi Zhuang, Jinjie Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of large language models (LLMs) has empowered intelligent agents to leverage diverse external tools for solving complex real-world problems. However, as agents increasingly depend on multiple tools, they encounter new challenges: extended contexts from disparate sources and noisy or irrelevant tool outputs can undermine system reliability and accuracy. These challenges underscore the necessity for enhanced stability in agent-based systems. To address this, we introduce dynamic supervision and maneuvering mechanisms, constructing a robust and dynamic Multi-Agent System (MAS) architecture within the AWorld framework. In our approach, the Execution Agent invokes the Guard Agent at critical steps to verify and correct the reasoning process, effectively reducing errors arising from noise and bolstering problem-solving robustness. Extensive experiments on the GAIA test dataset reveal that our dynamic maneuvering mechanism significantly improves both the effectiveness and stability of solutions, outperforming single-agent system (SAS) and standard tool-augmented systems. As a result, our dynamic MAS system achieved first place among open-source projects on the prestigious GAIA leaderboard. These findings highlight the practical value of collaborative agent roles in developing more reliable and trustworthy intelligent systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09889</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 15:46:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Story2Board: A Training-Free Approach for Expressive Storyboard   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09983</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09983.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; David Dinkevich, Matan Levy, Omri Avrahami, Dvir Samuel, Dani Lischinski&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 66&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Story2Board, a training-free framework for expressive storyboard generation from natural language. Existing methods narrowly focus on subject identity, overlooking key aspects of visual storytelling such as spatial composition, background evolution, and narrative pacing. To address this, we introduce a lightweight consistency framework composed of two components: Latent Panel Anchoring, which preserves a shared character reference across panels, and Reciprocal Attention Value Mixing, which softly blends visual features between token pairs with strong reciprocal attention. Together, these mechanisms enhance coherence without architectural changes or fine-tuning, enabling state-of-the-art diffusion models to generate visually diverse yet consistent storyboards. To structure generation, we use an off-the-shelf language model to convert free-form stories into grounded panel-level prompts. To evaluate, we propose the Rich Storyboard Benchmark, a suite of open-domain narratives designed to assess layout diversity and background-grounded storytelling, in addition to consistency. We also introduce a new Scene Diversity metric that quantifies spatial and pose variation across storyboards. Our qualitative and quantitative results, as well as a user study, show that Story2Board produces more dynamic, coherent, and narratively engaging storyboards than existing baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09983</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 17:56:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DINOv3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10104</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10104.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Oriane Simoni, Huy V. Vo, Maximilian Seitzer, Federico Baldassarre, Maxime Oquab, Cijo Jose, Vasil Khalidov, Marc Szafraniec, Seungeun Yi, Michal Ramamonjisoa, Francisco Massa, Daniel Haziza, Luca Wehrstedt, Jianyuan Wang, Timothe Darcet, Tho Moutakanni, Leonel Sentana, Claire Roberts, Andrea Vedaldi, Jamie Tolan, John Brandt, Camille Couprie, Julien Mairal, Herv Jgou, Patrick Labatut, Piotr Bojanowski&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 221&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-supervised learning holds the promise of eliminating the need for manual data annotation, enabling models to scale effortlessly to massive datasets and larger architectures. By not being tailored to specific tasks or domains, this training paradigm has the potential to learn visual representations from diverse sources, ranging from natural to aerial images -- using a single algorithm. This technical report introduces DINOv3, a major milestone toward realizing this vision by leveraging simple yet effective strategies. First, we leverage the benefit of scaling both dataset and model size by careful data preparation, design, and optimization. Second, we introduce a new method called Gram anchoring, which effectively addresses the known yet unsolved issue of dense feature maps degrading during long training schedules. Finally, we apply post-hoc strategies that further enhance our models' flexibility with respect to resolution, model size, and alignment with text. As a result, we present a versatile vision foundation model that outperforms the specialized state of the art across a broad range of settings, without fine-tuning. DINOv3 produces high-quality dense features that achieve outstanding performance on various vision tasks, significantly surpassing previous self- and weakly-supervised foundation models. We also share the DINOv3 suite of vision models, designed to advance the state of the art on a wide spectrum of tasks and data by providing scalable solutions for diverse resource constraints and deployment scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10104</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 18:00:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XQuant: Breaking the Memory Wall for LLM Inference with KV Cache   Rematerialization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10395</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10395.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aditya Tomar, Coleman Hooper, Minjae Lee, Haocheng Xi, Rishabh Tiwari, Wonjun Kang, Luca Manolache, Michael W. Mahoney, Kurt Keutzer, Amir Gholami&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although LLM inference has emerged as a critical workload for many downstream applications, efficiently inferring LLMs is challenging due to the substantial memory footprint and bandwidth requirements. In parallel, compute capabilities have steadily outpaced both memory capacity and bandwidth over the last few decades, a trend that remains evident in modern GPU hardware and exacerbates the challenge of LLM inference. As such, new algorithms are emerging that trade increased computation for reduced memory operations. To that end, we present XQuant, which takes advantage of this trend, enabling an order-of-magnitude reduction in memory consumption through low-bit quantization with substantial accuracy benefits relative to state-of-the-art KV cache quantization methods. We accomplish this by quantizing and caching the layer input activations X, instead of using standard KV caching, and then rematerializing the Keys and Values on-the-fly during inference. This results in an immediate 2times memory savings compared to KV caching. By applying XQuant, we achieve up to sim 7.7times memory savings with &lt;0.1 perplexity degradation compared to the FP16 baseline. Furthermore, our approach leverages the fact that X values are similar across layers. Building on this observation, we introduce XQuant-CL, which exploits the cross-layer similarity in the X embeddings for extreme compression. Across different models, XQuant-CL attains up to 10times memory savings relative to the FP16 baseline with only 0.01 perplexity degradation, and 12.5times memory savings with only 0.1 perplexity degradation. XQuant exploits the rapidly increasing compute capabilities of hardware platforms to eliminate the memory bottleneck, while surpassing state-of-the-art KV cache quantization methods and achieving near-FP16 accuracy across a wide range of models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10395</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 06:52:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ComoRAG: A Cognitive-Inspired Memory-Organized RAG for Stateful Long   Narrative Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10419</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10419.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Juyuan Wang, Rongchen Zhao, Wei Wei, Yufeng Wang, Mo Yu, Jie Zhou, Jin Xu, Liyan Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Narrative comprehension on long stories and novels has been a challenging domain attributed to their intricate plotlines and entangled, often evolving relations among characters and entities. Given the LLM's diminished reasoning over extended context and high computational cost, retrieval-based approaches remain a pivotal role in practice. However, traditional RAG methods can fall short due to their stateless, single-step retrieval process, which often overlooks the dynamic nature of capturing interconnected relations within long-range context. In this work, we propose ComoRAG, holding the principle that narrative reasoning is not a one-shot process, but a dynamic, evolving interplay between new evidence acquisition and past knowledge consolidation, analogous to human cognition when reasoning with memory-related signals in the brain. Specifically, when encountering a reasoning impasse, ComoRAG undergoes iterative reasoning cycles while interacting with a dynamic memory workspace. In each cycle, it generates probing queries to devise new exploratory paths, then integrates the retrieved evidence of new aspects into a global memory pool, thereby supporting the emergence of a coherent context for the query resolution. Across four challenging long-context narrative benchmarks (200K+ tokens), ComoRAG outperforms strong RAG baselines with consistent relative gains up to 11% compared to the strongest baseline. Further analysis reveals that ComoRAG is particularly advantageous for complex queries requiring global comprehension, offering a principled, cognitively motivated paradigm for retrieval-based long context comprehension towards stateful reasoning. Our code is publicly released at https://github.com/EternityJune25/ComoRAG&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10419</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 07:52:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>We-Math 2.0: A Versatile MathBook System for Incentivizing Visual   Mathematical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10433</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10433.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runqi Qiao, Qiuna Tan, Peiqing Yang, Yanzi Wang, Xiaowan Wang, Enhui Wan, Sitong Zhou, Guanting Dong, Yuchen Zeng, Yida Xu, Jie Wang, Chong Sun, Chen Li, Honggang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 142&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have demonstrated impressive capabilities across various tasks, but still struggle with complex mathematical reasoning. Existing research primarily focuses on dataset construction and method optimization, often overlooking two critical aspects: comprehensive knowledge-driven design and model-centric data space modeling. In this paper, we introduce We-Math 2.0, a unified system that integrates a structured mathematical knowledge system, model-centric data space modeling, and a reinforcement learning (RL)-based training paradigm to comprehensively enhance the mathematical reasoning abilities of MLLMs. The key contributions of We-Math 2.0 are fourfold: (1) MathBook Knowledge System: We construct a five-level hierarchical system encompassing 491 knowledge points and 1,819 fundamental principles. (2) MathBook-Standard &amp; Pro: We develop MathBook-Standard, a dataset that ensures broad conceptual coverage and flexibility through dual expansion. Additionally, we define a three-dimensional difficulty space and generate 7 progressive variants per problem to build MathBook-Pro, a challenging dataset for robust training. (3) MathBook-RL: We propose a two-stage RL framework comprising: (i) Cold-Start Fine-tuning, which aligns the model with knowledge-oriented chain-of-thought reasoning; and (ii) Progressive Alignment RL, leveraging average-reward learning and dynamic data scheduling to achieve progressive alignment across difficulty levels. (4) MathBookEval: We introduce a comprehensive benchmark covering all 491 knowledge points with diverse reasoning step distributions. Experimental results show that MathBook-RL performs competitively with existing baselines on four widely-used benchmarks and achieves strong results on MathBookEval, suggesting promising generalization in mathematical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10433</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 08:15:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NextStep-1: Toward Autoregressive Image Generation with Continuous   Tokens at Scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10711</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10711.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NextStep Team, Chunrui Han, Guopeng Li, Jingwei Wu, Quan Sun, Yan Cai, Yuang Peng, Zheng Ge, Deyu Zhou, Haomiao Tang, Hongyu Zhou, Kenkun Liu, Ailin Huang, Bin Wang, Changxin Miao, Deshan Sun, En Yu, Fukun Yin, Gang Yu, Hao Nie, Haoran Lv, Hanpeng Hu, Jia Wang, Jian Zhou, Jianjian Sun, Kaijun Tan, Kang An, Kangheng Lin, Liang Zhao, Mei Chen, Peng Xing, Rui Wang, Shiyu Liu, Shutao Xia, Tianhao You, Wei Ji, Xianfang Zeng, Xin Han, Xuelin Zhang, Yana Wei, Yanming Xu, Yimin Jiang, Yingming Wang, Yu Zhou, Yucheng Han, Ziyang Meng, Binxing Jiao, Daxin Jiang, Xiangyu Zhang, Yibo Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 139&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Prevailing autoregressive (AR) models for text-to-image generation either rely on heavy, computationally-intensive diffusion models to process continuous image tokens, or employ vector quantization (VQ) to obtain discrete tokens with quantization loss. In this paper, we push the autoregressive paradigm forward with NextStep-1, a 14B autoregressive model paired with a 157M flow matching head, training on discrete text tokens and continuous image tokens with next-token prediction objectives. NextStep-1 achieves state-of-the-art performance for autoregressive models in text-to-image generation tasks, exhibiting strong capabilities in high-fidelity image synthesis. Furthermore, our method shows strong performance in image editing, highlighting the power and versatility of our unified approach. To facilitate open research, we will release our code and models to the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10711</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 14:54:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI-Venus Technical Report: Building High-performance UI Agents with RFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10833</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10833.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhangxuan Gu, Zhengwen Zeng, Zhenyu Xu, Xingran Zhou, Shuheng Shen, Yunfei Liu, Beitong Zhou, Changhua Meng, Tianyu Xia, Weizhi Chen, Yue Wen, Jingya Dou, Fei Tang, Jinzhen Lin, Yulin Liu, Zhenlin Guo, Yichen Gong, Heng Jia, Changlong Gao, Yuan Guo, Yong Deng, Zhenyu Guo, Liang Chen, Weiqiang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present UI-Venus, a native UI agent that takes only screenshots as input based on a multimodal large language model. UI-Venus achieves SOTA performance on both UI grounding and navigation tasks using only several hundred thousand high-quality training samples through reinforcement finetune (RFT) based on Qwen2.5-VL. Specifically, the 7B and 72B variants of UI-Venus obtain 94.1% / 50.8% and 95.3% / 61.9% on the standard grounding benchmarks, i.e., Screenspot-V2 / Pro, surpassing the previous SOTA baselines including open-source GTA1 and closed-source UI-TARS-1.5.To show UI-Venus's summary and planing ability, we also evaluate it on the AndroidWorld, an online UI navigation arena, on which our 7B and 72B variants achieve 49.1% and 65.9% success rate, also beating existing models.To achieve this, we introduce carefully designed reward functions for both UI grounding and navigation tasks and corresponding efficient data cleaning strategies.To further boost navigation performance, we propose Self-Evolving Trajectory History Alignment \&amp; Sparse Action Enhancement that refine historical reasoning traces and balances the distribution of sparse but critical actions, leading to more coherent planning and better generalization in complex UI tasks. Our contributions include the publish of SOTA open-source UI agents, comprehensive data cleaning protocols and a novel self-evolving framework for improving navigation performance, which encourage further research and development in the community. Code is available at https://github.com/antgroup/UI-Venus.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10833</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 16:58:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSRL: Self-Search Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10874</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10874.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuchen Fan, Kaiyan Zhang, Heng Zhou, Yuxin Zuo, Yanxu Chen, Yu Fu, Xinwei Long, Xuekai Zhu, Che Jiang, Yuchen Zhang, Li Kang, Gang Chen, Cheng Huang, Zhizhou He, Bingning Wang, Lei Bai, Ning Ding, Bowen Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 90&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We investigate the potential of large language models (LLMs) to serve as efficient simulators for agentic search tasks in reinforcement learning (RL), thereby reducing dependence on costly interactions with external search engines. To this end, we first quantify the intrinsic search capability of LLMs via structured prompting and repeated sampling, which we term Self-Search. Our results reveal that LLMs exhibit strong scaling behavior with respect to the inference budget, achieving high pass@k on question-answering benchmarks, including the challenging BrowseComp task. Building on these observations, we introduce Self-Search RL (SSRL), which enhances LLMs' Self-Search capability through format-based and rule-based rewards. SSRL enables models to iteratively refine their knowledge utilization internally, without requiring access to external tools. Empirical evaluations demonstrate that SSRL-trained policy models provide a cost-effective and stable environment for search-driven RL training, reducing reliance on external search engines and facilitating robust sim-to-real transfer. We draw the following conclusions: 1) LLMs possess world knowledge that can be effectively elicited to achieve high performance; 2) SSRL demonstrates the potential of leveraging internal knowledge to reduce hallucination; 3) SSRL-trained models integrate seamlessly with external search engines without additional effort. Our findings highlight the potential of LLMs to support more scalable RL agent training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10874</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:46:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10875</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10875.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyi Li, Mingda Chen, Bowei Guo, Zhiqiang Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Language Models (DLMs) are rapidly emerging as a powerful and promising alternative to the dominant autoregressive (AR) paradigm. By generating tokens in parallel through an iterative denoising process, DLMs possess inherent advantages in reducing inference latency and capturing bidirectional context, thereby enabling fine-grained control over the generation process. While achieving a several-fold speed-up, recent advancements have allowed DLMs to show performance comparable to their autoregressive counterparts, making them a compelling choice for various natural language processing tasks. In this survey, we provide a holistic overview of the current DLM landscape. We trace its evolution and relationship with other paradigms, such as autoregressive and masked language models, and cover both foundational principles and state-of-the-art models. Our work offers an up-to-date, comprehensive taxonomy and an in-depth analysis of current techniques, from pre-training strategies to advanced post-training methods. Another contribution of this survey is a thorough review of DLM inference strategies and optimizations, including improvements in decoding parallelism, caching mechanisms, and generation quality. We also highlight the latest approaches to multimodal extensions of DLMs and delineate their applications across various practical scenarios. Furthermore, our discussion addresses the limitations and challenges of DLMs, including efficiency, long-sequence handling, and infrastructure requirements, while outlining future research directions to sustain progress in this rapidly evolving field. Project GitHub is available at https://github.com/VILA-Lab/Awesome-DLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10875</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:47:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ToonComposer: Streamlining Cartoon Production with Generative   Post-Keyframing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10881</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10881.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lingen Li, Guangzhi Wang, Zhaoyang Zhang, Yaowei Li, Xiaoyu Li, Qi Dou, Jinwei Gu, Tianfan Xue, Ying Shan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional cartoon and anime production involves keyframing, inbetweening, and colorization stages, which require intensive manual effort. Despite recent advances in AI, existing methods often handle these stages separately, leading to error accumulation and artifacts. For instance, inbetweening approaches struggle with large motions, while colorization methods require dense per-frame sketches. To address this, we introduce ToonComposer, a generative model that unifies inbetweening and colorization into a single post-keyframing stage. ToonComposer employs a sparse sketch injection mechanism to provide precise control using keyframe sketches. Additionally, it uses a cartoon adaptation method with the spatial low-rank adapter to tailor a modern video foundation model to the cartoon domain while keeping its temporal prior intact. Requiring as few as a single sketch and a colored reference frame, ToonComposer excels with sparse inputs, while also supporting multiple sketches at any temporal location for more precise motion control. This dual capability reduces manual workload and improves flexibility, empowering artists in real-world scenarios. To evaluate our model, we further created PKBench, a benchmark featuring human-drawn sketches that simulate real-world use cases. Our evaluation demonstrates that ToonComposer outperforms existing methods in visual quality, motion consistency, and production efficiency, offering a superior and more flexible solution for AI-assisted cartoon production.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10881</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:50:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BeyondWeb: Lessons from Scaling Synthetic Data for Trillion-scale   Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10975</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10975.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pratyush Maini, Vineeth Dorna, Parth Doshi, Aldo Carranza, Fan Pan, Jack Urbanek, Paul Burstein, Alex Fang, Alvin Deng, Amro Abbas, Brett Larsen, Cody Blakeney, Charvi Bannur, Christina Baek, Darren Teh, David Schwab, Haakon Mongstad, Haoli Yin, Josh Wills, Kaleigh Mentzer, Luke Merrick, Ricardo Monti, Rishabh Adiga, Siddharth Joshi, Spandan Das, Zhengping Wang, Bogdan Gaza, Ari Morcos, Matthew Leavitt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language model (LLM) pretraining have shown that simply scaling data quantity eventually leads to diminishing returns, hitting a data wall. In response, the use of synthetic data for pretraining has emerged as a promising paradigm for pushing the frontier of performance. Despite this, the factors affecting synthetic data quality remain poorly understood. In this work, we introduce BeyondWeb, a synthetic data generation framework that produces high-quality synthetic data for pretraining. BeyondWeb significantly extends the capabilities of traditional web-scale datasets, outperforming state-of-the-art synthetic pretraining datasets such as Cosmopedia and Nemotron-CC's high-quality synthetic subset (Nemotron-Synth) by up to 5.1 percentage points (pp) and 2.6pp, respectively, when averaged across a suite of 14 benchmark evaluations. It delivers up to 7.7x faster training than open web data and 2.7x faster than Nemotron-Synth. Remarkably, a 3B model trained for 180B tokens on BeyondWeb outperforms an 8B model trained for the same token budget on Cosmopedia. We also present several insights from BeyondWeb on synthetic data for pretraining: what drives its benefits, which data to rephrase and how, and the impact of model size and family on data quality. Overall, our work shows that there's no silver bullet for generating high-quality synthetic pretraining data. The best outcomes require jointly optimizing many factors, a challenging task that requires rigorous science and practical expertise. Naive approaches can yield modest improvements, potentially at great cost, while well-executed methods can yield transformative improvements, as exemplified by BeyondWeb.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10975</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 17:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Punctuation Matters: A Large-Scale Comparison of Prompt Robustness   Methods for LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11383</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11383.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mikhail Seleznyov, Mikhail Chaichuk, Gleb Ershov, Alexander Panchenko, Elena Tutubalina, Oleg Somov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are highly sensitive to subtle, non-semantic variations in prompt phrasing and formatting. In this work, we present the first systematic evaluation of 5 methods for improving prompt robustness within a unified experimental framework. We benchmark these techniques on 8 models from Llama, Qwen and Gemma families across 52 tasks from Natural Instructions dataset. Our evaluation covers robustness methods from both fine-tuned and in-context learning paradigms, and tests their generalization against multiple types of distribution shifts. Finally, we extend our analysis to GPT-4.1 and DeepSeek V3 to assess frontier models' current robustness to format perturbations. Our findings offer actionable insights into the relative effectiveness of these robustness methods, enabling practitioners to make informed decisions when aiming for stable and reliable LLM performance in real-world applications. Code: https://github.com/AIRI-Institute/when-punctuation-matters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11383</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 10:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ovis2.5 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11737</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11737.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shiyin Lu, Yang Li, Yu Xia, Yuwei Hu, Shanshan Zhao, Yanqing Ma, Zhichao Wei, Yinglun Li, Lunhao Duan, Jianshan Zhao, Yuxuan Han, Haijun Li, Wanying Chen, Junke Tang, Chengkun Hou, Zhixing Du, Tianli Zhou, Wenjie Zhang, Huping Ding, Jiahe Li, Wen Li, Gui Hu, Yiliang Gu, Siran Yang, Jiamang Wang, Hailong Sun, Yibo Wang, Hui Sun, Jinlong Huang, Yuping He, Shengze Shi, Weihong Zhang, Guodong Zheng, Junpeng Jiang, Sensen Gao, Yi-Feng Wu, Sijia Chen, Yuhui Chen, Qing-Guo Chen, Zhao Xu, Weihua Luo, Kaifu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 104&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Ovis2.5, a successor to Ovis2 designed for native-resolution visual perception and strong multimodal reasoning. Ovis2.5 integrates a native-resolution vision transformer that processes images at their native, variable resolutions, avoiding the degradation from fixed-resolution tiling and preserving both fine detail and global layout -- crucial for visually dense content like complex charts. To strengthen reasoning, we train the model to move beyond linear chain-of-thought and perform reflection -- including self-checking and revision. This advanced capability is exposed as an optional "thinking mode" at inference time, allowing users to trade latency for enhanced accuracy on difficult inputs. The model is trained via a comprehensive five-phase curriculum that progressively builds its skills. The process begins with foundational visual and multimodal pretraining, advances through large-scale instruction tuning, and culminates in alignment and reasoning enhancement using DPO and GRPO. To scale these upgrades efficiently, we employ multimodal data packing and hybrid parallelism, yielding a significant end-to-end speedup. We release two open-source models: Ovis2.5-9B and Ovis2.5-2B. The latter continues the "small model, big performance" philosophy of Ovis2, making it ideal for resource-constrained, on-device scenarios. On the OpenCompass multimodal leaderboard, Ovis2.5-9B averages 78.3, marking a substantial improvement over its predecessor, Ovis2-8B, and achieving state-of-the-art results among open-source MLLMs in the sub-40B parameter range; Ovis2.5-2B scores 73.9, establishing SOTA for its size. Beyond aggregate scores, Ovis2.5 achieves leading results on STEM benchmarks, exhibits strong capabilities on grounding and video tasks, and achieves open-source SOTA at its scale for complex chart analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11737</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:01:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thyme: Think Beyond Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11630</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11630.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi-Fan Zhang, Xingyu Lu, Shukang Yin, Chaoyou Fu, Wei Chen, Xiao Hu, Bin Wen, Kaiyu Jiang, Changyi Liu, Tianke Zhang, Haonan Fan, Kaibing Chen, Jiankang Chen, Haojie Ding, Kaiyu Tang, Zhang Zhang, Liang Wang, Fan Yang, Tingting Gao, Guorui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 77&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Following OpenAI's introduction of the ``thinking with images'' concept, recent efforts have explored stimulating the use of visual information in the reasoning process to enhance model performance in perception and reasoning tasks. However, to the best of our knowledge, no open-source work currently offers a feature set as rich as proprietary models (O3), which can perform diverse image manipulations and simultaneously enhance logical reasoning capabilities through code. In this paper, we make a preliminary attempt in this direction by introducing Thyme (Think Beyond Images), a novel paradigm for enabling MLLMs to transcend existing ``think with images'' approaches by autonomously generating and executing diverse image processing and computational operations via executable code. This approach not only facilitates a rich, on-the-fly set of image manipulations (e.g., cropping, rotation, contrast enhancement) but also allows for mathematical computations, all while maintaining high autonomy in deciding when and how to apply these operations. We activate this capability through a two-stage training strategy: an initial SFT on a curated dataset of 500K samples to teach code generation, followed by a RL phase to refine decision-making. For the RL stage, we manually collect and design high-resolution question-answer pairs to increase the learning difficulty, and we propose GRPO-ATS (Group Relative Policy Optimization with Adaptive Temperature Sampling), an algorithm that applies distinct temperatures to text and code generation to balance reasoning exploration with code execution precision. We conduct extensive experimental analysis and ablation studies. Comprehensive evaluations on nearly 20 benchmarks show that Thyme yields significant and consistent performance gains, particularly in challenging high-resolution perception and complex reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11630</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 17:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FutureX: An Advanced Live Benchmark for LLM Agents in Future Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11987</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11987.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Zeng, Jiashuo Liu, Siyuan Chen, Tianci He, Yali Liao, Jinpeng Wang, Zaiyuan Wang, Yang Yang, Lingyue Yin, Mingren Yin, Zhenwei Zhu, Tianle Cai, Zehui Chen, Jiecao Chen, Yantao Du, Xiang Gao, Jiacheng Guo, Liang Hu, Jianpeng Jiao, Xiangsheng Li, Jingkai Liu, Shuang Ni, Zhoufutu Wen, Ge Zhang, Kaiyuan Zhang, Xin Zhou, Jose Blanchet, Xipeng Qiu, Mengdi Wang, Wenhao Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Future prediction is a complex task for LLM agents, requiring a high level of analytical thinking, information gathering, contextual understanding, and decision-making under uncertainty. Agents must not only gather and interpret vast amounts of dynamic information but also integrate diverse data sources, weigh uncertainties, and adapt predictions based on emerging trends, just as human experts do in fields like politics, economics, and finance. Despite its importance, no large-scale benchmark exists for evaluating agents on future prediction, largely due to challenges in handling real-time updates and retrieving timely, accurate answers. To address this, we introduce FutureX, a dynamic and live evaluation benchmark specifically designed for LLM agents performing future prediction tasks. FutureX is the largest and most diverse live benchmark for future prediction, supporting real-time daily updates and eliminating data contamination through an automated pipeline for question gathering and answer collection. We evaluate 25 LLM/agent models, including those with reasoning, search capabilities, and integration of external tools such as the open-source Deep Research Agent and closed-source Deep Research models. This comprehensive evaluation assesses agents' adaptive reasoning and performance in dynamic environments. Additionally, we provide in-depth analyses of agents' failure modes and performance pitfalls in future-oriented tasks, including the vulnerability to fake web pages and the temporal validity. Our goal is to establish a dynamic, contamination-free evaluation standard that drives the development of LLM agents capable of performing at the level of professional human analysts in complex reasoning and predictive thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11987</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 08:54:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next Visual Granularity Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12811</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12811.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yikai Wang, Zhouxia Wang, Zhonghua Wu, Qingyi Tao, Kang Liao, Chen Change Loy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel approach to image generation by decomposing an image into a structured sequence, where each element in the sequence shares the same spatial resolution but differs in the number of unique tokens used, capturing different level of visual granularity. Image generation is carried out through our newly introduced Next Visual Granularity (NVG) generation framework, which generates a visual granularity sequence beginning from an empty image and progressively refines it, from global layout to fine details, in a structured manner. This iterative process encodes a hierarchical, layered representation that offers fine-grained control over the generation process across multiple granularity levels. We train a series of NVG models for class-conditional image generation on the ImageNet dataset and observe clear scaling behavior. Compared to the VAR series, NVG consistently outperforms it in terms of FID scores (3.30 -&gt; 3.03, 2.57 -&gt;2.44, 2.09 -&gt; 2.06). We also conduct extensive analysis to showcase the capability and potential of the NVG framework. Our code and models will be released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12811</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 10:47:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S^2-Guidance: Stochastic Self Guidance for Training-Free Enhancement of   Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12880</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12880.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chubin Chen, Jiashu Zhu, Xiaokun Feng, Nisha Huang, Meiqi Wu, Fangyuan Mao, Jiahong Wu, Xiangxiang Chu, Xiu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Classifier-free Guidance (CFG) is a widely used technique in modern diffusion models for enhancing sample quality and prompt adherence. However, through an empirical analysis on Gaussian mixture modeling with a closed-form solution, we observe a discrepancy between the suboptimal results produced by CFG and the ground truth. The model's excessive reliance on these suboptimal predictions often leads to semantic incoherence and low-quality outputs. To address this issue, we first empirically demonstrate that the model's suboptimal predictions can be effectively refined using sub-networks of the model itself. Building on this insight, we propose S^2-Guidance, a novel method that leverages stochastic block-dropping during the forward process to construct stochastic sub-networks, effectively guiding the model away from potential low-quality predictions and toward high-quality outputs. Extensive qualitative and quantitative experiments on text-to-image and text-to-video generation tasks demonstrate that S^2-Guidance delivers superior performance, consistently surpassing CFG and other advanced guidance strategies. Our code will be released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12880</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 12:31:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Has GPT-5 Achieved Spatial Intelligence? An Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13142</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13142.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongang Cai, Yubo Wang, Qingping Sun, Ruisi Wang, Chenyang Gu, Wanqi Yin, Zhiqian Lin, Zhitao Yang, Chen Wei, Xuanke Shi, Kewang Deng, Xiaoyang Han, Zukai Chen, Jiaqi Li, Xiangyu Fan, Hanming Deng, Lewei Lu, Bo Li, Ziwei Liu, Quan Wang, Dahua Lin, Lei Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-modal models have achieved remarkable progress in recent years. Nevertheless, they continue to exhibit notable limitations in spatial understanding and reasoning, which are fundamental capabilities to achieving artificial general intelligence. With the recent release of GPT-5, allegedly the most powerful AI model to date, it is timely to examine where the leading models stand on the path toward spatial intelligence. First, we propose a comprehensive taxonomy of spatial tasks that unifies existing benchmarks and discuss the challenges in ensuring fair evaluation. We then evaluate state-of-the-art proprietary and open-source models on eight key benchmarks, at a cost exceeding one billion total tokens. Our empirical study reveals that (1) GPT-5 demonstrates unprecedented strength in spatial intelligence, yet (2) still falls short of human performance across a broad spectrum of tasks. Moreover, we (3) identify the more challenging spatial intelligence problems for multi-modal models, and (4) proprietary models do not exhibit a decisive advantage when facing the most difficult problems. In addition, we conduct a qualitative evaluation across a diverse set of scenarios that are intuitive for humans yet fail even the most advanced multi-modal models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13142</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:55:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4DNeX: Feed-Forward 4D Generative Modeling Made Easy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13154</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13154.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaoxi Chen, Tianqi Liu, Long Zhuo, Jiawei Ren, Zeng Tao, He Zhu, Fangzhou Hong, Liang Pan, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present 4DNeX, the first feed-forward framework for generating 4D (i.e., dynamic 3D) scene representations from a single image. In contrast to existing methods that rely on computationally intensive optimization or require multi-frame video inputs, 4DNeX enables efficient, end-to-end image-to-4D generation by fine-tuning a pretrained video diffusion model. Specifically, 1) to alleviate the scarcity of 4D data, we construct 4DNeX-10M, a large-scale dataset with high-quality 4D annotations generated using advanced reconstruction approaches. 2) we introduce a unified 6D video representation that jointly models RGB and XYZ sequences, facilitating structured learning of both appearance and geometry. 3) we propose a set of simple yet effective adaptation strategies to repurpose pretrained video diffusion models for 4D modeling. 4DNeX produces high-quality dynamic point clouds that enable novel-view video synthesis. Extensive experiments demonstrate that 4DNeX outperforms existing 4D generation methods in efficiency and generalizability, offering a scalable solution for image-to-4D modeling and laying the foundation for generative 4D world models that simulate dynamic scene evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13154</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Scores to Skills: A Cognitive Diagnosis Framework for Evaluating   Financial Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13491</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13491.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyan Kuang, Feiyu Zhu, Maowei Jiang, Yanzhao Lai, Zelin Wang, Zhitong Wang, Meikang Qiu, Jiajia Huang, Min Peng, Qianqian Xie, Sophia Ananiadou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown promise for financial applications, yet their suitability for this high-stakes domain remains largely unproven due to inadequacies in existing benchmarks. Existing benchmarks solely rely on score-level evaluation, summarizing performance with a single score that obscures the nuanced understanding of what models truly know and their precise limitations. They also rely on datasets that cover only a narrow subset of financial concepts, while overlooking other essentials for real-world applications. To address these gaps, we introduce FinCDM, the first cognitive diagnosis evaluation framework tailored for financial LLMs, enabling the evaluation of LLMs at the knowledge-skill level, identifying what financial skills and knowledge they have or lack based on their response patterns across skill-tagged tasks, rather than a single aggregated number. We construct CPA-QKA, the first cognitively informed financial evaluation dataset derived from the Certified Public Accountant (CPA) examination, with comprehensive coverage of real-world accounting and financial skills. It is rigorously annotated by domain experts, who author, validate, and annotate questions with high inter-annotator agreement and fine-grained knowledge labels. Our extensive experiments on 30 proprietary, open-source, and domain-specific LLMs show that FinCDM reveals hidden knowledge gaps, identifies under-tested areas such as tax and regulatory reasoning overlooked by traditional benchmarks, and uncovers behavioral clusters among models. FinCDM introduces a new paradigm for financial LLM evaluation by enabling interpretable, skill-aware diagnosis that supports more trustworthy and targeted model development, and all datasets and evaluation scripts will be publicly released to support further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13491</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 03:52:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prompt Orchestration Markup Language</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13948</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13948.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuge Zhang, Nan Chen, Jiahang Xu, Yuqing Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) require sophisticated prompting, yet current practices face challenges in structure, data integration, format sensitivity, and tooling. Existing methods lack comprehensive solutions for organizing complex prompts involving diverse data types (documents, tables, images) or managing presentation variations systematically. To address these gaps, we introduce POML (Prompt Orchestration Markup Language). POML employs component-based markup for logical structure (roles, tasks, examples), specialized tags for seamless data integration, and a CSS-like styling system to decouple content from presentation, reducing formatting sensitivity. It includes templating for dynamic prompts and a comprehensive developer toolkit (IDE support, SDKs) to improve version control and collaboration. We validate POML through two case studies demonstrating its impact on complex application integration (PomLink) and accuracy performance (TableQA), as well as a user study assessing its effectiveness in real-world development scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13948</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 15:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Pass@1: Self-Play with Variational Problem Synthesis Sustains   RLVR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14029</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14029.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiao Liang, Zhongzhi Li, Yeyun Gong, Yelong Shen, Ying Nian Wu, Zhijiang Guo, Weizhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 115&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has recently emerged as a key paradigm for post-training Large Language Models (LLMs), particularly for complex reasoning tasks. However, vanilla RLVR training has been shown to improve Pass@1 performance at the expense of policy entropy, leading to reduced generation diversity and limiting the Pass@k performance, which typically represents the upper bound of LLM reasoning capability. In this paper, we systematically analyze the policy's generation diversity from the perspective of training problems and find that augmenting and updating training problems helps mitigate entropy collapse during training. Based on these observations, we propose an online Self-play with Variational problem Synthesis (SvS) strategy for RLVR training, which uses the policy's correct solutions to synthesize variational problems while ensuring their reference answers remain identical to the originals. This self-improving strategy effectively maintains policy entropy during training and substantially improves Pass@k compared with standard RLVR, sustaining prolonged improvements and achieving absolute gains of 18.3% and 22.8% in Pass@32 performance on the competition-level AIME24 and AIME25 benchmarks. Experiments on 12 reasoning benchmarks across varying model sizes from 3B to 32B consistently demonstrate the generalizability and robustness of SvS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14029</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 17:42:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongSplat: Robust Unposed 3D Gaussian Splatting for Casual Long Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14041</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14041.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chin-Yang Lin, Cheng Sun, Fu-En Yang, Min-Hung Chen, Yen-Yu Lin, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LongSplat addresses critical challenges in novel view synthesis (NVS) from casually captured long videos characterized by irregular camera motion, unknown camera poses, and expansive scenes. Current methods often suffer from pose drift, inaccurate geometry initialization, and severe memory limitations. To address these issues, we introduce LongSplat, a robust unposed 3D Gaussian Splatting framework featuring: (1) Incremental Joint Optimization that concurrently optimizes camera poses and 3D Gaussians to avoid local minima and ensure global consistency; (2) a robust Pose Estimation Module leveraging learned 3D priors; and (3) an efficient Octree Anchor Formation mechanism that converts dense point clouds into anchors based on spatial density. Extensive experiments on challenging benchmarks demonstrate that LongSplat achieves state-of-the-art results, substantially improving rendering quality, pose accuracy, and computational efficiency compared to prior approaches. Project page: https://linjohnss.github.io/longsplat/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14041</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NVIDIA Nemotron Nano 2: An Accurate and Efficient Hybrid   Mamba-Transformer Reasoning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14444</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14444.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NVIDIA, Aarti Basant, Abhijit Khairnar, Abhijit Paithankar, Abhinav Khattar, Adi Renduchintala, Adithya Renduchintala, Aditya Malte, Akhiad Bercovich, Akshay Hazare, Alejandra Rico, Aleksander Ficek, Alex Kondratenko, Alex Shaposhnikov, Ali Taghibakhshi, Amelia Barton, Ameya Sunil Mahabaleshwarkar, Amy Shen, Andrew Tao, Ann Guan, Anna Shors, Anubhav Mandarwal, Arham Mehta, Arun Venkatesan, Ashton Sharabiani, Ashwath Aithal, Ashwin Poojary, Ayush Dattagupta, Balaram Buddharaju, Banghua Zhu, Barnaby Simkin, Bilal Kartal, Bita Darvish Rouhani, Bobby Chen, Boris Ginsburg, Brandon Norick, Brian Yu, Bryan Catanzaro, Charles Wang, Charlie Truong, Chetan Mungekar, Chintan Patel, Chris Alexiuk, Christian Munley, Christopher Parisien, Dan Su, Daniel Afrimi, Daniel Korzekwa, Daniel Rohrer, Daria Gitman, David Mosallanezhad, Deepak Narayanan, Dima Rekesh, Dina Yared, Dmytro Pykhtar, Dong Ahn, Duncan Riach, Eileen Long, Elliott Ning, Eric Chung, Erick Galinkin, Evelina Bakhturina, Gargi Prasad, Gerald Shen, Haim Elisha, Harsh Sharma, Hayley Ross, Helen Ngo, Herman Sahota, Hexin Wang, Hoo Chang Shin, Hua Huang, Iain Cunningham, Igor Gitman, Ivan Moshkov, Jaehun Jung, Jan Kautz, Jane Polak Scowcroft, Jared Casper, Jimmy Zhang, Jinze Xue, Jocelyn Huang, Joey Conway, John Kamalu, Jonathan Cohen, Joseph Jennings, Julien Veron Vialard, Junkeun Yi, Jupinder Parmar, Kari Briski, Katherine Cheung, Katherine Luna, Keith Wyss, Keshav Santhanam, Kezhi Kong, Krzysztof Pawelec, Kumar Anik, Kunlun Li, Kushan Ahmadian, Lawrence McAfee, Laya Sleiman, Leon Derczynski, Luis Vega, Maer Rodrigues de Melo, Makesh Narsimhan Sreedhar, Marcin Chochowski, Mark Cai, Markus Kliegl, Marta Stepniewska-Dziubinska, Matvei Novikov, Mehrzad Samadi, Meredith Price, Meriem Boubdir, Michael Boone, Michael Evans, Michal Bien, Michal Zawalski, Miguel Martinez, Mike Chrzanowski, Mohammad Shoeybi, Mostofa Patwary, Namit Dhameja, Nave Assaf, Negar Habibi, Nidhi Bhatia, Nikki Pope, Nima Tajbakhsh, Nirmal Kumar Juluru, Oleg Rybakov, Oleksii Hrinchuk, Oleksii Kuchaiev, Oluwatobi Olabiyi, Pablo Ribalta, Padmavathy Subramanian, Parth Chadha, Pavlo Molchanov, Peter Dykas, Peter Jin, Piotr Bialecki, Piotr Januszewski, Pradeep Thalasta, Prashant Gaikwad, Prasoon Varshney, Pritam Gundecha, Przemek Tredak, Rabeeh Karimi Mahabadi, Rajen Patel, Ran El-Yaniv, Ranjit Rajan, Ria Cheruvu, Rima Shahbazyan, Ritika Borkar, Ritu Gala, Roger Waleffe, Ruoxi Zhang, Russell J. Hewett, Ryan Prenger, Sahil Jain, Samuel Kriman, Sanjeev Satheesh, Saori Kaji, Sarah Yurick, Saurav Muralidharan, Sean Narenthiran, Seonmyeong Bak, Sepehr Sameni, Seungju Han, Shanmugam Ramasamy, Shaona Ghosh, Sharath Turuvekere Sreenivas, Shelby Thomas, Shizhe Diao, Shreya Gopal, Shrimai Prabhumoye, Shubham Toshniwal, Shuoyang Ding, Siddharth Singh, Siddhartha Jain, Somshubra Majumdar, Stefania Alborghetti, Syeda Nahida Akter, Terry Kong, Tim Moon, Tomasz Hliwiak, Tomer Asida, Tony Wang, Twinkle Vashishth, Tyler Poon, Udi Karpas, Vahid Noroozi, Venkat Srinivasan, Vijay Korthikanti, Vikram Fugro, Vineeth Kalluru, Vitaly Kurin, Vitaly Lavrukhin, Wasi Uddin Ahmad, Wei Du, Wonmin Byeon, Ximing Lu, Xin Dong, Yashaswi Karnati, Yejin Choi, Yian Zhang, Ying Lin, Yonggan Fu, Yoshi Suhara, Zhen Dong, Zhiyu Li, Zhongbo Zhu, Zijia Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2, a hybrid Mamba-Transformer language model designed to increase throughput for reasoning workloads while achieving state-of-the-art accuracy compared to similarly-sized models. Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2 builds on the Nemotron-H architecture, in which the majority of the self-attention layers in the common Transformer architecture are replaced with Mamba-2 layers, to achieve improved inference speed when generating the long thinking traces needed for reasoning. We create Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2 by first pre-training a 12-billion-parameter model (Nemotron-Nano-12B-v2-Base) on 20 trillion tokens using an FP8 training recipe. After aligning Nemotron-Nano-12B-v2-Base, we employ the Minitron strategy to compress and distill the model with the goal of enabling inference on up to 128k tokens on a single NVIDIA A10G GPU (22GiB of memory, bfloat16 precision). Compared to existing similarly-sized models (e.g., Qwen3-8B), we show that Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2 achieves on-par or better accuracy on reasoning benchmarks while achieving up to 6x higher inference throughput in reasoning settings like 8k input and 16k output tokens. We are releasing Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2, Nemotron-Nano12B-v2-Base, and Nemotron-Nano-9B-v2-Base checkpoints along with the majority of our pre- and post-training datasets on Hugging Face.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14444</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 06:00:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DuPO: Enabling Reliable LLM Self-Verification via Dual Preference   Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14460</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14460.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuaijie She, Yu Bao, Yu Lu, Lu Xu, Tao Li, Wenhao Zhu, Shujian Huang, Shanbo Cheng, Lu Lu, Yuxuan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 79&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present DuPO, a dual learning-based preference optimization framework that generates annotation-free feedback via a generalized duality. DuPO addresses two key limitations: Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR)'s reliance on costly labels and applicability restricted to verifiable tasks, and traditional dual learning's restriction to strictly dual task pairs (e.g., translation and back-translation). Specifically, DuPO decomposes a primal task's input into known and unknown components, then constructs its dual task to reconstruct the unknown part using the primal output and known information (e.g., reversing math solutions to recover hidden variables), broadening applicability to non-invertible tasks. The quality of this reconstruction serves as a self-supervised reward to optimize the primal task, synergizing with LLMs' ability to instantiate both tasks via a single model. Empirically, DuPO achieves substantial gains across diverse tasks: it enhances the average translation quality by 2.13 COMET over 756 directions, boosts the mathematical reasoning accuracy by an average of 6.4 points on three challenge benchmarks, and enhances performance by 9.3 points as an inference-time reranker (trading computation for accuracy). These results position DuPO as a scalable, general, and annotation-free paradigm for LLM optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14460</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 06:31:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MCP-Universe: Benchmarking Large Language Models with Real-World Model   Context Protocol Servers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14704</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14704.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyang Luo, Zhiqi Shen, Wenzhuo Yang, Zirui Zhao, Prathyusha Jwalapuram, Amrita Saha, Doyen Sahoo, Silvio Savarese, Caiming Xiong, Junnan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Model Context Protocol has emerged as a transformative standard for connecting large language models to external data sources and tools, rapidly gaining adoption across major AI providers and development platforms. However, existing benchmarks are overly simplistic and fail to capture real application challenges such as long-horizon reasoning and large, unfamiliar tool spaces. To address this critical gap, we introduce MCP-Universe, the first comprehensive benchmark specifically designed to evaluate LLMs in realistic and hard tasks through interaction with real-world MCP servers. Our benchmark encompasses 6 core domains spanning 11 different MCP servers: Location Navigation, Repository Management, Financial Analysis, 3D Design, Browser Automation, and Web Searching. To ensure rigorous evaluation, we implement execution-based evaluators, including format evaluators for agent format compliance, static evaluators for time-invariant content matching, and dynamic evaluators that automatically retrieve real-time ground truth for temporally sensitive tasks. Through extensive evaluation of leading LLMs, we find that even SOTA models such as GPT-5 (43.72%), Grok-4 (33.33%) and Claude-4.0-Sonnet (29.44%) exhibit significant performance limitations. In addition, our benchmark poses a significant long-context challenge for LLM agents, as the number of input tokens increases rapidly with the number of interaction steps. Moreover, it introduces an unknown-tools challenge, as LLM agents often lack familiarity with the precise usage of the MCP servers. Notably, enterprise-level agents like Cursor cannot achieve better performance than standard ReAct frameworks. Beyond evaluation, we open-source our extensible evaluation framework with UI support, enabling researchers and practitioners to seamlessly integrate new agents and MCP servers while fostering innovation in the rapidly evolving MCP ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14704</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 13:28:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tinker: Diffusion's Gift to 3D--Multi-View Consistent Editing From   Sparse Inputs without Per-Scene Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14811</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14811.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Canyu Zhao, Xiaoman Li, Tianjian Feng, Zhiyue Zhao, Hao Chen, Chunhua Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Tinker, a versatile framework for high-fidelity 3D editing that operates in both one-shot and few-shot regimes without any per-scene finetuning. Unlike prior techniques that demand extensive per-scene optimization to ensure multi-view consistency or to produce dozens of consistent edited input views, Tinker delivers robust, multi-view consistent edits from as few as one or two images. This capability stems from repurposing pretrained diffusion models, which unlocks their latent 3D awareness. To drive research in this space, we curate the first large-scale multi-view editing dataset and data pipeline, spanning diverse scenes and styles. Building on this dataset, we develop our framework capable of generating multi-view consistent edited views without per-scene training, which consists of two novel components: (1) Referring multi-view editor: Enables precise, reference-driven edits that remain coherent across all viewpoints. (2) Any-view-to-video synthesizer: Leverages spatial-temporal priors from video diffusion to perform high-quality scene completion and novel-view generation even from sparse inputs. Through extensive experiments, Tinker significantly reduces the barrier to generalizable 3D content creation, achieving state-of-the-art performance on editing, novel-view synthesis, and rendering enhancement tasks. We believe that Tinker represents a key step towards truly scalable, zero-shot 3D editing. Project webpage: https://aim-uofa.github.io/Tinker&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14811</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 16:02:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MeshCoder: LLM-Powered Structured Mesh Code Generation from Point Clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14879</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14879.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bingquan Dai, Li Ray Luo, Qihong Tang, Jie Wang, Xinyu Lian, Hao Xu, Minghan Qin, Xudong Xu, Bo Dai, Haoqian Wang, Zhaoyang Lyu, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reconstructing 3D objects into editable programs is pivotal for applications like reverse engineering and shape editing. However, existing methods often rely on limited domain-specific languages (DSLs) and small-scale datasets, restricting their ability to model complex geometries and structures. To address these challenges, we introduce MeshCoder, a novel framework that reconstructs complex 3D objects from point clouds into editable Blender Python scripts. We develop a comprehensive set of expressive Blender Python APIs capable of synthesizing intricate geometries. Leveraging these APIs, we construct a large-scale paired object-code dataset, where the code for each object is decomposed into distinct semantic parts. Subsequently, we train a multimodal large language model (LLM) that translates 3D point cloud into executable Blender Python scripts. Our approach not only achieves superior performance in shape-to-code reconstruction tasks but also facilitates intuitive geometric and topological editing through convenient code modifications. Furthermore, our code-based representation enhances the reasoning capabilities of LLMs in 3D shape understanding tasks. Together, these contributions establish MeshCoder as a powerful and flexible solution for programmatic 3D shape reconstruction and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14879</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 17:50:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pixie: Fast and Generalizable Supervised Learning of 3D Physics from   Pixels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17437</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.17437.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Long Le, Ryan Lucas, Chen Wang, Chuhao Chen, Dinesh Jayaraman, Eric Eaton, Lingjie Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Inferring the physical properties of 3D scenes from visual information is a critical yet challenging task for creating interactive and realistic virtual worlds. While humans intuitively grasp material characteristics such as elasticity or stiffness, existing methods often rely on slow, per-scene optimization, limiting their generalizability and application. To address this problem, we introduce PIXIE, a novel method that trains a generalizable neural network to predict physical properties across multiple scenes from 3D visual features purely using supervised losses. Once trained, our feed-forward network can perform fast inference of plausible material fields, which coupled with a learned static scene representation like Gaussian Splatting enables realistic physics simulation under external forces. To facilitate this research, we also collected PIXIEVERSE, one of the largest known datasets of paired 3D assets and physic material annotations. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that PIXIE is about 1.46-4.39x better and orders of magnitude faster than test-time optimization methods. By leveraging pretrained visual features like CLIP, our method can also zero-shot generalize to real-world scenes despite only ever been trained on synthetic data. https://pixie-3d.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17437</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 19:24:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mobile-Agent-v3: Foundamental Agents for GUI Automation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15144</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15144.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiabo Ye, Xi Zhang, Haiyang Xu, Haowei Liu, Junyang Wang, Zhaoqing Zhu, Ziwei Zheng, Feiyu Gao, Junjie Cao, Zhengxi Lu, Jitong Liao, Qi Zheng, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces GUI-Owl, a foundational GUI agent model that achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-source end-to-end models on ten GUI benchmarks across desktop and mobile environments, covering grounding, question answering, planning, decision-making, and procedural knowledge. GUI-Owl-7B achieves 66.4 on AndroidWorld and 29.4 on OSWorld. Building on this, we propose Mobile-Agent-v3, a general-purpose GUI agent framework that further improves performance to 73.3 on AndroidWorld and 37.7 on OSWorld, setting a new state-of-the-art for open-source GUI agent frameworks. GUI-Owl incorporates three key innovations: (1) Large-scale Environment Infrastructure: a cloud-based virtual environment spanning Android, Ubuntu, macOS, and Windows, enabling our Self-Evolving GUI Trajectory Production framework. This generates high-quality interaction data via automated query generation and correctness validation, leveraging GUI-Owl to refine trajectories iteratively, forming a self-improving loop. It supports diverse data pipelines and reduces manual annotation. (2) Diverse Foundational Agent Capabilities: by integrating UI grounding, planning, action semantics, and reasoning patterns, GUI-Owl supports end-to-end decision-making and can act as a modular component in multi-agent systems. (3) Scalable Environment RL: we develop a scalable reinforcement learning framework with fully asynchronous training for real-world alignment. We also introduce Trajectory-aware Relative Policy Optimization (TRPO) for online RL, achieving 34.9 on OSWorld. GUI-Owl and Mobile-Agent-v3 are open-sourced at https://github.com/X-PLUG/MobileAgent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15144</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:39:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Think with Confidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15260</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15260.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yichao Fu, Xuewei Wang, Yuandong Tian, Jiawei Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 78&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown great potential in reasoning tasks through test-time scaling methods like self-consistency with majority voting. However, this approach often leads to diminishing returns in accuracy and high computational overhead. To address these challenges, we introduce Deep Think with Confidence (DeepConf), a simple yet powerful method that enhances both reasoning efficiency and performance at test time. DeepConf leverages model-internal confidence signals to dynamically filter out low-quality reasoning traces during or after generation. It requires no additional model training or hyperparameter tuning and can be seamlessly integrated into existing serving frameworks. We evaluate DeepConf across a variety of reasoning tasks and the latest open-source models, including Qwen 3 and GPT-OSS series. Notably, on challenging benchmarks such as AIME 2025, DeepConf@512 achieves up to 99.9% accuracy and reduces generated tokens by up to 84.7% compared to full parallel thinking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15260</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 05:48:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Transcription: Mechanistic Interpretability in ASR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15882</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15882.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Neta Glazer, Yael Segal-Feldman, Hilit Segev, Aviv Shamsian, Asaf Buchnick, Gill Hetz, Ethan Fetaya, Joseph Keshet, Aviv Navon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Interpretability methods have recently gained significant attention, particularly in the context of large language models, enabling insights into linguistic representations, error detection, and model behaviors such as hallucinations and repetitions. However, these techniques remain underexplored in automatic speech recognition (ASR), despite their potential to advance both the performance and interpretability of ASR systems. In this work, we adapt and systematically apply established interpretability methods such as logit lens, linear probing, and activation patching, to examine how acoustic and semantic information evolves across layers in ASR systems. Our experiments reveal previously unknown internal dynamics, including specific encoder-decoder interactions responsible for repetition hallucinations and semantic biases encoded deep within acoustic representations. These insights demonstrate the benefits of extending and applying interpretability techniques to speech recognition, opening promising directions for future research on improving model transparency and robustness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15882</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 15:42:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiveMCP-101: Stress Testing and Diagnosing MCP-enabled Agents on   Challenging Queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15760</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15760.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Yin, Dinghan Shen, Silei Xu, Jianbing Han, Sixun Dong, Mian Zhang, Yebowen Hu, Shujian Liu, Simin Ma, Song Wang, Sathish Reddy Indurthi, Xun Wang, Yiran Chen, Kaiqiang Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Tool calling has emerged as a critical capability for AI agents to interact with the real world and solve complex tasks. While the Model Context Protocol (MCP) provides a powerful standardized framework for tool integration, there is a significant gap in benchmarking how well AI agents can effectively solve multi-step tasks using diverse MCP tools in realistic, dynamic scenarios. In this work, we present LiveMCP-101, a benchmark of 101 carefully curated real-world queries, refined through iterative LLM rewriting and manual review, that require coordinated use of multiple MCP tools including web search, file operations, mathematical reasoning, and data analysis. Moreover, we introduce a novel evaluation approach that leverages ground-truth execution plans rather than raw API outputs, better reflecting the evolving nature of real-world environments. Experiments show that even frontier LLMs achieve a success rate below 60\%, highlighting major challenges in tool orchestration. Detailed ablations and error analysis further reveal distinct failure modes and inefficiencies in token usage, pointing to concrete directions for advancing current models. LiveMCP-101 sets a rigorous standard for evaluating real-world agent capabilities, advancing toward autonomous AI systems that reliably execute complex tasks through tool use.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15760</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:55:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Waver: Wave Your Way to Lifelike Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15761</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15761.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifu Zhang, Hao Yang, Yuqi Zhang, Yifei Hu, Fengda Zhu, Chuang Lin, Xiaofeng Mei, Yi Jiang, Zehuan Yuan, Bingyue Peng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Waver, a high-performance foundation model for unified image and video generation. Waver can directly generate videos with durations ranging from 5 to 10 seconds at a native resolution of 720p, which are subsequently upscaled to 1080p. The model simultaneously supports text-to-video (T2V), image-to-video (I2V), and text-to-image (T2I) generation within a single, integrated framework. We introduce a Hybrid Stream DiT architecture to enhance modality alignment and accelerate training convergence. To ensure training data quality, we establish a comprehensive data curation pipeline and manually annotate and train an MLLM-based video quality model to filter for the highest-quality samples. Furthermore, we provide detailed training and inference recipes to facilitate the generation of high-quality videos. Building on these contributions, Waver excels at capturing complex motion, achieving superior motion amplitude and temporal consistency in video synthesis. Notably, it ranks among the Top 3 on both the T2V and I2V leaderboards at Artificial Analysis (data as of 2025-07-30 10:00 GMT+8), consistently outperforming existing open-source models and matching or surpassing state-of-the-art commercial solutions. We hope this technical report will help the community more efficiently train high-quality video generation models and accelerate progress in video generation technologies. Official page: https://github.com/FoundationVision/Waver.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15761</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:56:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intern-S1: A Scientific Multimodal Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15763</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.15763.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lei Bai, Zhongrui Cai, Maosong Cao, Weihan Cao, Chiyu Chen, Haojiong Chen, Kai Chen, Pengcheng Chen, Ying Chen, Yongkang Chen, Yu Cheng, Yu Cheng, Pei Chu, Tao Chu, Erfei Cui, Ganqu Cui, Long Cui, Ziyun Cui, Nianchen Deng, Ning Ding, Nanqin Dong, Peijie Dong, Shihan Dou, Sinan Du, Haodong Duan, Caihua Fan, Ben Gao, Changjiang Gao, Jianfei Gao, Songyang Gao, Yang Gao, Zhangwei Gao, Jiaye Ge, Qiming Ge, Lixin Gu, Yuzhe Gu, Aijia Guo, Qipeng Guo, Xu Guo, Conghui He, Junjun He, Yili Hong, Siyuan Hou, Caiyu Hu, Hanglei Hu, Jucheng Hu, Ming Hu, Zhouqi Hua, Haian Huang, Junhao Huang, Xu Huang, Zixian Huang, Zhe Jiang, Lingkai Kong, Linyang Li, Peiji Li, Pengze Li, Shuaibin Li, Tianbin Li, Wei Li, Yuqiang Li, Dahua Lin, Junyao Lin, Tianyi Lin, Zhishan Lin, Hongwei Liu, Jiangning Liu, Jiyao Liu, Junnan Liu, Kai Liu, Kaiwen Liu, Kuikun Liu, Shichun Liu, Shudong Liu, Wei Liu, Xinyao Liu, Yuhong Liu, Zhan Liu, Yinquan Lu, Haijun Lv, Hongxia Lv, Huijie Lv, Qidang Lv, Ying Lv, Chengqi Lyu, Chenglong Ma, Jianpeng Ma, Ren Ma, Runmin Ma, Runyuan Ma, Xinzhu Ma, Yichuan Ma, Zihan Ma, Sixuan Mi, Junzhi Ning, Wenchang Ning, Xinle Pang, Jiahui Peng, Runyu Peng, Yu Qiao, Jiantao Qiu, Xiaoye Qu, Yuan Qu, Yuchen Ren, Fukai Shang, Wenqi Shao, Junhao Shen, Shuaike Shen, Chunfeng Song, Demin Song, Diping Song, Chenlin Su, Weijie Su, Weigao Sun, Yu Sun, Qian Tan, Cheng Tang, Huanze Tang, Kexian Tang, Shixiang Tang, Jian Tong, Aoran Wang, Bin Wang, Dong Wang, Lintao Wang, Rui Wang, Weiyun Wang, Wenhai Wang, Yi Wang, Ziyi Wang, Ling-I Wu, Wen Wu, Yue Wu, Zijian Wu, Linchen Xiao, Shuhao Xing, Chao Xu, Huihui Xu, Jun Xu, Ruiliang Xu, Wanghan Xu, GanLin Yang, Yuming Yang, Haochen Ye, Jin Ye, Shenglong Ye, Jia Yu, Jiashuo Yu, Jing Yu, Fei Yuan, Bo Zhang, Chao Zhang, Chen Zhang, Hongjie Zhang, Jin Zhang, Qiaosheng Zhang, Qiuyinzhe Zhang, Songyang Zhang, Taolin Zhang, Wenlong Zhang, Wenwei Zhang, Yechen Zhang, Ziyang Zhang, Haiteng Zhao, Qian Zhao, Xiangyu Zhao, Xiangyu Zhao, Bowen Zhou, Dongzhan Zhou, Peiheng Zhou, Yuhao Zhou, Yunhua Zhou, Dongsheng Zhu, Lin Zhu, Yicheng Zou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 242&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In recent years, a plethora of open-source foundation models have emerged, achieving remarkable progress in some widely attended fields, with performance being quite close to that of closed-source models. However, in high-value but more challenging scientific professional fields, either the fields still rely on expert models, or the progress of general foundation models lags significantly compared to those in popular areas, far from sufficient for transforming scientific research and leaving substantial gap between open-source models and closed-source models in these scientific domains. To mitigate this gap and explore a step further toward Artificial General Intelligence (AGI), we introduce Intern-S1, a specialized generalist equipped with general understanding and reasoning capabilities with expertise to analyze multiple science modal data. Intern-S1 is a multimodal Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) model with 28 billion activated parameters and 241 billion total parameters, continually pre-trained on 5T tokens, including over 2.5T tokens from scientific domains. In the post-training stage, Intern-S1 undergoes offline and then online reinforcement learning (RL) in InternBootCamp, where we propose Mixture-of-Rewards (MoR) to synergize the RL training on more than 1000 tasks simultaneously. Through integrated innovations in algorithms, data, and training systems, Intern-S1 achieved top-tier performance in online RL training.On comprehensive evaluation benchmarks, Intern-S1 demonstrates competitive performance on general reasoning tasks among open-source models and significantly outperforms open-source models in scientific domains, surpassing closed-source state-of-the-art models in professional tasks, such as molecular synthesis planning, reaction condition prediction, predicting thermodynamic stabilities for crystals. Our models are available at https://huggingface.co/internlm/Intern-S1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15763</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 17:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AgentFly: Fine-tuning LLM Agents without Fine-tuning LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16153</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.16153.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huichi Zhou, Yihang Chen, Siyuan Guo, Xue Yan, Kin Hei Lee, Zihan Wang, Ka Yiu Lee, Guchun Zhang, Kun Shao, Linyi Yang, Jun Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 115&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce a novel learning paradigm for adaptive Large Language Model (LLM) agents that eliminates the need for fine-tuning the underlying LLMs. Existing approaches are often either rigid, relying on static, handcrafted reflection workflows, or computationally intensive, requiring gradient updates of LLM model parameters. In contrast, our method enables low-cost continual adaptation via memory-based online reinforcement learning. We formalise this as a Memory-augmented Markov Decision Process (M-MDP), equipped with a neural case-selection policy to guide action decisions. Past experiences are stored in an episodic memory, either differentiable or non-parametric. The policy is continually updated based on environmental feedback through a memory rewriting mechanism, whereas policy improvement is achieved through efficient memory reading (retrieval). We instantiate our agent model in the deep research setting, namely AgentFly, which attains top-1 on GAIA validation (87.88% Pass@3) and 79.40% on the test set. It reaches 66.6% F1 and 80.4% PM on the DeepResearcher dataset, outperforming the state-of-the-art training-based method, while case-based memory adds 4.7% to 9.6% absolute points on out-of-distribution tasks. Our approach offers a scalable and efficient pathway for developing generalist LLM agents capable of continuous, real-time learning without gradient updates, advancing machine learning towards open-ended skill acquisition and deep research scenarios. The code is available at https://github.com/Agent-on-the-Fly/AgentFly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16153</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 07:25:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MV-RAG: Retrieval Augmented Multiview Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16577</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.16577.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yosef Dayani, Omer Benishu, Sagie Benaim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-3D generation approaches have advanced significantly by leveraging pretrained 2D diffusion priors, producing high-quality and 3D-consistent outputs. However, they often fail to produce out-of-domain (OOD) or rare concepts, yielding inconsistent or inaccurate results. To this end, we propose MV-RAG, a novel text-to-3D pipeline that first retrieves relevant 2D images from a large in-the-wild 2D database and then conditions a multiview diffusion model on these images to synthesize consistent and accurate multiview outputs. Training such a retrieval-conditioned model is achieved via a novel hybrid strategy bridging structured multiview data and diverse 2D image collections. This involves training on multiview data using augmented conditioning views that simulate retrieval variance for view-specific reconstruction, alongside training on sets of retrieved real-world 2D images using a distinctive held-out view prediction objective: the model predicts the held-out view from the other views to infer 3D consistency from 2D data. To facilitate a rigorous OOD evaluation, we introduce a new collection of challenging OOD prompts. Experiments against state-of-the-art text-to-3D, image-to-3D, and personalization baselines show that our approach significantly improves 3D consistency, photorealism, and text adherence for OOD/rare concepts, while maintaining competitive performance on standard benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16577</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 17:59:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TreePO: Bridging the Gap of Policy Optimization and Efficacy and   Inference Efficiency with Heuristic Tree-based Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17445</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.17445.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yizhi Li, Qingshui Gu, Zhoufutu Wen, Ziniu Li, Tianshun Xing, Shuyue Guo, Tianyu Zheng, Xin Zhou, Xingwei Qu, Wangchunshu Zhou, Zheng Zhang, Wei Shen, Qian Liu, Chenghua Lin, Jian Yang, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in aligning large language models via reinforcement learning have achieved remarkable gains in solving complex reasoning problems, but at the cost of expensive on-policy rollouts and limited exploration of diverse reasoning paths. In this work, we introduce TreePO, involving a self-guided rollout algorithm that views sequence generation as a tree-structured searching process. Composed of dynamic tree sampling policy and fixed-length segment decoding, TreePO leverages local uncertainty to warrant additional branches. By amortizing computation across common prefixes and pruning low-value paths early, TreePO essentially reduces the per-update compute burden while preserving or enhancing exploration diversity. Key contributions include: (1) a segment-wise sampling algorithm that alleviates the KV cache burden through contiguous segments and spawns new branches along with an early-stop mechanism; (2) a tree-based segment-level advantage estimation that considers both global and local proximal policy optimization. and (3) analysis on the effectiveness of probability and quality-driven dynamic divergence and fallback strategy. We empirically validate the performance gain of TreePO on a set reasoning benchmarks and the efficiency saving of GPU hours from 22\% up to 43\% of the sampling design for the trained models, meanwhile showing up to 40\% reduction at trajectory-level and 35\% at token-level sampling compute for the existing models. While offering a free lunch of inference efficiency, TreePO reveals a practical path toward scaling RL-based post-training with fewer samples and less compute. Home page locates at https://m-a-p.ai/TreePO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.17445</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 16:52:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual-CoG: Stage-Aware Reinforcement Learning with Chain of Guidance   for Text-to-Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18032</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.18032.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yaqi Li, Peng Chen, Mingyang Han, Bu Pi, Haoxiang Shi, Runzhou Zhao, Yang Yao, Xuan Zhang, Jun Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the promising progress of recent autoregressive models in text-to-image (T2I) generation, their ability to handle multi-attribute and ambiguous prompts remains limited. To address these limitations, existing works have applied chain-of-thought (CoT) to enable stage-aware visual synthesis and employed reinforcement learning (RL) to improve reasoning capabilities. However, most models provide reward signals only at the end of the generation stage. This monolithic final-only guidance makes it difficult to identify which stages contribute positively to the final outcome and may lead to suboptimal policies. To tackle this issue, we propose a Visual-Chain of Guidance (Visual-CoG) paradigm consisting of three stages: semantic reasoning, process refining, and outcome evaluation, with stage-aware rewards providing immediate guidance throughout the image generation pipeline. We further construct a visual cognition benchmark, VisCog-Bench, which comprises four subtasks to evaluate the effectiveness of semantic reasoning. Comprehensive evaluations on GenEval, T2I-CompBench, and the proposed VisCog-Bench show improvements of 15%, 5%, and 19%, respectively, demonstrating the superior performance of the proposed Visual-CoG. We will release all the resources soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18032</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 13:53:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CMPhysBench: A Benchmark for Evaluating Large Language Models in   Condensed Matter Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18124</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.18124.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weida Wang, Dongchen Huang, Jiatong Li, Tengchao Yang, Ziyang Zheng, Di Zhang, Dong Han, Benteng Chen, Binzhao Luo, Zhiyu Liu, Kunling Liu, Zhiyuan Gao, Shiqi Geng, Wei Ma, Jiaming Su, Xin Li, Shuchen Pu, Yuhan Shui, Qianjia Cheng, Zhihao Dou, Dongfei Cui, Changyong He, Jin Zeng, Zeke Xie, Mao Su, Dongzhan Zhou, Yuqiang Li, Wanli Ouyang, Yunqi Cai, Xi Dai, Shufei Zhang, Lei Bai, Jinguang Cheng, Zhong Fang, Hongming Weng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce CMPhysBench, designed to assess the proficiency of Large Language Models (LLMs) in Condensed Matter Physics, as a novel Benchmark. CMPhysBench is composed of more than 520 graduate-level meticulously curated questions covering both representative subfields and foundational theoretical frameworks of condensed matter physics, such as magnetism, superconductivity, strongly correlated systems, etc. To ensure a deep understanding of the problem-solving process,we focus exclusively on calculation problems, requiring LLMs to independently generate comprehensive solutions. Meanwhile, leveraging tree-based representations of expressions, we introduce the Scalable Expression Edit Distance (SEED) score, which provides fine-grained (non-binary) partial credit and yields a more accurate assessment of similarity between prediction and ground-truth. Our results show that even the best models, Grok-4, reach only 36 average SEED score and 28% accuracy on CMPhysBench, underscoring a significant capability gap, especially for this practical and frontier domain relative to traditional physics. The code anddataset are publicly available at https://github.com/CMPhysBench/CMPhysBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18124</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 15:32:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InternVL3.5: Advancing Open-Source Multimodal Models in Versatility,   Reasoning, and Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18265</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.18265.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weiyun Wang, Zhangwei Gao, Lixin Gu, Hengjun Pu, Long Cui, Xingguang Wei, Zhaoyang Liu, Linglin Jing, Shenglong Ye, Jie Shao, Zhaokai Wang, Zhe Chen, Hongjie Zhang, Ganlin Yang, Haomin Wang, Qi Wei, Jinhui Yin, Wenhao Li, Erfei Cui, Guanzhou Chen, Zichen Ding, Changyao Tian, Zhenyu Wu, Jingjing Xie, Zehao Li, Bowen Yang, Yuchen Duan, Xuehui Wang, Songze Li, Xiangyu Zhao, Haodong Duan, Nianchen Deng, Bin Fu, Yinan He, Yi Wang, Conghui He, Botian Shi, Junjun He, Yingtong Xiong, Han Lv, Lijun Wu, Wenqi Shao, Kaipeng Zhang, Huipeng Deng, Biqing Qi, Jiaye Ge, Qipeng Guo, Wenwei Zhang, Wanli Ouyang, Limin Wang, Min Dou, Xizhou Zhu, Tong Lu, Dahua Lin, Jifeng Dai, Bowen Zhou, Weijie Su, Kai Chen, Yu Qiao, Wenhai Wang, Gen Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 165&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce InternVL 3.5, a new family of open-source multimodal models that significantly advances versatility, reasoning capability, and inference efficiency along the InternVL series. A key innovation is the Cascade Reinforcement Learning (Cascade RL) framework, which enhances reasoning through a two-stage process: offline RL for stable convergence and online RL for refined alignment. This coarse-to-fine training strategy leads to substantial improvements on downstream reasoning tasks, e.g., MMMU and MathVista. To optimize efficiency, we propose a Visual Resolution Router (ViR) that dynamically adjusts the resolution of visual tokens without compromising performance. Coupled with ViR, our Decoupled Vision-Language Deployment (DvD) strategy separates the vision encoder and language model across different GPUs, effectively balancing computational load. These contributions collectively enable InternVL3.5 to achieve up to a +16.0\% gain in overall reasoning performance and a 4.05times inference speedup compared to its predecessor, i.e., InternVL3. In addition, InternVL3.5 supports novel capabilities such as GUI interaction and embodied agency. Notably, our largest model, i.e., InternVL3.5-241B-A28B, attains state-of-the-art results among open-source MLLMs across general multimodal, reasoning, text, and agentic tasks -- narrowing the performance gap with leading commercial models like GPT-5. All models and code are publicly released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18265</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 17:58:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UltraMemV2: Memory Networks Scaling to 120B Parameters with Superior   Long-Context Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18756</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.18756.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihao Huang, Yu Bao, Qiyang Min, Siyan Chen, Ran Guo, Hongzhi Huang, Defa Zhu, Yutao Zeng, Banggu Wu, Xun Zhou, Siyuan Qiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Mixture of Experts (MoE) models achieve remarkable efficiency by activating only subsets of parameters, they suffer from high memory access costs during inference. Memory-layer architectures offer an appealing alternative with very few memory access, but previous attempts like UltraMem have only matched the performance of 2-expert MoE models, falling significantly short of state-of-the-art 8-expert configurations. We present UltraMemV2, a redesigned memory-layer architecture that closes this performance gap. Our approach introduces five key improvements: integrating memory layers into every transformer block, simplifying value expansion with single linear projections, adopting FFN-based value processing from PEER, implementing principled parameter initialization, and rebalancing memory-to-FFN computation ratios. Through extensive evaluation, we demonstrate that UltraMemV2 achieves performance parity with 8-expert MoE models under same computation and parameters but significantly low memory access. Notably, UltraMemV2 shows superior performance on memory-intensive tasks, with improvements of +1.6 points on long-context memorization, +6.2 points on multi-round memorization, and +7.9 points on in-context learning. We validate our approach at scale with models up to 2.5B activated parameters from 120B total parameters, and establish that activation density has greater impact on performance than total sparse parameter count. Our work brings memory-layer architectures to performance parity with state-of-the-art MoE models, presenting a compelling alternative for efficient sparse computation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18756</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 07:33:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>USO: Unified Style and Subject-Driven Generation via Disentangled and   Reward Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18966</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.18966.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaojin Wu, Mengqi Huang, Yufeng Cheng, Wenxu Wu, Jiahe Tian, Yiming Luo, Fei Ding, Qian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing literature typically treats style-driven and subject-driven generation as two disjoint tasks: the former prioritizes stylistic similarity, whereas the latter insists on subject consistency, resulting in an apparent antagonism. We argue that both objectives can be unified under a single framework because they ultimately concern the disentanglement and re-composition of content and style, a long-standing theme in style-driven research. To this end, we present USO, a Unified Style-Subject Optimized customization model. First, we construct a large-scale triplet dataset consisting of content images, style images, and their corresponding stylized content images. Second, we introduce a disentangled learning scheme that simultaneously aligns style features and disentangles content from style through two complementary objectives, style-alignment training and content-style disentanglement training. Third, we incorporate a style reward-learning paradigm denoted as SRL to further enhance the model's performance. Finally, we release USO-Bench, the first benchmark that jointly evaluates style similarity and subject fidelity across multiple metrics. Extensive experiments demonstrate that USO achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-source models along both dimensions of subject consistency and style similarity. Code and model: https://github.com/bytedance/USO&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18966</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 12:10:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VibeVoice Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19205</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.19205.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiliang Peng, Jianwei Yu, Wenhui Wang, Yaoyao Chang, Yutao Sun, Li Dong, Yi Zhu, Weijiang Xu, Hangbo Bao, Zehua Wang, Shaohan Huang, Yan Xia, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 102&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This report presents VibeVoice, a novel model designed to synthesize long-form speech with multiple speakers by employing next-token diffusion, which is a unified method for modeling continuous data by autoregressively generating latent vectors via diffusion. To enable this, we introduce a novel continuous speech tokenizer that, when compared to the popular Encodec model, improves data compression by 80 times while maintaining comparable performance. The tokenizer effectively preserves audio fidelity while significantly boosting computational efficiency for processing long sequences. Thus, VibeVoice can synthesize long-form speech for up to 90 minutes (in a 64K context window length) with a maximum of 4 speakers, capturing the authentic conversational ``vibe'' and surpassing open-source and proprietary dialogue models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19205</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 17:09:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniHuman-1.5: Instilling an Active Mind in Avatars via Cognitive   Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19209</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.19209.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianwen Jiang, Weihong Zeng, Zerong Zheng, Jiaqi Yang, Chao Liang, Wang Liao, Han Liang, Yuan Zhang, Mingyuan Gao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing video avatar models can produce fluid human animations, yet they struggle to move beyond mere physical likeness to capture a character's authentic essence. Their motions typically synchronize with low-level cues like audio rhythm, lacking a deeper semantic understanding of emotion, intent, or context. To bridge this gap, we propose a framework designed to generate character animations that are not only physically plausible but also semantically coherent and expressive. Our model, OmniHuman-1.5, is built upon two key technical contributions. First, we leverage Multimodal Large Language Models to synthesize a structured textual representation of conditions that provides high-level semantic guidance. This guidance steers our motion generator beyond simplistic rhythmic synchronization, enabling the production of actions that are contextually and emotionally resonant. Second, to ensure the effective fusion of these multimodal inputs and mitigate inter-modality conflicts, we introduce a specialized Multimodal DiT architecture with a novel Pseudo Last Frame design. The synergy of these components allows our model to accurately interpret the joint semantics of audio, images, and text, thereby generating motions that are deeply coherent with the character, scene, and linguistic content. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our model achieves leading performance across a comprehensive set of metrics, including lip-sync accuracy, video quality, motion naturalness and semantic consistency with textual prompts. Furthermore, our approach shows remarkable extensibility to complex scenarios, such as those involving multi-person and non-human subjects. Homepage: https://omnihuman-lab.github.io/v1_5/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19209</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 17:15:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VoxHammer: Training-Free Precise and Coherent 3D Editing in Native 3D   Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19247</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.19247.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lin Li, Zehuan Huang, Haoran Feng, Gengxiong Zhuang, Rui Chen, Chunchao Guo, Lu Sheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D local editing of specified regions is crucial for game industry and robot interaction. Recent methods typically edit rendered multi-view images and then reconstruct 3D models, but they face challenges in precisely preserving unedited regions and overall coherence. Inspired by structured 3D generative models, we propose VoxHammer, a novel training-free approach that performs precise and coherent editing in 3D latent space. Given a 3D model, VoxHammer first predicts its inversion trajectory and obtains its inverted latents and key-value tokens at each timestep. Subsequently, in the denoising and editing phase, we replace the denoising features of preserved regions with the corresponding inverted latents and cached key-value tokens. By retaining these contextual features, this approach ensures consistent reconstruction of preserved areas and coherent integration of edited parts. To evaluate the consistency of preserved regions, we constructed Edit3D-Bench, a human-annotated dataset comprising hundreds of samples, each with carefully labeled 3D editing regions. Experiments demonstrate that VoxHammer significantly outperforms existing methods in terms of both 3D consistency of preserved regions and overall quality. Our method holds promise for synthesizing high-quality edited paired data, thereby laying the data foundation for in-context 3D generation. See our project page at https://huanngzh.github.io/VoxHammer-Page/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19247</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 17:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Rewarding Vision-Language Model via Reasoning Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19652</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.19652.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zongxia Li, Wenhao Yu, Chengsong Huang, Rui Liu, Zhenwen Liang, Fuxiao Liu, Jingxi Che, Dian Yu, Jordan Boyd-Graber, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 77&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language Models (VLMs) often suffer from visual hallucinations, saying things that are not actually in the image, and language shortcuts, where they skip the visual part and just rely on text priors. These issues arise because most post-training methods for VLMs rely on simple verifiable answer matching and supervise only final outputs, leaving intermediate visual reasoning without explicit guidance. As a result, VLMs receive sparse visual signals and often learn to prioritize language-based reasoning over visual perception. To mitigate this, some existing methods add visual supervision using human annotations or distilled labels from external large models. However, human annotations are labor-intensive and costly, and because external signals cannot adapt to the evolving policy, they cause distributional shifts that can lead to reward hacking. In this paper, we introduce Vision-SR1, a self-rewarding method that improves visual reasoning without relying on external visual supervisions via reinforcement learning. Vision-SR1 decomposes VLM reasoning into two stages: visual perception and language reasoning. The model is first prompted to produce self-contained visual perceptions that are sufficient to answer the question without referring back the input image. To validate this self-containment, the same VLM model is then re-prompted to perform language reasoning using only the generated perception as input to compute reward. This self-reward is combined with supervision on final outputs, providing a balanced training signal that strengthens both visual perception and language reasoning. Our experiments demonstrate that Vision-SR1 improves visual reasoning, mitigates visual hallucinations, and reduces reliance on language shortcuts across diverse vision-language tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19652</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 08:01:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CODA: Coordinating the Cerebrum and Cerebellum for a Dual-Brain Computer   Use Agent with Decoupled Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20096</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20096.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeyi Sun, Yuhang Cao, Jianze Liang, Qiushi Sun, Ziyu Liu, Zhixiong Zhang, Yuhang Zang, Xiaoyi Dong, Kai Chen, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autonomous agents for Graphical User Interfaces (GUIs) face significant challenges in specialized domains such as scientific computing, where both long-horizon planning and precise execution are required. Existing approaches suffer from a trade-off: generalist agents excel at planning but perform poorly in execution, while specialized agents demonstrate the opposite weakness. Recent compositional frameworks attempt to bridge this gap by combining a planner and an actor, but they are typically static and non-trainable, which prevents adaptation from experience. This is a critical limitation given the scarcity of high-quality data in scientific domains. To address these limitations, we introduce CODA, a novel and trainable compositional framework that integrates a generalist planner (Cerebrum) with a specialist executor (Cerebellum), trained via a dedicated two-stage pipeline. In the first stage, Specialization, we apply a decoupled GRPO approach to train an expert planner for each scientific application individually, bootstrapping from a small set of task trajectories. In the second stage, Generalization, we aggregate all successful trajectories from the specialized experts to build a consolidated dataset, which is then used for supervised fine-tuning of the final planner. This equips CODA with both robust execution and cross-domain generalization. Evaluated on four challenging applications from the ScienceBoard benchmark, CODA significantly outperforms baselines and establishes a new state of the art among open-source models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20096</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 17:59:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MCP-Bench: Benchmarking Tool-Using LLM Agents with Complex Real-World   Tasks via MCP Servers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20453</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20453.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenting Wang, Qi Chang, Hemani Patel, Shashank Biju, Cheng-En Wu, Quan Liu, Aolin Ding, Alireza Rezazadeh, Ankit Shah, Yujia Bao, Eugene Siow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce MCP-Bench, a benchmark for evaluating large language models (LLMs) on realistic, multi-step tasks that demand tool use, cross-tool coordination, precise parameter control, and planning/reasoning for solving tasks. Built on the Model Context Protocol (MCP), MCP-Bench connects LLMs to 28 representative live MCP servers spanning 250 tools across domains such as finance, traveling, scientific computing, and academic search. Unlike prior API-based benchmarks, each MCP server provides a set of complementary tools designed to work together, enabling the construction of authentic, multi-step tasks with rich input-output coupling. Tasks in MCP-Bench test agents' ability to retrieve relevant tools from fuzzy instructions without explicit tool names, plan multi-hop execution trajectories for complex objectives, ground responses in intermediate tool outputs, and orchestrate cross-domain workflows - capabilities not adequately evaluated by existing benchmarks that rely on explicit tool specifications, shallow few-step workflows, and isolated domain operations. We propose a multi-faceted evaluation framework covering tool-level schema understanding and usage, trajectory-level planning, and task completion. Experiments on 20 advanced LLMs reveal persistent challenges in MCP-Bench. Code and data: https://github.com/Accenture/mcp-bench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20453</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 05:58:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>rStar2-Agent: Agentic Reasoning Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20722</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20722.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ning Shang, Yifei Liu, Yi Zhu, Li Lyna Zhang, Weijiang Xu, Xinyu Guan, Buze Zhang, Bingcheng Dong, Xudong Zhou, Bowen Zhang, Ying Xin, Ziming Miao, Scarlett Li, Fan Yang, Mao Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 67&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce rStar2-Agent, a 14B math reasoning model trained with agentic reinforcement learning to achieve frontier-level performance. Beyond current long CoT, the model demonstrates advanced cognitive behaviors, such as thinking carefully before using Python coding tools and reflecting on code execution feedback to autonomously explore, verify, and refine intermediate steps in complex problem-solving. This capability is enabled through three key innovations that makes agentic RL effective at scale: (i) an efficient RL infrastructure with a reliable Python code environment that supports high-throughput execution and mitigates the high rollout costs, enabling training on limited GPU resources (64 MI300X GPUs); (ii) GRPO-RoC, an agentic RL algorithm with a Resample-on-Correct rollout strategy that addresses the inherent environment noises from coding tools, allowing the model to reason more effectively in a code environment; (iii) An efficient agent training recipe that starts with non-reasoning SFT and progresses through multi-RL stages, yielding advanced cognitive abilities with minimal compute cost. To this end, rStar2-Agent boosts a pre-trained 14B model to state of the art in only 510 RL steps within one week, achieving average pass@1 scores of 80.6% on AIME24 and 69.8% on AIME25, surpassing DeepSeek-R1 (671B) with significantly shorter responses. Beyond mathematics, rStar2-Agent-14B also demonstrates strong generalization to alignment, scientific reasoning, and agentic tool-use tasks. Code and training recipes are available at https://github.com/microsoft/rStar.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20722</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 12:45:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pref-GRPO: Pairwise Preference Reward-based GRPO for Stable   Text-to-Image Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20751</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.20751.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yibin Wang, Zhimin Li, Yuhang Zang, Yujie Zhou, Jiazi Bu, Chunyu Wang, Qinglin Lu, Cheng Jin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements highlight the importance of GRPO-based reinforcement learning methods and benchmarking in enhancing text-to-image (T2I) generation. However, current methods using pointwise reward models (RM) for scoring generated images are susceptible to reward hacking. We reveal that this happens when minimal score differences between images are amplified after normalization, creating illusory advantages that drive the model to over-optimize for trivial gains, ultimately destabilizing the image generation process. To address this, we propose Pref-GRPO, a pairwise preference reward-based GRPO method that shifts the optimization objective from score maximization to preference fitting, ensuring more stable training. In Pref-GRPO, images are pairwise compared within each group using preference RM, and the win rate is used as the reward signal. Extensive experiments demonstrate that PREF-GRPO differentiates subtle image quality differences, providing more stable advantages and mitigating reward hacking. Additionally, existing T2I benchmarks are limited by coarse evaluation criteria, hindering comprehensive model assessment. To solve this, we introduce UniGenBench, a unified T2I benchmark comprising 600 prompts across 5 main themes and 20 subthemes. It evaluates semantic consistency through 10 primary and 27 sub-criteria, leveraging MLLM for benchmark construction and evaluation. Our benchmarks uncover the strengths and weaknesses of both open and closed-source T2I models and validate the effectiveness of Pref-GRPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20751</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 13:11:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
