<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:12:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>VIKI-R: Coordinating Embodied Multi-Agent Cooperation via Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09049</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.09049.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Li Kang, Xiufeng Song, Heng Zhou, Yiran Qin, Jie Yang, Xiaohong Liu, Philip Torr, Lei Bai, Zhenfei Yin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Coordinating multiple embodied agents in dynamic environments remains a core challenge in artificial intelligence, requiring both perception-driven reasoning and scalable cooperation strategies. While recent works have leveraged large language models (LLMs) for multi-agent planning, a few have begun to explore vision-language models (VLMs) for visual reasoning. However, these VLM-based approaches remain limited in their support for diverse embodiment types. In this work, we introduce VIKI-Bench, the first hierarchical benchmark tailored for embodied multi-agent cooperation, featuring three structured levels: agent activation, task planning, and trajectory perception. VIKI-Bench includes diverse robot embodiments, multi-view visual observations, and structured supervision signals to evaluate reasoning grounded in visual inputs. To demonstrate the utility of VIKI-Bench, we propose VIKI-R, a two-stage framework that fine-tunes a pretrained vision-language model (VLM) using Chain-of-Thought annotated demonstrations, followed by reinforcement learning under multi-level reward signals. Our extensive experiments show that VIKI-R significantly outperforms baselines method across all task levels. Furthermore, we show that reinforcement learning enables the emergence of compositional cooperation patterns among heterogeneous agents. Together, VIKI-Bench and VIKI-R offer a unified testbed and method for advancing multi-agent, visual-driven cooperation in embodied AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09049</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 17:59:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Intention to Execution: Probing the Generalization Boundaries of   Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09930</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.09930.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Irving Fang, Juexiao Zhang, Shengbang Tong, Chen Feng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; One promise that Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models hold over traditional imitation learning for robotics is to leverage the broad generalization capabilities of large Vision-Language Models (VLMs) to produce versatile, "generalist" robot policies. However, current evaluations of VLAs remain insufficient. Traditional imitation learning benchmarks are unsuitable due to the lack of language instructions. Emerging benchmarks for VLAs that incorporate language often come with limited evaluation tasks and do not intend to investigate how much VLM pretraining truly contributes to the generalization capabilities of the downstream robotic policy. Meanwhile, much research relies on real-world robot setups designed in isolation by different institutions, which creates a barrier for reproducibility and accessibility. To address this gap, we introduce a unified probing suite of 50 simulation-based tasks across 10 subcategories spanning language instruction, vision, and objects. We systematically evaluate several state-of-the-art VLA architectures on this suite to understand their generalization capability. Our results show that while VLM backbones endow VLAs with robust perceptual understanding and high level planning, which we refer to as good intentions, this does not reliably translate into precise motor execution: when faced with out-of-distribution observations, policies often exhibit coherent intentions, but falter in action execution. Moreover, finetuning on action data can erode the original VLM's generalist reasoning abilities. We release our task suite and evaluation code to serve as a standardized benchmark for future VLAs and to drive research on closing the perception-to-action gap. More information, including the source code, can be found at https://ai4ce.github.io/INT-ACT/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09930</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 16:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SoK: Evaluating Jailbreak Guardrails for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10597</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.10597.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xunguang Wang, Zhenlan Ji, Wenxuan Wang, Zongjie Li, Daoyuan Wu, Shuai Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have achieved remarkable progress, but their deployment has exposed critical vulnerabilities, particularly to jailbreak attacks that circumvent safety mechanisms. Guardrails--external defense mechanisms that monitor and control LLM interaction--have emerged as a promising solution. However, the current landscape of LLM guardrails is fragmented, lacking a unified taxonomy and comprehensive evaluation framework. In this Systematization of Knowledge (SoK) paper, we present the first holistic analysis of jailbreak guardrails for LLMs. We propose a novel, multi-dimensional taxonomy that categorizes guardrails along six key dimensions, and introduce a Security-Efficiency-Utility evaluation framework to assess their practical effectiveness. Through extensive analysis and experiments, we identify the strengths and limitations of existing guardrail approaches, explore their universality across attack types, and provide insights into optimizing defense combinations. Our work offers a structured foundation for future research and development, aiming to guide the principled advancement and deployment of robust LLM guardrails. The code is available at https://github.com/xunguangwang/SoK4JailbreakGuardrails.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10597</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 11:42:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lost in the Mix: Evaluating LLM Understanding of Code-Switched Text</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14012</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.14012.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amr Mohamed, Yang Zhang, Michalis Vazirgiannis, Guokan Shang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Code-switching (CSW) is the act of alternating between two or more languages within a single discourse. This phenomenon is widespread in multilingual communities, and increasingly prevalent in online content, where users naturally mix languages in everyday communication. As a result, Large Language Models (LLMs), now central to content processing and generation, are frequently exposed to code-switched inputs. Given their widespread use, it is crucial to understand how LLMs process and reason about such mixed-language text. This paper presents a systematic evaluation of LLM comprehension under code-switching by generating CSW variants of established reasoning and comprehension benchmarks. While degradation is evident when foreign tokens disrupt English textx2013even under linguistic constraintsx2013embedding English into other languages often improves comprehension. Though prompting yields mixed results, fine-tuning offers a more stable path to degradation mitigation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14012</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 21:19:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OAgents: An Empirical Study of Building Effective Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15741</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.15741.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; He Zhu, Tianrui Qin, King Zhu, Heyuan Huang, Yeyi Guan, Jinxiang Xia, Yi Yao, Hanhao Li, Ningning Wang, Pai Liu, Tianhao Peng, Xin Gui, Xiaowan Li, Yuhui Liu, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Jun Wang, Changwang Zhang, Xiangru Tang, Ge Zhang, Jian Yang, Minghao Liu, Xitong Gao, Jiaheng Liu, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, Agentic AI has become an increasingly popular research field. However, we argue that current agent research practices lack standardization and scientific rigor, making it hard to conduct fair comparisons among methods. As a result, it is still unclear how different design choices in agent frameworks affect effectiveness, and measuring their progress remains challenging. In this work, we conduct a systematic empirical study on GAIA benchmark and BrowseComp to examine the impact of popular design choices in key agent components in a fair and rigorous manner. We find that the lack of a standard evaluation protocol makes previous works, even open-sourced ones, non-reproducible, with significant variance between random runs. Therefore, we introduce a more robust evaluation protocol to stabilize comparisons. Our study reveals which components and designs are crucial for effective agents, while others are redundant, despite seeming logical. Based on our findings, we build and open-source OAgents, a new foundation agent framework that achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-source projects. OAgents offers a modular design for various agent components, promoting future research in Agentic AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15741</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfiniPot-V: Memory-Constrained KV Cache Compression for Streaming Video   Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15745</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.15745.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minsoo Kim, Kyuhong Shim, Jungwook Choi, Simyung Chang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern multimodal large language models (MLLMs) can reason over hour-long video, yet their key-value (KV) cache grows linearly with time--quickly exceeding the fixed memory of phones, AR glasses, and edge robots. Prior compression schemes either assume the whole video and user query are available offline or must first build the full cache, so memory still scales with stream length. InfiniPot-V is the first training-free, query-agnostic framework that enforces a hard, length-independent memory cap for streaming video understanding. During video encoding it monitors the cache and, once a user-set threshold is reached, runs a lightweight compression pass that (i) removes temporally redundant tokens via Temporal-axis Redundancy (TaR) metric and (ii) keeps semantically significant tokens via Value-Norm (VaN) ranking. Across four open-source MLLMs and four long-video and two streaming-video benchmarks, InfiniPot-V cuts peak GPU memory by up to 94%, sustains real-time generation, and matches or surpasses full-cache accuracy--even in multi-turn dialogues. By dissolving the KV cache bottleneck without retraining or query knowledge, InfiniPot-V closes the gap for on-device streaming video assistants.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15745</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 02:22:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hunyuan3D 2.1: From Images to High-Fidelity 3D Assets with   Production-Ready PBR Material</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15442</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.15442.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Team Hunyuan3D, Shuhui Yang, Mingxin Yang, Yifei Feng, Xin Huang, Sheng Zhang, Zebin He, Di Luo, Haolin Liu, Yunfei Zhao, Qingxiang Lin, Zeqiang Lai, Xianghui Yang, Huiwen Shi, Zibo Zhao, Bowen Zhang, Hongyu Yan, Lifu Wang, Sicong Liu, Jihong Zhang, Meng Chen, Liang Dong, Yiwen Jia, Yulin Cai, Jiaao Yu, Yixuan Tang, Dongyuan Guo, Junlin Yu, Hao Zhang, Zheng Ye, Peng He, Runzhou Wu, Shida Wei, Chao Zhang, Yonghao Tan, Yifu Sun, Lin Niu, Shirui Huang, Bojian Zheng, Shu Liu, Shilin Chen, Xiang Yuan, Xiaofeng Yang, Kai Liu, Jianchen Zhu, Peng Chen, Tian Liu, Di Wang, Yuhong Liu, Linus, Jie Jiang, Jingwei Huang, Chunchao Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D AI-generated content (AIGC) is a passionate field that has significantly accelerated the creation of 3D models in gaming, film, and design. Despite the development of several groundbreaking models that have revolutionized 3D generation, the field remains largely accessible only to researchers, developers, and designers due to the complexities involved in collecting, processing, and training 3D models. To address these challenges, we introduce Hunyuan3D 2.1 as a case study in this tutorial. This tutorial offers a comprehensive, step-by-step guide on processing 3D data, training a 3D generative model, and evaluating its performance using Hunyuan3D 2.1, an advanced system for producing high-resolution, textured 3D assets. The system comprises two core components: the Hunyuan3D-DiT for shape generation and the Hunyuan3D-Paint for texture synthesis. We will explore the entire workflow, including data preparation, model architecture, training strategies, evaluation metrics, and deployment. By the conclusion of this tutorial, you will have the knowledge to finetune or develop a robust 3D generative model suitable for applications in gaming, virtual reality, and industrial design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15442</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 13:14:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying the Visual Quality Paradox in Multimodal Large Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15645</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.15645.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuo Xing, Lanqing Guo, Hongyuan Hua, Seoyoung Lee, Peiran Li, Yufei Wang, Zhangyang Wang, Zhengzhong Tu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) excel on benchmark vision-language tasks, yet little is known about how input visual quality shapes their responses. Does higher perceptual quality of images already translate to better MLLM understanding? We conduct the first systematic study spanning leading MLLMs and a suite of vision-language benchmarks, applying controlled degradations and stylistic shifts to each image. Surprisingly, we uncover a visual-quality paradox: model, task, and even individual-instance performance can improve when images deviate from human-perceived fidelity. Off-the-shelf restoration pipelines fail to reconcile these idiosyncratic preferences. To close the gap, we introduce Visual-Quality Test-Time Tuning (VQ-TTT)-a lightweight adaptation module that: (1) inserts a learnable, low-rank kernel before the frozen vision encoder to modulate frequency content; and (2) fine-tunes only shallow vision-encoder layers via LoRA. VQ-TTT dynamically adjusts each input image in a single forward pass, aligning it with task-specific model preferences. Across the evaluated MLLMs and all datasets, VQ-TTT lifts significant average accuracy, with no external models, cached features, or extra training data. These findings redefine ``better'' visual inputs for MLLMs and highlight the need for adaptive, rather than universally ``clean'', imagery, in the new era of AI being the main data customer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15645</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 17:14:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I Know Which LLM Wrote Your Code Last Summer: LLM generated Code   Stylometry for Authorship Attribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17323</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17323.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tamas Bisztray, Bilel Cherif, Richard A. Dubniczky, Nils Gruschka, Bertalan Borsos, Mohamed Amine Ferrag, Attila Kovacs, Vasileios Mavroeidis, Norbert Tihanyi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Detecting AI-generated code, deepfakes, and other synthetic content is an emerging research challenge. As code generated by Large Language Models (LLMs) becomes more common, identifying the specific model behind each sample is increasingly important. This paper presents the first systematic study of LLM authorship attribution for C programs. We released CodeT5-Authorship, a novel model that uses only the encoder layers from the original CodeT5 encoder-decoder architecture, discarding the decoder to focus on classification. Our model's encoder output (first token) is passed through a two-layer classification head with GELU activation and dropout, producing a probability distribution over possible authors. To evaluate our approach, we introduce LLM-AuthorBench, a benchmark of 32,000 compilable C programs generated by eight state-of-the-art LLMs across diverse tasks. We compare our model to seven traditional ML classifiers and eight fine-tuned transformer models, including BERT, RoBERTa, CodeBERT, ModernBERT, DistilBERT, DeBERTa-V3, Longformer, and LoRA-fine-tuned Qwen2-1.5B. In binary classification, our model achieves 97.56% accuracy in distinguishing C programs generated by closely related models such as GPT-4.1 and GPT-4o, and 95.40% accuracy for multi-class attribution among five leading LLMs (Gemini 2.5 Flash, Claude 3.5 Haiku, GPT-4.1, Llama 3.3, and DeepSeek-V3). To support open science, we release the CodeT5-Authorship architecture, the LLM-AuthorBench benchmark, and all relevant Google Colab scripts on GitHub: https://github.com/LLMauthorbench/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17323</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 19:49:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4Real-Video-V2: Fused View-Time Attention and Feedforward Reconstruction   for 4D Scene Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18839</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18839.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaoyang Wang, Ashkan Mirzaei, Vidit Goel, Willi Menapace, Aliaksandr Siarohin, Avalon Vinella, Michael Vasilkovsky, Ivan Skorokhodov, Vladislav Shakhrai, Sergey Korolev, Sergey Tulyakov, Peter Wonka&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose the first framework capable of computing a 4D spatio-temporal grid of video frames and 3D Gaussian particles for each time step using a feed-forward architecture. Our architecture has two main components, a 4D video model and a 4D reconstruction model. In the first part, we analyze current 4D video diffusion architectures that perform spatial and temporal attention either sequentially or in parallel within a two-stream design. We highlight the limitations of existing approaches and introduce a novel fused architecture that performs spatial and temporal attention within a single layer. The key to our method is a sparse attention pattern, where tokens attend to others in the same frame, at the same timestamp, or from the same viewpoint. In the second part, we extend existing 3D reconstruction algorithms by introducing a Gaussian head, a camera token replacement algorithm, and additional dynamic layers and training. Overall, we establish a new state of the art for 4D generation, improving both visual quality and reconstruction capability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18839</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 23:44:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reranking-based Generation for Unbiased Perspective Summarization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15925</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.15925.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Narutatsu Ri, Nicholas Deas, Kathleen McKeown&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating unbiased summaries in real-world settings such as political perspective summarization remains a crucial application of Large Language Models (LLMs). Yet, existing evaluation frameworks rely on traditional metrics for measuring key attributes such as coverage and faithfulness without verifying their applicability, and efforts to develop improved summarizers are still nascent. We address these gaps by (1) identifying reliable metrics for measuring perspective summary quality, and (2) investigating the efficacy of LLM-based methods beyond zero-shot inference. Namely, we build a test set for benchmarking metric reliability using human annotations and show that traditional metrics underperform compared to language model-based metrics, which prove to be strong evaluators. Using these metrics, we show that reranking-based methods yield strong results, and preference tuning with synthetically generated and reranking-labeled data further boosts performance. Our findings aim to contribute to the reliable evaluation and development of perspective summarization methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15925</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 00:01:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DualTHOR: A Dual-Arm Humanoid Simulation Platform for Contingency-Aware   Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16012</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16012.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Boyu Li, Siyuan He, Hang Xu, Haoqi Yuan, Yu Zang, Liwei Hu, Junpeng Yue, Zhenxiong Jiang, Pengbo Hu, Börje F. Karlsson, Yehui Tang, Zongqing Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Developing embodied agents capable of performing complex interactive tasks in real-world scenarios remains a fundamental challenge in embodied AI. Although recent advances in simulation platforms have greatly enhanced task diversity to train embodied Vision Language Models (VLMs), most platforms rely on simplified robot morphologies and bypass the stochastic nature of low-level execution, which limits their transferability to real-world robots. To address these issues, we present a physics-based simulation platform DualTHOR for complex dual-arm humanoid robots, built upon an extended version of AI2-THOR. Our simulator includes real-world robot assets, a task suite for dual-arm collaboration, and inverse kinematics solvers for humanoid robots. We also introduce a contingency mechanism that incorporates potential failures through physics-based low-level execution, bridging the gap to real-world scenarios. Our simulator enables a more comprehensive evaluation of the robustness and generalization of VLMs in household environments. Extensive evaluations reveal that current VLMs struggle with dual-arm coordination and exhibit limited robustness in realistic environments with contingencies, highlighting the importance of using our simulator to develop more capable VLMs for embodied tasks. The code is available at https://github.com/ds199895/DualTHOR.git.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16012</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 04:13:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision-Guided Chunking Is All You Need: Enhancing RAG with Multimodal   Document Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16035</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16035.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vishesh Tripathi, Tanmay Odapally, Indraneel Das, Uday Allu, Biddwan Ahmed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) systems have revolutionized information retrieval and question answering, but traditional text-based chunking methods struggle with complex document structures, multi-page tables, embedded figures, and contextual dependencies across page boundaries. We present a novel multimodal document chunking approach that leverages Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) to process PDF documents in batches while maintaining semantic coherence and structural integrity. Our method processes documents in configurable page batches with cross-batch context preservation, enabling accurate handling of tables spanning multiple pages, embedded visual elements, and procedural content. We evaluate our approach on a curated dataset of PDF documents with manually crafted queries, demonstrating improvements in chunk quality and downstream RAG performance. Our vision-guided approach achieves better accuracy compared to traditional vanilla RAG systems, with qualitative analysis showing superior preservation of document structure and semantic coherence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16035</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 05:11:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PAROAttention: Pattern-Aware ReOrdering for Efficient Sparse and   Quantized Attention in Visual Generation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16054</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16054.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianchen Zhao, Ke Hong, Xinhao Yang, Xuefeng Xiao, Huixia Li, Feng Ling, Ruiqi Xie, Siqi Chen, Hongyu Zhu, Yichong Zhang, Yu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In visual generation, the quadratic complexity of attention mechanisms results in high memory and computational costs, especially for longer token sequences required in high-resolution image or multi-frame video generation. To address this, prior research has explored techniques such as sparsification and quantization. However, these techniques face significant challenges under low density and reduced bitwidths. Through systematic analysis, we identify that the core difficulty stems from the dispersed and irregular characteristics of visual attention patterns. Therefore, instead of introducing specialized sparsification and quantization design to accommodate such patterns, we propose an alternative strategy: *reorganizing* the attention pattern to alleviate the challenges. Inspired by the local aggregation nature of visual feature extraction, we design a novel **Pattern-Aware token ReOrdering (PARO)** technique, which unifies the diverse attention patterns into a hardware-friendly block-wise pattern. This unification substantially simplifies and enhances both sparsification and quantization. We evaluate the performance-efficiency trade-offs of various design choices and finalize a methodology tailored for the unified pattern. Our approach, **PAROAttention**, achieves video and image generation with lossless metrics, and nearly identical results from full-precision (FP) baselines, while operating at notably lower density (~20%-30%) and bitwidth (**INT8/INT4**), achieving a **1.9x** to **2.7x** end-to-end latency speedup.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16054</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 06:25:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent Operation and Maintenance and Prediction Model Optimization   for Improving Wind Power Generation Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16095</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16095.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xun Liu, Xiaobin Wu, Jiaqi He, Rajan Das Gupta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This study explores the effectiveness of predictive maintenance models and the optimization of intelligent Operation and Maintenance (O&amp;M) systems in improving wind power generation efficiency. Through qualitative research, structured interviews were conducted with five wind farm engineers and maintenance managers, each with extensive experience in turbine operations. Using thematic analysis, the study revealed that while predictive maintenance models effectively reduce downtime by identifying major faults, they often struggle with detecting smaller, gradual failures. Key challenges identified include false positives, sensor malfunctions, and difficulties in integrating new models with older turbine systems. Advanced technologies such as digital twins, SCADA systems, and condition monitoring have significantly enhanced turbine maintenance practices. However, these technologies still require improvements, particularly in AI refinement and real-time data integration. The findings emphasize the need for continuous development to fully optimize wind turbine performance and support the broader adoption of renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16095</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 07:31:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FinCoT: Grounding Chain-of-Thought in Expert Financial Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16123</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16123.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Natapong Nitarach, Warit Sirichotedumrong, Panop Pitchayarthorn, Pittawat Taveekitworachai, Potsawee Manakul, Kunat Pipatanakul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents FinCoT, a structured chain-of-thought (CoT) prompting approach that incorporates insights from domain-specific expert financial reasoning to guide the reasoning traces of large language models. We investigate that there are three main prompting styles in FinNLP: (1) standard prompting--zero-shot prompting; (2) unstructured CoT--CoT prompting without an explicit reasoning structure, such as the use of tags; and (3) structured CoT prompting--CoT prompting with explicit instructions or examples that define structured reasoning steps. Previously, FinNLP has primarily focused on prompt engineering with either standard or unstructured CoT prompting. However, structured CoT prompting has received limited attention in prior work. Furthermore, the design of reasoning structures in structured CoT prompting is often based on heuristics from non-domain experts. In this study, we investigate each prompting approach in FinNLP. We evaluate the three main prompting styles and FinCoT on CFA-style questions spanning ten financial domains. We observe that FinCoT improves performance from 63.2% to 80.5% and Qwen-2.5-7B-Instruct from 69.7% to 74.2%, while reducing generated tokens eight-fold compared to structured CoT prompting. Our findings show that domain-aligned structured prompts not only improve performance and reduce inference costs but also yield more interpretable and expert-aligned reasoning traces.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16123</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 08:18:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRPO-CARE: Consistency-Aware Reinforcement Learning for Multimodal   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16141</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16141.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Chen, Yuying Ge, Rui Wang, Yixiao Ge, Junhao Cheng, Ying Shan, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reinforcement learning approaches, such as outcome-supervised GRPO, have advanced Chain-of-Thought reasoning in large language models (LLMs), yet their adaptation to multimodal LLMs (MLLMs) is unexplored. To address the lack of rigorous evaluation for MLLM post-training methods, we introduce SEED-Bench-R1, a benchmark with complex real-world videos requiring balanced perception and reasoning. It offers a large training set and evaluates generalization across three escalating challenges: in-distribution, cross-environment, and cross-environment-task scenarios. Using SEED-Bench-R1, we find that standard GRPO, while improving answer accuracy, often reduces logical coherence between reasoning steps and answers, with only a 57.9% consistency rate. This stems from reward signals focusing solely on final answers, encouraging shortcuts, and strict KL penalties limiting exploration.To address this, we propose GRPO-CARE, a consistency-aware RL framework optimizing both answer correctness and reasoning coherence without explicit supervision. GRPO-CARE introduces a two-tiered reward: (1) a base reward for answer correctness, and (2) an adaptive consistency bonus, computed by comparing the model's reasoning-to-answer likelihood (via a slowly-evolving reference model) against group peers.This dual mechanism amplifies rewards for reasoning paths that are both correct and logically consistent. Replacing KL penalties with this adaptive bonus, GRPO-CARE outperforms standard GRPO on SEED-Bench-R1, achieving a 6.7% performance gain on the hardest evaluation level and a 24.5% improvement in consistency. It also shows strong transferability, improving model performance across diverse video understanding benchmarks. Our work contributes a systematically designed benchmark and a generalizable post-training framework, advancing the development of more interpretable and robust MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16141</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 08:49:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Multilingual Text-To-Speech with Accents &amp; Emotions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16310</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16310.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pranav Pawar, Akshansh Dwivedi, Jenish Boricha, Himanshu Gohil, Aditya Dubey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; State-of-the-art text-to-speech (TTS) systems realize high naturalness in monolingual environments, synthesizing speech with correct multilingual accents (especially for Indic languages) and context-relevant emotions still poses difficulty owing to cultural nuance discrepancies in current frameworks. This paper introduces a new TTS architecture integrating accent along with preserving transliteration with multi-scale emotion modelling, in particularly tuned for Hindi and Indian English accent. Our approach extends the Parler-TTS model by integrating A language-specific phoneme alignment hybrid encoder-decoder architecture, and culture-sensitive emotion embedding layers trained on native speaker corpora, as well as incorporating a dynamic accent code switching with residual vector quantization. Quantitative tests demonstrate 23.7% improvement in accent accuracy (Word Error Rate reduction from 15.4% to 11.8%) and 85.3% emotion recognition accuracy from native listeners, surpassing METTS and VECL-TTS baselines. The novelty of the system is that it can mix code in real time - generating statements such as "Namaste, let's talk about &lt;Hindi phrase&gt;" with uninterrupted accent shifts while preserving emotional consistency. Subjective evaluation with 200 users reported a mean opinion score (MOS) of 4.2/5 for cultural correctness, much better than existing multilingual systems (p&lt;0.01). This research makes cross-lingual synthesis more feasible by showcasing scalable accent-emotion disentanglement, with direct application in South Asian EdTech and accessibility software.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16310</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 13:35:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Watermarking Autoregressive Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16349</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16349.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nikola Jovanović, Ismail Labiad, Tomáš Souček, Martin Vechev, Pierre Fernandez&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Watermarking the outputs of generative models has emerged as a promising approach for tracking their provenance. Despite significant interest in autoregressive image generation models and their potential for misuse, no prior work has attempted to watermark their outputs at the token level. In this work, we present the first such approach by adapting language model watermarking techniques to this setting. We identify a key challenge: the lack of reverse cycle-consistency (RCC), wherein re-tokenizing generated image tokens significantly alters the token sequence, effectively erasing the watermark. To address this and to make our method robust to common image transformations, neural compression, and removal attacks, we introduce (i) a custom tokenizer-detokenizer finetuning procedure that improves RCC, and (ii) a complementary watermark synchronization layer. As our experiments demonstrate, our approach enables reliable and robust watermark detection with theoretically grounded p-values.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16349</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 14:25:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drag-and-Drop LLMs: Zero-Shot Prompt-to-Weights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16406</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16406.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Liang, Dongwen Tang, Yuhao Zhou, Xuanlei Zhao, Mingjia Shi, Wangbo Zhao, Zekai Li, Peihao Wang, Konstantin Schürholt, Damian Borth, Michael M. Bronstein, Yang You, Zhangyang Wang, Kai Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 111&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) methods such as low-rank adaptation (LoRA) reduce the cost of customizing large language models (LLMs), yet still require a separate optimization run for every downstream dataset. We introduce Drag-and-Drop LLMs (\textit{DnD)}, a prompt-conditioned parameter generator that eliminates per-task training by mapping a handful of unlabeled task prompts directly to LoRA weight updates. A lightweight text encoder distills each prompt batch into condition embeddings, which are then transformed by a cascaded hyper-convolutional decoder into the full set of LoRA matrices. Once trained in a diverse collection of prompt-checkpoint pairs, DnD produces task-specific parameters in seconds, yielding i) up to 12,000times lower overhead than full fine-tuning, ii) average gains up to 30\% in performance over the strongest training LoRAs on unseen common-sense reasoning, math, coding, and multimodal benchmarks, and iii) robust cross-domain generalization despite never seeing the target data or labels. Our results demonstrate that prompt-conditioned parameter generation is a viable alternative to gradient-based adaptation for rapidly specializing LLMs. Our project is available at https://jerryliang24.github.io/DnD{https://jerryliang24.github.io/DnD}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16406</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 15:38:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hunyuan3D 2.5: Towards High-Fidelity 3D Assets Generation with Ultimate   Details</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16504</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16504.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeqiang Lai, Yunfei Zhao, Haolin Liu, Zibo Zhao, Qingxiang Lin, Huiwen Shi, Xianghui Yang, Mingxin Yang, Shuhui Yang, Yifei Feng, Sheng Zhang, Xin Huang, Di Luo, Fan Yang, Fang Yang, Lifu Wang, Sicong Liu, Yixuan Tang, Yulin Cai, Zebin He, Tian Liu, Yuhong Liu, Jie Jiang, Linus, Jingwei Huang, Chunchao Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this report, we present Hunyuan3D 2.5, a robust suite of 3D diffusion models aimed at generating high-fidelity and detailed textured 3D assets. Hunyuan3D 2.5 follows two-stages pipeline of its previous version Hunyuan3D 2.0, while demonstrating substantial advancements in both shape and texture generation. In terms of shape generation, we introduce a new shape foundation model -- LATTICE, which is trained with scaled high-quality datasets, model-size, and compute. Our largest model reaches 10B parameters and generates sharp and detailed 3D shape with precise image-3D following while keeping mesh surface clean and smooth, significantly closing the gap between generated and handcrafted 3D shapes. In terms of texture generation, it is upgraded with phyiscal-based rendering (PBR) via a novel multi-view architecture extended from Hunyuan3D 2.0 Paint model. Our extensive evaluation shows that Hunyuan3D 2.5 significantly outperforms previous methods in both shape and end-to-end texture generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16504</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 17:57:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Reward Modeling via Causal Rubrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16507</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16507.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pragya Srivastava, Harman Singh, Rahul Madhavan, Gandharv Patil, Sravanti Addepalli, Arun Suggala, Rengarajan Aravamudhan, Soumya Sharma, Anirban Laha, Aravindan Raghuveer, Karthikeyan Shanmugam, Doina Precup&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward models (RMs) are fundamental to aligning Large Language Models (LLMs) via human feedback, yet they often suffer from reward hacking. They tend to latch on to superficial or spurious attributes, such as response length or formatting, mistaking these cues learned from correlations in training data for the true causal drivers of quality (e.g., factuality, relevance). This occurs because standard training objectives struggle to disentangle these factors, leading to brittle RMs and misaligned policies. We introduce Crome (Causally Robust Reward Modeling), a novel framework grounded in an explicit causal model designed to mitigate reward hacking. Crome employs the following synthetic targeted augmentations during training: (1) Causal Augmentations, which are pairs that differ along specific causal attributes, to enforce sensitivity along each causal attribute individually, and (2) Neutral Augmentations, which are tie-label pairs varying primarily in spurious attributes, to enforce invariance along spurious attributes. Notably, our augmentations are produced without any knowledge of spurious factors, via answer interventions only along causal rubrics, that are identified by querying an oracle LLM. Empirically, Crome significantly outperforms standard baselines on RewardBench, improving average accuracy by up to 5.4% and achieving gains of up to 13.2% and 7.2% in specific categories. The robustness of Crome is further testified by the consistent gains obtained in a Best-of-N inference setting across increasing N, across various benchmarks, including the popular RewardBench (covering chat, chat-hard, safety, and reasoning tasks), the safety-focused WildGuardTest, and the reasoning-specific GSM8k.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16507</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 17:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arch-Router: Aligning LLM Routing with Human Preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16655</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16655.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Co Tran, Salman Paracha, Adil Hafeez, Shuguang Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the rapid proliferation of large language models (LLMs) -- each optimized for different strengths, style, or latency/cost profile -- routing has become an essential technique to operationalize the use of different models. However, existing LLM routing approaches are limited in two key ways: they evaluate performance using benchmarks that often fail to capture human preferences driven by subjective evaluation criteria, and they typically select from a limited pool of models. In this work, we propose a preference-aligned routing framework that guides model selection by matching queries to user-defined domains (e.g., travel) or action types (e.g., image editing) -- offering a practical mechanism to encode preferences in routing decisions. Specifically, we introduce Arch-Router, a compact 1.5B model that learns to map queries to domain-action preferences for model routing decisions. Our approach also supports seamlessly adding new models for routing without requiring retraining or architectural modifications. Experiments on conversational datasets demonstrate that our approach achieves state-of-the-art (SOTA) results in matching queries with human preferences, outperforming top proprietary models. Our approach captures subjective evaluation criteria and makes routing decisions more transparent and flexible. Our model is available at: https://huggingface.co/katanemo/Arch-Router-1.5B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16655</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 23:57:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Step-by-Step and Verifiable Medical Reasoning in MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16962</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16962.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran Sun, Yankai Jiang, Wenjie Lou, Yujie Zhang, Wenjie Li, Lilong Wang, Mianxin Liu, Lei Liu, Xiaosong Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have begun to demonstrate robust reasoning capabilities on general tasks, yet their application in the medical domain remains in its early stages. Constructing chain-of-thought (CoT) training data is essential for bolstering the reasoning abilities of medical MLLMs. However, existing approaches exhibit a deficiency in offering a comprehensive framework for searching and evaluating effective reasoning paths towards critical diagnosis. To address this challenge, we propose Mentor-Intern Collaborative Search (MICS), a novel reasoning-path searching scheme to generate rigorous and effective medical CoT data. MICS first leverages mentor models to initialize the reasoning, one step at a time, then prompts each intern model to continue the thinking along those initiated paths, and finally selects the optimal reasoning path according to the overall reasoning performance of multiple intern models. The reasoning performance is determined by an MICS-Score, which assesses the quality of generated reasoning paths. Eventually, we construct MMRP, a multi-task medical reasoning dataset with ranked difficulty, and Chiron-o1, a new medical MLLM devised via a curriculum learning strategy, with robust visual question-answering and generalizable reasoning capabilities. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Chiron-o1, trained on our CoT dataset constructed using MICS, achieves state-of-the-art performance across a list of medical visual question answering and reasoning benchmarks. Codes are available at GitHub - manglu097/Chiron-o1: Enhancing Step-by-Step and Verifiable Medical Reasoning in MLLMs&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16962</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 12:51:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MEXA: Towards General Multimodal Reasoning with Dynamic Multi-Expert   Aggregation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17113</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17113.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shoubin Yu, Yue Zhang, Ziyang Wang, Jaehong Yoon, Mohit Bansal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Combining pre-trained expert models offers substantial potential for scalable multimodal reasoning, but building a unified framework remains challenging due to the increasing diversity of input modalities and task complexity. For instance, medical diagnosis requires precise reasoning over structured clinical tables, while financial forecasting depends on interpreting plot-based data to make informed predictions. To tackle this challenge, we introduce MEXA, a training-free framework that performs modality- and task-aware aggregation of multiple expert models to enable effective multimodal reasoning across diverse and distinct domains. MEXA dynamically selects expert models based on the input modality and the task-specific reasoning demands (i.e., skills). Each expert model, specialized in a modality task pair, generates interpretable textual reasoning outputs. MEXA then aggregates and reasons over these outputs using a Large Reasoning Model (LRM) to produce the final answer. This modular design allows flexible and transparent multimodal reasoning across diverse domains without additional training overhead. We extensively evaluate our approach on diverse multimodal benchmarks, including Video Reasoning, Audio Reasoning, 3D Understanding, and Medical QA. MEXA consistently delivers performance improvements over strong multimodal baselines, highlighting the effectiveness and broad applicability of our expert-driven selection and aggregation in diverse multimodal reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17113</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 16:14:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hunyuan-GameCraft: High-dynamic Interactive Game Video Generation with   Hybrid History Condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17201</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17201.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Li, Junshu Tang, Zhiyong Xu, Longhuang Wu, Yuan Zhou, Shuai Shao, Tianbao Yu, Zhiguo Cao, Qinglin Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in diffusion-based and controllable video generation have enabled high-quality and temporally coherent video synthesis, laying the groundwork for immersive interactive gaming experiences. However, current methods face limitations in dynamics, generality, long-term consistency, and efficiency, which limit the ability to create various gameplay videos. To address these gaps, we introduce Hunyuan-GameCraft, a novel framework for high-dynamic interactive video generation in game environments. To achieve fine-grained action control, we unify standard keyboard and mouse inputs into a shared camera representation space, facilitating smooth interpolation between various camera and movement operations. Then we propose a hybrid history-conditioned training strategy that extends video sequences autoregressively while preserving game scene information. Additionally, to enhance inference efficiency and playability, we achieve model distillation to reduce computational overhead while maintaining consistency across long temporal sequences, making it suitable for real-time deployment in complex interactive environments. The model is trained on a large-scale dataset comprising over one million gameplay recordings across over 100 AAA games, ensuring broad coverage and diversity, then fine-tuned on a carefully annotated synthetic dataset to enhance precision and control. The curated game scene data significantly improves the visual fidelity, realism and action controllability. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Hunyuan-GameCraft significantly outperforms existing models, advancing the realism and playability of interactive game video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17201</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 17:50:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniFork: Exploring Modality Alignment for Unified Multimodal   Understanding and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17202</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17202.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Teng Li, Quanfeng Lu, Lirui Zhao, Hao Li, Xizhou Zhu, Yu Qiao, Jun Zhang, Wenqi Shao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified image understanding and generation has emerged as a promising paradigm in multimodal artificial intelligence. Despite recent progress, the optimal architectural design for such unified models remains an open challenge. In this work, we start by analyzing the modality alignment behaviors of task-specific expert models for understanding and generation, as well as current unified models. Our analysis reveals a crucial observation: understanding tasks benefit from a progressively increasing modality alignment across network depth, which helps build up semantic information for better comprehension; In contrast, generation tasks follow a different trend: modality alignment increases in the early layers but decreases in the deep layers to recover spatial details. These divergent alignment patterns create a fundamental conflict in fully shared Transformer backbones, where a uniform representational flow often leads to performance compromises across two tasks. Motivated by this finding, we introduce UniFork, a novel Y-shaped architecture that shares the shallow layers for cross-task representation learning, while employing task-specific branches in deeper layers to avoid task interference. This design effectively balances shared learning and task specialization. Through extensive ablation experiments, we demonstrate that Unifork consistently outperforms conventional fully shared Transformer architectures, and achieves performance on par with or better than task-specific models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17202</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 17:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamCube: 3D Panorama Generation via Multi-plane Synchronization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17206</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17206.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yukun Huang, Yanning Zhou, Jianan Wang, Kaiyi Huang, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D panorama synthesis is a promising yet challenging task that demands high-quality and diverse visual appearance and geometry of the generated omnidirectional content. Existing methods leverage rich image priors from pre-trained 2D foundation models to circumvent the scarcity of 3D panoramic data, but the incompatibility between 3D panoramas and 2D single views limits their effectiveness. In this work, we demonstrate that by applying multi-plane synchronization to the operators from 2D foundation models, their capabilities can be seamlessly extended to the omnidirectional domain. Based on this design, we further introduce DreamCube, a multi-plane RGB-D diffusion model for 3D panorama generation, which maximizes the reuse of 2D foundation model priors to achieve diverse appearances and accurate geometry while maintaining multi-view consistency. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach in panoramic image generation, panoramic depth estimation, and 3D scene generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17206</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 17:55:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-term Traffic Simulation with Interleaved Autoregressive Motion and   Scenario Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17213</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17213.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiuyu Yang, Shuhan Tan, Philipp Krähenbühl&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; An ideal traffic simulator replicates the realistic long-term point-to-point trip that a self-driving system experiences during deployment. Prior models and benchmarks focus on closed-loop motion simulation for initial agents in a scene. This is problematic for long-term simulation. Agents enter and exit the scene as the ego vehicle enters new regions. We propose InfGen, a unified next-token prediction model that performs interleaved closed-loop motion simulation and scene generation. InfGen automatically switches between closed-loop motion simulation and scene generation mode. It enables stable long-term rollout simulation. InfGen performs at the state-of-the-art in short-term (9s) traffic simulation, and significantly outperforms all other methods in long-term (30s) simulation. The code and model of InfGen will be released at https://orangesodahub.github.io/InfGen&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17213</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 17:59:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Mental Imagery: Empower Multimodal Reasoning with Latent Visual   Tokens</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17218</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17218.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeyuan Yang, Xueyang Yu, Delin Chen, Maohao Shen, Chuang Gan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language models (VLMs) excel at multimodal understanding, yet their text-only decoding forces them to verbalize visual reasoning, limiting performance on tasks that demand visual imagination. Recent attempts train VLMs to render explicit images, but the heavy image-generation pre-training often hinders the reasoning ability. Inspired by the way humans reason with mental imagery-the internal construction and manipulation of visual cues-we investigate whether VLMs can reason through interleaved multimodal trajectories without producing explicit images. To this end, we present a Machine Mental Imagery framework, dubbed as Mirage, which augments VLM decoding with latent visual tokens alongside ordinary text. Concretely, whenever the model chooses to ``think visually'', it recasts its hidden states as next tokens, thereby continuing a multimodal trajectory without generating pixel-level images. Begin by supervising the latent tokens through distillation from ground-truth image embeddings, we then switch to text-only supervision to make the latent trajectory align tightly with the task objective. A subsequent reinforcement learning stage further enhances the multimodal reasoning capability. Experiments on diverse benchmarks demonstrate that Mirage unlocks stronger multimodal reasoning without explicit image generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17218</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 17:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DuaShepherd: Integrating Stepwise Correctness and Potential Rewards for   Mathematical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17533</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17533.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuanhao Wu, Juntong Song, Hanning Zhang, Tong Zhang, Cheng Niu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we propose DuaShepherd, a novel reward modeling framework that integrates two complementary reward signals, correctness and potential, to enhance the mathematical reasoning capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs). While correctness-based signals emphasize identification of stepwise errors, potential-based signals focus on the likelihood of reaching the correct final answer. We developed an automated pipeline for constructing large-scale reward modeling dataset with both signals. A unified, multi-head architecture was explored to train the two reward models in a multi-task setup, demonstrating benefits from learning both correctness and potential in parallel. By combining these two signals into a compound probability, our model achieves consistent performance improvements across multiple benchmarks. Empirical evaluations on MATH500 and ProcessBench confirm that this combined reward significantly outperforms models trained on either reward type alone, achieving state-of-the-art performance under comparable resource constraints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17533</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 01:11:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ConsumerBench: Benchmarking Generative AI Applications on End-User   Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17538</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17538.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yile Gu, Rohan Kadekodi, Hoang Nguyen, Keisuke Kamahori, Yiyu Liu, Baris Kasikci&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The recent shift in Generative AI (GenAI) applications from cloud-only environments to end-user devices introduces new challenges in resource management, system efficiency, and user experience. This paper presents ConsumerBench, a comprehensive benchmarking framework designed to evaluate the system efficiency and response time of GenAI models running on end-user devices. Unlike existing benchmarks that assume exclusive model access on dedicated GPUs, ConsumerBench simulates realistic multi-application scenarios executing concurrently on constrained hardware. Furthermore, ConsumerBench supports customizable workflows that simulate complex tasks requiring coordination among multiple applications. ConsumerBench captures both application-level metrics, including latency and Service Level Objective (SLO) attainment, and system-level metrics like CPU/GPU utilization and memory bandwidth. Through extensive experiments, ConsumerBench reveals inefficiencies in resource sharing, unfair scheduling under greedy allocation, and performance pitfalls of static model server configurations. The paper also provides practical insights for model developers and system designers, highlighting the benefits of custom kernels tailored to consumer-grade GPU architectures and the value of implementing SLO-aware scheduling strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17538</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 01:32:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JarvisArt: Liberating Human Artistic Creativity via an Intelligent Photo   Retouching Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17612</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17612.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunlong Lin, Zixu Lin, Kunjie Lin, Jinbin Bai, Panwang Pan, Chenxin Li, Haoyu Chen, Zhongdao Wang, Xinghao Ding, Wenbo Li, Shuicheng Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Photo retouching has become integral to contemporary visual storytelling, enabling users to capture aesthetics and express creativity. While professional tools such as Adobe Lightroom offer powerful capabilities, they demand substantial expertise and manual effort. In contrast, existing AI-based solutions provide automation but often suffer from limited adjustability and poor generalization, failing to meet diverse and personalized editing needs. To bridge this gap, we introduce JarvisArt, a multi-modal large language model (MLLM)-driven agent that understands user intent, mimics the reasoning process of professional artists, and intelligently coordinates over 200 retouching tools within Lightroom. JarvisArt undergoes a two-stage training process: an initial Chain-of-Thought supervised fine-tuning to establish basic reasoning and tool-use skills, followed by Group Relative Policy Optimization for Retouching (GRPO-R) to further enhance its decision-making and tool proficiency. We also propose the Agent-to-Lightroom Protocol to facilitate seamless integration with Lightroom. To evaluate performance, we develop MMArt-Bench, a novel benchmark constructed from real-world user edits. JarvisArt demonstrates user-friendly interaction, superior generalization, and fine-grained control over both global and local adjustments, paving a new avenue for intelligent photo retouching. Notably, it outperforms GPT-4o with a 60% improvement in average pixel-level metrics on MMArt-Bench for content fidelity, while maintaining comparable instruction-following capabilities. Project Page: https://jarvisart.vercel.app/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17612</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 06:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FaithfulSAE: Towards Capturing Faithful Features with Sparse   Autoencoders without External Dataset Dependencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17673</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17673.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seonglae Cho, Harryn Oh, Donghyun Lee, Luis Eduardo Rodrigues Vieira, Andrew Bermingham, Ziad El Sayed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse Autoencoders (SAEs) have emerged as a promising solution for decomposing large language model representations into interpretable features. However, Paulo and Belrose (2025) have highlighted instability across different initialization seeds, and Heap et al. (2025) have pointed out that SAEs may not capture model-internal features. These problems likely stem from training SAEs on external datasets - either collected from the Web or generated by another model - which may contain out-of-distribution (OOD) data beyond the model's generalisation capabilities. This can result in hallucinated SAE features, which we term "Fake Features", that misrepresent the model's internal activations. To address these issues, we propose FaithfulSAE, a method that trains SAEs on the model's own synthetic dataset. Using FaithfulSAEs, we demonstrate that training SAEs on less-OOD instruction datasets results in SAEs being more stable across seeds. Notably, FaithfulSAEs outperform SAEs trained on web-based datasets in the SAE probing task and exhibit a lower Fake Feature Ratio in 5 out of 7 models. Overall, our approach eliminates the dependency on external datasets, advancing interpretability by better capturing model-internal features while highlighting the often neglected importance of SAE training datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17673</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 10:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CultureMERT: Continual Pre-Training for Cross-Cultural Music   Representation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17818</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17818.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Angelos-Nikolaos Kanatas, Charilaos Papaioannou, Alexandros Potamianos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in music foundation models have improved audio representation learning, yet their effectiveness across diverse musical traditions remains limited. We introduce CultureMERT-95M, a multi-culturally adapted foundation model developed to enhance cross-cultural music representation learning and understanding. To achieve this, we propose a two-stage continual pre-training strategy that integrates learning rate re-warming and re-decaying, enabling stable adaptation even with limited computational resources. Training on a 650-hour multi-cultural data mix, comprising Greek, Turkish, and Indian music traditions, results in an average improvement of 4.9% in ROC-AUC and AP across diverse non-Western music auto-tagging tasks, surpassing prior state-of-the-art, with minimal forgetting on Western-centric benchmarks. We further investigate task arithmetic, an alternative approach to multi-cultural adaptation that merges single-culture adapted models in the weight space. Task arithmetic performs on par with our multi-culturally trained model on non-Western auto-tagging tasks and shows no regression on Western datasets. Cross-cultural evaluation reveals that single-culture models transfer with varying effectiveness across musical traditions, whereas the multi-culturally adapted model achieves the best overall performance. To support research on world music representation learning, we publicly release CultureMERT-95M and CultureMERT-TA-95M, fostering the development of more culturally aware music foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17818</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 21:16:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Alignment Shrinks the Generative Horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17871</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17871.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenghao Yang, Ari Holtzman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite their impressive capabilities, aligned large language models (LLMs) often generate outputs that lack diversity. What drives this stability in the generation? We investigate this phenomenon through the lens of probability concentration in the model's output distribution. To quantify this concentration, we introduce the Branching Factor (BF) -- a token-invariant measure of the effective number of plausible next steps during generation. Our empirical analysis reveals two key findings: (1) BF often decreases as generation progresses, suggesting that LLMs become more predictable as they generate. (2) alignment tuning substantially sharpens the model's output distribution from the outset, reducing BF by nearly an order of magnitude (e.g., from 12 to 1.2) relative to base models. This stark reduction helps explain why aligned models often appear less sensitive to decoding strategies. Building on this insight, we find this stability has surprising implications for complex reasoning. Aligned Chain-of-Thought (CoT) models (e.g., DeepSeek-distilled models), for instance, leverage this effect; by generating longer reasoning chains, they push generation into later, more deterministic (lower BF) stages, resulting in more stable outputs. We hypothesize that alignment tuning does not fundamentally change a model's behavior, but instead steers it toward stylistic tokens (e.g., "Sure") that unlock low-entropy trajectories already present in the base model. This view is supported by nudging experiments, which show that prompting base models with such tokens can similarly reduce BF. Together, our findings establish BF as a powerful diagnostic for understanding and controlling LLM outputs - clarifying how alignment reduces variability, how CoT promotes stable generations, and how base models can be steered away from diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17871</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 02:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboTwin 2.0: A Scalable Data Generator and Benchmark with Strong Domain   Randomization for Robust Bimanual Robotic Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18088</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18088.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianxing Chen, Zanxin Chen, Baijun Chen, Zijian Cai, Yibin Liu, Qiwei Liang, Zixuan Li, Xianliang Lin, Yiheng Ge, Zhenyu Gu, Weiliang Deng, Yubin Guo, Tian Nian, Xuanbing Xie, Qiangyu Chen, Kailun Su, Tianling Xu, Guodong Liu, Mengkang Hu, Huan-ang Gao, Kaixuan Wang, Zhixuan Liang, Yusen Qin, Xiaokang Yang, Ping Luo, Yao Mu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Simulation-based data synthesis has emerged as a powerful paradigm for enhancing real-world robotic manipulation. However, existing synthetic datasets remain insufficient for robust bimanual manipulation due to two challenges: (1) the lack of an efficient, scalable data generation method for novel tasks, and (2) oversimplified simulation environments that fail to capture real-world complexity. We present RoboTwin 2.0, a scalable simulation framework that enables automated, large-scale generation of diverse and realistic data, along with unified evaluation protocols for dual-arm manipulation. We first construct RoboTwin-OD, a large-scale object library comprising 731 instances across 147 categories, each annotated with semantic and manipulation-relevant labels. Building on this foundation, we develop an expert data synthesis pipeline that combines multimodal large language models (MLLMs) with simulation-in-the-loop refinement to generate task-level execution code automatically. To improve sim-to-real transfer, RoboTwin 2.0 incorporates structured domain randomization along five axes: clutter, lighting, background, tabletop height and language instructions, thereby enhancing data diversity and policy robustness. We instantiate this framework across 50 dual-arm tasks spanning five robot embodiments, and pre-collect over 100,000 domain-randomized expert trajectories. Empirical results show a 10.9% gain in code generation success and improved generalization to novel real-world scenarios. A VLA model fine-tuned on our dataset achieves a 367% relative improvement (42.0% vs. 9.0%) on unseen scene real-world tasks, while zero-shot models trained solely on our synthetic data achieve a 228% relative gain, highlighting strong generalization without real-world supervision. We release the data generator, benchmark, dataset, and code to support scalable research in robust bimanual manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18088</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 16:26:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ShareGPT-4o-Image: Aligning Multimodal Models with GPT-4o-Level Image   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18095</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18095.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junying Chen, Zhenyang Cai, Pengcheng Chen, Shunian Chen, Ke Ji, Xidong Wang, Yunjin Yang, Benyou Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal generative models have unlocked photorealistic, instruction-aligned image generation, yet leading systems like GPT-4o-Image remain proprietary and inaccessible. To democratize these capabilities, we present ShareGPT-4o-Image, the first dataset comprising 45K text-to-image and 46K text-and-image-to-image data, all synthesized using GPT-4o's image generation capabilities for distilling its advanced image generation abilities. Leveraging this dataset, we develop Janus-4o, a multimodal large language model capable of both text-to-image and text-and-image-to-image generation. Janus-4o not only significantly improves text-to-image generation over its predecessor, Janus-Pro, but also newly supports text-and-image-to-image generation. Notably, it achieves impressive performance in text-and-image-to-image generation from scratch, using only 91K synthetic samples and 6 hours of training on an 8 A800-GPU machine. We hope the release of ShareGPT-4o-Image and Janus-4o will foster open research in photorealistic, instruction-aligned image generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18095</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 16:51:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain-of-Experts: Unlocking the Communication Power of   Mixture-of-Experts Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18945</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18945.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihan Wang, Rui Pan, Jiarui Yao, Robert Csordas, Linjie Li, Lu Yin, Jiajun Wu, Tong Zhang, Manling Li, Shiwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose Chain-of-Experts (CoE), a new Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture that introduces sequential expert communication within each layer. Unlike traditional MoE models, where experts operate independently in parallel, CoE processes tokens iteratively across a chain of experts inside a layer. To support dynamic expert selection across iterations, CoE employs a dedicated router at each iteration step within a layer. This design allows tokens to re-evaluate and select different experts during each iteration, rather than being statically assigned. As a result, CoE introduces a flexible routing mechanism that increases the diversity of expert combinations and enriches the model's representational capacity. CoE demonstrates improved performance under fixed compute: on math reasoning tasks, it reduces validation loss from 1.20 to 1.12 compared to a standard MoE. Beyond performance, CoE offers a new scaling axis: depth through expert iteration, which complements conventional width/depth scaling. For example, using 2x iterations matches the performance of 3x expert selections (in width), while reducing memory usage by 17.6-42% relative to other scaling strategies. Our analysis reveals that CoE's benefits stem from its iterative residual structure and enhanced expert specialization empowered by iterative routing, which together unlock more expressive representations. Code is available at https://github.com/ZihanWang314/coe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18945</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 02:15:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLPR: Extrapolating RLVR to General Domains without Verifiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18254</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18254.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Yu, Bo Ji, Shouli Wang, Shu Yao, Zefan Wang, Ganqu Cui, Lifan Yuan, Ning Ding, Yuan Yao, Zhiyuan Liu, Maosong Sun, Tat-Seng Chua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) demonstrates promising potential in advancing the reasoning capabilities of LLMs. However, its success remains largely confined to mathematical and code domains. This primary limitation stems from the heavy reliance on domain-specific verifiers, which results in prohibitive complexity and limited scalability. To address the challenge, our key observation is that LLM's intrinsic probability of generating a correct free-form answer directly indicates its own evaluation of the reasoning reward (i.e., how well the reasoning process leads to the correct answer). Building on this insight, we propose RLPR, a simple verifier-free framework that extrapolates RLVR to broader general domains. RLPR uses the LLM's own token probability scores for reference answers as the reward signal and maximizes the expected reward during training. We find that addressing the high variance of this noisy probability reward is crucial to make it work, and propose prob-to-reward and stabilizing methods to ensure a precise and stable reward from LLM intrinsic probabilities. Comprehensive experiments in four general-domain benchmarks and three mathematical benchmarks show that RLPR consistently improves reasoning capabilities in both areas for Gemma, Llama, and Qwen based models. Notably, RLPR outperforms concurrent VeriFree by 7.6 points on TheoremQA and 7.5 points on Minerva, and even surpasses strong verifier-model-dependent approaches General-Reasoner by 1.6 average points across seven benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18254</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 02:56:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LettinGo: Explore User Profile Generation for Recommendation System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18309</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18309.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lu Wang, Di Zhang, Fangkai Yang, Pu Zhao, Jianfeng Liu, Yuefeng Zhan, Hao Sun, Qingwei Lin, Weiwei Deng, Dongmei Zhang, Feng Sun, Qi Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; User profiling is pivotal for recommendation systems, as it transforms raw user interaction data into concise and structured representations that drive personalized recommendations. While traditional embedding-based profiles lack interpretability and adaptability, recent advances with large language models (LLMs) enable text-based profiles that are semantically richer and more transparent. However, existing methods often adhere to fixed formats that limit their ability to capture the full diversity of user behaviors. In this paper, we introduce LettinGo, a novel framework for generating diverse and adaptive user profiles. By leveraging the expressive power of LLMs and incorporating direct feedback from downstream recommendation tasks, our approach avoids the rigid constraints imposed by supervised fine-tuning (SFT). Instead, we employ Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) to align the profile generator with task-specific performance, ensuring that the profiles remain adaptive and effective. LettinGo operates in three stages: (1) exploring diverse user profiles via multiple LLMs, (2) evaluating profile quality based on their impact in recommendation systems, and (3) aligning the profile generation through pairwise preference data derived from task performance. Experimental results demonstrate that our framework significantly enhances recommendation accuracy, flexibility, and contextual awareness. This work enhances profile generation as a key innovation for next-generation recommendation systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18309</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 05:51:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use Property-Based Testing to Bridge LLM Code Generation and Validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18315</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18315.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lehan He, Zeren Chen, Zhe Zhang, Jing Shao, Xiang Gao, Lu Sheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) excel at code generation, but ensuring their outputs to be functionally correct, especially in complex programming tasks, is a persistent challenge. While traditional Test-Driven Development (TDD) offers a path for code refinement, its efficacy with LLMs is often undermined by the scarcity of high-quality test cases or the pitfalls of automated test generation, including biased tests or inaccurate output predictions that can misdirect the correction process. This paper introduces Property-Generated Solver, a novel framework that leverages Property-Based Testing (PBT) to validate high-level program properties or invariants, instead of relying on specific input-output examples. These properties are often simpler to define and verify than directly predicting exhaustive test oracles, breaking the "cycle of self-deception" where tests might share flaws with the code they are meant to validate. Property-Generated Solver employs two collaborative LLM-based agents: a Generator dedicated to code generation and iterative refinement, and a Tester that manages the PBT life-cycle and formulate semantically rich feedback from property violations. The resulting comprehensive and actionable feedback then guides the Generator in its refinement efforts. By establishing PBT as the core validation engine within this iterative, closed-loop paradigm, Property-Generated Solver provides a robust mechanism for steering LLMs towards more correct and generalizable code. Extensive experimental results on multiple code generation benchmarks demonstrate that Property-Generated Solver achieves substantial pass@1 improvements, ranging from 23.1% to 37.3% relative gains over established TDD methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18315</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 06:01:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SlimMoE: Structured Compression of Large MoE Models via Expert Slimming   and Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18349</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18349.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zichong Li, Chen Liang, Zixuan Zhang, Ilgee Hong, Young Jin Kim, Weizhu Chen, Tuo Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Mixture of Experts (MoE) architecture has emerged as a powerful paradigm for scaling large language models (LLMs) while maintaining inference efficiency. However, their enormous memory requirements make them prohibitively expensive to fine-tune or deploy in resource-constrained environments. To address this challenge, we introduce SlimMoE, a multi-stage compression framework for transforming large MoE models into much smaller, efficient variants without incurring the prohibitive costs of training from scratch. Our method systematically reduces parameter counts by slimming experts and transferring knowledge through intermediate stages, effectively mitigating the performance degradation common in one-shot pruning approaches. Using this framework, we compress Phi 3.5-MoE (41.9B total/6.6B activated parameters) to create Phi-mini-MoE (7.6B total/2.4B activated parameters) and Phi-tiny-MoE (3.8B total/1.1B activated parameters) using only 400B tokens--less than 10% of the original model's training data. These compressed models can be fine-tuned on a single GPU (A100 for Phi-mini-MoE, A6000 for Phi-tiny-MoE), making them highly suitable for academic and resource-limited settings. Our experiments demonstrate that these compressed models outperform others of similar size and remain competitive with larger models. For instance, Phi-mini-MoE achieves similar or better performance to Phi-3-mini using only 2/3 of the activated parameters and yields comparable MMLU scores to Llama 3.1 8B despite having significantly lower latency. Our findings demonstrate that structured pruning combined with staged distillation offers an effective path to creating high-quality, compact MoE models, paving the way for broader adoption of MoE architectures. We make our models publicly available at https://huggingface.co/microsoft/Phi-mini-MoE-instruct and https://huggingface.co/microsoft/Phi-tiny-MoE-instruct .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18349</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 07:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Debugging Decay Index: Rethinking Debugging Strategies for Code LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18403</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18403.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muntasir Adnan, Carlos C. N. Kuhn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The effectiveness of AI debugging follows a predictable exponential decay pattern; most models lose 60-80% of their debugging capability within just 2-3 attempts, despite iterative debugging being a critical capability for practical code generation systems. We introduce the Debugging Decay Index (DDI), a mathematical framework that quantifies when debugging becomes ineffective and predicts intervention points. Our strategic fresh start approach shifts from exploitation to exploration at strategic points in the debugging process, demonstrating that well-timed interventions can rescue the effectiveness of debugging. DDI reveals a fundamental limitation in current AI debugging and provides the first quantitative framework for optimising iterative code generation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18403</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 08:40:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-SQL: Illuminating LLM Pathways to Solve User SQL Issues in   Real-World Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18951</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18951.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinyang Li, Xiaolong Li, Ge Qu, Per Jacobsson, Bowen Qin, Binyuan Hui, Shuzheng Si, Nan Huo, Xiaohan Xu, Yue Zhang, Ziwei Tang, Yuanshuai Li, Florensia Widjaja, Xintong Zhu, Feige Zhou, Yongfeng Huang, Yannis Papakonstantinou, Fatma Ozcan, Chenhao Ma, Reynold Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Resolution of complex SQL issues persists as a significant bottleneck in real-world database applications. Current Large Language Models (LLMs), while adept at text-to-SQL translation, have not been rigorously evaluated on the more challenging task of debugging SQL issues. To address this gap, we introduce BIRD-CRITIC, a new SQL issue debugging benchmark comprising 530 PostgreSQL tasks (BIRD-CRITIC-PG) and 570 multi-dialect tasks (BIRD-CRITIC-Multi), distilled from authentic user issues and replayed within new environments to facilitate rigorous evaluation. Baseline evaluations underscore the task's complexity, with the leading reasoning model O3-Mini achieving only 38.87% success rate on BIRD-CRITIC-PG and 33.33% on BIRD-CRITIC-Multi. Meanwhile, advancing open-source models for database tasks is crucial for empowering local development while safeguarding data privacy. Therefore, we present Six-Gym (Sql-fIX-Gym), a training environment for elevating open-source model capabilities for SQL issue debugging. This environment leverages SQL-Rewind strategy, which automatically generates executable issue-solution datasets by reverse-engineering issues from verified SQLs. However, popular trajectory-based fine-tuning methods do not explore substantial supervisory signals. We further propose f-Plan Boosting, which extracts high-level debugging plans from SQL solutions, enabling teacher LLMs to produce 73.7% more successful trajectories for training. We integrate these components into an open-source agent, Bird-Fixer. Based on Qwen-2.5-Coder-14B, Bird-Fixer achieves 38.11% success rate on BIRD-CRITIC-PG and 29.65% on BIRD-CRITIC-Multi, surpassing leading proprietary models such as Claude-3.7-Sonnet and GPT-4.1, marking a significant step toward democratizing sophisticated SQL-debugging capabilities. The leaderboard and source code are available: https://bird-critic.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18951</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 09:41:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DIP: Unsupervised Dense In-Context Post-training of Visual   Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18463</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18463.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sophia Sirko-Galouchenko, Spyros Gidaris, Antonin Vobecky, Andrei Bursuc, Nicolas Thome&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce DIP, a novel unsupervised post-training method designed to enhance dense image representations in large-scale pretrained vision encoders for in-context scene understanding. Unlike prior approaches that rely on complex self-distillation architectures, our method trains the vision encoder using pseudo-tasks that explicitly simulate downstream in-context scenarios, inspired by meta-learning principles. To enable post-training on unlabeled data, we propose an automatic mechanism for generating in-context tasks that combines a pretrained diffusion model and the vision encoder itself. DIP is simple, unsupervised, and computationally efficient, requiring less than 9 hours on a single A100 GPU. By learning dense representations through pseudo in-context tasks, it achieves strong performance across a wide variety of downstream real-world in-context scene understanding tasks. It outperforms both the initial vision encoder and prior methods, offering a practical and effective solution for improving dense representations. Code available here: https://github.com/sirkosophia/DIP&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18463</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 10:01:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Auto-Regressively Generating Multi-View Consistent Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18527</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18527.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; JiaKui Hu, Yuxiao Yang, Jialun Liu, Jinbo Wu, Chen Zhao, Yanye Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating multi-view images from human instructions is crucial for 3D content creation. The primary challenges involve maintaining consistency across multiple views and effectively synthesizing shapes and textures under diverse conditions. In this paper, we propose the Multi-View Auto-Regressive (MV-AR) method, which leverages an auto-regressive model to progressively generate consistent multi-view images from arbitrary prompts. Firstly, the next-token-prediction capability of the AR model significantly enhances its effectiveness in facilitating progressive multi-view synthesis. When generating widely-separated views, MV-AR can utilize all its preceding views to extract effective reference information. Subsequently, we propose a unified model that accommodates various prompts via architecture designing and training strategies. To address multiple conditions, we introduce condition injection modules for text, camera pose, image, and shape. To manage multi-modal conditions simultaneously, a progressive training strategy is employed. This strategy initially adopts the text-to-multi-view (t2mv) model as a baseline to enhance the development of a comprehensive X-to-multi-view (X2mv) model through the randomly dropping and combining conditions. Finally, to alleviate the overfitting problem caused by limited high-quality data, we propose the "Shuffle View" data augmentation technique, thus significantly expanding the training data by several magnitudes. Experiments demonstrate the performance and versatility of our MV-AR, which consistently generates consistent multi-view images across a range of conditions and performs on par with leading diffusion-based multi-view image generation models. Code and models will be released at https://github.com/MILab-PKU/MVAR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18527</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 11:28:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReDit: Reward Dithering for Improved LLM Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18631</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18631.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenxing Wei, Jiarui Yu, Ying Tiffany He, Hande Dong, Yao Shu, Fei Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; DeepSeek-R1 has successfully enhanced Large Language Model (LLM) reasoning capabilities through its rule-based reward system. While it's a ''perfect'' reward system that effectively mitigates reward hacking, such reward functions are often discrete. Our experimental observations suggest that discrete rewards can lead to gradient anomaly, unstable optimization, and slow convergence. To address this issue, we propose ReDit (Reward Dithering), a method that dithers the discrete reward signal by adding simple random noise. With this perturbed reward, exploratory gradients are continuously provided throughout the learning process, enabling smoother gradient updates and accelerating convergence. The injected noise also introduces stochasticity into flat reward regions, encouraging the model to explore novel policies and escape local optima. Experiments across diverse tasks demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of ReDit. On average, ReDit achieves performance comparable to vanilla GRPO with only approximately 10% the training steps, and furthermore, still exhibits a 4% performance improvement over vanilla GRPO when trained for a similar duration. Visualizations confirm significant mitigation of gradient issues with ReDit. Moreover, theoretical analyses are provided to further validate these advantages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18631</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 13:36:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is There a Case for Conversation Optimized Tokenizers in Large Language   Models?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18674</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18674.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Raquel Ferrando, Javier Conde, Gonzalo Martínez, Pedro Reviriego&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The computational and energy costs of Large Language Models (LLMs) have increased exponentially driven by the growing model sizes and the massive adoption of LLMs by hundreds of millions of users. The unit cost of an LLM is the computation of a token. Therefore, the tokenizer plays an important role in the efficiency of a model, and they are carefully optimized to minimize the number of tokens for the text in their training corpus. One of the most popular applications of LLMs are chatbots that interact with users. A key observation is that, for those chatbots, what is important is the performance of the tokenizer in the user text input and the chatbot responses. Those are most likely different from the text in the training corpus. So, a question that immediately arises is whether there is a potential benefit in optimizing tokenizers for chatbot conversations. In this paper, this idea is explored for different tokenizers by using a publicly available corpus of chatbot conversations to redesign their vocabularies and evaluate their performance in this domain. The results show that conversation-optimized tokenizers consistently reduce the number of tokens in chatbot dialogues, which can lead to meaningful energy savings, in the range of 5% to 10% while having minimal or even slightly positive impact on tokenization efficiency for the original training corpus.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18674</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 14:18:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix-Game: Interactive World Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18701</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18701.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Zhang, Chunli Peng, Boyang Wang, Puyi Wang, Qingcheng Zhu, Fei Kang, Biao Jiang, Zedong Gao, Eric Li, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Matrix-Game, an interactive world foundation model for controllable game world generation. Matrix-Game is trained using a two-stage pipeline that first performs large-scale unlabeled pretraining for environment understanding, followed by action-labeled training for interactive video generation. To support this, we curate Matrix-Game-MC, a comprehensive Minecraft dataset comprising over 2,700 hours of unlabeled gameplay video clips and over 1,000 hours of high-quality labeled clips with fine-grained keyboard and mouse action annotations. Our model adopts a controllable image-to-world generation paradigm, conditioned on a reference image, motion context, and user actions. With over 17 billion parameters, Matrix-Game enables precise control over character actions and camera movements, while maintaining high visual quality and temporal coherence. To evaluate performance, we develop GameWorld Score, a unified benchmark measuring visual quality, temporal quality, action controllability, and physical rule understanding for Minecraft world generation. Extensive experiments show that Matrix-Game consistently outperforms prior open-source Minecraft world models (including Oasis and MineWorld) across all metrics, with particularly strong gains in controllability and physical consistency. Double-blind human evaluations further confirm the superiority of Matrix-Game, highlighting its ability to generate perceptually realistic and precisely controllable videos across diverse game scenarios. To facilitate future research on interactive image-to-world generation, we will open-source the Matrix-Game model weights and the GameWorld Score benchmark at https://github.com/SkyworkAI/Matrix-Game.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18701</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 14:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Arena: An Open Platform for Generative 3D Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18787</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18787.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dylan Ebert&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating Generative 3D models remains challenging due to misalignment between automated metrics and human perception of quality. Current benchmarks rely on image-based metrics that ignore 3D structure or geometric measures that fail to capture perceptual appeal and real-world utility. To address this gap, we present 3D Arena, an open platform for evaluating image-to-3D generation models through large-scale human preference collection using pairwise comparisons.   Since launching in June 2024, the platform has collected 123,243 votes from 8,096 users across 19 state-of-the-art models, establishing the largest human preference evaluation for Generative 3D. We contribute the iso3d dataset of 100 evaluation prompts and demonstrate quality control achieving 99.75% user authenticity through statistical fraud detection. Our ELO-based ranking system provides reliable model assessment, with the platform becoming an established evaluation resource.   Through analysis of this preference data, we present insights into human preference patterns. Our findings reveal preferences for visual presentation features, with Gaussian splat outputs achieving a 16.6 ELO advantage over meshes and textured models receiving a 144.1 ELO advantage over untextured models. We provide recommendations for improving evaluation methods, including multi-criteria assessment, task-oriented evaluation, and format-aware comparison. The platform's community engagement establishes 3D Arena as a benchmark for the field while advancing understanding of human-centered evaluation in Generative 3D.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18787</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 15:57:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ViDAR: Video Diffusion-Aware 4D Reconstruction From Monocular Inputs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18792</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18792.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Michal Nazarczuk, Sibi Catley-Chandar, Thomas Tanay, Zhensong Zhang, Gregory Slabaugh, Eduardo Pérez-Pellitero&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Dynamic Novel View Synthesis aims to generate photorealistic views of moving subjects from arbitrary viewpoints. This task is particularly challenging when relying on monocular video, where disentangling structure from motion is ill-posed and supervision is scarce. We introduce Video Diffusion-Aware Reconstruction (ViDAR), a novel 4D reconstruction framework that leverages personalised diffusion models to synthesise a pseudo multi-view supervision signal for training a Gaussian splatting representation. By conditioning on scene-specific features, ViDAR recovers fine-grained appearance details while mitigating artefacts introduced by monocular ambiguity. To address the spatio-temporal inconsistency of diffusion-based supervision, we propose a diffusion-aware loss function and a camera pose optimisation strategy that aligns synthetic views with the underlying scene geometry. Experiments on DyCheck, a challenging benchmark with extreme viewpoint variation, show that ViDAR outperforms all state-of-the-art baselines in visual quality and geometric consistency. We further highlight ViDAR's strong improvement over baselines on dynamic regions and provide a new benchmark to compare performance in reconstructing motion-rich parts of the scene. Project page: https://vidar-4d.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18792</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 16:01:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongWriter-Zero: Mastering Ultra-Long Text Generation via Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18841</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18841.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhao Wu, Yushi Bai, Zhiqiang Hu, Roy Ka-Wei Lee, Juanzi Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Ultra-long generation by large language models (LLMs) is a widely demanded scenario, yet it remains a significant challenge due to their maximum generation length limit and overall quality degradation as sequence length increases. Previous approaches, exemplified by LongWriter, typically rely on ''teaching'', which involves supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on synthetic long-form outputs. However, this strategy heavily depends on synthetic SFT data, which is difficult and costly to construct, often lacks coherence and consistency, and tends to be overly artificial and structurally monotonous. In this work, we propose an incentivization-based approach that, starting entirely from scratch and without relying on any annotated or synthetic data, leverages reinforcement learning (RL) to foster the emergence of ultra-long, high-quality text generation capabilities in LLMs. We perform RL training starting from a base model, similar to R1-Zero, guiding it to engage in reasoning that facilitates planning and refinement during the writing process. To support this, we employ specialized reward models that steer the LLM towards improved length control, writing quality, and structural formatting. Experimental evaluations show that our LongWriter-Zero model, trained from Qwen2.5-32B, consistently outperforms traditional SFT methods on long-form writing tasks, achieving state-of-the-art results across all metrics on WritingBench and Arena-Write, and even surpassing 100B+ models such as DeepSeek R1 and Qwen3-235B. We open-source our data and model checkpoints under https://huggingface.co/THU-KEG/LongWriter-Zero-32B&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18841</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 16:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>USAD: Universal Speech and Audio Representation via Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18843</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18843.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Heng-Jui Chang, Saurabhchand Bhati, James Glass, Alexander H. Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-supervised learning (SSL) has revolutionized audio representations, yet models often remain domain-specific, focusing on either speech or non-speech tasks. In this work, we present Universal Speech and Audio Distillation (USAD), a unified approach to audio representation learning that integrates diverse audio types - speech, sound, and music - into a single model. USAD employs efficient layer-to-layer distillation from domain-specific SSL models to train a student on a comprehensive audio dataset. USAD offers competitive performance across various benchmarks and datasets, including frame and instance-level speech processing tasks, audio tagging, and sound classification, achieving near state-of-the-art results with a single encoder on SUPERB and HEAR benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18843</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phantom-Data : Towards a General Subject-Consistent Video Generation   Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18851</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18851.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuowei Chen, Bingchuan Li, Tianxiang Ma, Lijie Liu, Mingcong Liu, Yi Zhang, Gen Li, Xinghui Li, Siyu Zhou, Qian He, Xinglong Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Subject-to-video generation has witnessed substantial progress in recent years. However, existing models still face significant challenges in faithfully following textual instructions. This limitation, commonly known as the copy-paste problem, arises from the widely used in-pair training paradigm. This approach inherently entangles subject identity with background and contextual attributes by sampling reference images from the same scene as the target video. To address this issue, we introduce Phantom-Data, the first general-purpose cross-pair subject-to-video consistency dataset, containing approximately one million identity-consistent pairs across diverse categories. Our dataset is constructed via a three-stage pipeline: (1) a general and input-aligned subject detection module, (2) large-scale cross-context subject retrieval from more than 53 million videos and 3 billion images, and (3) prior-guided identity verification to ensure visual consistency under contextual variation. Comprehensive experiments show that training with Phantom-Data significantly improves prompt alignment and visual quality while preserving identity consistency on par with in-pair baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18851</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:11:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniGen2: Exploration to Advanced Multimodal Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18871</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18871.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenyuan Wu, Pengfei Zheng, Ruiran Yan, Shitao Xiao, Xin Luo, Yueze Wang, Wanli Li, Xiyan Jiang, Yexin Liu, Junjie Zhou, Ze Liu, Ziyi Xia, Chaofan Li, Haoge Deng, Jiahao Wang, Kun Luo, Bo Zhang, Defu Lian, Xinlong Wang, Zhongyuan Wang, Tiejun Huang, Zheng Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we introduce OmniGen2, a versatile and open-source generative model designed to provide a unified solution for diverse generation tasks, including text-to-image, image editing, and in-context generation. Unlike OmniGen v1, OmniGen2 features two distinct decoding pathways for text and image modalities, utilizing unshared parameters and a decoupled image tokenizer. This design enables OmniGen2 to build upon existing multimodal understanding models without the need to re-adapt VAE inputs, thereby preserving the original text generation capabilities. To facilitate the training of OmniGen2, we developed comprehensive data construction pipelines, encompassing image editing and in-context generation data. Additionally, we introduce a reflection mechanism tailored for image generation tasks and curate a dedicated reflection dataset based on OmniGen2. Despite its relatively modest parameter size, OmniGen2 achieves competitive results on multiple task benchmarks, including text-to-image and image editing. To further evaluate in-context generation, also referred to as subject-driven tasks, we introduce a new benchmark named OmniContext. OmniGen2 achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-source models in terms of consistency. We will release our models, training code, datasets, and data construction pipeline to support future research in this field. Project Page: https://vectorspacelab.github.io/OmniGen2; GitHub Link: https://github.com/VectorSpaceLab/OmniGen2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18871</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:38:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CommVQ: Commutative Vector Quantization for KV Cache Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18879</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18879.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyan Li, Yang Zhang, Muhammad Yusuf Hassan, Talha Chafekar, Tianle Cai, Zhile Ren, Pengsheng Guo, Foroozan Karimzadeh, Colorado Reed, Chong Wang, Chuang Gan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly used in applications requiring long context lengths, but the key-value (KV) cache often becomes a memory bottleneck on GPUs as context grows. To address this, we propose Commutative Vector Quantization (CommVQ) to significantly reduce memory usage for long-context LLM inference. We first introduce additive quantization with a lightweight encoder and codebook to compress the KV cache, which can be decoded via simple matrix multiplication. To further reduce computational costs during decoding, we design the codebook to be commutative with Rotary Position Embedding (RoPE) and train it using an Expectation-Maximization (EM) algorithm. This enables efficient integration of decoding into the self-attention mechanism. Our approach achieves high accuracy with additive quantization and low overhead via the RoPE-commutative codebook. Experiments on long-context benchmarks and GSM8K show that our method reduces FP16 KV cache size by 87.5% with 2-bit quantization, while outperforming state-of-the-art KV cache quantization methods. Notably, it enables 1-bit KV cache quantization with minimal accuracy loss, allowing a LLaMA-3.1 8B model to run with a 128K context length on a single RTX 4090 GPU. The source code is available at: https://github.com/UMass-Embodied-AGI/CommVQ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18879</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:50:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light of Normals: Unified Feature Representation for Universal   Photometric Stereo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18882</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18882.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hong Li, Houyuan Chen, Chongjie Ye, Zhaoxi Chen, Bohan Li, Shaocong Xu, Xianda Guo, Xuhui Liu, Yikai Wang, Baochang Zhang, Satoshi Ikehata, Boxin Shi, Anyi Rao, Hao Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal photometric stereo (PS) aims to recover high-quality surface normals from objects under arbitrary lighting conditions without relying on specific illumination models. Despite recent advances such as SDM-UniPS and Uni MS-PS, two fundamental challenges persist: 1) the deep coupling between varying illumination and surface normal features, where ambiguity in observed intensity makes it difficult to determine whether brightness variations stem from lighting changes or surface orientation; and 2) the preservation of high-frequency geometric details in complex surfaces, where intricate geometries create self-shadowing, inter-reflections, and subtle normal variations that conventional feature processing operations struggle to capture accurately.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18882</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steering Conceptual Bias via Transformer Latent-Subspace Activation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18887</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18887.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vansh Sharma, Venkat Raman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This work examines whether activating latent subspaces in language models (LLMs) can steer scientific code generation toward a specific programming language. Five causal LLMs were first evaluated on scientific coding prompts to quantify their baseline bias among four programming languages. A static neuron-attribution method, perturbing the highest activated MLP weight for a C++ or CPP token, proved brittle and exhibited limited generalization across prompt styles and model scales. To address these limitations, a gradient-refined adaptive activation steering framework (G-ACT) was developed: per-prompt activation differences are clustered into a small set of steering directions, and lightweight per-layer probes are trained and refined online to select the appropriate steering vector. In LLaMA-3.2 3B, this approach reliably biases generation towards the CPP language by increasing the average probe classification accuracy by 15% and the early layers (0-6) improving the probe classification accuracy by 61.5% compared to the standard ACT framework. For LLaMA-3.3 70B, where attention-head signals become more diffuse, targeted injections at key layers still improve language selection. Although per-layer probing introduces a modest inference overhead, it remains practical by steering only a subset of layers and enables reproducible model behavior. These results demonstrate a scalable, interpretable and efficient mechanism for concept-level control for practical agentic systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18887</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:56:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4D-LRM: Large Space-Time Reconstruction Model From and To Any View at   Any Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18890</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18890.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziqiao Ma, Xuweiyi Chen, Shoubin Yu, Sai Bi, Kai Zhang, Chen Ziwen, Sihan Xu, Jianing Yang, Zexiang Xu, Kalyan Sunkavalli, Mohit Bansal, Joyce Chai, Hao Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Can we scale 4D pretraining to learn general space-time representations that reconstruct an object from a few views at some times to any view at any time? We provide an affirmative answer with 4D-LRM, the first large-scale 4D reconstruction model that takes input from unconstrained views and timestamps and renders arbitrary novel view-time combinations. Unlike prior 4D approaches, e.g., optimization-based, geometry-based, or generative, that struggle with efficiency, generalization, or faithfulness, 4D-LRM learns a unified space-time representation and directly predicts per-pixel 4D Gaussian primitives from posed image tokens across time, enabling fast, high-quality rendering at, in principle, infinite frame rate. Our results demonstrate that scaling spatiotemporal pretraining enables accurate and efficient 4D reconstruction. We show that 4D-LRM generalizes to novel objects, interpolates across time, and handles diverse camera setups. It reconstructs 24-frame sequences in one forward pass with less than 1.5 seconds on a single A100 GPU.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18890</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:57:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReasonFlux-PRM: Trajectory-Aware PRMs for Long Chain-of-Thought   Reasoning in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18896</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18896.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaru Zou, Ling Yang, Jingwen Gu, Jiahao Qiu, Ke Shen, Jingrui He, Mengdi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Process Reward Models (PRMs) have recently emerged as a powerful framework for supervising intermediate reasoning steps in large language models (LLMs). Previous PRMs are primarily trained on model final output responses and struggle to evaluate intermediate thinking trajectories robustly, especially in the emerging setting of trajectory-response outputs generated by frontier reasoning models like Deepseek-R1. In this work, we introduce ReasonFlux-PRM, a novel trajectory-aware PRM explicitly designed to evaluate the trajectory-response type of reasoning traces. ReasonFlux-PRM incorporates both step-level and trajectory-level supervision, enabling fine-grained reward assignment aligned with structured chain-of-thought data. We adapt ReasonFlux-PRM to support reward supervision under both offline and online settings, including (i) selecting high-quality model distillation data for downstream supervised fine-tuning of smaller models, (ii) providing dense process-level rewards for policy optimization during reinforcement learning, and (iii) enabling reward-guided Best-of-N test-time scaling. Empirical results on challenging downstream benchmarks such as AIME, MATH500, and GPQA-Diamond demonstrate that ReasonFlux-PRM-7B selects higher quality data than strong PRMs (e.g., Qwen2.5-Math-PRM-72B) and human-curated baselines. Furthermore, our derived ReasonFlux-PRM-7B yields consistent performance improvements, achieving average gains of 12.1% in supervised fine-tuning, 4.5% in reinforcement learning, and 6.3% in test-time scaling. We also release our efficient ReasonFlux-PRM-1.5B for resource-constrained applications and edge deployment. Projects: https://github.com/Gen-Verse/ReasonFlux&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18896</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision as a Dialect: Unifying Visual Understanding and Generation via   Text-Aligned Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18898</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18898.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaming Han, Hao Chen, Yang Zhao, Hanyu Wang, Qi Zhao, Ziyan Yang, Hao He, Xiangyu Yue, Lu Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents a multimodal framework that attempts to unify visual understanding and generation within a shared discrete semantic representation. At its core is the Text-Aligned Tokenizer (TA-Tok), which converts images into discrete tokens using a text-aligned codebook projected from a large language model's (LLM) vocabulary. By integrating vision and text into a unified space with an expanded vocabulary, our multimodal LLM, Tar, enables cross-modal input and output through a shared interface, without the need for modality-specific designs. Additionally, we propose scale-adaptive encoding and decoding to balance efficiency and visual detail, along with a generative de-tokenizer to produce high-fidelity visual outputs. To address diverse decoding needs, we utilize two complementary de-tokenizers: a fast autoregressive model and a diffusion-based model. To enhance modality fusion, we investigate advanced pre-training tasks, demonstrating improvements in both visual understanding and generation. Experiments across benchmarks show that Tar matches or surpasses existing multimodal LLM methods, achieving faster convergence and greater training efficiency. Code, models, and data are available at https://tar.csuhan.com&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18898</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FilMaster: Bridging Cinematic Principles and Generative AI for Automated   Film Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18899</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18899.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaiyi Huang, Yukun Huang, Xintao Wang, Zinan Lin, Xuefei Ning, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Yu Wang, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI-driven content creation has shown potential in film production. However, existing film generation systems struggle to implement cinematic principles and thus fail to generate professional-quality films, particularly lacking diverse camera language and cinematic rhythm. This results in templated visuals and unengaging narratives. To address this, we introduce FilMaster, an end-to-end AI system that integrates real-world cinematic principles for professional-grade film generation, yielding editable, industry-standard outputs. FilMaster is built on two key principles: (1) learning cinematography from extensive real-world film data and (2) emulating professional, audience-centric post-production workflows. Inspired by these principles, FilMaster incorporates two stages: a Reference-Guided Generation Stage which transforms user input to video clips, and a Generative Post-Production Stage which transforms raw footage into audiovisual outputs by orchestrating visual and auditory elements for cinematic rhythm. Our generation stage highlights a Multi-shot Synergized RAG Camera Language Design module to guide the AI in generating professional camera language by retrieving reference clips from a vast corpus of 440,000 film clips. Our post-production stage emulates professional workflows by designing an Audience-Centric Cinematic Rhythm Control module, including Rough Cut and Fine Cut processes informed by simulated audience feedback, for effective integration of audiovisual elements to achieve engaging content. The system is empowered by generative AI models like (M)LLMs and video generation models. Furthermore, we introduce FilmEval, a comprehensive benchmark for evaluating AI-generated films. Extensive experiments show FilMaster's superior performance in camera language design and cinematic rhythm control, advancing generative AI in professional filmmaking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18899</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Virtual Games to Real-World Play</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18901</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18901.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenqiang Sun, Fangyun Wei, Jinjing Zhao, Xi Chen, Zilong Chen, Hongyang Zhang, Jun Zhang, Yan Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce RealPlay, a neural network-based real-world game engine that enables interactive video generation from user control signals. Unlike prior works focused on game-style visuals, RealPlay aims to produce photorealistic, temporally consistent video sequences that resemble real-world footage. It operates in an interactive loop: users observe a generated scene, issue a control command, and receive a short video chunk in response. To enable such realistic and responsive generation, we address key challenges including iterative chunk-wise prediction for low-latency feedback, temporal consistency across iterations, and accurate control response. RealPlay is trained on a combination of labeled game data and unlabeled real-world videos, without requiring real-world action annotations. Notably, we observe two forms of generalization: (1) control transfer-RealPlay effectively maps control signals from virtual to real-world scenarios; and (2) entity transfer-although training labels originate solely from a car racing game, RealPlay generalizes to control diverse real-world entities, including bicycles and pedestrians, beyond vehicles. Project page can be found: https://wenqsun.github.io/RealPlay/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18901</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VMem: Consistent Interactive Video Scene Generation with Surfel-Indexed   View Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18903</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18903.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runjia Li, Philip Torr, Andrea Vedaldi, Tomas Jakab&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel memory mechanism to build video generators that can explore environments interactively. Similar results have previously been achieved by out-painting 2D views of the scene while incrementally reconstructing its 3D geometry, which quickly accumulates errors, or by video generators with a short context window, which struggle to maintain scene coherence over the long term. To address these limitations, we introduce Surfel-Indexed View Memory (VMem), a mechanism that remembers past views by indexing them geometrically based on the 3D surface elements (surfels) they have observed. VMem enables the efficient retrieval of the most relevant past views when generating new ones. By focusing only on these relevant views, our method produces consistent explorations of imagined environments at a fraction of the computational cost of using all past views as context. We evaluate our approach on challenging long-term scene synthesis benchmarks and demonstrate superior performance compared to existing methods in maintaining scene coherence and camera control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18903</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TC-Light: Temporally Consistent Relighting for Dynamic Long Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18904</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18904.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Liu, Chuanchen Luo, Zimo Tang, Yingyan Li, Yuran Yang, Yuanyong Ning, Lue Fan, Junran Peng, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Editing illumination in long videos with complex dynamics has significant value in various downstream tasks, including visual content creation and manipulation, as well as data scaling up for embodied AI through sim2real and real2real transfer. Nevertheless, existing video relighting techniques are predominantly limited to portrait videos or fall into the bottleneck of temporal consistency and computation efficiency. In this paper, we propose TC-Light, a novel paradigm characterized by the proposed two-stage post optimization mechanism. Starting from the video preliminarily relighted by an inflated video relighting model, it optimizes appearance embedding in the first stage to align global illumination. Then it optimizes the proposed canonical video representation, i.e., Unique Video Tensor (UVT), to align fine-grained texture and lighting in the second stage. To comprehensively evaluate performance, we also establish a long and highly dynamic video benchmark. Extensive experiments show that our method enables physically plausible relighting results with superior temporal coherence and low computation cost. The code and video demos are available at https://dekuliutesla.github.io/tclight/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18904</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse-and-Edit: Effective and Fast Image Editing by Cycle Consistency   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19103</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19103.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ilia Beletskii, Andrey Kuznetsov, Aibek Alanov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in image editing with diffusion models have achieved impressive results, offering fine-grained control over the generation process. However, these methods are computationally intensive because of their iterative nature. While distilled diffusion models enable faster inference, their editing capabilities remain limited, primarily because of poor inversion quality. High-fidelity inversion and reconstruction are essential for precise image editing, as they preserve the structural and semantic integrity of the source image. In this work, we propose a novel framework that enhances image inversion using consistency models, enabling high-quality editing in just four steps. Our method introduces a cycle-consistency optimization strategy that significantly improves reconstruction accuracy and enables a controllable trade-off between editability and content preservation. We achieve state-of-the-art performance across various image editing tasks and datasets, demonstrating that our method matches or surpasses full-step diffusion models while being substantially more efficient. The code of our method is available on GitHub at https://github.com/ControlGenAI/Inverse-and-Edit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19103</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 20:34:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thought Anchors: Which LLM Reasoning Steps Matter?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19143</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19143.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Paul C. Bogdan, Uzay Macar, Neel Nanda, Arthur Conmy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning large language models have recently achieved state-of-the-art performance in many fields. However, their long-form chain-of-thought reasoning creates interpretability challenges as each generated token depends on all previous ones, making the computation harder to decompose. We argue that analyzing reasoning traces at the sentence level is a promising approach to understanding reasoning processes. We present three complementary attribution methods: (1) a black-box method measuring each sentence's counterfactual importance by comparing final answers across 100 rollouts conditioned on the model generating that sentence or one with a different meaning; (2) a white-box method of aggregating attention patterns between pairs of sentences, which identified ``broadcasting'' sentences that receive disproportionate attention from all future sentences via ``receiver'' attention heads; (3) a causal attribution method measuring logical connections between sentences by suppressing attention toward one sentence and measuring the effect on each future sentence's tokens. Each method provides evidence for the existence of thought anchors, reasoning steps that have outsized importance and that disproportionately influence the subsequent reasoning process. These thought anchors are typically planning or backtracking sentences. We provide an open-source tool (www.thought-anchors.com) for visualizing the outputs of our methods, and present a case study showing converging patterns across methods that map how a model performs multi-step reasoning. The consistency across methods demonstrates the potential of sentence-level analysis for a deeper understanding of reasoning models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19143</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 21:28:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork-SWE: Unveiling Data Scaling Laws for Software Engineering in   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19290</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19290.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liang Zeng, Yongcong Li, Yuzhen Xiao, Changshi Li, Chris Yuhao Liu, Rui Yan, Tianwen Wei, Jujie He, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Software engineering (SWE) has recently emerged as a crucial testbed for next-generation LLM agents, demanding inherent capabilities in two critical dimensions: sustained iterative problem-solving (e.g., &gt;50 interaction rounds) and long-context dependency resolution (e.g., &gt;32k tokens). However, the data curation process in SWE remains notoriously time-consuming, as it heavily relies on manual annotation for code file filtering and the setup of dedicated runtime environments to execute and validate unit tests. Consequently, most existing datasets are limited to only a few thousand GitHub-sourced instances. To this end, we propose an incremental, automated data-curation pipeline that systematically scales both the volume and diversity of SWE datasets. Our dataset comprises 10,169 real-world Python task instances from 2,531 distinct GitHub repositories, each accompanied by a task specified in natural language and a dedicated runtime-environment image for automated unit-test validation. We have carefully curated over 8,000 successfully runtime-validated training trajectories from our proposed SWE dataset. When fine-tuning the Skywork-SWE model on these trajectories, we uncover a striking data scaling phenomenon: the trained model's performance for software engineering capabilities in LLMs continues to improve as the data size increases, showing no signs of saturation. Notably, our Skywork-SWE model achieves 38.0% pass@1 accuracy on the SWE-bench Verified benchmark without using verifiers or multiple rollouts, establishing a new state-of-the-art (SOTA) among the Qwen2.5-Coder-32B-based LLMs built on the OpenHands agent framework. Furthermore, with the incorporation of test-time scaling techniques, the performance further improves to 47.0% accuracy, surpassing the previous SOTA results for sub-32B parameter models. We release the Skywork-SWE-32B model checkpoint to accelerate future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19290</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 03:53:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mem4Nav: Boosting Vision-and-Language Navigation in Urban Environments   with a Hierarchical Spatial-Cognition Long-Short Memory System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19433</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19433.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lixuan He, Haoyu Dong, Zhenxing Chen, Yangcheng Yu, Jie Feng, Yong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-and-Language Navigation (VLN) in large-scale urban environments requires embodied agents to ground linguistic instructions in complex scenes and recall relevant experiences over extended time horizons. Prior modular pipelines offer interpretability but lack unified memory, while end-to-end (M)LLM agents excel at fusing vision and language yet remain constrained by fixed context windows and implicit spatial reasoning. We introduce Mem4Nav, a hierarchical spatial-cognition long-short memory system that can augment any VLN backbone. Mem4Nav fuses a sparse octree for fine-grained voxel indexing with a semantic topology graph for high-level landmark connectivity, storing both in trainable memory tokens embedded via a reversible Transformer. Long-term memory (LTM) compresses and retains historical observations at both octree and graph nodes, while short-term memory (STM) caches recent multimodal entries in relative coordinates for real-time obstacle avoidance and local planning. At each step, STM retrieval sharply prunes dynamic context, and, when deeper history is needed, LTM tokens are decoded losslessly to reconstruct past embeddings. Evaluated on Touchdown and Map2Seq across three backbones (modular, state-of-the-art VLN with prompt-based LLM, and state-of-the-art VLN with strided-attention MLLM), Mem4Nav yields 7-13 pp gains in Task Completion, sufficient SPD reduction, and &gt;10 pp nDTW improvement. Ablations confirm the indispensability of both the hierarchical map and dual memory modules. Our codes are open-sourced via https://github.com/tsinghua-fib-lab/Mem4Nav.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19433</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 09:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Large Language Models Capture Human Annotator Disagreements?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19467</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19467.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingwei Ni, Yu Fan, Vilém Zouhar, Donya Rooein, Alexander Hoyle, Mrinmaya Sachan, Markus Leippold, Dirk Hovy, Elliott Ash&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human annotation variation (i.e., annotation disagreements) is common in NLP and often reflects important information such as task subjectivity and sample ambiguity. While Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly used for automatic annotation to reduce human effort, their evaluation often focuses on predicting the majority-voted "ground truth" labels. It is still unclear, however, whether these models also capture informative human annotation variation. Our work addresses this gap by extensively evaluating LLMs' ability to predict annotation disagreements without access to repeated human labels. Our results show that LLMs struggle with modeling disagreements, which can be overlooked by majority label-based evaluations. Notably, while RLVR-style (Reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards) reasoning generally boosts LLM performance, it degrades performance in disagreement prediction. Our findings highlight the critical need for evaluating and improving LLM annotators in disagreement modeling. Code and data at https://github.com/EdisonNi-hku/Disagreement_Prediction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19467</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 09:49:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MATE: LLM-Powered Multi-Agent Translation Environment for Accessibility   Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19502</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19502.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aleksandr Algazinov, Matt Laing, Paul Laban&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Accessibility remains a critical concern in today's society, as many technologies are not developed to support the full range of user needs. Existing multi-agent systems (MAS) often cannot provide comprehensive assistance for users in need due to the lack of customization stemming from closed-source designs. Consequently, individuals with disabilities frequently encounter significant barriers when attempting to interact with digital environments. We introduce MATE, a multimodal accessibility MAS, which performs the modality conversions based on the user's needs. The system is useful for assisting people with disabilities by ensuring that data will be converted to an understandable format. For instance, if the user cannot see well and receives an image, the system converts this image to its audio description. MATE can be applied to a wide range of domains, industries, and areas, such as healthcare, and can become a useful assistant for various groups of users. The system supports multiple types of models, ranging from LLM API calling to using custom machine learning (ML) classifiers. This flexibility ensures that the system can be adapted to various needs and is compatible with a wide variety of hardware. Since the system is expected to run locally, it ensures the privacy and security of sensitive information. In addition, the framework can be effectively integrated with institutional technologies (e.g., digital healthcare service) for real-time user assistance. Furthermore, we introduce ModCon-Task-Identifier, a model that is capable of extracting the precise modality conversion task from the user input. Numerous experiments show that ModCon-Task-Identifier consistently outperforms other LLMs and statistical models on our custom data. Our code and data are publicly available at https://github.com/AlgazinovAleksandr/Multi-Agent-MATE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19502</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 10:40:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Outlier-Safe Pre-Training for Robust 4-Bit Quantization of Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19697</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19697.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jungwoo Park, Taewhoo Lee, Chanwoong Yoon, Hyeon Hwang, Jaewoo Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Extreme activation outliers in Large Language Models (LLMs) critically degrade quantization performance, hindering efficient on-device deployment. While channel-wise operations and adaptive gradient scaling are recognized causes, practical mitigation remains challenging. We introduce Outlier-Safe Pre-Training (OSP), a practical guideline that proactively prevents outlier formation rather than relying on post-hoc mitigation. OSP combines three key innovations: (1) the Muon optimizer, eliminating privileged bases while maintaining training efficiency; (2) Single-Scale RMSNorm, preventing channel-wise amplification; and (3) a learnable embedding projection, redistributing activation magnitudes originating from embedding matrices. We validate OSP by training a 1.4B-parameter model on 1 trillion tokens, which is the first production-scale LLM trained without such outliers. Under aggressive 4-bit quantization, our OSP model achieves a 35.7 average score across 10 benchmarks (compared to 26.5 for an Adam-trained model), with only a 2% training overhead. Remarkably, OSP models exhibit near-zero excess kurtosis (0.04) compared to extreme values (1818.56) in standard models, fundamentally altering LLM quantization behavior. Our work demonstrates that outliers are not inherent to LLMs but are consequences of training strategies, paving the way for more efficient LLM deployment. The source code and pretrained checkpoints are available at https://github.com/dmis-lab/Outlier-Safe-Pre-Training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19697</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 15:03:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guidance in the Frequency Domain Enables High-Fidelity Sampling at Low   CFG Scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19713</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19713.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seyedmorteza Sadat, Tobias Vontobel, Farnood Salehi, Romann M. Weber&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Classifier-free guidance (CFG) has become an essential component of modern conditional diffusion models. Although highly effective in practice, the underlying mechanisms by which CFG enhances quality, detail, and prompt alignment are not fully understood. We present a novel perspective on CFG by analyzing its effects in the frequency domain, showing that low and high frequencies have distinct impacts on generation quality. Specifically, low-frequency guidance governs global structure and condition alignment, while high-frequency guidance mainly enhances visual fidelity. However, applying a uniform scale across all frequencies -- as is done in standard CFG -- leads to oversaturation and reduced diversity at high scales and degraded visual quality at low scales. Based on these insights, we propose frequency-decoupled guidance (FDG), an effective approach that decomposes CFG into low- and high-frequency components and applies separate guidance strengths to each component. FDG improves image quality at low guidance scales and avoids the drawbacks of high CFG scales by design. Through extensive experiments across multiple datasets and models, we demonstrate that FDG consistently enhances sample fidelity while preserving diversity, leading to improved FID and recall compared to CFG, establishing our method as a plug-and-play alternative to standard classifier-free guidance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19713</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 15:19:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SRFT: A Single-Stage Method with Supervised and Reinforcement   Fine-Tuning for Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19767</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19767.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqian Fu, Tinghong Chen, Jiajun Chai, Xihuai Wang, Songjun Tu, Guojun Yin, Wei Lin, Qichao Zhang, Yuanheng Zhu, Dongbin Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have achieved remarkable progress in reasoning tasks, yet the optimal integration of Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) and Reinforcement Learning (RL) remains a fundamental challenge. Through comprehensive analysis of token distributions, learning dynamics, and integration mechanisms from entropy-based perspectives, we reveal key differences between these paradigms: SFT induces coarse-grained global changes to LLM policy distributions, while RL performs fine-grained selective optimizations, with entropy serving as a critical indicator of training effectiveness. Building on these observations, we propose Supervised Reinforcement Fine-Tuning (SRFT), a single-stage method that unifies both fine-tuning paradigms through entropy-aware weighting mechanisms. Our approach simultaneously applies SFT and RL to directly optimize the LLM using demonstrations and self-exploration rollouts rather than through two-stage sequential methods. Extensive experiments show that SRFT achieves 59.1% average accuracy, outperforming zero-RL methods by 9.0% on five mathematical reasoning benchmarks and 10.9% on three out-of-distribution benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19767</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 16:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Do Open-Source LLMs Struggle with Data Analysis? A Systematic   Empirical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19794</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19794.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqi Zhu, Yi Zhong, Jintian Zhang, Ziheng Zhang, Shuofei Qiao, Yujie Luo, Lun Du, Da Zheng, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) hold promise in automating data analysis tasks, yet open-source models face significant limitations in these kinds of reasoning-intensive scenarios. In this work, we investigate strategies to enhance the data analysis capabilities of open-source LLMs. By curating a seed dataset of diverse, realistic scenarios, we evaluate models across three dimensions: data understanding, code generation, and strategic planning. Our analysis reveals three key findings: (1) Strategic planning quality serves as the primary determinant of model performance; (2) Interaction design and task complexity significantly influence reasoning capabilities; (3) Data quality demonstrates a greater impact than diversity in achieving optimal performance. We leverage these insights to develop a data synthesis methodology, demonstrating significant improvements in open-source LLMs' analytical reasoning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19794</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:04:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KnowRL: Exploring Knowledgeable Reinforcement Learning for Factuality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19807</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19807.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baochang Ren, Shuofei Qiao, Wenhao Yu, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs), particularly slow-thinking models, often exhibit severe hallucination, outputting incorrect content due to an inability to accurately recognize knowledge boundaries during reasoning. While Reinforcement Learning (RL) can enhance complex reasoning abilities, its outcome-oriented reward mechanism often lacks factual supervision over the thinking process, further exacerbating the hallucination problem. To address the high hallucination in slow-thinking models, we propose Knowledge-enhanced RL, KnowRL. KnowRL guides models to perform fact-based slow thinking by integrating a factuality reward, based on knowledge verification, into the RL training process, helping them recognize their knowledge boundaries. KnowRL guides models to perform fact-based slow thinking by integrating a factuality reward, based on knowledge verification, into the RL training process, helping them recognize their knowledge boundaries. This targeted factual input during RL training enables the model to learn and internalize fact-based reasoning strategies. By directly rewarding adherence to facts within the reasoning steps, KnowRL fosters a more reliable thinking process. Experimental results on three hallucination evaluation datasets and two reasoning evaluation datasets demonstrate that KnowRL effectively mitigates hallucinations in slow-thinking models while maintaining their original strong reasoning capabilities. Our code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/KnowRL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19807</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:17:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Speculative Decoding with Lookahead Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19830</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19830.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yichao Fu, Rui Ge, Zelei Shao, Zhijie Deng, Hao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning models excel by generating long chain-of-thoughts, but decoding the resulting thousands of tokens is slow. Token-level speculative decoding (SD) helps, but its benefit is capped, because the chance that an entire gamma-token guess is correct falls exponentially as gamma grows. This means allocating more compute for longer token drafts faces an algorithmic ceiling -- making the speedup modest and hardware-agnostic. We raise this ceiling with Lookahead Reasoning, which exploits a second, step-level layer of parallelism. Our key insight is that reasoning models generate step-by-step, and each step needs only to be semantically correct, not exact token matching. In Lookahead Reasoning, a lightweight draft model proposes several future steps; the target model expands each proposal in one batched pass, and a verifier keeps semantically correct steps while letting the target regenerate any that fail. Token-level SD still operates within each reasoning step, so the two layers of parallelism multiply. We show Lookahead Reasoning lifts the peak speedup of SD both theoretically and empirically. Across GSM8K, AIME, and other benchmarks, Lookahead Reasoning improves the speedup of SD from 1.4x to 2.1x while preserving answer quality, and its speedup scales better with additional GPU throughput. Our code is available at https://github.com/hao-ai-lab/LookaheadReasoning&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19830</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:48:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SimpleGVR: A Simple Baseline for Latent-Cascaded Video Super-Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19838</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19838.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liangbin Xie, Yu Li, Shian Du, Menghan Xia, Xintao Wang, Fanghua Yu, Ziyan Chen, Pengfei Wan, Jiantao Zhou, Chao Dong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Latent diffusion models have emerged as a leading paradigm for efficient video generation. However, as user expectations shift toward higher-resolution outputs, relying solely on latent computation becomes inadequate. A promising approach involves decoupling the process into two stages: semantic content generation and detail synthesis. The former employs a computationally intensive base model at lower resolutions, while the latter leverages a lightweight cascaded video super-resolution (VSR) model to achieve high-resolution output. In this work, we focus on studying key design principles for latter cascaded VSR models, which are underexplored currently. First, we propose two degradation strategies to generate training pairs that better mimic the output characteristics of the base model, ensuring alignment between the VSR model and its upstream generator. Second, we provide critical insights into VSR model behavior through systematic analysis of (1) timestep sampling strategies, (2) noise augmentation effects on low-resolution (LR) inputs. These findings directly inform our architectural and training innovations. Finally, we introduce interleaving temporal unit and sparse local attention to achieve efficient training and inference, drastically reducing computational overhead. Extensive experiments demonstrate the superiority of our framework over existing methods, with ablation studies confirming the efficacy of each design choice. Our work establishes a simple yet effective baseline for cascaded video super-resolution generation, offering practical insights to guide future advancements in efficient cascaded synthesis systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19838</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:57:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Progressive Generation with Decomposable Flow Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19839</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19839.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Moayed Haji-Ali, Willi Menapace, Ivan Skorokhodov, Arpit Sahni, Sergey Tulyakov, Vicente Ordonez, Aliaksandr Siarohin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating high-dimensional visual modalities is a computationally intensive task. A common solution is progressive generation, where the outputs are synthesized in a coarse-to-fine spectral autoregressive manner. While diffusion models benefit from the coarse-to-fine nature of denoising, explicit multi-stage architectures are rarely adopted. These architectures have increased the complexity of the overall approach, introducing the need for a custom diffusion formulation, decomposition-dependent stage transitions, add-hoc samplers, or a model cascade. Our contribution, Decomposable Flow Matching (DFM), is a simple and effective framework for the progressive generation of visual media. DFM applies Flow Matching independently at each level of a user-defined multi-scale representation (such as Laplacian pyramid). As shown by our experiments, our approach improves visual quality for both images and videos, featuring superior results compared to prior multistage frameworks. On Imagenet-1k 512px, DFM achieves 35.2% improvements in FDD scores over the base architecture and 26.4% over the best-performing baseline, under the same training compute. When applied to finetuning of large models, such as FLUX, DFM shows faster convergence speed to the training distribution. Crucially, all these advantages are achieved with a single model, architectural simplicity, and minimal modifications to existing training pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19839</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:58:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal Finetuning Made Scalable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19847</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19847.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeju Qiu, Weiyang Liu, Adrian Weller, Bernhard Schölkopf&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Orthogonal finetuning (OFT) offers highly parameter-efficient adaptation while preventing catastrophic forgetting, but its high runtime and memory demands limit practical deployment. We identify the core computational bottleneck in OFT as its weight-centric implementation, which relies on costly matrix-matrix multiplications with cubic complexity. To overcome this, we propose OFTv2, an input-centric reformulation that instead uses matrix-vector multiplications (i.e., matrix-free computation), reducing the computational cost to quadratic. We further introduce the Cayley-Neumann parameterization, an efficient orthogonal parameterization that approximates the matrix inversion in Cayley transform via a truncated Neumann series. These modifications allow OFTv2 to achieve up to 10x faster training and 3x lower GPU memory usage without compromising performance. In addition, we extend OFTv2 to support finetuning quantized foundation models and show that it outperforms the popular QLoRA in training stability, efficiency, and memory usage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19847</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ScaleCap: Inference-Time Scalable Image Captioning via Dual-Modality   Debiasing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19848</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19848.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Long Xing, Qidong Huang, Xiaoyi Dong, Pan Zhang, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Jinsong Li, Shuangrui Ding, Weiming Zhang, Nenghai Yu, Jiaqi Wang, Feng Wu, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents ScaleCap, an inference-time scalable image captioning strategy that generates comprehensive and detailed image captions. The key challenges of high-quality image captioning lie in the inherent biases of LVLMs: multimodal bias resulting in imbalanced descriptive granularity, offering detailed accounts of some elements while merely skimming over others; linguistic bias leading to hallucinated descriptions of non-existent objects. To address these issues, we propose a scalable debiased captioning strategy, which continuously enriches and calibrates the caption with increased inference budget. Specifically, we propose two novel components: heuristic question answering and contrastive sentence rating. The former generates content-specific questions based on the image and answers them to progressively inject relevant information into the caption. The latter employs sentence-level offline contrastive decoding to effectively identify and eliminate hallucinations caused by linguistic biases. With increased inference cost, more heuristic questions are raised by ScaleCap to progressively capture additional visual details, generating captions that are more accurate, balanced, and informative. Extensive modality alignment experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of ScaleCap. Annotating 450K images with ScaleCap and using them for LVLM pretraining leads to consistent performance gains across 11 widely used benchmarks. Furthermore, ScaleCap showcases superb richness and fidelity of generated captions with two additional tasks: replacing images with captions in VQA task, and reconstructing images from captions to assess semantic coverage. Code is available at https://github.com/Cooperx521/ScaleCap.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19848</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Vision-Language-Action Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19850</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19850.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqi Wang, Xinghang Li, Wenxuan Wang, Junbo Zhang, Yingyan Li, Yuntao Chen, Xinlong Wang, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language-action models (VLAs) have garnered significant attention for their potential in advancing robotic manipulation. However, previous approaches predominantly rely on the general comprehension capabilities of vision-language models (VLMs) to generate action signals, often overlooking the rich temporal and causal structure embedded in visual observations. In this paper, we present UniVLA, a unified and native multimodal VLA model that autoregressively models vision, language, and action signals as discrete token sequences. This formulation enables flexible multimodal tasks learning, particularly from large-scale video data. By incorporating world modeling during post-training, UniVLA captures causal dynamics from videos, facilitating effective transfer to downstream policy learning--especially for long-horizon tasks. Our approach sets new state-of-the-art results across several widely used simulation benchmarks, including CALVIN, LIBERO, and Simplenv-Bridge, significantly surpassing previous methods. For example, UniVLA achieves 95.5% average success rate on LIBERO benchmark, surpassing pi0-FAST's 85.5%. We further demonstrate its broad applicability on real-world ALOHA manipulation and autonomous driving.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19850</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AnimaX: Animating the Inanimate in 3D with Joint Video-Pose Diffusion   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19851</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.19851.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zehuan Huang, Haoran Feng, Yangtian Sun, Yuanchen Guo, Yanpei Cao, Lu Sheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present AnimaX, a feed-forward 3D animation framework that bridges the motion priors of video diffusion models with the controllable structure of skeleton-based animation. Traditional motion synthesis methods are either restricted to fixed skeletal topologies or require costly optimization in high-dimensional deformation spaces. In contrast, AnimaX effectively transfers video-based motion knowledge to the 3D domain, supporting diverse articulated meshes with arbitrary skeletons. Our method represents 3D motion as multi-view, multi-frame 2D pose maps, and enables joint video-pose diffusion conditioned on template renderings and a textual motion prompt. We introduce shared positional encodings and modality-aware embeddings to ensure spatial-temporal alignment between video and pose sequences, effectively transferring video priors to motion generation task. The resulting multi-view pose sequences are triangulated into 3D joint positions and converted into mesh animation via inverse kinematics. Trained on a newly curated dataset of 160,000 rigged sequences, AnimaX achieves state-of-the-art results on VBench in generalization, motion fidelity, and efficiency, offering a scalable solution for category-agnostic 3D animation. Project page: https://anima-x.github.io/{https://anima-x.github.io/}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19851</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biomed-Enriched: A Biomedical Dataset Enriched with LLMs for Pretraining   and Extracting Rare and Hidden Content</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20331</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20331.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rian Touchent, Nathan Godey, Eric de la Clergerie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Biomed-Enriched, a biomedical text dataset constructed from PubMed via a two-stage annotation process. In the first stage, a large language model annotates 400K paragraphs from PubMed scientific articles, assigning scores for their type (review, study, clinical case, other), domain (clinical, biomedical, other), and educational quality. The educational quality score (rated 1 to 5) estimates how useful a paragraph is for college-level learning. These annotations are then used to fine-tune a small language model, which propagates the labels across the full PMC-OA corpus. The resulting metadata allows us to extract refined subsets, including 2M clinical case paragraphs with over 450K high-quality ones from articles with commercial-use licenses, and to construct several variants via quality filtering and domain upsampling. Clinical text is typically difficult to access due to privacy constraints, as hospital records cannot be publicly shared. Hence, our dataset provides an alternative large-scale, openly available collection of clinical cases from PubMed, making it a valuable resource for biomedical and clinical NLP. Preliminary continual-pretraining experiments with OLMo2 suggest these curated subsets enable targeted improvements, with clinical upsampling boosting performance by ~5% on MMLU ProfMed and educational quality filtering improving MedQA and MedMCQA by ~1%. Combinations of these techniques led to faster convergence, reaching same performance with a third of training tokens, indicating potential for more efficient and effective biomedical pretraining strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20331</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 11:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Agentic System for Rare Disease Diagnosis with Traceable Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20430</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20430.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weike Zhao, Chaoyi Wu, Yanjie Fan, Xiaoman Zhang, Pengcheng Qiu, Yuze Sun, Xiao Zhou, Yanfeng Wang, Ya Zhang, Yongguo Yu, Kun Sun, Weidi Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Rare diseases collectively affect over 300 million individuals worldwide, yet timely and accurate diagnosis remains a pervasive challenge. This is largely due to their clinical heterogeneity, low individual prevalence, and the limited familiarity most clinicians have with rare conditions. Here, we introduce DeepRare, the first rare disease diagnosis agentic system powered by a large language model (LLM), capable of processing heterogeneous clinical inputs. The system generates ranked diagnostic hypotheses for rare diseases, each accompanied by a transparent chain of reasoning that links intermediate analytic steps to verifiable medical evidence.   DeepRare comprises three key components: a central host with a long-term memory module; specialized agent servers responsible for domain-specific analytical tasks integrating over 40 specialized tools and web-scale, up-to-date medical knowledge sources, ensuring access to the most current clinical information. This modular and scalable design enables complex diagnostic reasoning while maintaining traceability and adaptability. We evaluate DeepRare on eight datasets. The system demonstrates exceptional diagnostic performance among 2,919 diseases, achieving 100% accuracy for 1013 diseases. In HPO-based evaluations, DeepRare significantly outperforms other 15 methods, like traditional bioinformatics diagnostic tools, LLMs, and other agentic systems, achieving an average Recall@1 score of 57.18% and surpassing the second-best method (Reasoning LLM) by a substantial margin of 23.79 percentage points. For multi-modal input scenarios, DeepRare achieves 70.60% at Recall@1 compared to Exomiser's 53.20% in 109 cases. Manual verification of reasoning chains by clinical experts achieves 95.40% agreements. Furthermore, the DeepRare system has been implemented as a user-friendly web application http://raredx.cn/doctor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20430</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 13:42:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HiWave: Training-Free High-Resolution Image Generation via Wavelet-Based   Diffusion Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20452</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20452.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tobias Vontobel, Seyedmorteza Sadat, Farnood Salehi, Romann M. Weber&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion models have emerged as the leading approach for image synthesis, demonstrating exceptional photorealism and diversity. However, training diffusion models at high resolutions remains computationally prohibitive, and existing zero-shot generation techniques for synthesizing images beyond training resolutions often produce artifacts, including object duplication and spatial incoherence. In this paper, we introduce HiWave, a training-free, zero-shot approach that substantially enhances visual fidelity and structural coherence in ultra-high-resolution image synthesis using pretrained diffusion models. Our method employs a two-stage pipeline: generating a base image from the pretrained model followed by a patch-wise DDIM inversion step and a novel wavelet-based detail enhancer module. Specifically, we first utilize inversion methods to derive initial noise vectors that preserve global coherence from the base image. Subsequently, during sampling, our wavelet-domain detail enhancer retains low-frequency components from the base image to ensure structural consistency, while selectively guiding high-frequency components to enrich fine details and textures. Extensive evaluations using Stable Diffusion XL demonstrate that HiWave effectively mitigates common visual artifacts seen in prior methods, achieving superior perceptual quality. A user study confirmed HiWave's performance, where it was preferred over the state-of-the-art alternative in more than 80% of comparisons, highlighting its effectiveness for high-quality, ultra-high-resolution image synthesis without requiring retraining or architectural modifications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20452</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 13:58:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPTailor: Large Language Model Pruning Through Layer Cutting and   Stitching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20480</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20480.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guinan Su, Li Shen, Lu Yin, Shiwei Liu, Yanwu Yang, Jonas Geiping&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable capabilities in language understanding and generation. However, such impressive capability typically comes with a substantial model size, which presents significant challenges in deployment and inference. While structured pruning of model parameters offers a promising way to reduce computational costs at deployment time, current methods primarily focus on single model pruning. In this work, we develop a novel strategy to compress models by strategically combining or merging layers from finetuned model variants, which preserves the original model's abilities by aggregating capabilities accentuated in different finetunes. We pose the optimal tailoring of these LLMs as a zero-order optimization problem, adopting a search space that supports three different operations: (1) Layer removal, (2) Layer selection from different candidate models, and (3) Layer merging. Our experiments demonstrate that this approach leads to competitive model pruning, for example, for the Llama2-13B model families, our compressed models maintain approximately 97.3\% of the original performance while removing sim25% of parameters, significantly outperforming previous state-of-the-art methods. The code is available at https://github.com/Guinan-Su/auto-merge-llm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20480</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 14:24:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReCode: Updating Code API Knowledge with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20495</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20495.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoze Wu, Yunzhi Yao, Wenhao Yu, Huajun Chen, Ningyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) exhibit remarkable code generation capabilities but falter when adapting to frequent updates in external library APIs. This critical limitation, stemming from reliance on outdated API knowledge from their training data, even with access to current documentation, impedes reliable code generation in dynamic environments. To tackle this issue, we propose ReCode (rule-based Reinforcement learning for Code Update), a novel framework that mimics human programmer adaptation to API changes. Specifically, we construct a dataset of approximately 2,000 data entries to train the LLMs to perform version migration based on updated information. Then, we introduce a modified string similarity metric for code evaluation as the reward for reinforcement learning. Our experiments demonstrate that ReCode substantially boosts LLMs' code generation performance in dynamic API scenarios, especially on the unseen CodeUpdateArena task. Crucially, compared to supervised fine-tuning, ReCode has less impact on LLMs' general code generation abilities. We apply ReCode on various LLMs and reinforcement learning algorithms (GRPO and DAPO), all achieving consistent improvements. Notably, after training, Qwen2.5-Coder-7B outperforms that of the 32B parameter code instruction-tuned model and the reasoning model with the same architecture. Code is available at https://github.com/zjunlp/ReCode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20495</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 14:41:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OctoThinker: Mid-training Incentivizes Reinforcement Learning Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20512</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20512.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zengzhi Wang, Fan Zhou, Xuefeng Li, Pengfei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Different base language model families, such as Llama and Qwen, exhibit divergent behaviors during post-training with reinforcement learning (RL), especially on reasoning-intensive tasks. What makes a base language model suitable for reinforcement learning? Gaining deeper insight into this question is essential for developing RL-scalable foundation models of the next generation. In this work, we investigate how mid-training strategies shape RL dynamics, focusing on two representative model families: Qwen and Llama. Our study reveals that (1) high-quality mathematical corpora, such as MegaMath-Web-Pro, significantly improve both base model and RL performance, while existing alternatives (e.g., FineMath-4plus) fail to do so; (2) further adding QA-style data, particularly long chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning examples, enhances RL outcomes, and instruction data further unlocks this effect; (3) while long-CoT improves reasoning depth, it can also induce verbosity of model responses and unstability of RL training, underscoring the importance of data formatting; (4) scaling mid-training consistently leads to stronger downstream RL performance. Building on these insights, we introduce a two-stage mid-training strategy, Stable-then-Decay, in which base models are first trained on 200B tokens with a constant learning rate, followed by 20B tokens across three CoT-focused branches with learning rate decay. This yields OctoThinker, a family of models demonstrating strong RL compatibility and closing the performance gap with more RL-friendly model families, i.e., Qwen. We hope our work will help shape pre-training strategies for foundation models in the RL era. To support further research, we release our open-source models along with a curated math reasoning-intensive corpus of over 70 billion tokens (i.e., MegaMath-Web-Pro-Max).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20512</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 14:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Life Gives You Samples: The Benefits of Scaling up Inference   Compute for Multilingual LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20544</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20544.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ammar Khairi, Daniel D'souza, Ye Shen, Julia Kreutzer, Sara Hooker&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in large language models (LLMs) have shifted focus toward scaling inference-time compute, improving performance without retraining the model. A common approach is to sample multiple outputs in parallel, and select one of these as the final output. However, work to date has focused on English and a handful of domains such as math and code. In contrast, we are most interested in techniques that generalize across open-ended tasks, formally verifiable tasks, and across languages. In this work, we study how to robustly scale inference-time compute for open-ended generative tasks in a multilingual, multi-task setting.   Our findings show that both sampling strategy based on temperature variation and selection strategy must be adapted to account for diverse domains and varied language settings. We evaluate existing selection methods, revealing that strategies effective in English often fail to generalize across languages. We propose novel sampling and selection strategies specifically adapted for multilingual and multi-task inference scenarios, and show they yield notable gains across languages and tasks. In particular, our combined sampling and selection methods lead to an average +6.8 jump in win-rates for our 8B models on m-ArenaHard-v2.0 prompts, against proprietary models such as Gemini. At larger scale, Command-A (111B model) equipped with our methods, shows +9.0 improvement in win-rates on the same benchmark with just five samples against single-sample decoding, a substantial increase at minimal cost. Our results underscore the need for language- and task-aware approaches to inference-time compute, aiming to democratize performance improvements in underrepresented languages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20544</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 15:37:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMSearch-R1: Incentivizing LMMs to Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20670</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20670.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinming Wu, Zihao Deng, Wei Li, Yiding Liu, Bo You, Bo Li, Zejun Ma, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Robust deployment of large multimodal models (LMMs) in real-world scenarios requires access to external knowledge sources, given the complexity and dynamic nature of real-world information. Existing approaches such as retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) and prompt engineered search agents rely on rigid pipelines, often leading to inefficient or excessive search behaviors. We present MMSearch-R1, the first end-to-end reinforcement learning framework that enables LMMs to perform on-demand, multi-turn search in real-world Internet environments. Our framework integrates both image and text search tools, allowing the model to reason about when and how to invoke them guided by an outcome-based reward with a search penalty. To support training, We collect a multimodal search VQA dataset through a semi-automated pipeline that covers diverse visual and textual knowledge needs and curate a search-balanced subset with both search-required and search-free samples, which proves essential for shaping efficient and on-demand search behavior. Extensive experiments on knowledge-intensive and info-seeking VQA tasks show that our model not only outperforms RAG-based baselines of the same model size, but also matches the performance of a larger RAG-based model while reducing search calls by over 30%. We further analyze key empirical findings to offer actionable insights for advancing research in multimodal search.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20670</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 17:59:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Blocks World: Moving Things Around in Pictures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20703</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20703.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vaibhav Vavilala, Seemandhar Jain, Rahul Vasanth, D. A. Forsyth, Anand Bhattad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We describe Generative Blocks World to interact with the scene of a generated image by manipulating simple geometric abstractions. Our method represents scenes as assemblies of convex 3D primitives, and the same scene can be represented by different numbers of primitives, allowing an editor to move either whole structures or small details. Once the scene geometry has been edited, the image is generated by a flow-based method which is conditioned on depth and a texture hint. Our texture hint takes into account the modified 3D primitives, exceeding texture-consistency provided by existing key-value caching techniques. These texture hints (a) allow accurate object and camera moves and (b) largely preserve the identity of objects depicted. Quantitative and qualitative experiments demonstrate that our approach outperforms prior works in visual fidelity, editability, and compositional generalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20703</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FaSTA^*: Fast-Slow Toolpath Agent with Subroutine Mining for Efficient   Multi-turn Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20911</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20911.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Advait Gupta, Rishie Raj, Dang Nguyen, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We develop a cost-efficient neurosymbolic agent to address challenging multi-turn image editing tasks such as "Detect the bench in the image while recoloring it to pink. Also, remove the cat for a clearer view and recolor the wall to yellow.'' It combines the fast, high-level subtask planning by large language models (LLMs) with the slow, accurate, tool-use, and local A^* search per subtask to find a cost-efficient toolpath -- a sequence of calls to AI tools. To save the cost of A^* on similar subtasks, we perform inductive reasoning on previously successful toolpaths via LLMs to continuously extract/refine frequently used subroutines and reuse them as new tools for future tasks in an adaptive fast-slow planning, where the higher-level subroutines are explored first, and only when they fail, the low-level A^* search is activated. The reusable symbolic subroutines considerably save exploration cost on the same types of subtasks applied to similar images, yielding a human-like fast-slow toolpath agent "FaSTA^*'': fast subtask planning followed by rule-based subroutine selection per subtask is attempted by LLMs at first, which is expected to cover most tasks, while slow A^* search is only triggered for novel and challenging subtasks. By comparing with recent image editing approaches, we demonstrate FaSTA^* is significantly more computationally efficient while remaining competitive with the state-of-the-art baseline in terms of success rate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20911</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:33:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FineWeb2: One Pipeline to Scale Them All -- Adapting Pre-Training Data   Processing to Every Language</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20920</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20920.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guilherme Penedo, Hynek Kydlíček, Vinko Sabolčec, Bettina Messmer, Negar Foroutan, Amir Hossein Kargaran, Colin Raffel, Martin Jaggi, Leandro Von Werra, Thomas Wolf&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Pre-training state-of-the-art large language models (LLMs) requires vast amounts of clean and diverse text data. While the open development of large high-quality English pre-training datasets has seen substantial recent progress, training performant multilingual LLMs remains a challenge, in large part due to the inherent difficulty of tailoring filtering and deduplication pipelines to a large number of languages. In this work, we introduce a new pre-training dataset curation pipeline based on FineWeb that can be automatically adapted to support any language. We extensively ablate our pipeline design choices on a set of nine diverse languages, guided by a set of meaningful and informative evaluation tasks that were chosen through a novel selection process based on measurable criteria. Ultimately, we show that our pipeline can be used to create non-English corpora that produce more performant models than prior datasets. We additionally introduce a straightforward and principled approach to rebalance datasets that takes into consideration both duplication count and quality, providing an additional performance uplift. Finally, we scale our pipeline to over 1000 languages using almost 100 Common Crawl snapshots to produce FineWeb2, a new 20 terabyte (5 billion document) multilingual dataset which we release along with our pipeline, training, and evaluation codebases.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20920</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 01:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhysRig: Differentiable Physics-Based Skinning and Rigging Framework for   Realistic Articulated Object Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20936</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.20936.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Zhang, Haolan Xu, Chun Feng, Varun Jampani, Narendra Ahuja&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Skinning and rigging are fundamental components in animation, articulated object reconstruction, motion transfer, and 4D generation. Existing approaches predominantly rely on Linear Blend Skinning (LBS), due to its simplicity and differentiability. However, LBS introduces artifacts such as volume loss and unnatural deformations, and it fails to model elastic materials like soft tissues, fur, and flexible appendages (e.g., elephant trunks, ears, and fatty tissues). In this work, we propose PhysRig: a differentiable physics-based skinning and rigging framework that overcomes these limitations by embedding the rigid skeleton into a volumetric representation (e.g., a tetrahedral mesh), which is simulated as a deformable soft-body structure driven by the animated skeleton. Our method leverages continuum mechanics and discretizes the object as particles embedded in an Eulerian background grid to ensure differentiability with respect to both material properties and skeletal motion. Additionally, we introduce material prototypes, significantly reducing the learning space while maintaining high expressiveness. To evaluate our framework, we construct a comprehensive synthetic dataset using meshes from Objaverse, The Amazing Animals Zoo, and MixaMo, covering diverse object categories and motion patterns. Our method consistently outperforms traditional LBS-based approaches, generating more realistic and physically plausible results. Furthermore, we demonstrate the applicability of our framework in the pose transfer task highlighting its versatility for articulated object modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.20936</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 01:58:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Skip the Middle Layers of Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21103</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21103.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tim Lawson, Laurence Aitchison&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Conditional computation is a popular strategy to make Transformers more efficient. Existing methods often target individual modules (e.g., mixture-of-experts layers) or skip layers independently of one another. However, interpretability research has demonstrated that the middle layers of Transformers exhibit greater redundancy, and that early layers aggregate information into token positions. Guided by these insights, we propose a novel architecture that dynamically skips a variable number of layers from the middle outward. In particular, a learned gating mechanism determines whether to bypass a symmetric span of central blocks based on the input, and a gated attention mechanism prevents subsequent tokens from attending to skipped token positions. Residual norms are controlled with a 'sandwich' or 'perilayernorm' scheme and gate sparsity with an adaptive regularization loss. We had aimed to reduce compute requirements for 'simpler' tokens and potentially foster an emergent multi-level representational hierarchy but, at the scales investigated, our approach does not achieve improvements in the trade-off between validation cross-entropy and estimated FLOPs compared to dense baselines with fewer layers. We release our code at https://github.com/tim-lawson/skip-middle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21103</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 09:01:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiLoCoX: A Low-Communication Large-Scale Training Framework for   Decentralized Cluster</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21263</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21263.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ji Qi, WenPeng Zhu, Li Li, Ming Wu, YingJun Wu, Wu He, Xun Gao, Jason Zeng, Michael Heinrich&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The distributed training of foundation models, particularly large language models (LLMs), demands a high level of communication. Consequently, it is highly dependent on a centralized cluster with fast and reliable interconnects. Can we conduct training on slow networks and thereby unleash the power of decentralized clusters when dealing with models exceeding 100 billion parameters? In this paper, we propose DiLoCoX, a low-communication large-scale decentralized cluster training framework. It combines Pipeline Parallelism with Dual Optimizer Policy, One-Step-Delay Overlap of Communication and Local Training, and an Adaptive Gradient Compression Scheme. This combination significantly improves the scale of parameters and the speed of model pre-training. We justify the benefits of one-step-delay overlap of communication and local training, as well as the adaptive gradient compression scheme, through a theoretical analysis of convergence. Empirically, we demonstrate that DiLoCoX is capable of pre-training a 107B foundation model over a 1Gbps network. Compared to vanilla AllReduce, DiLoCoX can achieve a 357x speedup in distributed training while maintaining negligible degradation in model convergence. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first decentralized training framework successfully applied to models with over 100 billion parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21263</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 13:45:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FairyGen: Storied Cartoon Video from a Single Child-Drawn Character</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21272</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21272.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiayi Zheng, Xiaodong Cun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose FairyGen, an automatic system for generating story-driven cartoon videos from a single child's drawing, while faithfully preserving its unique artistic style. Unlike previous storytelling methods that primarily focus on character consistency and basic motion, FairyGen explicitly disentangles character modeling from stylized background generation and incorporates cinematic shot design to support expressive and coherent storytelling. Given a single character sketch, we first employ an MLLM to generate a structured storyboard with shot-level descriptions that specify environment settings, character actions, and camera perspectives. To ensure visual consistency, we introduce a style propagation adapter that captures the character's visual style and applies it to the background, faithfully retaining the character's full visual identity while synthesizing style-consistent scenes. A shot design module further enhances visual diversity and cinematic quality through frame cropping and multi-view synthesis based on the storyboard. To animate the story, we reconstruct a 3D proxy of the character to derive physically plausible motion sequences, which are then used to fine-tune an MMDiT-based image-to-video diffusion model. We further propose a two-stage motion customization adapter: the first stage learns appearance features from temporally unordered frames, disentangling identity from motion; the second stage models temporal dynamics using a timestep-shift strategy with frozen identity weights. Once trained, FairyGen directly renders diverse and coherent video scenes aligned with the storyboard. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our system produces animations that are stylistically faithful, narratively structured natural motion, highlighting its potential for personalized and engaging story animation. The code will be available at https://github.com/GVCLab/FairyGen&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21272</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 13:58:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mind2Web 2: Evaluating Agentic Search with Agent-as-a-Judge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21506</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21506.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Boyu Gou, Zanming Huang, Yuting Ning, Yu Gu, Michael Lin, Weijian Qi, Andrei Kopanev, Botao Yu, Bernal Jiménez Gutiérrez, Yiheng Shu, Chan Hee Song, Jiaman Wu, Shijie Chen, Hanane Nour Moussa, Tianshu Zhang, Jian Xie, Yifei Li, Tianci Xue, Zeyi Liao, Kai Zhang, Boyuan Zheng, Zhaowei Cai, Viktor Rozgic, Morteza Ziyadi, Huan Sun, Yu Su&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic search such as Deep Research systems, where large language models autonomously browse the web, synthesize information, and return comprehensive citation-backed answers, represents a major shift in how users interact with web-scale information. While promising greater efficiency and cognitive offloading, the growing complexity and open-endedness of agentic search have outpaced existing evaluation benchmarks and methodologies, which largely assume short search horizons and static answers. In this paper, we introduce Mind2Web 2, a benchmark of 130 realistic, high-quality, and long-horizon tasks that require real-time web browsing and extensive information synthesis, constructed with over 1,000 hours of human labor. To address the challenge of evaluating time-varying and complex answers, we propose a novel Agent-as-a-Judge framework. Our method constructs task-specific judge agents based on a tree-structured rubric design to automatically assess both answer correctness and source attribution. We conduct a comprehensive evaluation of nine frontier agentic search systems and human performance, along with a detailed error analysis to draw insights for future development. The best-performing system, OpenAI Deep Research, can already achieve 50-70% of human performance while spending half the time, showing a great potential. Altogether, Mind2Web 2 provides a rigorous foundation for developing and benchmarking the next generation of agentic search systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21506</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 17:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MADrive: Memory-Augmented Driving Scene Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21520</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21520.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Polina Karpikova, Daniil Selikhanovych, Kirill Struminsky, Ruslan Musaev, Maria Golitsyna, Dmitry Baranchuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in scene reconstruction have pushed toward highly realistic modeling of autonomous driving (AD) environments using 3D Gaussian splatting. However, the resulting reconstructions remain closely tied to the original observations and struggle to support photorealistic synthesis of significantly altered or novel driving scenarios. This work introduces MADrive, a memory-augmented reconstruction framework designed to extend the capabilities of existing scene reconstruction methods by replacing observed vehicles with visually similar 3D assets retrieved from a large-scale external memory bank. Specifically, we release MAD-Cars, a curated dataset of {sim}70K 360{\deg} car videos captured in the wild and present a retrieval module that finds the most similar car instances in the memory bank, reconstructs the corresponding 3D assets from video, and integrates them into the target scene through orientation alignment and relighting. The resulting replacements provide complete multi-view representations of vehicles in the scene, enabling photorealistic synthesis of substantially altered configurations, as demonstrated in our experiments. Project page: https://yandex-research.github.io/madrive/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21520</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 17:41:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WorldVLA: Towards Autoregressive Action World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21539</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21539.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jun Cen, Chaohui Yu, Hangjie Yuan, Yuming Jiang, Siteng Huang, Jiayan Guo, Xin Li, Yibing Song, Hao Luo, Fan Wang, Deli Zhao, Hao Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present WorldVLA, an autoregressive action world model that unifies action and image understanding and generation. Our WorldVLA intergrates Vision-Language-Action (VLA) model and world model in one single framework. The world model predicts future images by leveraging both action and image understanding, with the purpose of learning the underlying physics of the environment to improve action generation. Meanwhile, the action model generates the subsequent actions based on image observations, aiding in visual understanding and in turn helps visual generation of the world model. We demonstrate that WorldVLA outperforms standalone action and world models, highlighting the mutual enhancement between the world model and the action model. In addition, we find that the performance of the action model deteriorates when generating sequences of actions in an autoregressive manner. This phenomenon can be attributed to the model's limited generalization capability for action prediction, leading to the propagation of errors from earlier actions to subsequent ones. To address this issue, we propose an attention mask strategy that selectively masks prior actions during the generation of the current action, which shows significant performance improvement in the action chunk generation task.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21539</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 17:55:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAM4D: Segment Anything in Camera and LiDAR Streams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21547</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21547.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianyun Xu, Song Wang, Ziqian Ni, Chunyong Hu, Sheng Yang, Jianke Zhu, Qiang Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present SAM4D, a multi-modal and temporal foundation model designed for promptable segmentation across camera and LiDAR streams. Unified Multi-modal Positional Encoding (UMPE) is introduced to align camera and LiDAR features in a shared 3D space, enabling seamless cross-modal prompting and interaction. Additionally, we propose Motion-aware Cross-modal Memory Attention (MCMA), which leverages ego-motion compensation to enhance temporal consistency and long-horizon feature retrieval, ensuring robust segmentation across dynamically changing autonomous driving scenes. To avoid annotation bottlenecks, we develop a multi-modal automated data engine that synergizes VFM-driven video masklets, spatiotemporal 4D reconstruction, and cross-modal masklet fusion. This framework generates camera-LiDAR aligned pseudo-labels at a speed orders of magnitude faster than human annotation while preserving VFM-derived semantic fidelity in point cloud representations. We conduct extensive experiments on the constructed Waymo-4DSeg, which demonstrate the powerful cross-modal segmentation ability and great potential in data annotation of proposed SAM4D.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21547</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 17:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Where to find Grokking in LLM Pretraining? Monitor   Memorization-to-Generalization without Test</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21551</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21551.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyue Li, Chenrui Fan, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Grokking, i.e., test performance keeps improving long after training loss converged, has been recently witnessed in neural network training, making the mechanism of generalization and other emerging capabilities such as reasoning mysterious. While prior studies usually train small models on a few toy or highly-specific tasks for thousands of epochs, we conduct the first study of grokking on checkpoints during one-pass pretraining of a 7B large language model (LLM), i.e., OLMoE. We compute the training loss and evaluate generalization on diverse benchmark tasks, including math reasoning, code generation, and commonsense/domain-specific knowledge retrieval tasks.   Our study, for the first time, verifies that grokking still happens in the pretraining of large-scale foundation models, though different data may enter grokking stages asynchronously. We further demystify grokking's "emergence of generalization" by investigating LLM internal dynamics. Specifically, we find that training samples' pathways (i.e., expert choices across layers) evolve from random, instance-specific to more structured and shareable between samples during grokking. Also, the complexity of a sample's pathway reduces despite the converged loss. These indicate a memorization-to-generalization conversion, providing a mechanistic explanation of delayed generalization. In the study, we develop two novel metrics to quantify pathway distance and the complexity of a single pathway. We show their ability to predict the generalization improvement on diverse downstream tasks. They are efficient, simple to compute and solely dependent on training data. Hence, they have practical value for pretraining, enabling us to monitor the generalization performance without finetuning and test. Theoretically, we show that more structured pathways reduce model complexity and improve the generalization bound.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21551</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whole-Body Conditioned Egocentric Video Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21552</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21552.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yutong Bai, Danny Tran, Amir Bar, Yann LeCun, Trevor Darrell, Jitendra Malik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We train models to Predict Ego-centric Video from human Actions (PEVA), given the past video and an action represented by the relative 3D body pose. By conditioning on kinematic pose trajectories, structured by the joint hierarchy of the body, our model learns to simulate how physical human actions shape the environment from a first-person point of view. We train an auto-regressive conditional diffusion transformer on Nymeria, a large-scale dataset of real-world egocentric video and body pose capture. We further design a hierarchical evaluation protocol with increasingly challenging tasks, enabling a comprehensive analysis of the model's embodied prediction and control abilities. Our work represents an initial attempt to tackle the challenges of modeling complex real-world environments and embodied agent behaviors with video prediction from the perspective of a human.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21552</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 17:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
