<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 00:02:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Speech Translation: Translating Across Space With Binaural   Hearables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18715</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.18715.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tuochao Chen, Qirui Wang, Runlin He, Shyam Gollakota&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Imagine being in a crowded space where people speak a different language and having hearables that transform the auditory space into your native language, while preserving the spatial cues for all speakers. We introduce spatial speech translation, a novel concept for hearables that translate speakers in the wearer's environment, while maintaining the direction and unique voice characteristics of each speaker in the binaural output. To achieve this, we tackle several technical challenges spanning blind source separation, localization, real-time expressive translation, and binaural rendering to preserve the speaker directions in the translated audio, while achieving real-time inference on the Apple M2 silicon. Our proof-of-concept evaluation with a prototype binaural headset shows that, unlike existing models, which fail in the presence of interference, we achieve a BLEU score of up to 22.01 when translating between languages, despite strong interference from other speakers in the environment. User studies further confirm the system's effectiveness in spatially rendering the translated speech in previously unseen real-world reverberant environments. Taking a step back, this work marks the first step towards integrating spatial perception into speech translation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18715</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 21:58:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MediAug: Exploring Visual Augmentation in Medical Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18983</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.18983.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuyin Qi, Zeyu Zhang, Canxuan Gang, Hao Zhang, Lei Zhang, Zhiwei Zhang, Yang Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data augmentation is essential in medical imaging for improving classification accuracy, lesion detection, and organ segmentation under limited data conditions. However, two significant challenges remain. First, a pronounced domain gap between natural photographs and medical images can distort critical disease features. Second, augmentation studies in medical imaging are fragmented and limited to single tasks or architectures, leaving the benefits of advanced mix-based strategies unclear. To address these challenges, we propose a unified evaluation framework with six mix-based augmentation methods integrated with both convolutional and transformer backbones on brain tumour MRI and eye disease fundus datasets. Our contributions are threefold. (1) We introduce MediAug, a comprehensive and reproducible benchmark for advanced data augmentation in medical imaging. (2) We systematically evaluate MixUp, YOCO, CropMix, CutMix, AugMix, and SnapMix with ResNet-50 and ViT-B backbones. (3) We demonstrate through extensive experiments that MixUp yields the greatest improvement on the brain tumor classification task for ResNet-50 with 79.19% accuracy and SnapMix yields the greatest improvement for ViT-B with 99.44% accuracy, and that YOCO yields the greatest improvement on the eye disease classification task for ResNet-50 with 91.60% accuracy and CutMix yields the greatest improvement for ViT-B with 97.94% accuracy. Code will be available at https://github.com/AIGeeksGroup/MediAug.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.18983</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 17:56:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLMs for Engineering: Teaching Models to Design High Powered Rockets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19394</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.19394.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Toby Simonds&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have transformed software engineering, but their application to physical engineering domains remains underexplored. This paper evaluates LLMs' capabilities in high-powered rocketry design through RocketBench, a benchmark connecting LLMs to high-fidelity rocket simulations. We test models on two increasingly complex design tasks: target altitude optimization and precision landing challenges. Our findings reveal that while state-of-the-art LLMs demonstrate strong baseline engineering knowledge, they struggle to iterate on their designs when given simulation results and ultimately plateau below human performance levels. However, when enhanced with reinforcement learning (RL), we show that a 7B parameter model outperforms both SoTA foundation models and human experts. This research demonstrates that RL-trained LLMs can serve as effective tools for complex engineering optimization, potentially transforming engineering domains beyond software development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19394</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2025 23:59:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TF1-EN-3M: Three Million Synthetic Moral Fables for Training Small, Open   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20605</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20605.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mihai Nadas, Laura Diosan, Andrei Piscoran, Andreea Tomescu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Moral stories are a time-tested vehicle for transmitting values, yet modern NLP lacks a large, structured corpus that couples coherent narratives with explicit ethical lessons. We close this gap with TF1-EN-3M, the first open dataset of three million English-language fables generated exclusively by instruction-tuned models no larger than 8B parameters. Each story follows a six-slot scaffold (character -&gt; trait -&gt; setting -&gt; conflict -&gt; resolution -&gt; moral), produced through a combinatorial prompt engine that guarantees genre fidelity while covering a broad thematic space.   A hybrid evaluation pipeline blends (i) a GPT-based critic that scores grammar, creativity, moral clarity, and template adherence with (ii) reference-free diversity and readability metrics. Among ten open-weight candidates, an 8B-parameter Llama-3 variant delivers the best quality-speed trade-off, producing high-scoring fables on a single consumer GPU (&lt;24 GB VRAM) at approximately 13.5 cents per 1,000 fables.   We release the dataset, generation code, evaluation scripts, and full metadata under a permissive license, enabling exact reproducibility and cost benchmarking. TF1-EN-3M opens avenues for research in instruction following, narrative intelligence, value alignment, and child-friendly educational AI, demonstrating that large-scale moral storytelling no longer requires proprietary giant models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20605</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 10:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdaR1: From Long-CoT to Hybrid-CoT via Bi-Level Adaptive Reasoning   Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21659</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21659.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haotian Luo, Haiying He, Yibo Wang, Jinluan Yang, Rui Liu, Naiqiang Tan, Xiaochun Cao, Dacheng Tao, Li Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, long-thought reasoning models achieve strong performance on complex reasoning tasks, but often incur substantial inference overhead, making efficiency a critical concern. Our empirical analysis reveals that the benefit of using Long-CoT varies across problems: while some problems require elaborate reasoning, others show no improvement, or even degraded accuracy. This motivates adaptive reasoning strategies that tailor reasoning depth to the input. However, prior work primarily reduces redundancy within long reasoning paths, limiting exploration of more efficient strategies beyond the Long-CoT paradigm. To address this, we propose a novel two-stage framework for adaptive and efficient reasoning. First, we construct a hybrid reasoning model by merging long and short CoT models to enable diverse reasoning styles. Second, we apply bi-level preference training to guide the model to select suitable reasoning styles (group-level), and prefer concise and correct reasoning within each style group (instance-level). Experiments demonstrate that our method significantly reduces inference costs compared to other baseline approaches, while maintaining performance. Notably, on five mathematical datasets, the average length of reasoning is reduced by more than 50%, highlighting the potential of adaptive strategies to optimize reasoning efficiency in large language models. Our code is coming soon at https://github.com/StarDewXXX/AdaR1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21659</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 14:01:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Interactive Generative Video</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21853</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21853.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiwen Yu, Yiran Qin, Haoxuan Che, Quande Liu, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Kun Gai, Hao Chen, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Interactive Generative Video (IGV) has emerged as a crucial technology in response to the growing demand for high-quality, interactive video content across various domains. In this paper, we define IGV as a technology that combines generative capabilities to produce diverse high-quality video content with interactive features that enable user engagement through control signals and responsive feedback. We survey the current landscape of IGV applications, focusing on three major domains: 1) gaming, where IGV enables infinite exploration in virtual worlds; 2) embodied AI, where IGV serves as a physics-aware environment synthesizer for training agents in multimodal interaction with dynamically evolving scenes; and 3) autonomous driving, where IGV provides closed-loop simulation capabilities for safety-critical testing and validation. To guide future development, we propose a comprehensive framework that decomposes an ideal IGV system into five essential modules: Generation, Control, Memory, Dynamics, and Intelligence. Furthermore, we systematically analyze the technical challenges and future directions in realizing each component for an ideal IGV system, such as achieving real-time generation, enabling open-domain control, maintaining long-term coherence, simulating accurate physics, and integrating causal reasoning. We believe that this systematic analysis will facilitate future research and development in the field of IGV, ultimately advancing the technology toward more sophisticated and practical applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21853</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Generated In-Context Examples Improve LLM Agents for Sequential   Decision-Making Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00234</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.00234.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vishnu Sarukkai, Zhiqiang Xie, Kayvon Fatahalian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Many methods for improving Large Language Model (LLM) agents for sequential decision-making tasks depend on task-specific knowledge engineering--such as prompt tuning, curated in-context examples, or customized observation and action spaces. Using these approaches, agent performance improves with the quality or amount of knowledge engineering invested. Instead, we investigate how LLM agents can automatically improve their performance by learning in-context from their own successful experiences on similar tasks. Rather than relying on task-specific knowledge engineering, we focus on constructing and refining a database of self-generated examples. We demonstrate that even a naive accumulation of successful trajectories across training tasks boosts test performance on three benchmarks: ALFWorld (73% to 89%), Wordcraft (55% to 64%), and InterCode-SQL (75% to 79%)--matching the performance the initial agent achieves if allowed two to three attempts per task. We then introduce two extensions: (1) database-level selection through population-based training to identify high-performing example collections, and (2) exemplar-level selection that retains individual trajectories based on their empirical utility as in-context examples. These extensions further enhance performance, achieving 91% on ALFWorld--matching more complex approaches that employ task-specific components and prompts. Our results demonstrate that automatic trajectory database construction offers a compelling alternative to labor-intensive knowledge engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00234</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:48:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KeySync: A Robust Approach for Leakage-free Lip Synchronization in High   Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00497</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.00497.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Antoni Bigata, Rodrigo Mira, Stella Bounareli, Michał Stypułkowski, Konstantinos Vougioukas, Stavros Petridis, Maja Pantic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Lip synchronization, known as the task of aligning lip movements in an existing video with new input audio, is typically framed as a simpler variant of audio-driven facial animation. However, as well as suffering from the usual issues in talking head generation (e.g., temporal consistency), lip synchronization presents significant new challenges such as expression leakage from the input video and facial occlusions, which can severely impact real-world applications like automated dubbing, but are often neglected in existing works. To address these shortcomings, we present KeySync, a two-stage framework that succeeds in solving the issue of temporal consistency, while also incorporating solutions for leakage and occlusions using a carefully designed masking strategy. We show that KeySync achieves state-of-the-art results in lip reconstruction and cross-synchronization, improving visual quality and reducing expression leakage according to LipLeak, our novel leakage metric. Furthermore, we demonstrate the effectiveness of our new masking approach in handling occlusions and validate our architectural choices through several ablation studies. Code and model weights can be found at https://antonibigata.github.io/KeySync.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00497</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 12:56:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Robust Deep Networks based Multi-Object MultiCamera Tracking System   for City Scale Traffic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00534</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.00534.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muhammad Imran Zaman, Usama Ijaz Bajwa, Gulshan Saleem, Rana Hammad Raza&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision sensors are becoming more important in Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITS) for traffic monitoring, management, and optimization as the number of network cameras continues to rise. However, manual object tracking and matching across multiple non-overlapping cameras pose significant challenges in city-scale urban traffic scenarios. These challenges include handling diverse vehicle attributes, occlusions, illumination variations, shadows, and varying video resolutions. To address these issues, we propose an efficient and cost-effective deep learning-based framework for Multi-Object Multi-Camera Tracking (MO-MCT). The proposed framework utilizes Mask R-CNN for object detection and employs Non-Maximum Suppression (NMS) to select target objects from overlapping detections. Transfer learning is employed for re-identification, enabling the association and generation of vehicle tracklets across multiple cameras. Moreover, we leverage appropriate loss functions and distance measures to handle occlusion, illumination, and shadow challenges. The final solution identification module performs feature extraction using ResNet-152 coupled with Deep SORT based vehicle tracking. The proposed framework is evaluated on the 5th AI City Challenge dataset (Track 3), comprising 46 camera feeds. Among these 46 camera streams, 40 are used for model training and validation, while the remaining six are utilized for model testing. The proposed framework achieves competitive performance with an IDF1 score of 0.8289, and precision and recall scores of 0.9026 and 0.8527 respectively, demonstrating its effectiveness in robust and accurate vehicle tracking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00534</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 14:00:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepCritic: Deliberate Critique with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00662</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.00662.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenkai Yang, Jingwen Chen, Yankai Lin, Ji-Rong Wen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As Large Language Models (LLMs) are rapidly evolving, providing accurate feedback and scalable oversight on their outputs becomes an urgent and critical problem. Leveraging LLMs as critique models to achieve automated supervision is a promising solution. In this work, we focus on studying and enhancing the math critique ability of LLMs. Current LLM critics provide critiques that are too shallow and superficial on each step, leading to low judgment accuracy and struggling to offer sufficient feedback for the LLM generator to correct mistakes. To tackle this issue, we propose a novel and effective two-stage framework to develop LLM critics that are capable of deliberately critiquing on each reasoning step of math solutions. In the first stage, we utilize Qwen2.5-72B-Instruct to generate 4.5K long-form critiques as seed data for supervised fine-tuning. Each seed critique consists of deliberate step-wise critiques that includes multi-perspective verifications as well as in-depth critiques of initial critiques for each reasoning step. Then, we perform reinforcement learning on the fine-tuned model with either existing human-labeled data from PRM800K or our automatically annotated data obtained via Monte Carlo sampling-based correctness estimation, to further incentivize its critique ability. Our developed critique model built on Qwen2.5-7B-Instruct not only significantly outperforms existing LLM critics (including the same-sized DeepSeek-R1-distill models and GPT-4o) on various error identification benchmarks, but also more effectively helps the LLM generator refine erroneous steps through more detailed feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00662</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 17:03:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T2I-R1: Reinforcing Image Generation with Collaborative Semantic-level   and Token-level CoT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00703</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.00703.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dongzhi Jiang, Ziyu Guo, Renrui Zhang, Zhuofan Zong, Hao Li, Le Zhuo, Shilin Yan, Pheng-Ann Heng, Hongsheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in large language models have demonstrated how chain-of-thought (CoT) and reinforcement learning (RL) can improve performance. However, applying such reasoning strategies to the visual generation domain remains largely unexplored. In this paper, we present T2I-R1, a novel reasoning-enhanced text-to-image generation model, powered by RL with a bi-level CoT reasoning process. Specifically, we identify two levels of CoT that can be utilized to enhance different stages of generation: (1) the semantic-level CoT for high-level planning of the prompt and (2) the token-level CoT for low-level pixel processing during patch-by-patch generation. To better coordinate these two levels of CoT, we introduce BiCoT-GRPO with an ensemble of generation rewards, which seamlessly optimizes both generation CoTs within the same training step. By applying our reasoning strategies to the baseline model, Janus-Pro, we achieve superior performance with 13% improvement on T2I-CompBench and 19% improvement on the WISE benchmark, even surpassing the state-of-the-art model FLUX.1. Code is available at: https://github.com/CaraJ7/T2I-R1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00703</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 17:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
