<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:14:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>PixelHacker: Image Inpainting with Structural and Semantic Consistency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20438</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20438.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyang Xu, Kangsheng Duan, Xiaolei Shen, Zhifeng Ding, Wenyu Liu, Xiaohu Ruan, Xiaoxin Chen, Xinggang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Image inpainting is a fundamental research area between image editing and image generation. Recent state-of-the-art (SOTA) methods have explored novel attention mechanisms, lightweight architectures, and context-aware modeling, demonstrating impressive performance. However, they often struggle with complex structure (e.g., texture, shape, spatial relations) and semantics (e.g., color consistency, object restoration, and logical correctness), leading to artifacts and inappropriate generation. To address this challenge, we design a simple yet effective inpainting paradigm called latent categories guidance, and further propose a diffusion-based model named PixelHacker. Specifically, we first construct a large dataset containing 14 million image-mask pairs by annotating foreground and background (potential 116 and 21 categories, respectively). Then, we encode potential foreground and background representations separately through two fixed-size embeddings, and intermittently inject these features into the denoising process via linear attention. Finally, by pre-training on our dataset and fine-tuning on open-source benchmarks, we obtain PixelHacker. Extensive experiments show that PixelHacker comprehensively outperforms the SOTA on a wide range of datasets (Places2, CelebA-HQ, and FFHQ) and exhibits remarkable consistency in both structure and semantics. Project page at https://hustvl.github.io/PixelHacker.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20438</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 05:28:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grokking in the Wild: Data Augmentation for Real-World Multi-Hop   Reasoning with Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20752</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.20752.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Roman Abramov, Felix Steinbauer, Gjergji Kasneci&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 90&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Transformers have achieved great success in numerous NLP tasks but continue to exhibit notable gaps in multi-step factual reasoning, especially when real-world knowledge is sparse. Recent advances in grokking have demonstrated that neural networks can transition from memorizing to perfectly generalizing once they detect underlying logical patterns - yet these studies have primarily used small, synthetic tasks. In this paper, for the first time, we extend grokking to real-world factual data and address the challenge of dataset sparsity by augmenting existing knowledge graphs with carefully designed synthetic data to raise the ratio phi_r of inferred facts to atomic facts above the threshold required for grokking. Surprisingly, we find that even factually incorrect synthetic data can strengthen emergent reasoning circuits rather than degrade accuracy, as it forces the model to rely on relational structure rather than memorization. When evaluated on multi-hop reasoning benchmarks, our approach achieves up to 95-100% accuracy on 2WikiMultiHopQA - substantially improving over strong baselines and matching or exceeding current state-of-the-art results. We further provide an in-depth analysis of how increasing phi_r drives the formation of generalizing circuits inside Transformers. Our findings suggest that grokking-based data augmentation can unlock implicit multi-hop reasoning capabilities, opening the door to more robust and interpretable factual reasoning in large-scale language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.20752</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 13:33:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phi-4-Mini-Reasoning: Exploring the Limits of Small Reasoning Language   Models in Math</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21233</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21233.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran Xu, Baolin Peng, Hany Awadalla, Dongdong Chen, Yen-Chun Chen, Mei Gao, Young Jin Kim, Yunsheng Li, Liliang Ren, Yelong Shen, Shuohang Wang, Weijian Xu, Jianfeng Gao, Weizhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-Thought (CoT) significantly enhances formal reasoning capabilities in Large Language Models (LLMs) by training them to explicitly generate intermediate reasoning steps. While LLMs readily benefit from such techniques, improving reasoning in Small Language Models (SLMs) remains challenging due to their limited model capacity. Recent work by Deepseek-R1 demonstrates that distillation from LLM-generated synthetic data can substantially improve the reasoning ability of SLM. However, the detailed modeling recipe is not disclosed. In this work, we present a systematic training recipe for SLMs that consists of four steps: (1) large-scale mid-training on diverse distilled long-CoT data, (2) supervised fine-tuning on high-quality long-CoT data, (3) Rollout DPO leveraging a carefully curated preference dataset, and (4) Reinforcement Learning (RL) with Verifiable Reward. We apply our method on Phi-4-Mini, a compact 3.8B-parameter model. The resulting Phi-4-Mini-Reasoning model exceeds, on math reasoning tasks, much larger reasoning models, e.g., outperforming DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-7B by 3.2 points and DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Llama-8B by 7.7 points on Math-500. Our results validate that a carefully designed training recipe, with large-scale high-quality CoT data, is effective to unlock strong reasoning capabilities even in resource-constrained small models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21233</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 00:04:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phi-4-reasoning Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21318</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21318.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marah Abdin, Sahaj Agarwal, Ahmed Awadallah, Vidhisha Balachandran, Harkirat Behl, Lingjiao Chen, Gustavo de Rosa, Suriya Gunasekar, Mojan Javaheripi, Neel Joshi, Piero Kauffmann, Yash Lara, Caio César Teodoro Mendes, Arindam Mitra, Besmira Nushi, Dimitris Papailiopoulos, Olli Saarikivi, Shital Shah, Vaishnavi Shrivastava, Vibhav Vineet, Yue Wu, Safoora Yousefi, Guoqing Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Phi-4-reasoning, a 14-billion parameter reasoning model that achieves strong performance on complex reasoning tasks. Trained via supervised fine-tuning of Phi-4 on carefully curated set of "teachable" prompts-selected for the right level of complexity and diversity-and reasoning demonstrations generated using o3-mini, Phi-4-reasoning generates detailed reasoning chains that effectively leverage inference-time compute. We further develop Phi-4-reasoning-plus, a variant enhanced through a short phase of outcome-based reinforcement learning that offers higher performance by generating longer reasoning traces. Across a wide range of reasoning tasks, both models outperform significantly larger open-weight models such as DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Llama-70B model and approach the performance levels of full DeepSeek-R1 model. Our comprehensive evaluations span benchmarks in math and scientific reasoning, coding, algorithmic problem solving, planning, and spatial understanding. Interestingly, we observe a non-trivial transfer of improvements to general-purpose benchmarks as well. In this report, we provide insights into our training data, our training methodologies, and our evaluations. We show that the benefit of careful data curation for supervised fine-tuning (SFT) extends to reasoning language models, and can be further amplified by reinforcement learning (RL). Finally, our evaluation points to opportunities for improving how we assess the performance and robustness of reasoning models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21318</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 05:05:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sadeed: Advancing Arabic Diacritization Through Small Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21635</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21635.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeina Aldallal, Sara Chrouf, Khalil Hennara, Mohamed Motaism Hamed, Muhammad Hreden, Safwan AlModhayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Arabic text diacritization remains a persistent challenge in natural language processing due to the language's morphological richness. In this paper, we introduce Sadeed, a novel approach based on a fine-tuned decoder-only language model adapted from Kuwain 1.5B Hennara et al. [2025], a compact model originally trained on diverse Arabic corpora. Sadeed is fine-tuned on carefully curated, high-quality diacritized datasets, constructed through a rigorous data-cleaning and normalization pipeline. Despite utilizing modest computational resources, Sadeed achieves competitive results compared to proprietary large language models and outperforms traditional models trained on similar domains. Additionally, we highlight key limitations in current benchmarking practices for Arabic diacritization. To address these issues, we introduce SadeedDiac-25, a new benchmark designed to enable fairer and more comprehensive evaluation across diverse text genres and complexity levels. Together, Sadeed and SadeedDiac-25 provide a robust foundation for advancing Arabic NLP applications, including machine translation, text-to-speech, and language learning tools.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21635</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 13:37:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebThinker: Empowering Large Reasoning Models with Deep Research   Capability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21776</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21776.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoxi Li, Jiajie Jin, Guanting Dong, Hongjin Qian, Yutao Zhu, Yongkang Wu, Ji-Rong Wen, Zhicheng Dou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs), such as OpenAI-o1 and DeepSeek-R1, demonstrate impressive long-horizon reasoning capabilities. However, their reliance on static internal knowledge limits their performance on complex, knowledge-intensive tasks and hinders their ability to produce comprehensive research reports requiring synthesis of diverse web information. To address this, we propose WebThinker, a deep research agent that empowers LRMs to autonomously search the web, navigate web pages, and draft research reports during the reasoning process. WebThinker integrates a Deep Web Explorer module, enabling LRMs to dynamically search, navigate, and extract information from the web when encountering knowledge gaps. It also employs an Autonomous Think-Search-and-Draft strategy, allowing the model to seamlessly interleave reasoning, information gathering, and report writing in real time. To further enhance research tool utilization, we introduce an RL-based training strategy via iterative online Direct Preference Optimization (DPO). Extensive experiments on complex reasoning benchmarks (GPQA, GAIA, WebWalkerQA, HLE) and scientific report generation tasks (Glaive) demonstrate that WebThinker significantly outperforms existing methods and strong proprietary systems. Our approach enhances LRM reliability and applicability in complex scenarios, paving the way for more capable and versatile deep research systems. The code is available at https://github.com/RUC-NLPIR/WebThinker.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21776</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 16:25:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Interactive Generative Video</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21853</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2504.21853.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiwen Yu, Yiran Qin, Haoxuan Che, Quande Liu, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Kun Gai, Hao Chen, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Interactive Generative Video (IGV) has emerged as a crucial technology in response to the growing demand for high-quality, interactive video content across various domains. In this paper, we define IGV as a technology that combines generative capabilities to produce diverse high-quality video content with interactive features that enable user engagement through control signals and responsive feedback. We survey the current landscape of IGV applications, focusing on three major domains: 1) gaming, where IGV enables infinite exploration in virtual worlds; 2) embodied AI, where IGV serves as a physics-aware environment synthesizer for training agents in multimodal interaction with dynamically evolving scenes; and 3) autonomous driving, where IGV provides closed-loop simulation capabilities for safety-critical testing and validation. To guide future development, we propose a comprehensive framework that decomposes an ideal IGV system into five essential modules: Generation, Control, Memory, Dynamics, and Intelligence. Furthermore, we systematically analyze the technical challenges and future directions in realizing each component for an ideal IGV system, such as achieving real-time generation, enabling open-domain control, maintaining long-term coherence, simulating accurate physics, and integrating causal reasoning. We believe that this systematic analysis will facilitate future research and development in the field of IGV, ultimately advancing the technology toward more sophisticated and practical applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.21853</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>100 Days After DeepSeek-R1: A Survey on Replication Studies and More   Directions for Reasoning Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00551</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.00551.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chong Zhang, Yue Deng, Xiang Lin, Bin Wang, Dianwen Ng, Hai Ye, Xingxuan Li, Yao Xiao, Zhanfeng Mo, Qi Zhang, Lidong Bing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The recent development of reasoning language models (RLMs) represents a novel evolution in large language models. In particular, the recent release of DeepSeek-R1 has generated widespread social impact and sparked enthusiasm in the research community for exploring the explicit reasoning paradigm of language models. However, the implementation details of the released models have not been fully open-sourced by DeepSeek, including DeepSeek-R1-Zero, DeepSeek-R1, and the distilled small models. As a result, many replication studies have emerged aiming to reproduce the strong performance achieved by DeepSeek-R1, reaching comparable performance through similar training procedures and fully open-source data resources. These works have investigated feasible strategies for supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and reinforcement learning from verifiable rewards (RLVR), focusing on data preparation and method design, yielding various valuable insights. In this report, we provide a summary of recent replication studies to inspire future research. We primarily focus on SFT and RLVR as two main directions, introducing the details for data construction, method design and training procedure of current replication studies. Moreover, we conclude key findings from the implementation details and experimental results reported by these studies, anticipating to inspire future research. We also discuss additional techniques of enhancing RLMs, highlighting the potential of expanding the application scope of these models, and discussing the challenges in development. By this survey, we aim to help researchers and developers of RLMs stay updated with the latest advancements, and seek to inspire new ideas to further enhance RLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00551</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 14:28:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepCritic: Deliberate Critique with Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00662</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.00662.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenkai Yang, Jingwen Chen, Yankai Lin, Ji-Rong Wen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As Large Language Models (LLMs) are rapidly evolving, providing accurate feedback and scalable oversight on their outputs becomes an urgent and critical problem. Leveraging LLMs as critique models to achieve automated supervision is a promising solution. In this work, we focus on studying and enhancing the math critique ability of LLMs. Current LLM critics provide critiques that are too shallow and superficial on each step, leading to low judgment accuracy and struggling to offer sufficient feedback for the LLM generator to correct mistakes. To tackle this issue, we propose a novel and effective two-stage framework to develop LLM critics that are capable of deliberately critiquing on each reasoning step of math solutions. In the first stage, we utilize Qwen2.5-72B-Instruct to generate 4.5K long-form critiques as seed data for supervised fine-tuning. Each seed critique consists of deliberate step-wise critiques that includes multi-perspective verifications as well as in-depth critiques of initial critiques for each reasoning step. Then, we perform reinforcement learning on the fine-tuned model with either existing human-labeled data from PRM800K or our automatically annotated data obtained via Monte Carlo sampling-based correctness estimation, to further incentivize its critique ability. Our developed critique model built on Qwen2.5-7B-Instruct not only significantly outperforms existing LLM critics (including the same-sized DeepSeek-R1-distill models and GPT-4o) on various error identification benchmarks, but also more effectively helps the LLM generator refine erroneous steps through more detailed feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00662</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 17:03:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T2I-R1: Reinforcing Image Generation with Collaborative Semantic-level   and Token-level CoT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00703</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.00703.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dongzhi Jiang, Ziyu Guo, Renrui Zhang, Zhuofan Zong, Hao Li, Le Zhuo, Shilin Yan, Pheng-Ann Heng, Hongsheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in large language models have demonstrated how chain-of-thought (CoT) and reinforcement learning (RL) can improve performance. However, applying such reasoning strategies to the visual generation domain remains largely unexplored. In this paper, we present T2I-R1, a novel reasoning-enhanced text-to-image generation model, powered by RL with a bi-level CoT reasoning process. Specifically, we identify two levels of CoT that can be utilized to enhance different stages of generation: (1) the semantic-level CoT for high-level planning of the prompt and (2) the token-level CoT for low-level pixel processing during patch-by-patch generation. To better coordinate these two levels of CoT, we introduce BiCoT-GRPO with an ensemble of generation rewards, which seamlessly optimizes both generation CoTs within the same training step. By applying our reasoning strategies to the baseline model, Janus-Pro, we achieve superior performance with 13% improvement on T2I-CompBench and 19% improvement on the WISE benchmark, even surpassing the state-of-the-art model FLUX.1. Code is available at: https://github.com/CaraJ7/T2I-R1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00703</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 17:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RM-R1: Reward Modeling as Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02387</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.02387.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiusi Chen, Gaotang Li, Ziqi Wang, Bowen Jin, Cheng Qian, Yu Wang, Hongru Wang, Yu Zhang, Denghui Zhang, Tong Zhang, Hanghang Tong, Heng Ji&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward modeling is essential for aligning large language models (LLMs) with human preferences, especially through reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF). To provide accurate reward signals, a reward model (RM) should stimulate deep thinking and conduct interpretable reasoning before assigning a score or a judgment. However, existing RMs either produce opaque scalar scores or directly generate the prediction of a preferred answer, making them struggle to integrate natural language critiques, thus lacking interpretability. Inspired by recent advances of long chain-of-thought (CoT) on reasoning-intensive tasks, we hypothesize and validate that integrating reasoning capabilities into reward modeling significantly enhances RM's interpretability and performance. In this work, we introduce a new class of generative reward models -- Reasoning Reward Models (ReasRMs) -- which formulate reward modeling as a reasoning task. We propose a reasoning-oriented training pipeline and train a family of ReasRMs, RM-R1. The training consists of two key stages: (1) distillation of high-quality reasoning chains and (2) reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards. RM-R1 improves LLM rollouts by self-generating reasoning traces or chat-specific rubrics and evaluating candidate responses against them. Empirically, our models achieve state-of-the-art or near state-of-the-art performance of generative RMs across multiple comprehensive reward model benchmarks, outperforming much larger open-weight models (e.g., Llama3.1-405B) and proprietary ones (e.g., GPT-4o) by up to 13.8%. Beyond final performance, we perform thorough empirical analysis to understand the key ingredients of successful ReasRM training. To facilitate future research, we release six ReasRM models along with code and data at https://github.com/RM-R1-UIUC/RM-R1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02387</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 06:11:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bielik 11B v2 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02410</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.02410.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Krzysztof Ociepa, Łukasz Flis, Krzysztof Wróbel, Adrian Gwoździej, Remigiusz Kinas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Bielik 11B v2, a state-of-the-art language model optimized for Polish text processing. Built on the Mistral 7B v0.2 architecture and scaled to 11B parameters using depth up-scaling, this model demonstrates exceptional performance across Polish language benchmarks while maintaining strong cross-lingual capabilities. We introduce two key technical innovations: Weighted Instruction Cross-Entropy Loss, which optimizes learning across diverse instruction types by assigning quality-based weights to training examples, and Adaptive Learning Rate, which dynamically adjusts based on context length. Comprehensive evaluation across multiple benchmarks demonstrates that Bielik 11B v2 outperforms many larger models, including those with 2-6 times more parameters, and significantly surpasses other specialized Polish language models on tasks ranging from linguistic understanding to complex reasoning. The model's parameter efficiency and extensive quantization options enable deployment across various hardware configurations, advancing Polish language AI capabilities and establishing new benchmarks for resource-efficient language modeling in less-represented languages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02410</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 07:03:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bielik v3 Small: Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02550</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.02550.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Krzysztof Ociepa, Łukasz Flis, Remigiusz Kinas, Krzysztof Wróbel, Adrian Gwoździej&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Bielik v3, a series of parameter-efficient generative text models (1.5B and 4.5B) optimized for Polish language processing. These models demonstrate that smaller, well-optimized architectures can achieve performance comparable to much larger counterparts while requiring substantially fewer computational resources. Our approach incorporates several key innovations: a custom Polish tokenizer (APT4) that significantly improves token efficiency, Weighted Instruction Cross-Entropy Loss to balance learning across instruction types, and Adaptive Learning Rate that dynamically adjusts based on training progress. Trained on a meticulously curated corpus of 292 billion tokens spanning 303 million documents, these models excel across multiple benchmarks, including the Open PL LLM Leaderboard, Complex Polish Text Understanding Benchmark, Polish EQ-Bench, and Polish Medical Leaderboard. The 4.5B parameter model achieves results competitive with models 2-3 times its size, while the 1.5B model delivers strong performance despite its extremely compact profile. These advances establish new benchmarks for parameter-efficient language modeling in less-represented languages, making high-quality Polish language AI more accessible for resource-constrained applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02550</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 10:39:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Multimodal Understanding and Generation Models: Advances,   Challenges, and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02567</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.02567.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinjie Zhang, Jintao Guo, Shanshan Zhao, Minghao Fu, Lunhao Duan, Guo-Hua Wang, Qing-Guo Chen, Zhao Xu, Weihua Luo, Kaifu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent years have seen remarkable progress in both multimodal understanding models and image generation models. Despite their respective successes, these two domains have evolved independently, leading to distinct architectural paradigms: While autoregressive-based architectures have dominated multimodal understanding, diffusion-based models have become the cornerstone of image generation. Recently, there has been growing interest in developing unified frameworks that integrate these tasks. The emergence of GPT-4o's new capabilities exemplifies this trend, highlighting the potential for unification. However, the architectural differences between the two domains pose significant challenges. To provide a clear overview of current efforts toward unification, we present a comprehensive survey aimed at guiding future research. First, we introduce the foundational concepts and recent advancements in multimodal understanding and text-to-image generation models. Next, we review existing unified models, categorizing them into three main architectural paradigms: diffusion-based, autoregressive-based, and hybrid approaches that fuse autoregressive and diffusion mechanisms. For each category, we analyze the structural designs and innovations introduced by related works. Additionally, we compile datasets and benchmarks tailored for unified models, offering resources for future exploration. Finally, we discuss the key challenges facing this nascent field, including tokenization strategy, cross-modal attention, and data. As this area is still in its early stages, we anticipate rapid advancements and will regularly update this survey. Our goal is to inspire further research and provide a valuable reference for the community. The references associated with this survey are available on GitHub (https://github.com/AIDC-AI/Awesome-Unified-Multimodal-Models).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02567</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 11:18:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voila: Voice-Language Foundation Models for Real-Time Autonomous   Interaction and Voice Role-Play</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02707</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.02707.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yemin Shi, Yu Shu, Siwei Dong, Guangyi Liu, Jaward Sesay, Jingwen Li, Zhiting Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A voice AI agent that blends seamlessly into daily life would interact with humans in an autonomous, real-time, and emotionally expressive manner. Rather than merely reacting to commands, it would continuously listen, reason, and respond proactively, fostering fluid, dynamic, and emotionally resonant interactions. We introduce Voila, a family of large voice-language foundation models that make a step towards this vision. Voila moves beyond traditional pipeline systems by adopting a new end-to-end architecture that enables full-duplex, low-latency conversations while preserving rich vocal nuances such as tone, rhythm, and emotion. It achieves a response latency of just 195 milliseconds, surpassing the average human response time. Its hierarchical multi-scale Transformer integrates the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs) with powerful acoustic modeling, enabling natural, persona-aware voice generation -- where users can simply write text instructions to define the speaker's identity, tone, and other characteristics. Moreover, Voila supports over one million pre-built voices and efficient customization of new ones from brief audio samples as short as 10 seconds. Beyond spoken dialogue, Voila is designed as a unified model for a wide range of voice-based applications, including automatic speech recognition (ASR), Text-to-Speech (TTS), and, with minimal adaptation, multilingual speech translation. Voila is fully open-sourced to support open research and accelerate progress toward next-generation human-machine interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02707</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 15:05:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Multimodal Chain-of-Thought Reward Model through Reinforcement   Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03318</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.03318.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yibin Wang, Zhimin Li, Yuhang Zang, Chunyu Wang, Qinglin Lu, Cheng Jin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 91&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal Reward Models (RMs) have shown significant promise in delivering reward signals to align vision models with human preferences. However, current RMs are generally restricted to providing direct responses or engaging in shallow reasoning processes with limited depth, often leading to inaccurate reward signals. We posit that incorporating explicit long chains of thought (CoT) into the reward reasoning process can significantly strengthen their reliability and robustness. Furthermore, we believe that once RMs internalize CoT reasoning, their direct response accuracy can also be improved through implicit reasoning capabilities. To this end, this paper proposes UnifiedReward-Think, the first unified multimodal CoT-based reward model, capable of multi-dimensional, step-by-step long-chain reasoning for both visual understanding and generation reward tasks. Specifically, we adopt an exploration-driven reinforcement fine-tuning approach to elicit and incentivize the model's latent complex reasoning ability: (1) We first use a small amount of image generation preference data to distill the reasoning process of GPT-4o, which is then used for the model's cold start to learn the format and structure of CoT reasoning. (2) Subsequently, by leveraging the model's prior knowledge and generalization capabilities, we prepare large-scale unified multimodal preference data to elicit the model's reasoning process across various vision tasks. During this phase, correct reasoning outputs are retained for rejection sampling to refine the model (3) while incorrect predicted samples are finally used for Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) based reinforcement fine-tuning, enabling the model to explore diverse reasoning paths and optimize for correct and robust solutions. Extensive experiments across various vision reward tasks demonstrate the superiority of our model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03318</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 08:46:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absolute Zero: Reinforced Self-play Reasoning with Zero Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03335</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.03335.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Andrew Zhao, Yiran Wu, Yang Yue, Tong Wu, Quentin Xu, Yang Yue, Matthieu Lin, Shenzhi Wang, Qingyun Wu, Zilong Zheng, Gao Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 165&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) has shown promise in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models by learning directly from outcome-based rewards. Recent RLVR works that operate under the zero setting avoid supervision in labeling the reasoning process, but still depend on manually curated collections of questions and answers for training. The scarcity of high-quality, human-produced examples raises concerns about the long-term scalability of relying on human supervision, a challenge already evident in the domain of language model pretraining. Furthermore, in a hypothetical future where AI surpasses human intelligence, tasks provided by humans may offer limited learning potential for a superintelligent system. To address these concerns, we propose a new RLVR paradigm called Absolute Zero, in which a single model learns to propose tasks that maximize its own learning progress and improves reasoning by solving them, without relying on any external data. Under this paradigm, we introduce the Absolute Zero Reasoner (AZR), a system that self-evolves its training curriculum and reasoning ability by using a code executor to both validate proposed code reasoning tasks and verify answers, serving as an unified source of verifiable reward to guide open-ended yet grounded learning. Despite being trained entirely without external data, AZR achieves overall SOTA performance on coding and mathematical reasoning tasks, outperforming existing zero-setting models that rely on tens of thousands of in-domain human-curated examples. Furthermore, we demonstrate that AZR can be effectively applied across different model scales and is compatible with various model classes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03335</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 09:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeCLIP: Decoupled Learning for Open-Vocabulary Dense Perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04410</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.04410.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junjie Wang, Bin Chen, Yulin Li, Bin Kang, Yichi Chen, Zhuotao Tian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Dense visual prediction tasks have been constrained by their reliance on predefined categories, limiting their applicability in real-world scenarios where visual concepts are unbounded. While Vision-Language Models (VLMs) like CLIP have shown promise in open-vocabulary tasks, their direct application to dense prediction often leads to suboptimal performance due to limitations in local feature representation. In this work, we present our observation that CLIP's image tokens struggle to effectively aggregate information from spatially or semantically related regions, resulting in features that lack local discriminability and spatial consistency. To address this issue, we propose DeCLIP, a novel framework that enhances CLIP by decoupling the self-attention module to obtain ``content'' and ``context'' features respectively. The ``content'' features are aligned with image crop representations to improve local discriminability, while ``context'' features learn to retain the spatial correlations under the guidance of vision foundation models, such as DINO. Extensive experiments demonstrate that DeCLIP significantly outperforms existing methods across multiple open-vocabulary dense prediction tasks, including object detection and semantic segmentation. Code is available at magenta{https://github.com/xiaomoguhz/DeCLIP}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04410</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 13:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZeroSearch: Incentivize the Search Capability of LLMs without Searching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04588</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.04588.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Sun, Zile Qiao, Jiayan Guo, Xuanbo Fan, Yingyan Hou, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Yan Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Effective information searching is essential for enhancing the reasoning and generation capabilities of large language models (LLMs). Recent research has explored using reinforcement learning (RL) to improve LLMs' search capabilities by interacting with live search engines in real-world environments. While these approaches show promising results, they face two major challenges: (1) Uncontrolled Document Quality: The quality of documents returned by search engines is often unpredictable, introducing noise and instability into the training process. (2) Prohibitively High API Costs: RL training requires frequent rollouts, potentially involving hundreds of thousands of search requests, which incur substantial API expenses and severely constrain scalability. To address these challenges, we introduce ZeroSearch, a reinforcement learning framework that incentivizes the search capabilities of LLMs without interacting with real search engines. Our approach begins with lightweight supervised fine-tuning to transform the LLM into a retrieval module capable of generating both relevant and noisy documents in response to a query. During RL training, we employ a curriculum-based rollout strategy that incrementally degrades the quality of generated documents, progressively eliciting the model's reasoning ability by exposing it to increasingly challenging retrieval scenarios. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ZeroSearch effectively incentivizes the search capabilities of LLMs using a 3B LLM as the retrieval module. Remarkably, a 7B retrieval module achieves comparable performance to the real search engine, while a 14B retrieval module even surpasses it. Furthermore, it generalizes well across both base and instruction-tuned models of various parameter sizes and is compatible with a wide range of RL algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04588</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 17:30:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Path to Multimodal Generalist: General-Level and General-Bench</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04620</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.04620.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Fei, Yuan Zhou, Juncheng Li, Xiangtai Li, Qingshan Xu, Bobo Li, Shengqiong Wu, Yaoting Wang, Junbao Zhou, Jiahao Meng, Qingyu Shi, Zhiyuan Zhou, Liangtao Shi, Minghe Gao, Daoan Zhang, Zhiqi Ge, Weiming Wu, Siliang Tang, Kaihang Pan, Yaobo Ye, Haobo Yuan, Tao Zhang, Tianjie Ju, Zixiang Meng, Shilin Xu, Liyu Jia, Wentao Hu, Meng Luo, Jiebo Luo, Tat-Seng Chua, Shuicheng Yan, Hanwang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 78&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Multimodal Large Language Model (MLLM) is currently experiencing rapid growth, driven by the advanced capabilities of LLMs. Unlike earlier specialists, existing MLLMs are evolving towards a Multimodal Generalist paradigm. Initially limited to understanding multiple modalities, these models have advanced to not only comprehend but also generate across modalities. Their capabilities have expanded from coarse-grained to fine-grained multimodal understanding and from supporting limited modalities to arbitrary ones. While many benchmarks exist to assess MLLMs, a critical question arises: Can we simply assume that higher performance across tasks indicates a stronger MLLM capability, bringing us closer to human-level AI? We argue that the answer is not as straightforward as it seems. This project introduces General-Level, an evaluation framework that defines 5-scale levels of MLLM performance and generality, offering a methodology to compare MLLMs and gauge the progress of existing systems towards more robust multimodal generalists and, ultimately, towards AGI. At the core of the framework is the concept of Synergy, which measures whether models maintain consistent capabilities across comprehension and generation, and across multiple modalities. To support this evaluation, we present General-Bench, which encompasses a broader spectrum of skills, modalities, formats, and capabilities, including over 700 tasks and 325,800 instances. The evaluation results that involve over 100 existing state-of-the-art MLLMs uncover the capability rankings of generalists, highlighting the challenges in reaching genuine AI. We expect this project to pave the way for future research on next-generation multimodal foundation models, providing a robust infrastructure to accelerate the realization of AGI. Project page: https://generalist.top/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04620</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 17:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perception, Reason, Think, and Plan: A Survey on Large Multimodal   Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04921</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.04921.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunxin Li, Zhenyu Liu, Zitao Li, Xuanyu Zhang, Zhenran Xu, Xinyu Chen, Haoyuan Shi, Shenyuan Jiang, Xintong Wang, Jifang Wang, Shouzheng Huang, Xinping Zhao, Borui Jiang, Lanqing Hong, Longyue Wang, Zhuotao Tian, Baoxing Huai, Wenhan Luo, Weihua Luo, Zheng Zhang, Baotian Hu, Min Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 170&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning lies at the heart of intelligence, shaping the ability to make decisions, draw conclusions, and generalize across domains. In artificial intelligence, as systems increasingly operate in open, uncertain, and multimodal environments, reasoning becomes essential for enabling robust and adaptive behavior. Large Multimodal Reasoning Models (LMRMs) have emerged as a promising paradigm, integrating modalities such as text, images, audio, and video to support complex reasoning capabilities and aiming to achieve comprehensive perception, precise understanding, and deep reasoning. As research advances, multimodal reasoning has rapidly evolved from modular, perception-driven pipelines to unified, language-centric frameworks that offer more coherent cross-modal understanding. While instruction tuning and reinforcement learning have improved model reasoning, significant challenges remain in omni-modal generalization, reasoning depth, and agentic behavior. To address these issues, we present a comprehensive and structured survey of multimodal reasoning research, organized around a four-stage developmental roadmap that reflects the field's shifting design philosophies and emerging capabilities. First, we review early efforts based on task-specific modules, where reasoning was implicitly embedded across stages of representation, alignment, and fusion. Next, we examine recent approaches that unify reasoning into multimodal LLMs, with advances such as Multimodal Chain-of-Thought (MCoT) and multimodal reinforcement learning enabling richer and more structured reasoning chains. Finally, drawing on empirical insights from challenging benchmarks and experimental cases of OpenAI O3 and O4-mini, we discuss the conceptual direction of native large multimodal reasoning models (N-LMRMs), which aim to support scalable, agentic, and adaptive reasoning and planning in complex, real-world environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04921</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 03:35:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flow-GRPO: Training Flow Matching Models via Online RL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05470</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.05470.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jie Liu, Gongye Liu, Jiajun Liang, Yangguang Li, Jiaheng Liu, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Wanli Ouyang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 76&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose Flow-GRPO, the first method integrating online reinforcement learning (RL) into flow matching models. Our approach uses two key strategies: (1) an ODE-to-SDE conversion that transforms a deterministic Ordinary Differential Equation (ODE) into an equivalent Stochastic Differential Equation (SDE) that matches the original model's marginal distribution at all timesteps, enabling statistical sampling for RL exploration; and (2) a Denoising Reduction strategy that reduces training denoising steps while retaining the original inference timestep number, significantly improving sampling efficiency without performance degradation. Empirically, Flow-GRPO is effective across multiple text-to-image tasks. For complex compositions, RL-tuned SD3.5 generates nearly perfect object counts, spatial relations, and fine-grained attributes, boosting GenEval accuracy from 63% to 95%. In visual text rendering, its accuracy improves from 59% to 92%, significantly enhancing text generation. Flow-GRPO also achieves substantial gains in human preference alignment. Notably, little to no reward hacking occurred, meaning rewards did not increase at the cost of image quality or diversity, and both remained stable in our experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05470</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 17:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seed1.5-VL Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07062</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.07062.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dong Guo, Faming Wu, Feida Zhu, Fuxing Leng, Guang Shi, Haobin Chen, Haoqi Fan, Jian Wang, Jianyu Jiang, Jiawei Wang, Jingji Chen, Jingjia Huang, Kang Lei, Liping Yuan, Lishu Luo, Pengfei Liu, Qinghao Ye, Rui Qian, Shen Yan, Shixiong Zhao, Shuai Peng, Shuangye Li, Sihang Yuan, Sijin Wu, Tianheng Cheng, Weiwei Liu, Wenqian Wang, Xianhan Zeng, Xiao Liu, Xiaobo Qin, Xiaohan Ding, Xiaojun Xiao, Xiaoying Zhang, Xuanwei Zhang, Xuehan Xiong, Yanghua Peng, Yangrui Chen, Yanwei Li, Yanxu Hu, Yi Lin, Yiyuan Hu, Yiyuan Zhang, Youbin Wu, Yu Li, Yudong Liu, Yue Ling, Yujia Qin, Zanbo Wang, Zhiwu He, Aoxue Zhang, Bairen Yi, Bencheng Liao, Can Huang, Can Zhang, Chaorui Deng, Chaoyi Deng, Cheng Lin, Cheng Yuan, Chenggang Li, Chenhui Gou, Chenwei Lou, Chengzhi Wei, Chundian Liu, Chunyuan Li, Deyao Zhu, Donghong Zhong, Feng Li, Feng Zhang, Gang Wu, Guodong Li, Guohong Xiao, Haibin Lin, Haihua Yang, Haoming Wang, Heng Ji, Hongxiang Hao, Hui Shen, Huixia Li, Jiahao Li, Jialong Wu, Jianhua Zhu, Jianpeng Jiao, Jiashi Feng, Jiaze Chen, Jianhui Duan, Jihao Liu, Jin Zeng, Jingqun Tang, Jingyu Sun, Joya Chen, Jun Long, Junda Feng, Junfeng Zhan, Junjie Fang, Junting Lu, Kai Hua, Kai Liu, Kai Shen, Kaiyuan Zhang, Ke Shen, Ke Wang, Keyu Pan, Kun Zhang, Kunchang Li, Lanxin Li, Lei Li, Lei Shi, Li Han, Liang Xiang, Liangqiang Chen, Lin Chen, Lin Li, Lin Yan, Liying Chi, Longxiang Liu, Mengfei Du, Mingxuan Wang, Ningxin Pan, Peibin Chen, Pengfei Chen, Pengfei Wu, Qingqing Yuan, Qingyao Shuai, Qiuyan Tao, Renjie Zheng, Renrui Zhang, Ru Zhang, Rui Wang, Rui Yang, Rui Zhao, Shaoqiang Xu, Shihao Liang, Shipeng Yan, Shu Zhong, Shuaishuai Cao, Shuangzhi Wu, Shufan Liu, Shuhan Chang, Songhua Cai, Tenglong Ao, Tianhao Yang, Tingting Zhang, Wanjun Zhong, Wei Jia, Wei Weng, Weihao Yu, Wenhao Huang, Wenjia Zhu, Wenli Yang, Wenzhi Wang, Xiang Long, XiangRui Yin, Xiao Li, Xiaolei Zhu, Xiaoying Jia, Xijin Zhang, Xin Liu, Xinchen Zhang, Xinyu Yang, Xiongcai Luo, Xiuli Chen, Xuantong Zhong, Xuefeng Xiao, Xujing Li, Yan Wu, Yawei Wen, Yifan Du, Yihao Zhang, Yining Ye, Yonghui Wu, Yu Liu, Yu Yue, Yufeng Zhou, Yufeng Yuan, Yuhang Xu, Yuhong Yang, Yun Zhang, Yunhao Fang, Yuntao Li, Yurui Ren, Yuwen Xiong, Zehua Hong, Zehua Wang, Zewei Sun, Zeyu Wang, Zhao Cai, Zhaoyue Zha, Zhecheng An, Zhehui Zhao, Zhengzhuo Xu, Zhipeng Chen, Zhiyong Wu, Zhuofan Zheng, Zihao Wang, Zilong Huang, Ziyu Zhu, Zuquan Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 140&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Seed1.5-VL, a vision-language foundation model designed to advance general-purpose multimodal understanding and reasoning. Seed1.5-VL is composed with a 532M-parameter vision encoder and a Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) LLM of 20B active parameters. Despite its relatively compact architecture, it delivers strong performance across a wide spectrum of public VLM benchmarks and internal evaluation suites, achieving the state-of-the-art performance on 38 out of 60 public benchmarks. Moreover, in agent-centric tasks such as GUI control and gameplay, Seed1.5-VL outperforms leading multimodal systems, including OpenAI CUA and Claude 3.7. Beyond visual and video understanding, it also demonstrates strong reasoning abilities, making it particularly effective for multimodal reasoning challenges such as visual puzzles. We believe these capabilities will empower broader applications across diverse tasks. In this report, we mainly provide a comprehensive review of our experiences in building Seed1.5-VL across model design, data construction, and training at various stages, hoping that this report can inspire further research. Seed1.5-VL is now accessible at https://www.volcengine.com/ (Volcano Engine Model ID: doubao-1-5-thinking-vision-pro-250428)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07062</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 17:28:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Continuous Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07447</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.07447.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peng Sun, Yi Jiang, Tao Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in continuous generative models, including multi-step approaches like diffusion and flow-matching (typically requiring 8-1000 sampling steps) and few-step methods such as consistency models (typically 1-8 steps), have demonstrated impressive generative performance. However, existing work often treats these approaches as distinct paradigms, resulting in separate training and sampling methodologies. We introduce a unified framework for training, sampling, and analyzing these models. Our implementation, the Unified Continuous Generative Models Trainer and Sampler (UCGM-{T,S}), achieves state-of-the-art (SOTA) performance. For example, on ImageNet 256x256 using a 675M diffusion transformer, UCGM-T trains a multi-step model achieving 1.30 FID in 20 steps and a few-step model reaching 1.42 FID in just 2 steps. Additionally, applying UCGM-S to a pre-trained model (previously 1.26 FID at 250 steps) improves performance to 1.06 FID in only 40 steps. Code is available at: https://github.com/LINs-lab/UCGM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07447</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 11:15:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiniMax-Speech: Intrinsic Zero-Shot Text-to-Speech with a Learnable   Speaker Encoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07916</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.07916.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bowen Zhang, Congchao Guo, Geng Yang, Hang Yu, Haozhe Zhang, Heidi Lei, Jialong Mai, Junjie Yan, Kaiyue Yang, Mingqi Yang, Peikai Huang, Ruiyang Jin, Sitan Jiang, Weihua Cheng, Yawei Li, Yichen Xiao, Yiying Zhou, Yongmao Zhang, Yuan Lu, Yucen He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 119&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce MiniMax-Speech, an autoregressive Transformer-based Text-to-Speech (TTS) model that generates high-quality speech. A key innovation is our learnable speaker encoder, which extracts timbre features from a reference audio without requiring its transcription. This enables MiniMax-Speech to produce highly expressive speech with timbre consistent with the reference in a zero-shot manner, while also supporting one-shot voice cloning with exceptionally high similarity to the reference voice. In addition, the overall quality of the synthesized audio is enhanced through the proposed Flow-VAE. Our model supports 32 languages and demonstrates excellent performance across multiple objective and subjective evaluations metrics. Notably, it achieves state-of-the-art (SOTA) results on objective voice cloning metrics (Word Error Rate and Speaker Similarity) and has secured the top position on the public TTS Arena leaderboard. Another key strength of MiniMax-Speech, granted by the robust and disentangled representations from the speaker encoder, is its extensibility without modifying the base model, enabling various applications such as: arbitrary voice emotion control via LoRA; text to voice (T2V) by synthesizing timbre features directly from text description; and professional voice cloning (PVC) by fine-tuning timbre features with additional data. We encourage readers to visit https://minimax-ai.github.io/tts_tech_report for more examples.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07916</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 14:25:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiMo: Unlocking the Reasoning Potential of Language Model -- From   Pretraining to Posttraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07608</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.07608.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaomi LLM-Core Team, Bingquan Xia, Bowen Shen, Cici, Dawei Zhu, Di Zhang, Gang Wang, Hailin Zhang, Huaqiu Liu, Jiebao Xiao, Jinhao Dong, Liang Zhao, Peidian Li, Peng Wang, Shihua Yu, Shimao Chen, Weikun Wang, Wenhan Ma, Xiangwei Deng, Yi Huang, Yifan Song, Zihan Jiang, Bowen Ye, Can Cai, Chenhong He, Dong Zhang, Duo Zhang, Guoan Wang, Hao Tian, Haochen Zhao, Heng Qu, Hongshen Xu, Jun Shi, Kainan Bao, QingKai Fang, Kang Zhou, Kangyang Zhou, Lei Li, Menghang Zhu, Nuo Chen, Qiantong Wang, Shaohui Liu, Shicheng Li, Shuhao Gu, Shuhuai Ren, Shuo Liu, Sirui Deng, Weiji Zhuang, Weiwei Lv, Wenyu Yang, Xin Zhang, Xing Yong, Xing Zhang, Xingchen Song, Xinzhe Xu, Xu Wang, Yihan Yan, Yu Tu, Yuanyuan Tian, Yudong Wang, Yue Yu, Zhenru Lin, Zhichao Song, Zihao Yue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 76&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present MiMo-7B, a large language model born for reasoning tasks, with optimization across both pre-training and post-training stages. During pre-training, we enhance the data preprocessing pipeline and employ a three-stage data mixing strategy to strengthen the base model's reasoning potential. MiMo-7B-Base is pre-trained on 25 trillion tokens, with additional Multi-Token Prediction objective for enhanced performance and accelerated inference speed. During post-training, we curate a dataset of 130K verifiable mathematics and programming problems for reinforcement learning, integrating a test-difficulty-driven code-reward scheme to alleviate sparse-reward issues and employing strategic data resampling to stabilize training. Extensive evaluations show that MiMo-7B-Base possesses exceptional reasoning potential, outperforming even much larger 32B models. The final RL-tuned model, MiMo-7B-RL, achieves superior performance on mathematics, code and general reasoning tasks, surpassing the performance of OpenAI o1-mini. The model checkpoints are available at https://github.com/xiaomimimo/MiMo.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07608</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 14:30:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step1X-3D: Towards High-Fidelity and Controllable Generation of Textured   3D Assets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07747</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.07747.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weiyu Li, Xuanyang Zhang, Zheng Sun, Di Qi, Hao Li, Wei Cheng, Weiwei Cai, Shihao Wu, Jiarui Liu, Zihao Wang, Xiao Chen, Feipeng Tian, Jianxiong Pan, Zeming Li, Gang Yu, Xiangyu Zhang, Daxin Jiang, Ping Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While generative artificial intelligence has advanced significantly across text, image, audio, and video domains, 3D generation remains comparatively underdeveloped due to fundamental challenges such as data scarcity, algorithmic limitations, and ecosystem fragmentation. To this end, we present Step1X-3D, an open framework addressing these challenges through: (1) a rigorous data curation pipeline processing &gt;5M assets to create a 2M high-quality dataset with standardized geometric and textural properties; (2) a two-stage 3D-native architecture combining a hybrid VAE-DiT geometry generator with an diffusion-based texture synthesis module; and (3) the full open-source release of models, training code, and adaptation modules. For geometry generation, the hybrid VAE-DiT component produces TSDF representations by employing perceiver-based latent encoding with sharp edge sampling for detail preservation. The diffusion-based texture synthesis module then ensures cross-view consistency through geometric conditioning and latent-space synchronization. Benchmark results demonstrate state-of-the-art performance that exceeds existing open-source methods, while also achieving competitive quality with proprietary solutions. Notably, the framework uniquely bridges the 2D and 3D generation paradigms by supporting direct transfer of 2D control techniques~(e.g., LoRA) to 3D synthesis. By simultaneously advancing data quality, algorithmic fidelity, and reproducibility, Step1X-3D aims to establish new standards for open research in controllable 3D asset generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07747</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 16:56:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning from Peers in Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07787</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.07787.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tongxu Luo, Wenyu Du, Jiaxi Bi, Stephen Chung, Zhengyang Tang, Hao Yang, Min Zhang, Benyou Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have the ability to self-correct even when they make mistakes in their reasoning paths. However, our study reveals that when the reasoning process starts with a short but poor beginning, it becomes difficult for the model to recover. We refer to this phenomenon as the "Prefix Dominance Trap". Inspired by psychological findings that peer interaction can promote self-correction without negatively impacting already accurate individuals, we propose **Learning from Peers** (LeaP) to address this phenomenon. Specifically, every tokens, each reasoning path summarizes its intermediate reasoning and shares it with others through a routing mechanism, enabling paths to incorporate peer insights during inference. However, we observe that smaller models sometimes fail to follow summarization and reflection instructions effectively. To address this, we fine-tune them into our **LeaP-T** model series. Experiments on AIME 2024, AIME 2025, AIMO 2025, and GPQA Diamond show that LeaP provides substantial improvements. For instance, QwQ-32B with LeaP achieves nearly 5 absolute points higher than the baseline on average, and surpasses DeepSeek-R1-671B on three math benchmarks with an average gain of 3.3 points. Notably, our fine-tuned LeaP-T-7B matches the performance of DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-14B on AIME 2024. In-depth analysis reveals LeaP's robust error correction by timely peer insights, showing strong error tolerance and handling varied task difficulty. LeaP marks a milestone by enabling LRMs to collaborate during reasoning. Our code, datasets, and models are available at https://learning-from-peers.github.io/ .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07787</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 17:39:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenThinkIMG: Learning to Think with Images via Visual Tool   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08617</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.08617.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaochen Su, Linjie Li, Mingyang Song, Yunzhuo Hao, Zhengyuan Yang, Jun Zhang, Guanjie Chen, Jiawei Gu, Juntao Li, Xiaoye Qu, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While humans can flexibly leverage interactive visual cognition for complex problem-solving, enabling Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs) to learn similarly adaptive behaviors with visual tools remains challenging. A significant hurdle is the current lack of standardized infrastructure, which hinders integrating diverse tools, generating rich interaction data, and training robust agents effectively. To address these gaps, we introduce OpenThinkIMG, the first open-source, comprehensive end-to-end framework for tool-augmented LVLMs. It features standardized vision tool interfaces, scalable trajectory generation for policy initialization, and a flexible training environment. Furthermore, considering supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on static demonstrations offers limited policy generalization for dynamic tool invocation, we propose a novel reinforcement learning (RL) framework V-ToolRL to train LVLMs to learn adaptive policies for invoking external vision tools. V-ToolRL enables LVLMs to autonomously discover optimal tool-usage strategies by directly optimizing for task success using feedback from tool interactions. We empirically validate V-ToolRL on challenging chart reasoning tasks. Our RL-trained agent, built upon a Qwen2-VL-2B, significantly outperforms its SFT-initialized counterpart (+28.83 points) and surpasses established supervised tool-learning baselines like Taco and CogCom by an average of +12.7 points. Notably, it also surpasses prominent closed-source models like GPT-4.1 by +8.68 accuracy points. We hope OpenThinkIMG can serve as a foundational framework for advancing dynamic, tool-augmented visual reasoning, helping the community develop AI agents that can genuinely "think with images".&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08617</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 14:35:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into DeepSeek-V3: Scaling Challenges and Reflections on   Hardware for AI Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09343</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.09343.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenggang Zhao, Chengqi Deng, Chong Ruan, Damai Dai, Huazuo Gao, Jiashi Li, Liyue Zhang, Panpan Huang, Shangyan Zhou, Shirong Ma, Wenfeng Liang, Ying He, Yuqing Wang, Yuxuan Liu, Y. X. Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid scaling of large language models (LLMs) has unveiled critical limitations in current hardware architectures, including constraints in memory capacity, computational efficiency, and interconnection bandwidth. DeepSeek-V3, trained on 2,048 NVIDIA H800 GPUs, demonstrates how hardware-aware model co-design can effectively address these challenges, enabling cost-efficient training and inference at scale. This paper presents an in-depth analysis of the DeepSeek-V3/R1 model architecture and its AI infrastructure, highlighting key innovations such as Multi-head Latent Attention (MLA) for enhanced memory efficiency, Mixture of Experts (MoE) architectures for optimized computation-communication trade-offs, FP8 mixed-precision training to unlock the full potential of hardware capabilities, and a Multi-Plane Network Topology to minimize cluster-level network overhead. Building on the hardware bottlenecks encountered during DeepSeek-V3's development, we engage in a broader discussion with academic and industry peers on potential future hardware directions, including precise low-precision computation units, scale-up and scale-out convergence, and innovations in low-latency communication fabrics. These insights underscore the critical role of hardware and model co-design in meeting the escalating demands of AI workloads, offering a practical blueprint for innovation in next-generation AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09343</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 12:39:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qwen3 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09388</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.09388.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; An Yang, Anfeng Li, Baosong Yang, Beichen Zhang, Binyuan Hui, Bo Zheng, Bowen Yu, Chang Gao, Chengen Huang, Chenxu Lv, Chujie Zheng, Dayiheng Liu, Fan Zhou, Fei Huang, Feng Hu, Hao Ge, Haoran Wei, Huan Lin, Jialong Tang, Jian Yang, Jianhong Tu, Jianwei Zhang, Jianxin Yang, Jiaxi Yang, Jing Zhou, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin, Kai Dang, Keqin Bao, Kexin Yang, Le Yu, Lianghao Deng, Mei Li, Mingfeng Xue, Mingze Li, Pei Zhang, Peng Wang, Qin Zhu, Rui Men, Ruize Gao, Shixuan Liu, Shuang Luo, Tianhao Li, Tianyi Tang, Wenbiao Yin, Xingzhang Ren, Xinyu Wang, Xinyu Zhang, Xuancheng Ren, Yang Fan, Yang Su, Yichang Zhang, Yinger Zhang, Yu Wan, Yuqiong Liu, Zekun Wang, Zeyu Cui, Zhenru Zhang, Zhipeng Zhou, Zihan Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 169&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we present Qwen3, the latest version of the Qwen model family. Qwen3 comprises a series of large language models (LLMs) designed to advance performance, efficiency, and multilingual capabilities. The Qwen3 series includes models of both dense and Mixture-of-Expert (MoE) architectures, with parameter scales ranging from 0.6 to 235 billion. A key innovation in Qwen3 is the integration of thinking mode (for complex, multi-step reasoning) and non-thinking mode (for rapid, context-driven responses) into a unified framework. This eliminates the need to switch between different models--such as chat-optimized models (e.g., GPT-4o) and dedicated reasoning models (e.g., QwQ-32B)--and enables dynamic mode switching based on user queries or chat templates. Meanwhile, Qwen3 introduces a thinking budget mechanism, allowing users to allocate computational resources adaptively during inference, thereby balancing latency and performance based on task complexity. Moreover, by leveraging the knowledge from the flagship models, we significantly reduce the computational resources required to build smaller-scale models, while ensuring their highly competitive performance. Empirical evaluations demonstrate that Qwen3 achieves state-of-the-art results across diverse benchmarks, including tasks in code generation, mathematical reasoning, agent tasks, etc., competitive against larger MoE models and proprietary models. Compared to its predecessor Qwen2.5, Qwen3 expands multilingual support from 29 to 119 languages and dialects, enhancing global accessibility through improved cross-lingual understanding and generation capabilities. To facilitate reproducibility and community-driven research and development, all Qwen3 models are publicly accessible under Apache 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09388</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 13:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>System Prompt Optimization with Meta-Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09666</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.09666.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yumin Choi, Jinheon Baek, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown remarkable capabilities, with optimizing their input prompts playing a pivotal role in maximizing their performance. However, while LLM prompts consist of both the task-agnostic system prompts and task-specific user prompts, existing work on prompt optimization has focused on user prompts specific to individual queries or tasks, and largely overlooked the system prompt that is, once optimized, applicable across different tasks and domains. Motivated by this, we introduce the novel problem of bilevel system prompt optimization, whose objective is to design system prompts that are robust to diverse user prompts and transferable to unseen tasks. To tackle this problem, we then propose a meta-learning framework, which meta-learns the system prompt by optimizing it over various user prompts across multiple datasets, while simultaneously updating the user prompts in an iterative manner to ensure synergy between them. We conduct experiments on 14 unseen datasets spanning 5 different domains, on which we show that our approach produces system prompts that generalize effectively to diverse user prompts. Also, our findings reveal that the optimized system prompt enables rapid adaptation even to unseen tasks, requiring fewer optimization steps for test-time user prompts while achieving improved performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09666</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 16:46:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BLIP3-o: A Family of Fully Open Unified Multimodal Models-Architecture,   Training and Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09568</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.09568.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiuhai Chen, Zhiyang Xu, Xichen Pan, Yushi Hu, Can Qin, Tom Goldstein, Lifu Huang, Tianyi Zhou, Saining Xie, Silvio Savarese, Le Xue, Caiming Xiong, Ran Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 85&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unifying image understanding and generation has gained growing attention in recent research on multimodal models. Although design choices for image understanding have been extensively studied, the optimal model architecture and training recipe for a unified framework with image generation remain underexplored. Motivated by the strong potential of autoregressive and diffusion models for high-quality generation and scalability, we conduct a comprehensive study of their use in unified multimodal settings, with emphasis on image representations, modeling objectives, and training strategies. Grounded in these investigations, we introduce a novel approach that employs a diffusion transformer to generate semantically rich CLIP image features, in contrast to conventional VAE-based representations. This design yields both higher training efficiency and improved generative quality. Furthermore, we demonstrate that a sequential pretraining strategy for unified models-first training on image understanding and subsequently on image generation-offers practical advantages by preserving image understanding capability while developing strong image generation ability. Finally, we carefully curate a high-quality instruction-tuning dataset BLIP3o-60k for image generation by prompting GPT-4o with a diverse set of captions covering various scenes, objects, human gestures, and more. Building on our innovative model design, training recipe, and datasets, we develop BLIP3-o, a suite of state-of-the-art unified multimodal models. BLIP3-o achieves superior performance across most of the popular benchmarks spanning both image understanding and generation tasks. To facilitate future research, we fully open-source our models, including code, model weights, training scripts, and pretraining and instruction tuning datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09568</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 17:11:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel Scaling Law for Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10475</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.10475.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mouxiang Chen, Binyuan Hui, Zeyu Cui, Jiaxi Yang, Dayiheng Liu, Jianling Sun, Junyang Lin, Zhongxin Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; It is commonly believed that scaling language models should commit a significant space or time cost, by increasing the parameters (parameter scaling) or output tokens (inference-time scaling). We introduce the third and more inference-efficient scaling paradigm: increasing the model's parallel computation during both training and inference time. We apply P diverse and learnable transformations to the input, execute forward passes of the model in parallel, and dynamically aggregate the P outputs. This method, namely parallel scaling (ParScale), scales parallel computation by reusing existing parameters and can be applied to any model structure, optimization procedure, data, or task. We theoretically propose a new scaling law and validate it through large-scale pre-training, which shows that a model with P parallel streams is similar to scaling the parameters by O(log P) while showing superior inference efficiency. For example, ParScale can use up to 22times less memory increase and 6times less latency increase compared to parameter scaling that achieves the same performance improvement. It can also recycle an off-the-shelf pre-trained model into a parallelly scaled one by post-training on a small amount of tokens, further reducing the training budget. The new scaling law we discovered potentially facilitates the deployment of more powerful models in low-resource scenarios, and provides an alternative perspective for the role of computation in machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10475</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 16:24:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMLongBench: Benchmarking Long-Context Vision-Language Models   Effectively and Thoroughly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10610</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.10610.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaowei Wang, Wenhao Yu, Xiyu Ren, Jipeng Zhang, Yu Zhao, Rohit Saxena, Liang Cheng, Ginny Wong, Simon See, Pasquale Minervini, Yangqiu Song, Mark Steedman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid extension of context windows in large vision-language models has given rise to long-context vision-language models (LCVLMs), which are capable of handling hundreds of images with interleaved text tokens in a single forward pass. In this work, we introduce MMLongBench, the first benchmark covering a diverse set of long-context vision-language tasks, to evaluate LCVLMs effectively and thoroughly. MMLongBench is composed of 13,331 examples spanning five different categories of downstream tasks, such as Visual RAG and Many-Shot ICL. It also provides broad coverage of image types, including various natural and synthetic images. To assess the robustness of the models to different input lengths, all examples are delivered at five standardized input lengths (8K-128K tokens) via a cross-modal tokenization scheme that combines vision patches and text tokens. Through a thorough benchmarking of 46 closed-source and open-source LCVLMs, we provide a comprehensive analysis of the current models' vision-language long-context ability. Our results show that: i) performance on a single task is a weak proxy for overall long-context capability; ii) both closed-source and open-source models face challenges in long-context vision-language tasks, indicating substantial room for future improvement; iii) models with stronger reasoning ability tend to exhibit better long-context performance. By offering wide task coverage, various image types, and rigorous length control, MMLongBench provides the missing foundation for diagnosing and advancing the next generation of LCVLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10610</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 17:52:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond 'Aha!': Toward Systematic Meta-Abilities Alignment in Large   Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10554</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.10554.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Hu, Yibo Wang, Hanze Dong, Yuhui Xu, Amrita Saha, Caiming Xiong, Bryan Hooi, Junnan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 114&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs) already possess a latent capacity for long chain-of-thought reasoning. Prior work has shown that outcome-based reinforcement learning (RL) can incidentally elicit advanced reasoning behaviors such as self-correction, backtracking, and verification phenomena often referred to as the model's "aha moment". However, the timing and consistency of these emergent behaviors remain unpredictable and uncontrollable, limiting the scalability and reliability of LRMs' reasoning capabilities. To address these limitations, we move beyond reliance on prompts and coincidental "aha moments". Instead, we explicitly align models with three meta-abilities: deduction, induction, and abduction, using automatically generated, self-verifiable tasks. Our three stage-pipeline individual alignment, parameter-space merging, and domain-specific reinforcement learning, boosting performance by over 10\% relative to instruction-tuned baselines. Furthermore, domain-specific RL from the aligned checkpoint yields an additional 2\% average gain in the performance ceiling across math, coding, and science benchmarks, demonstrating that explicit meta-ability alignment offers a scalable and dependable foundation for reasoning. Code is available at: https://github.com/zhiyuanhubj/Meta-Ability-Alignment&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10554</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 17:58:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MathCoder-VL: Bridging Vision and Code for Enhanced Multimodal   Mathematical Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10557</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.10557.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ke Wang, Junting Pan, Linda Wei, Aojun Zhou, Weikang Shi, Zimu Lu, Han Xiao, Yunqiao Yang, Houxing Ren, Mingjie Zhan, Hongsheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Natural language image-caption datasets, widely used for training Large Multimodal Models, mainly focus on natural scenarios and overlook the intricate details of mathematical figures that are critical for problem-solving, hindering the advancement of current LMMs in multimodal mathematical reasoning. To this end, we propose leveraging code as supervision for cross-modal alignment, since code inherently encodes all information needed to generate corresponding figures, establishing a precise connection between the two modalities. Specifically, we co-develop our image-to-code model and dataset with model-in-the-loop approach, resulting in an image-to-code model, FigCodifier and ImgCode-8.6M dataset, the largest image-code dataset to date. Furthermore, we utilize FigCodifier to synthesize novel mathematical figures and then construct MM-MathInstruct-3M, a high-quality multimodal math instruction fine-tuning dataset. Finally, we present MathCoder-VL, trained with ImgCode-8.6M for cross-modal alignment and subsequently fine-tuned on MM-MathInstruct-3M for multimodal math problem solving. Our model achieves a new open-source SOTA across all six metrics. Notably, it surpasses GPT-4o and Claude 3.5 Sonnet in the geometry problem-solving subset of MathVista, achieving improvements of 8.9% and 9.2%. The dataset and models will be released at https://github.com/mathllm/MathCoder.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10557</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 17:59:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GuardReasoner-VL: Safeguarding VLMs via Reinforced Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11049</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11049.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yue Liu, Shengfang Zhai, Mingzhe Du, Yulin Chen, Tri Cao, Hongcheng Gao, Cheng Wang, Xinfeng Li, Kun Wang, Junfeng Fang, Jiaheng Zhang, Bryan Hooi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; To enhance the safety of VLMs, this paper introduces a novel reasoning-based VLM guard model dubbed GuardReasoner-VL. The core idea is to incentivize the guard model to deliberatively reason before making moderation decisions via online RL. First, we construct GuardReasoner-VLTrain, a reasoning corpus with 123K samples and 631K reasoning steps, spanning text, image, and text-image inputs. Then, based on it, we cold-start our model's reasoning ability via SFT. In addition, we further enhance reasoning regarding moderation through online RL. Concretely, to enhance diversity and difficulty of samples, we conduct rejection sampling followed by data augmentation via the proposed safety-aware data concatenation. Besides, we use a dynamic clipping parameter to encourage exploration in early stages and exploitation in later stages. To balance performance and token efficiency, we design a length-aware safety reward that integrates accuracy, format, and token cost. Extensive experiments demonstrate the superiority of our model. Remarkably, it surpasses the runner-up by 19.27% F1 score on average. We release data, code, and models (3B/7B) of GuardReasoner-VL at https://github.com/yueliu1999/GuardReasoner-VL/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11049</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 09:46:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delta Attention: Fast and Accurate Sparse Attention Inference by Delta   Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11254</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11254.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jeffrey Willette, Heejun Lee, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The attention mechanism of a transformer has a quadratic complexity, leading to high inference costs and latency for long sequences. However, attention matrices are mostly sparse, which implies that many entries may be omitted from computation for efficient inference. Sparse attention inference methods aim to reduce this computational burden; however, they also come with a troublesome performance degradation. We discover that one reason for this degradation is that the sparse calculation induces a distributional shift in the attention outputs. The distributional shift causes decoding-time queries to fail to align well with the appropriate keys from the prefill stage, leading to a drop in performance. We propose a simple, novel, and effective procedure for correcting this distributional shift, bringing the distribution of sparse attention outputs closer to that of quadratic attention. Our method can be applied on top of any sparse attention method, and results in an average 36%pt performance increase, recovering 88% of quadratic attention accuracy on the 131K RULER benchmark when applied on top of sliding window attention with sink tokens while only adding a small overhead. Our method can maintain approximately 98.5% sparsity over full quadratic attention, making our model 32 times faster than Flash Attention 2 when processing 1M token prefills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11254</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 13:48:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Planning: Let's Think Only with Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11409</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11409.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Xu, Chengzu Li, Han Zhou, Xingchen Wan, Caiqi Zhang, Anna Korhonen, Ivan Vulić&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in Large Language Models (LLMs) and their multimodal extensions (MLLMs) have substantially enhanced machine reasoning across diverse tasks. However, these models predominantly rely on pure text as the medium for both expressing and structuring reasoning, even when visual information is present. In this work, we argue that language may not always be the most natural or effective modality for reasoning, particularly in tasks involving spatial and geometrical information. Motivated by this, we propose a new paradigm, Visual Planning, which enables planning through purely visual representations, independent of text. In this paradigm, planning is executed via sequences of images that encode step-by-step inference in the visual domain, akin to how humans sketch or visualize future actions. We introduce a novel reinforcement learning framework, Visual Planning via Reinforcement Learning (VPRL), empowered by GRPO for post-training large vision models, leading to substantial improvements in planning in a selection of representative visual navigation tasks, FrozenLake, Maze, and MiniBehavior. Our visual planning paradigm outperforms all other planning variants that conduct reasoning in the text-only space. Our results establish Visual Planning as a viable and promising alternative to language-based reasoning, opening new avenues for tasks that benefit from intuitive, image-based inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11409</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 16:17:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SageAttention3: Microscaling FP4 Attention for Inference and An   Exploration of 8-Bit Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11594</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11594.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Jia Wei, Pengle Zhang, Xiaoming Xu, Haofeng Huang, Haoxu Wang, Kai Jiang, Jun Zhu, Jianfei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 67&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The efficiency of attention is important due to its quadratic time complexity. We enhance the efficiency of attention through two key contributions: First, we leverage the new FP4 Tensor Cores in Blackwell GPUs to accelerate attention computation. Our implementation achieves 1038 TOPS on RTX5090, which is a 5x speedup over the fastest FlashAttention on RTX5090. Experiments show that our FP4 attention can accelerate inference of various models in a plug-and-play way. Second, we pioneer low-bit attention to training tasks. Existing low-bit attention works like FlashAttention3 and SageAttention focus only on inference. However, the efficiency of training large models is also important. To explore whether low-bit attention can be effectively applied to training tasks, we design an accurate and efficient 8-bit attention for both forward and backward propagation. Experiments indicate that 8-bit attention achieves lossless performance in fine-tuning tasks but exhibits slower convergence in pretraining tasks. The code will be available at https://github.com/thu-ml/SageAttention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11594</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 18:01:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain-of-Model Learning for Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11820</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11820.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaitao Song, Xiaohua Wang, Xu Tan, Huiqiang Jiang, Chengruidong Zhang, Yongliang Shen, Cen LU, Zihao Li, Zifan Song, Caihua Shan, Yansen Wang, Kan Ren, Xiaoqing Zheng, Tao Qin, Yuqing Yang, Dongsheng Li, Lili Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 109&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we propose a novel learning paradigm, termed Chain-of-Model (CoM), which incorporates the causal relationship into the hidden states of each layer as a chain style, thereby introducing great scaling efficiency in model training and inference flexibility in deployment. We introduce the concept of Chain-of-Representation (CoR), which formulates the hidden states at each layer as a combination of multiple sub-representations (i.e., chains) at the hidden dimension level. In each layer, each chain from the output representations can only view all of its preceding chains in the input representations. Consequently, the model built upon CoM framework can progressively scale up the model size by increasing the chains based on the previous models (i.e., chains), and offer multiple sub-models at varying sizes for elastic inference by using different chain numbers. Based on this principle, we devise Chain-of-Language-Model (CoLM), which incorporates the idea of CoM into each layer of Transformer architecture. Based on CoLM, we further introduce CoLM-Air by introducing a KV sharing mechanism, that computes all keys and values within the first chain and then shares across all chains. This design demonstrates additional extensibility, such as enabling seamless LM switching, prefilling acceleration and so on. Experimental results demonstrate our CoLM family can achieve comparable performance to the standard Transformer, while simultaneously enabling greater flexiblity, such as progressive scaling to improve training efficiency and offer multiple varying model sizes for elastic inference, paving a a new way toward building language models. Our code will be released in the future at: https://github.com/microsoft/CoLM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11820</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 04:06:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdaCoT: Pareto-Optimal Adaptive Chain-of-Thought Triggering via   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11896</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.11896.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenwei Lou, Zewei Sun, Xinnian Liang, Meng Qu, Wei Shen, Wenqi Wang, Yuntao Li, Qingping Yang, Shuangzhi Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities but often face challenges with tasks requiring sophisticated reasoning. While Chain-of-Thought (CoT) prompting significantly enhances reasoning, it indiscriminately generates lengthy reasoning steps for all queries, leading to substantial computational costs and inefficiency, especially for simpler inputs. To address this critical issue, we introduce AdaCoT (Adaptive Chain-of-Thought), a novel framework enabling LLMs to adaptively decide when to invoke CoT. AdaCoT framed adaptive reasoning as a Pareto optimization problem that seeks to balance model performance with the costs associated with CoT invocation (both frequency and computational overhead). We propose a reinforcement learning (RL) based method, specifically utilizing Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO), to dynamically control the CoT triggering decision boundary by adjusting penalty coefficients, thereby allowing the model to determine CoT necessity based on implicit query complexity. A key technical contribution is Selective Loss Masking (SLM), designed to counteract decision boundary collapse during multi-stage RL training, ensuring robust and stable adaptive triggering. Experimental results demonstrate that AdaCoT successfully navigates the Pareto frontier, achieving substantial reductions in CoT usage for queries not requiring elaborate reasoning. For instance, on our production traffic testset, AdaCoT reduced CoT triggering rates to as low as 3.18\% and decreased average response tokens by 69.06%, while maintaining high performance on complex tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11896</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 08:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Merging in Pre-training of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12082</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.12082.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunshui Li, Yiyuan Ma, Shen Yan, Chaoyi Zhang, Jing Liu, Jianqiao Lu, Ziwen Xu, Mengzhao Chen, Minrui Wang, Shiyi Zhan, Jin Ma, Xunhao Lai, Yao Luo, Xingyan Bin, Hongbin Ren, Mingji Han, Wenhao Hao, Bairen Yi, LingJun Liu, Bole Ma, Xiaoying Jia, Zhou Xun, Liang Xiang, Yonghui Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Model merging has emerged as a promising technique for enhancing large language models, though its application in large-scale pre-training remains relatively unexplored. In this paper, we present a comprehensive investigation of model merging techniques during the pre-training process. Through extensive experiments with both dense and Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architectures ranging from millions to over 100 billion parameters, we demonstrate that merging checkpoints trained with constant learning rates not only achieves significant performance improvements but also enables accurate prediction of annealing behavior. These improvements lead to both more efficient model development and significantly lower training costs. Our detailed ablation studies on merging strategies and hyperparameters provide new insights into the underlying mechanisms while uncovering novel applications. Through comprehensive experimental analysis, we offer the open-source community practical pre-training guidelines for effective model merging.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12082</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 16:53:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Computer-Use Grounding via User Interface Decomposition and   Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13227</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13227.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianbao Xie, Jiaqi Deng, Xiaochuan Li, Junlin Yang, Haoyuan Wu, Jixuan Chen, Wenjing Hu, Xinyuan Wang, Yuhui Xu, Zekun Wang, Yiheng Xu, Junli Wang, Doyen Sahoo, Tao Yu, Caiming Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graphical user interface (GUI) grounding, the ability to map natural language instructions to specific actions on graphical user interfaces, remains a critical bottleneck in computer use agent development. Current benchmarks oversimplify grounding tasks as short referring expressions, failing to capture the complexity of real-world interactions that require software commonsense, layout understanding, and fine-grained manipulation capabilities. To address these limitations, we introduce OSWorld-G, a comprehensive benchmark comprising 564 finely annotated samples across diverse task types including text matching, element recognition, layout understanding, and precise manipulation. Additionally, we synthesize and release the largest computer use grounding dataset Jedi, which contains 4 million examples through multi-perspective decoupling of tasks. Our multi-scale models trained on Jedi demonstrate its effectiveness by outperforming existing approaches on ScreenSpot-v2, ScreenSpot-Pro, and our OSWorld-G. Furthermore, we demonstrate that improved grounding with Jedi directly enhances agentic capabilities of general foundation models on complex computer tasks, improving from 5% to 27% on OSWorld. Through detailed ablation studies, we identify key factors contributing to grounding performance and verify that combining specialized data for different interface elements enables compositional generalization to novel interfaces. All benchmark, data, checkpoints, and code are open-sourced and available at https://osworld-grounding.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13227</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 15:09:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinkless: LLM Learns When to Think</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13379</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13379.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gongfan Fang, Xinyin Ma, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning Language Models, capable of extended chain-of-thought reasoning, have demonstrated remarkable performance on tasks requiring complex logical inference. However, applying elaborate reasoning for all queries often results in substantial computational inefficiencies, particularly when many problems admit straightforward solutions. This motivates an open question: Can LLMs learn when to think? To answer this, we propose Thinkless, a learnable framework that empowers an LLM to adaptively select between short-form and long-form reasoning, based on both task complexity and the model's ability. Thinkless is trained under a reinforcement learning paradigm and employs two control tokens, &lt;short&gt; for concise responses and &lt;think&gt; for detailed reasoning. At the core of our method is a Decoupled Group Relative Policy Optimization (DeGRPO) algorithm, which decomposes the learning objective of hybrid reasoning into two components: (1) a control token loss that governs the selection of the reasoning mode, and (2) a response loss that improves the accuracy of the generated answers. This decoupled formulation enables fine-grained control over the contributions of each objective, stabilizing training and effectively preventing collapse observed in vanilla GRPO. Empirically, on several benchmarks such as Minerva Algebra, MATH-500, and GSM8K, Thinkless is able to reduce the usage of long-chain thinking by 50% - 90%, significantly improving the efficiency of Reasoning Language Models. The code is available at https://github.com/VainF/Thinkless&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13379</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:24:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdaptThink: Reasoning Models Can Learn When to Think</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13417</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13417.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiajie Zhang, Nianyi Lin, Lei Hou, Ling Feng, Juanzi Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, large reasoning models have achieved impressive performance on various tasks by employing human-like deep thinking. However, the lengthy thinking process substantially increases inference overhead, making efficiency a critical bottleneck. In this work, we first demonstrate that NoThinking, which prompts the reasoning model to skip thinking and directly generate the final solution, is a better choice for relatively simple tasks in terms of both performance and efficiency. Motivated by this, we propose AdaptThink, a novel RL algorithm to teach reasoning models to choose the optimal thinking mode adaptively based on problem difficulty. Specifically, AdaptThink features two core components: (1) a constrained optimization objective that encourages the model to choose NoThinking while maintaining the overall performance; (2) an importance sampling strategy that balances Thinking and NoThinking samples during on-policy training, thereby enabling cold start and allowing the model to explore and exploit both thinking modes throughout the training process. Our experiments indicate that AdaptThink significantly reduces the inference costs while further enhancing performance. Notably, on three math datasets, AdaptThink reduces the average response length of DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-1.5B by 53% and improves its accuracy by 2.4%, highlighting the promise of adaptive thinking-mode selection for optimizing the balance between reasoning quality and efficiency. Our codes and models are available at https://github.com/THU-KEG/AdaptThink.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13417</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:50:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Anytime Reasoning via Budget Relative Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13438</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13438.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Penghui Qi, Zichen Liu, Tianyu Pang, Chao Du, Wee Sun Lee, Min Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling test-time compute is crucial for enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). Existing approaches typically employ reinforcement learning (RL) to maximize a verifiable reward obtained at the end of reasoning traces. However, such methods optimize only the final performance under a large and fixed token budget, which hinders efficiency in both training and deployment. In this work, we present a novel framework, AnytimeReasoner, to optimize anytime reasoning performance, which aims to improve token efficiency and the flexibility of reasoning under varying token budget constraints. To achieve this, we truncate the complete thinking process to fit within sampled token budgets from a prior distribution, compelling the model to summarize the optimal answer for each truncated thinking for verification. This introduces verifiable dense rewards into the reasoning process, facilitating more effective credit assignment in RL optimization. We then optimize the thinking and summary policies in a decoupled manner to maximize the cumulative reward. Additionally, we introduce a novel variance reduction technique, Budget Relative Policy Optimization (BRPO), to enhance the robustness and efficiency of the learning process when reinforcing the thinking policy. Empirical results in mathematical reasoning tasks demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms GRPO across all thinking budgets under various prior distributions, enhancing both training and token efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13438</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 17:58:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Agent Training for Computer Use</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13909</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.13909.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanheng He, Jiahe Jin, Pengfei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling up high-quality trajectory data has long been a critical bottleneck for developing human-like computer use agents. We introduce PC Agent-E, an efficient agent training framework that significantly reduces reliance on large-scale human demonstrations. Starting with just 312 human-annotated computer use trajectories, we further improved data quality by synthesizing diverse action decisions with Claude 3.7 Sonnet. Trained on these enriched trajectories, our PC Agent-E model achieved a remarkable 141% relative improvement, surpassing the strong Claude 3.7 Sonnet with extended thinking on WindowsAgentArena-V2, an improved benchmark we also released. Furthermore, PC Agent-E demonstrates strong generalizability to different operating systems on OSWorld. Our findings suggest that strong computer use capabilities can be stimulated from a small amount of high-quality trajectory data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13909</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 04:20:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniVG-R1: Reasoning Guided Universal Visual Grounding with Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14231</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14231.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sule Bai, Mingxing Li, Yong Liu, Jing Tang, Haoji Zhang, Lei Sun, Xiangxiang Chu, Yansong Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional visual grounding methods primarily focus on single-image scenarios with simple textual references. However, extending these methods to real-world scenarios that involve implicit and complex instructions, particularly in conjunction with multiple images, poses significant challenges, which is mainly due to the lack of advanced reasoning ability across diverse multi-modal contexts. In this work, we aim to address the more practical universal grounding task, and propose UniVG-R1, a reasoning guided multimodal large language model (MLLM) for universal visual grounding, which enhances reasoning capabilities through reinforcement learning (RL) combined with cold-start data. Specifically, we first construct a high-quality Chain-of-Thought (CoT) grounding dataset, annotated with detailed reasoning chains, to guide the model towards correct reasoning paths via supervised fine-tuning. Subsequently, we perform rule-based reinforcement learning to encourage the model to identify correct reasoning chains, thereby incentivizing its reasoning capabilities. In addition, we identify a difficulty bias arising from the prevalence of easy samples as RL training progresses, and we propose a difficulty-aware weight adjustment strategy to further strengthen the performance. Experimental results demonstrate the effectiveness of UniVG-R1, which achieves state-of-the-art performance on MIG-Bench with a 9.1% improvement over the previous method. Furthermore, our model exhibits strong generalizability, achieving an average improvement of 23.4% in zero-shot performance across four image and video reasoning grounding benchmarks. The project page can be accessed at https://amap-ml.github.io/UniVG-R1-page/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14231</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 11:40:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Law for Quantization-Aware Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14302</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14302.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengzhao Chen, Chaoyi Zhang, Jing Liu, Yutao Zeng, Zeyue Xue, Zhiheng Liu, Yunshui Li, Jin Ma, Jie Huang, Xun Zhou, Ping Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) demand substantial computational and memory resources, creating deployment challenges. Quantization-aware training (QAT) addresses these challenges by reducing model precision while maintaining performance. However, the scaling behavior of QAT, especially at 4-bit precision (W4A4), is not well understood. Existing QAT scaling laws often ignore key factors such as the number of training tokens and quantization granularity, which limits their applicability. This paper proposes a unified scaling law for QAT that models quantization error as a function of model size, training data volume, and quantization group size. Through 268 QAT experiments, we show that quantization error decreases as model size increases, but rises with more training tokens and coarser quantization granularity. To identify the sources of W4A4 quantization error, we decompose it into weight and activation components. Both components follow the overall trend of W4A4 quantization error, but with different sensitivities. Specifically, weight quantization error increases more rapidly with more training tokens. Further analysis shows that the activation quantization error in the FC2 layer, caused by outliers, is the primary bottleneck of W4A4 QAT quantization error. By applying mixed-precision quantization to address this bottleneck, we demonstrate that weight and activation quantization errors can converge to similar levels. Additionally, with more training data, weight quantization error eventually exceeds activation quantization error, suggesting that reducing weight quantization error is also important in such scenarios. These findings offer key insights for improving QAT research and development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14302</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 12:54:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This Time is Different: An Observability Perspective on Time Series   Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14766</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14766.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ben Cohen, Emaad Khwaja, Youssef Doubli, Salahidine Lemaachi, Chris Lettieri, Charles Masson, Hugo Miccinilli, Elise Ramé, Qiqi Ren, Afshin Rostamizadeh, Jean Ogier du Terrail, Anna-Monica Toon, Kan Wang, Stephan Xie, David Asker, Ameet Talwalkar, Othmane Abou-Amal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Toto, a time series forecasting foundation model with 151 million parameters. Toto uses a modern decoder-only architecture coupled with architectural innovations designed to account for specific challenges found in multivariate observability time series data. Toto's pre-training corpus is a mixture of observability data, open datasets, and synthetic data, and is 4-10times larger than those of leading time series foundation models. Additionally, we introduce BOOM, a large-scale benchmark consisting of 350 million observations across 2,807 real-world time series. For both Toto and BOOM, we source observability data exclusively from Datadog's own telemetry and internal observability metrics. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that Toto achieves state-of-the-art performance on both BOOM and on established general purpose time series forecasting benchmarks. Toto's model weights, inference code, and evaluation scripts, as well as BOOM's data and evaluation code, are all available as open source under the Apache 2.0 License available at https://huggingface.co/Datadog/Toto-Open-Base-1.0 and https://github.com/DataDog/toto.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14766</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:48:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quartet: Native FP4 Training Can Be Optimal for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14669</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14669.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Roberto L. Castro, Andrei Panferov, Soroush Tabesh, Oliver Sieberling, Jiale Chen, Mahdi Nikdan, Saleh Ashkboos, Dan Alistarh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of large language models (LLMs) has been paralleled by unprecedented increases in computational demands, with training costs for state-of-the-art models doubling every few months. Training models directly in low-precision arithmetic offers a solution, by improving both computational throughput and energy efficiency. Specifically, NVIDIA's recent Blackwell architecture facilitates extremely low-precision operations, specifically FP4 variants, promising substantial efficiency gains. Yet, current algorithms for training LLMs in FP4 precision face significant accuracy degradation and often rely on mixed-precision fallbacks. In this paper, we systematically investigate hardware-supported FP4 training and introduce Quartet, a new approach enabling accurate, end-to-end FP4 training with all the major computations (in e.g. linear layers) being performed in low precision. Through extensive evaluations on Llama-type models, we reveal a new low-precision scaling law that quantifies performance trade-offs across varying bit-widths and allows us to identify a "near-optimal" low-precision training technique in terms of accuracy-vs-computation, called Quartet. We implement Quartet using optimized CUDA kernels tailored for NVIDIA Blackwell GPUs, and show that it can achieve state-of-the-art accuracy for FP4 precision, successfully training billion-scale models. Our method demonstrates that fully FP4-based training is a competitive alternative to standard-precision and FP8 training. Our code is available at https://github.com/IST-DASLab/Quartet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14669</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:55:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emerging Properties in Unified Multimodal Pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14683</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14683.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaorui Deng, Deyao Zhu, Kunchang Li, Chenhui Gou, Feng Li, Zeyu Wang, Shu Zhong, Weihao Yu, Xiaonan Nie, Ziang Song, Guang Shi, Haoqi Fan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 124&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unifying multimodal understanding and generation has shown impressive capabilities in cutting-edge proprietary systems. In this work, we introduce BAGEL, an open0source foundational model that natively supports multimodal understanding and generation. BAGEL is a unified, decoder0only model pretrained on trillions of tokens curated from large0scale interleaved text, image, video, and web data. When scaled with such diverse multimodal interleaved data, BAGEL exhibits emerging capabilities in complex multimodal reasoning. As a result, it significantly outperforms open-source unified models in both multimodal generation and understanding across standard benchmarks, while exhibiting advanced multimodal reasoning abilities such as free-form image manipulation, future frame prediction, 3D manipulation, and world navigation. In the hope of facilitating further opportunities for multimodal research, we share the key findings, pretraining details, data creation protocal, and release our code and checkpoints to the community. The project page is at https://bagel-ai.org/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14683</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 17:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Reasoning, Losing Control: Evaluating Instruction Following in   Large Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14810</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.14810.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tingchen Fu, Jiawei Gu, Yafu Li, Xiaoye Qu, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-following is essential for aligning large language models (LLMs) with user intent. While recent reasoning-oriented models exhibit impressive performance on complex mathematical problems, their ability to adhere to natural language instructions remains underexplored. In this work, we introduce MathIF, a dedicated benchmark for evaluating instruction-following in mathematical reasoning tasks. Our empirical analysis reveals a consistent tension between scaling up reasoning capacity and maintaining controllability, as models that reason more effectively often struggle to comply with user directives. We find that models tuned on distilled long chains-of-thought or trained with reasoning-oriented reinforcement learning often degrade in instruction adherence, especially when generation length increases. Furthermore, we show that even simple interventions can partially recover obedience, though at the cost of reasoning performance. These findings highlight a fundamental tension in current LLM training paradigms and motivate the need for more instruction-aware reasoning models. We release the code and data at https://github.com/TingchenFu/MathIF.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14810</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2025 18:18:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion vs. Autoregressive Language Models: A Text Embedding   Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15045</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15045.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyue Zhang, Yilun Zhao, Liyuan Geng, Arman Cohan, Anh Tuan Luu, Chen Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM)-based embedding models, benefiting from large scale pre-training and post-training, have begun to surpass BERT and T5-based models on general-purpose text embedding tasks such as document retrieval. However, a fundamental limitation of LLM embeddings lies in the unidirectional attention used during autoregressive pre-training, which misaligns with the bidirectional nature of text embedding tasks. To this end, We propose adopting diffusion language models for text embeddings, motivated by their inherent bidirectional architecture and recent success in matching or surpassing LLMs especially on reasoning tasks. We present the first systematic study of the diffusion language embedding model, which outperforms the LLM-based embedding model by 20% on long-document retrieval, 8% on reasoning-intensive retrieval, 2% on instruction-following retrieval, and achieve competitive performance on traditional text embedding benchmarks. Our analysis verifies that bidirectional attention is crucial for encoding global context in long and complex text.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15045</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 02:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Web-Shepherd: Advancing PRMs for Reinforcing Web Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15277</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15277.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyungjoo Chae, Sunghwan Kim, Junhee Cho, Seungone Kim, Seungjun Moon, Gyeom Hwangbo, Dongha Lim, Minjin Kim, Yeonjun Hwang, Minju Gwak, Dongwook Choi, Minseok Kang, Gwanhoon Im, ByeongUng Cho, Hyojun Kim, Jun Hee Han, Taeyoon Kwon, Minju Kim, Beong-woo Kwak, Dongjin Kang, Jinyoung Yeo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 97&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Web navigation is a unique domain that can automate many repetitive real-life tasks and is challenging as it requires long-horizon sequential decision making beyond typical multimodal large language model (MLLM) tasks. Yet, specialized reward models for web navigation that can be utilized during both training and test-time have been absent until now. Despite the importance of speed and cost-effectiveness, prior works have utilized MLLMs as reward models, which poses significant constraints for real-world deployment. To address this, in this work, we propose the first process reward model (PRM) called Web-Shepherd which could assess web navigation trajectories in a step-level. To achieve this, we first construct the WebPRM Collection, a large-scale dataset with 40K step-level preference pairs and annotated checklists spanning diverse domains and difficulty levels. Next, we also introduce the WebRewardBench, the first meta-evaluation benchmark for evaluating PRMs. In our experiments, we observe that our Web-Shepherd achieves about 30 points better accuracy compared to using GPT-4o on WebRewardBench. Furthermore, when testing on WebArena-lite by using GPT-4o-mini as the policy and Web-Shepherd as the verifier, we achieve 10.9 points better performance, in 10 less cost compared to using GPT-4o-mini as the verifier. Our model, dataset, and code are publicly available at LINK.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15277</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 08:56:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMaDA: Multimodal Large Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15809</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15809.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ling Yang, Ye Tian, Bowen Li, Xinchen Zhang, Ke Shen, Yunhai Tong, Mengdi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 83&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce MMaDA, a novel class of multimodal diffusion foundation models designed to achieve superior performance across diverse domains such as textual reasoning, multimodal understanding, and text-to-image generation. The approach is distinguished by three key innovations: (i) MMaDA adopts a unified diffusion architecture with a shared probabilistic formulation and a modality-agnostic design, eliminating the need for modality-specific components. This architecture ensures seamless integration and processing across different data types. (ii) We implement a mixed long chain-of-thought (CoT) fine-tuning strategy that curates a unified CoT format across modalities. By aligning reasoning processes between textual and visual domains, this strategy facilitates cold-start training for the final reinforcement learning (RL) stage, thereby enhancing the model's ability to handle complex tasks from the outset. (iii) We propose UniGRPO, a unified policy-gradient-based RL algorithm specifically tailored for diffusion foundation models. Utilizing diversified reward modeling, UniGRPO unifies post-training across both reasoning and generation tasks, ensuring consistent performance improvements. Experimental results demonstrate that MMaDA-8B exhibits strong generalization capabilities as a unified multimodal foundation model. It surpasses powerful models like LLaMA-3-7B and Qwen2-7B in textual reasoning, outperforms Show-o and SEED-X in multimodal understanding, and excels over SDXL and Janus in text-to-image generation. These achievements highlight MMaDA's effectiveness in bridging the gap between pretraining and post-training within unified diffusion architectures, providing a comprehensive framework for future research and development. We open-source our code and trained models at: https://github.com/Gen-Verse/MMaDA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15809</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 17:59:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pixel Reasoner: Incentivizing Pixel-Space Reasoning with   Curiosity-Driven Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15966</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.15966.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alex Su, Haozhe Wang, Weimin Ren, Fangzhen Lin, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Chain-of-thought reasoning has significantly improved the performance of Large Language Models (LLMs) across various domains. However, this reasoning process has been confined exclusively to textual space, limiting its effectiveness in visually intensive tasks. To address this limitation, we introduce the concept of reasoning in the pixel-space. Within this novel framework, Vision-Language Models (VLMs) are equipped with a suite of visual reasoning operations, such as zoom-in and select-frame. These operations enable VLMs to directly inspect, interrogate, and infer from visual evidences, thereby enhancing reasoning fidelity for visual tasks. Cultivating such pixel-space reasoning capabilities in VLMs presents notable challenges, including the model's initially imbalanced competence and its reluctance to adopt the newly introduced pixel-space operations. We address these challenges through a two-phase training approach. The first phase employs instruction tuning on synthesized reasoning traces to familiarize the model with the novel visual operations. Following this, a reinforcement learning (RL) phase leverages a curiosity-driven reward scheme to balance exploration between pixel-space reasoning and textual reasoning. With these visual operations, VLMs can interact with complex visual inputs, such as information-rich images or videos to proactively gather necessary information. We demonstrate that this approach significantly improves VLM performance across diverse visual reasoning benchmarks. Our 7B model, \model, achieves 84\% on V* bench, 74\% on TallyQA-Complex, and 84\% on InfographicsVQA, marking the highest accuracy achieved by any open-source model to date. These results highlight the importance of pixel-space reasoning and the effectiveness of our framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.15966</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 19:35:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuickVideo: Real-Time Long Video Understanding with System Algorithm   Co-Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16175</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16175.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Benjamin Schneider, Dongfu Jiang, Chao Du, Tianyu Pang, Wenhu Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-video understanding has emerged as a crucial capability in real-world applications such as video surveillance, meeting summarization, educational lecture analysis, and sports broadcasting. However, it remains computationally prohibitive for VideoLLMs, primarily due to two bottlenecks: 1) sequential video decoding, the process of converting the raw bit stream to RGB frames can take up to a minute for hour-long video inputs, and 2) costly prefilling of up to several million tokens for LLM inference, resulting in high latency and memory use. To address these challenges, we propose QuickVideo, a system-algorithm co-design that substantially accelerates long-video understanding to support real-time downstream applications. It comprises three key innovations: QuickDecoder, a parallelized CPU-based video decoder that achieves 2-3 times speedup by splitting videos into keyframe-aligned intervals processed concurrently; QuickPrefill, a memory-efficient prefilling method using KV-cache pruning to support more frames with less GPU memory; and an overlapping scheme that overlaps CPU video decoding with GPU inference. Together, these components infernece time reduce by a minute on long video inputs, enabling scalable, high-quality video understanding even on limited hardware. Experiments show that QuickVideo generalizes across durations and sampling rates, making long video processing feasible in practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16175</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 03:26:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied Agents Meet Personalization: Exploring Memory Utilization for   Personalized Assistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16348</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16348.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taeyoon Kwon, Dongwook Choi, Sunghwan Kim, Hyojun Kim, Seungjun Moon, Beong-woo Kwak, Kuan-Hao Huang, Jinyoung Yeo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Embodied agents empowered by large language models (LLMs) have shown strong performance in household object rearrangement tasks. However, these tasks primarily focus on single-turn interactions with simplified instructions, which do not truly reflect the challenges of providing meaningful assistance to users. To provide personalized assistance, embodied agents must understand the unique semantics that users assign to the physical world (e.g., favorite cup, breakfast routine) by leveraging prior interaction history to interpret dynamic, real-world instructions. Yet, the effectiveness of embodied agents in utilizing memory for personalized assistance remains largely underexplored. To address this gap, we present MEMENTO, a personalized embodied agent evaluation framework designed to comprehensively assess memory utilization capabilities to provide personalized assistance. Our framework consists of a two-stage memory evaluation process design that enables quantifying the impact of memory utilization on task performance. This process enables the evaluation of agents' understanding of personalized knowledge in object rearrangement tasks by focusing on its role in goal interpretation: (1) the ability to identify target objects based on personal meaning (object semantics), and (2) the ability to infer object-location configurations from consistent user patterns, such as routines (user patterns). Our experiments across various LLMs reveal significant limitations in memory utilization, with even frontier models like GPT-4o experiencing a 30.5% performance drop when required to reference multiple memories, particularly in tasks involving user patterns. These findings, along with our detailed analyses and case studies, provide valuable insights for future research in developing more effective personalized embodied agents. Project website: https://connoriginal.github.io/MEMENTO&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16348</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 08:00:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tool-Star: Empowering LLM-Brained Multi-Tool Reasoner via Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16410</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16410.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guanting Dong, Yifei Chen, Xiaoxi Li, Jiajie Jin, Hongjin Qian, Yutao Zhu, Hangyu Mao, Guorui Zhou, Zhicheng Dou, Ji-Rong Wen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, large language models (LLMs) have shown remarkable reasoning capabilities via large-scale reinforcement learning (RL). However, leveraging the RL algorithm to empower effective multi-tool collaborative reasoning in LLMs remains an open challenge. In this paper, we introduce Tool-Star, an RL-based framework designed to empower LLMs to autonomously invoke multiple external tools during stepwise reasoning. Tool-Star integrates six types of tools and incorporates systematic designs in both data synthesis and training. To address the scarcity of tool-use data, we propose a general tool-integrated reasoning data synthesis pipeline, which combines tool-integrated prompting with hint-based sampling to automatically and scalably generate tool-use trajectories. A subsequent quality normalization and difficulty-aware classification process filters out low-quality samples and organizes the dataset from easy to hard. Furthermore, we propose a two-stage training framework to enhance multi-tool collaborative reasoning by: (1) cold-start fine-tuning, which guides LLMs to explore reasoning patterns via tool-invocation feedback; and (2) a multi-tool self-critic RL algorithm with hierarchical reward design, which reinforces reward understanding and promotes effective tool collaboration. Experimental analyses on over 10 challenging reasoning benchmarks highlight the effectiveness and efficiency of Tool-Star. The code is available at https://github.com/dongguanting/Tool-Star.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16410</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 09:00:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMMR: Benchmarking Massive Multi-Modal Reasoning Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16459</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16459.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guiyao Tie, Xueyang Zhou, Tianhe Gu, Ruihang Zhang, Chaoran Hu, Sizhe Zhang, Mengqu Sun, Yan Zhang, Pan Zhou, Lichao Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Multi-Modal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have enabled unified processing of language, vision, and structured inputs, opening the door to complex tasks such as logical deduction, spatial reasoning, and scientific analysis. Despite their promise, the reasoning capabilities of MLLMs, particularly those augmented with intermediate thinking traces (MLLMs-T), remain poorly understood and lack standardized evaluation benchmarks. Existing work focuses primarily on perception or final answer correctness, offering limited insight into how models reason or fail across modalities. To address this gap, we introduce the MMMR, a new benchmark designed to rigorously evaluate multi-modal reasoning with explicit thinking. The MMMR comprises 1) a high-difficulty dataset of 1,083 questions spanning six diverse reasoning types with symbolic depth and multi-hop demands and 2) a modular Reasoning Trace Evaluation Pipeline (RTEP) for assessing reasoning quality beyond accuracy through metrics like relevance, consistency, and structured error annotations. Empirical results show that MLLMs-T overall outperform non-thinking counterparts, but even top models like Claude-3.7-Sonnet and Gemini-2.5 Pro suffer from reasoning pathologies such as inconsistency and overthinking. This benchmark reveals persistent gaps between accuracy and reasoning quality and provides an actionable evaluation pipeline for future model development. Overall, the MMMR offers a scalable foundation for evaluating, comparing, and improving the next generation of multi-modal reasoning systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16459</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 09:41:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KRIS-Bench: Benchmarking Next-Level Intelligent Image Editing Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16707</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16707.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yongliang Wu, Zonghui Li, Xinting Hu, Xinyu Ye, Xianfang Zeng, Gang Yu, Wenbo Zhu, Bernt Schiele, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Xu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multi-modal generative models have enabled significant progress in instruction-based image editing. However, while these models produce visually plausible outputs, their capacity for knowledge-based reasoning editing tasks remains under-explored. In this paper, we introduce KRIS-Bench (Knowledge-based Reasoning in Image-editing Systems Benchmark), a diagnostic benchmark designed to assess models through a cognitively informed lens. Drawing from educational theory, KRIS-Bench categorizes editing tasks across three foundational knowledge types: Factual, Conceptual, and Procedural. Based on this taxonomy, we design 22 representative tasks spanning 7 reasoning dimensions and release 1,267 high-quality annotated editing instances. To support fine-grained evaluation, we propose a comprehensive protocol that incorporates a novel Knowledge Plausibility metric, enhanced by knowledge hints and calibrated through human studies. Empirical results on 10 state-of-the-art models reveal significant gaps in reasoning performance, highlighting the need for knowledge-centric benchmarks to advance the development of intelligent image editing systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16707</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 14:08:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NovelSeek: When Agent Becomes the Scientist -- Building Closed-Loop   System from Hypothesis to Verification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16938</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.16938.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NovelSeek Team, Bo Zhang, Shiyang Feng, Xiangchao Yan, Jiakang Yuan, Zhiyin Yu, Xiaohan He, Songtao Huang, Shaowei Hou, Zheng Nie, Zhilong Wang, Jinyao Liu, Runmin Ma, Tianshuo Peng, Peng Ye, Dongzhan Zhou, Shufei Zhang, Xiaosong Wang, Yilan Zhang, Meng Li, Zhongying Tu, Xiangyu Yue, Wangli Ouyang, Bowen Zhou, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 110&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Artificial Intelligence (AI) is accelerating the transformation of scientific research paradigms, not only enhancing research efficiency but also driving innovation. We introduce NovelSeek, a unified closed-loop multi-agent framework to conduct Autonomous Scientific Research (ASR) across various scientific research fields, enabling researchers to tackle complicated problems in these fields with unprecedented speed and precision. NovelSeek highlights three key advantages: 1) Scalability: NovelSeek has demonstrated its versatility across 12 scientific research tasks, capable of generating innovative ideas to enhance the performance of baseline code. 2) Interactivity: NovelSeek provides an interface for human expert feedback and multi-agent interaction in automated end-to-end processes, allowing for the seamless integration of domain expert knowledge. 3) Efficiency: NovelSeek has achieved promising performance gains in several scientific fields with significantly less time cost compared to human efforts. For instance, in reaction yield prediction, it increased from 27.6% to 35.4% in just 12 hours; in enhancer activity prediction, accuracy rose from 0.52 to 0.79 with only 4 hours of processing; and in 2D semantic segmentation, precision advanced from 78.8% to 81.0% in a mere 30 hours.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16938</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 17:27:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Model is Stubborn: Diagnosing Instruction Overriding in   Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17225</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17225.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Doohyuk Jang, Yoonjeon Kim, Chanjae Park, Hyun Ryu, Eunho Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models have demonstrated remarkable proficiency in long and complex reasoning tasks. However, they frequently exhibit a problematic reliance on familiar reasoning patterns, a phenomenon we term reasoning rigidity. Despite explicit instructions from users, these models often override clearly stated conditions and default to habitual reasoning trajectories, leading to incorrect conclusions. This behavior presents significant challenges, particularly in domains such as mathematics and logic puzzle, where precise adherence to specified constraints is critical. To systematically investigate reasoning rigidity, a behavior largely unexplored in prior work, we introduce a expert-curated diagnostic set, . Our dataset includes specially modified variants of existing mathematical benchmarks, namely AIME and MATH500, as well as well-known puzzles deliberately redesigned to require deviation from familiar reasoning strategies. Using this dataset, we identify recurring contamination patterns that occur when models default to ingrained reasoning. Specifically, we categorize this contamination into three distinctive modes: (i) Interpretation Overload, (ii) Input Distrust, and (iii) Partial Instruction Attention, each causing models to ignore or distort provided instructions. We publicly release our diagnostic set to facilitate future research on mitigating reasoning rigidity in language models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17225</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 19:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distilling LLM Agent into Small Models with Retrieval and Code Tools</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17612</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17612.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minki Kang, Jongwon Jeong, Seanie Lee, Jaewoong Cho, Sung Ju Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) excel at complex reasoning tasks but remain computationally expensive, limiting their practical deployment. To address this, recent works have focused on distilling reasoning capabilities into smaller language models (sLMs) using chain-of-thought (CoT) traces from teacher LLMs. However, this approach struggles in scenarios requiring rare factual knowledge or precise computation, where sLMs often hallucinate due to limited capability. In this work, we propose Agent Distillation, a framework for transferring not only reasoning capability but full task-solving behavior from LLM-based agents into sLMs with retrieval and code tools. We improve agent distillation along two complementary axes: (1) we introduce a prompting method called first-thought prefix to enhance the quality of teacher-generated trajectories; and (2) we propose a self-consistent action generation for improving test-time robustness of small agents. We evaluate our method on eight reasoning tasks across factual and mathematical domains, covering both in-domain and out-of-domain generalization. Our results show that sLMs as small as 0.5B, 1.5B, 3B parameters can achieve performance competitive with next-tier larger 1.5B, 3B, 7B models fine-tuned using CoT distillation, demonstrating the potential of agent distillation for building practical, tool-using small agents. Our code is available at https://github.com/Nardien/agent-distillation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17612</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 08:20:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Image and Video Generation via Test-Time Evolutionary Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17618</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17618.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran He, Jiajun Liang, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Kun Gai, Ling Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As the marginal cost of scaling computation (data and parameters) during model pre-training continues to increase substantially, test-time scaling (TTS) has emerged as a promising direction for improving generative model performance by allocating additional computation at inference time. While TTS has demonstrated significant success across multiple language tasks, there remains a notable gap in understanding the test-time scaling behaviors of image and video generative models (diffusion-based or flow-based models). Although recent works have initiated exploration into inference-time strategies for vision tasks, these approaches face critical limitations: being constrained to task-specific domains, exhibiting poor scalability, or falling into reward over-optimization that sacrifices sample diversity. In this paper, we propose Evolutionary Search (EvoSearch), a novel, generalist, and efficient TTS method that effectively enhances the scalability of both image and video generation across diffusion and flow models, without requiring additional training or model expansion. EvoSearch reformulates test-time scaling for diffusion and flow models as an evolutionary search problem, leveraging principles from biological evolution to efficiently explore and refine the denoising trajectory. By incorporating carefully designed selection and mutation mechanisms tailored to the stochastic differential equation denoising process, EvoSearch iteratively generates higher-quality offspring while preserving population diversity. Through extensive evaluation across both diffusion and flow architectures for image and video generation tasks, we demonstrate that our method consistently outperforms existing approaches, achieves higher diversity, and shows strong generalizability to unseen evaluation metrics. Our project is available at the website https://tinnerhrhe.github.io/evosearch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17618</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 08:25:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QwenLong-L1: Towards Long-Context Large Reasoning Models with   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17667</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17667.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fanqi Wan, Weizhou Shen, Shengyi Liao, Yingcheng Shi, Chenliang Li, Ziyi Yang, Ji Zhang, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent large reasoning models (LRMs) have demonstrated strong reasoning capabilities through reinforcement learning (RL). These improvements have primarily been observed within the short-context reasoning tasks. In contrast, extending LRMs to effectively process and reason on long-context inputs via RL remains a critical unsolved challenge. To bridge this gap, we first formalize the paradigm of long-context reasoning RL, and identify key challenges in suboptimal training efficiency and unstable optimization process. To address these issues, we propose QwenLong-L1, a framework that adapts short-context LRMs to long-context scenarios via progressive context scaling. Specifically, we utilize a warm-up supervised fine-tuning (SFT) stage to establish a robust initial policy, followed by a curriculum-guided phased RL technique to stabilize the policy evolution, and enhanced with a difficulty-aware retrospective sampling strategy to incentivize the policy exploration. Experiments on seven long-context document question-answering benchmarks demonstrate that QwenLong-L1-32B outperforms flagship LRMs like OpenAI-o3-mini and Qwen3-235B-A22B, achieving performance on par with Claude-3.7-Sonnet-Thinking, demonstrating leading performance among state-of-the-art LRMs. This work advances the development of practical long-context LRMs capable of robust reasoning across information-intensive environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17667</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 09:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Overthink it. Preferring Shorter Thinking Chains for Improved LLM   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17813</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17813.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Michael Hassid, Gabriel Synnaeve, Yossi Adi, Roy Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning large language models (LLMs) heavily rely on scaling test-time compute to perform complex reasoning tasks by generating extensive "thinking" chains. While demonstrating impressive results, this approach incurs significant computational costs and inference time. In this work, we challenge the assumption that long thinking chains results in better reasoning capabilities. We first demonstrate that shorter reasoning chains within individual questions are significantly more likely to yield correct answers - up to 34.5% more accurate than the longest chain sampled for the same question. Based on these results, we suggest short-m@k, a novel reasoning LLM inference method. Our method executes k independent generations in parallel and halts computation once the first m thinking processes are done. The final answer is chosen using majority voting among these m chains. Basic short-1@k demonstrates similar or even superior performance over standard majority voting in low-compute settings - using up to 40% fewer thinking tokens. short-3@k, while slightly less efficient than short-1@k, consistently surpasses majority voting across all compute budgets, while still being substantially faster (up to 33% wall time reduction). Inspired by our results, we finetune an LLM using short, long, and randomly selected reasoning chains. We then observe that training on the shorter ones leads to better performance. Our findings suggest rethinking current methods of test-time compute in reasoning LLMs, emphasizing that longer "thinking" does not necessarily translate to improved performance and can, counter-intuitively, lead to degraded results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17813</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 12:29:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutarjim: Advancing Bidirectional Arabic-English Translation with a   Small Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17894</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.17894.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Khalil Hennara, Muhammad Hreden, Mohamed Motaism Hamed, Zeina Aldallal, Sara Chrouf, Safwan AlModhayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 205&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Mutarjim, a compact yet powerful language model for bidirectional Arabic-English translation. While large-scale LLMs have shown impressive progress in natural language processing tasks, including machine translation, smaller models. Leveraging this insight, we developed Mutarjim based on Kuwain-1.5B , a language model tailored for both Arabic and English. Despite its modest size, Mutarjim outperforms much larger models on several established benchmarks, achieved through an optimized two-phase training approach and a carefully curated, high-quality training corpus.. Experimental results show that Mutarjim rivals models up to 20 times larger while significantly reducing computational costs and training requirements. We also introduce Tarjama-25, a new benchmark designed to overcome limitations in existing Arabic-English benchmarking datasets, such as domain narrowness, short sentence lengths, and English-source bias. Tarjama-25 comprises 5,000 expert-reviewed sentence pairs and spans a wide range of domains, offering a more comprehensive and balanced evaluation framework. Notably, Mutarjim achieves state-of-the-art performance on the English-to-Arabic task in Tarjama-25, surpassing even significantly larger and proprietary models like GPT-4o mini. We publicly release Tarjama-25 to support future research and advance the evaluation of Arabic-English translation systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17894</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 13:42:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QwenLong-CPRS: Towards infty-LLMs with Dynamic Context Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18092</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18092.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weizhou Shen, Chenliang Li, Fanqi Wan, Shengyi Liao, Shaopeng Lai, Bo Zhang, Yingcheng Shi, Yuning Wu, Gang Fu, Zhansheng Li, Bin Yang, Ji Zhang, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This technical report presents QwenLong-CPRS, a context compression framework designed for explicit long-context optimization, addressing prohibitive computation overhead during the prefill stage and the "lost in the middle" performance degradation of large language models (LLMs) during long sequence processing. Implemented through a novel dynamic context optimization mechanism, QwenLong-CPRS enables multi-granularity context compression guided by natural language instructions, achieving both efficiency gains and improved performance.   Evolved from the Qwen architecture series, QwenLong-CPRS introduces four key innovations: (1) Natural language-guided dynamic optimization, (2) Bidirectional reasoning layers for enhanced boundary awareness, (3) Token critic mechanisms with language modeling heads, and (4) Window-parallel inference.   Comprehensive evaluations across five benchmarks (4K-2M word contexts) demonstrate QwenLong-CPRS's threefold effectiveness: (1) Consistent superiority over other context management methods like RAG and sparse attention in both accuracy and efficiency. (2) Architecture-agnostic integration with all flagship LLMs, including GPT-4o, Gemini2.0-pro, Claude3.7-sonnet, DeepSeek-v3, and Qwen2.5-max, achieves 21.59times context compression alongside 19.15-point average performance gains; (3) Deployed with Qwen2.5-32B-Instruct, QwenLong-CPRS surpasses leading proprietary LLMs by 4.85 and 10.88 points on Ruler-128K and InfiniteBench, establishing new SOTA performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18092</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 16:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TabSTAR: A Foundation Tabular Model With Semantically Target-Aware   Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18125</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18125.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alan Arazi, Eilam Shapira, Roi Reichart&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 106&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While deep learning has achieved remarkable success across many domains, it has historically underperformed on tabular learning tasks, which remain dominated by gradient boosting decision trees (GBDTs). However, recent advancements are paving the way for Tabular Foundation Models, which can leverage real-world knowledge and generalize across diverse datasets, particularly when the data contains free-text. Although incorporating language model capabilities into tabular tasks has been explored, most existing methods utilize static, target-agnostic textual representations, limiting their effectiveness. We introduce TabSTAR: a Foundation Tabular Model with Semantically Target-Aware Representations. TabSTAR is designed to enable transfer learning on tabular data with textual features, with an architecture free of dataset-specific parameters. It unfreezes a pretrained text encoder and takes as input target tokens, which provide the model with the context needed to learn task-specific embeddings. TabSTAR achieves state-of-the-art performance for both medium- and large-sized datasets across known benchmarks of classification tasks with text features, and its pretraining phase exhibits scaling laws in the number of datasets, offering a pathway for further performance improvements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18125</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One RL to See Them All: Visual Triple Unified Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18129</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18129.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yan Ma, Linge Du, Xuyang Shen, Shaoxiang Chen, Pengfei Li, Qibing Ren, Lizhuang Ma, Yuchao Dai, Pengfei Liu, Junjie Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) has significantly advanced the reasoning capabilities of vision-language models (VLMs). However, the use of RL beyond reasoning tasks remains largely unexplored, especially for perceptionintensive tasks like object detection and grounding. We propose V-Triune, a Visual Triple Unified Reinforcement Learning system that enables VLMs to jointly learn visual reasoning and perception tasks within a single training pipeline. V-Triune comprises triple complementary components: Sample-Level Data Formatting (to unify diverse task inputs), Verifier-Level Reward Computation (to deliver custom rewards via specialized verifiers) , and Source-Level Metric Monitoring (to diagnose problems at the data-source level). We further introduce a novel Dynamic IoU reward, which provides adaptive, progressive, and definite feedback for perception tasks handled by V-Triune. Our approach is instantiated within off-the-shelf RL training framework using open-source 7B and 32B backbone models. The resulting model, dubbed Orsta (One RL to See Them All), demonstrates consistent improvements across both reasoning and perception tasks. This broad capability is significantly shaped by its training on a diverse dataset, constructed around four representative visual reasoning tasks (Math, Puzzle, Chart, and Science) and four visual perception tasks (Grounding, Detection, Counting, and OCR). Subsequently, Orsta achieves substantial gains on MEGA-Bench Core, with improvements ranging from +2.1 to an impressive +14.1 across its various 7B and 32B model variants, with performance benefits extending to a wide range of downstream tasks. These results highlight the effectiveness and scalability of our unified RL approach for VLMs. The V-Triune system, along with the Orsta models, is publicly available at https://github.com/MiniMax-AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18129</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 17:41:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guided by Gut: Efficient Test-Time Scaling with Reinforced Intrinsic   Confidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20325</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20325.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Amirhosein Ghasemabadi, Keith G. Mills, Baochun Li, Di Niu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Test-Time Scaling (TTS) methods for enhancing Large Language Model (LLM) reasoning often incur substantial computational costs, primarily due to extensive reliance on external Process Reward Models (PRMs) or sampling methods like Best-of-N (BoN). This paper introduces Guided by Gut (GG), an efficient self-guided TTS framework that achieves PRM-level performance without costly external verifier models. Our method employs a lightweight tree search guided solely by intrinsic LLM signals, token-level confidence and step novelty. One critical innovation is improving the reliability of internal confidence estimates via a targeted reinforcement learning fine-tuning phase. Empirical evaluations on challenging mathematical reasoning benchmarks demonstrate that GG enables smaller models (e.g., 1.5B parameters) to achieve accuracy matching or surpassing significantly larger models (e.g., 32B-70B parameters), while reducing GPU memory usage by up to 10x. Compared to PRM-based methods, GG achieves comparable accuracy with 8x faster inference speeds and 4-5x lower memory usage. Additionally, GG reduces KV cache memory usage by approximately 50% compared to the BoN strategy, facilitating more efficient and practical deployment of TTS techniques.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20325</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 18:19:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniConsistency: Learning Style-Agnostic Consistency from Paired   Stylization Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18445</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18445.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiren Song, Cheng Liu, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion models have advanced image stylization significantly, yet two core challenges persist: (1) maintaining consistent stylization in complex scenes, particularly identity, composition, and fine details, and (2) preventing style degradation in image-to-image pipelines with style LoRAs. GPT-4o's exceptional stylization consistency highlights the performance gap between open-source methods and proprietary models. To bridge this gap, we propose OmniConsistency, a universal consistency plugin leveraging large-scale Diffusion Transformers (DiTs). OmniConsistency contributes: (1) an in-context consistency learning framework trained on aligned image pairs for robust generalization; (2) a two-stage progressive learning strategy decoupling style learning from consistency preservation to mitigate style degradation; and (3) a fully plug-and-play design compatible with arbitrary style LoRAs under the Flux framework. Extensive experiments show that OmniConsistency significantly enhances visual coherence and aesthetic quality, achieving performance comparable to commercial state-of-the-art model GPT-4o.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18445</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 01:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse VideoGen2: Accelerate Video Generation with Sparse Attention via   Semantic-Aware Permutation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18875</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.18875.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuo Yang, Haocheng Xi, Yilong Zhao, Muyang Li, Jintao Zhang, Han Cai, Yujun Lin, Xiuyu Li, Chenfeng Xu, Kelly Peng, Jianfei Chen, Song Han, Kurt Keutzer, Ion Stoica&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Transformers (DiTs) are essential for video generation but suffer from significant latency due to the quadratic complexity of attention. By computing only critical tokens, sparse attention reduces computational costs and offers a promising acceleration approach. However, we identify that existing methods fail to approach optimal generation quality under the same computation budget for two reasons: (1) Inaccurate critical token identification: current methods cluster tokens based on position rather than semantics, leading to imprecise aggregated representations. (2) Excessive computation waste: critical tokens are scattered among non-critical ones, leading to wasted computation on GPUs, which are optimized for processing contiguous tokens. In this paper, we propose SVG2, a training-free framework that maximizes identification accuracy and minimizes computation waste, achieving a Pareto frontier trade-off between generation quality and efficiency. The core of SVG2 is semantic-aware permutation, which clusters and reorders tokens based on semantic similarity using k-means. This approach ensures both a precise cluster representation, improving identification accuracy, and a densified layout of critical tokens, enabling efficient computation without padding. Additionally, SVG2 integrates top-p dynamic budget control and customized kernel implementations, achieving up to 2.30x and 1.89x speedup while maintaining a PSNR of up to 30 and 26 on HunyuanVideo and Wan 2.1, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.18875</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 21:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VerIPO: Cultivating Long Reasoning in Video-LLMs via Verifier-Gudied   Iterative Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19000</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19000.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunxin Li, Xinyu Chen, Zitao Li, Zhenyu Liu, Longyue Wang, Wenhan Luo, Baotian Hu, Min Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Applying Reinforcement Learning (RL) to Video Large Language Models (Video-LLMs) shows significant promise for complex video reasoning. However, popular Reinforcement Fine-Tuning (RFT) methods, such as outcome-based Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), are limited by data preparation bottlenecks (e.g., noise or high cost) and exhibit unstable improvements in the quality of long chain-of-thoughts (CoTs) and downstream performance.To address these limitations, we propose VerIPO, a Verifier-guided Iterative Policy Optimization method designed to gradually improve video LLMs' capacity for generating deep, long-term reasoning chains. The core component is Rollout-Aware Verifier, positioned between the GRPO and Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) training phases to form the GRPO-Verifier-DPO training loop. This verifier leverages small LLMs as a judge to assess the reasoning logic of rollouts, enabling the construction of high-quality contrastive data, including reflective and contextually consistent CoTs. These curated preference samples drive the efficient DPO stage (7x faster than GRPO), leading to marked improvements in reasoning chain quality, especially in terms of length and contextual consistency. This training loop benefits from GRPO's expansive search and DPO's targeted optimization. Experimental results demonstrate: 1) Significantly faster and more effective optimization compared to standard GRPO variants, yielding superior performance; 2) Our trained models exceed the direct inference of large-scale instruction-tuned Video-LLMs, producing long and contextually consistent CoTs on diverse video reasoning tasks; and 3) Our model with one iteration outperforms powerful LMMs (e.g., Kimi-VL) and long reasoning models (e.g., Video-R1), highlighting its effectiveness and stability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 06:41:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shifting AI Efficiency From Model-Centric to Data-Centric Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19147</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19147.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuyang Liu, Zichen Wen, Shaobo Wang, Junjie Chen, Zhishan Tao, Yubo Wang, Xiangqi Jin, Chang Zou, Yiyu Wang, Chenfei Liao, Xu Zheng, Honggang Chen, Weijia Li, Xuming Hu, Conghui He, Linfeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 139&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of large language models (LLMs) and multi-modal LLMs (MLLMs) has historically relied on model-centric scaling through increasing parameter counts from millions to hundreds of billions to drive performance gains. However, as we approach hardware limits on model size, the dominant computational bottleneck has fundamentally shifted to the quadratic cost of self-attention over long token sequences, now driven by ultra-long text contexts, high-resolution images, and extended videos. In this position paper, we argue that the focus of research for efficient AI is shifting from model-centric compression to data-centric compression. We position token compression as the new frontier, which improves AI efficiency via reducing the number of tokens during model training or inference. Through comprehensive analysis, we first examine recent developments in long-context AI across various domains and establish a unified mathematical framework for existing model efficiency strategies, demonstrating why token compression represents a crucial paradigm shift in addressing long-context overhead. Subsequently, we systematically review the research landscape of token compression, analyzing its fundamental benefits and identifying its compelling advantages across diverse scenarios. Furthermore, we provide an in-depth analysis of current challenges in token compression research and outline promising future directions. Ultimately, our work aims to offer a fresh perspective on AI efficiency, synthesize existing research, and catalyze innovative developments to address the challenges that increasing context lengths pose to the AI community's advancement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19147</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 13:51:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PATS: Process-Level Adaptive Thinking Mode Switching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19250</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19250.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Wang, Junxiao Liu, Shimao Zhang, Jiajun Chen, Shujian Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current large-language models (LLMs) typically adopt a fixed reasoning strategy, either simple or complex, for all questions, regardless of their difficulty. This neglect of variation in task and reasoning process complexity leads to an imbalance between performance and efficiency. Existing methods attempt to implement training-free fast-slow thinking system switching to handle problems of varying difficulty, but are limited by coarse-grained solution-level strategy adjustments. To address this issue, we propose a novel reasoning paradigm: Process-Level Adaptive Thinking Mode Switching (PATS), which enables LLMs to dynamically adjust their reasoning strategy based on the difficulty of each step, optimizing the balance between accuracy and computational efficiency. Our approach integrates Process Reward Models (PRMs) with Beam Search, incorporating progressive mode switching and bad-step penalty mechanisms. Experiments on diverse mathematical benchmarks demonstrate that our methodology achieves high accuracy while maintaining moderate token usage. This study emphasizes the significance of process-level, difficulty-aware reasoning strategy adaptation, offering valuable insights into efficient inference for LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19250</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 17:58:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alchemist: Turning Public Text-to-Image Data into Generative Gold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19297</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19297.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Valerii Startsev, Alexander Ustyuzhanin, Alexey Kirillov, Dmitry Baranchuk, Sergey Kastryulin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Pre-training equips text-to-image (T2I) models with broad world knowledge, but this alone is often insufficient to achieve high aesthetic quality and alignment. Consequently, supervised fine-tuning (SFT) is crucial for further refinement. However, its effectiveness highly depends on the quality of the fine-tuning dataset. Existing public SFT datasets frequently target narrow domains (e.g., anime or specific art styles), and the creation of high-quality, general-purpose SFT datasets remains a significant challenge. Current curation methods are often costly and struggle to identify truly impactful samples. This challenge is further complicated by the scarcity of public general-purpose datasets, as leading models often rely on large, proprietary, and poorly documented internal data, hindering broader research progress. This paper introduces a novel methodology for creating general-purpose SFT datasets by leveraging a pre-trained generative model as an estimator of high-impact training samples. We apply this methodology to construct and release Alchemist, a compact (3,350 samples) yet highly effective SFT dataset. Experiments demonstrate that Alchemist substantially improves the generative quality of five public T2I models while preserving diversity and style. Additionally, we release the fine-tuned models' weights to the public.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19297</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 20:08:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BizFinBench: A Business-Driven Real-World Financial Benchmark for   Evaluating LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19457</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19457.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guilong Lu, Xuntao Guo, Rongjunchen Zhang, Wenqiao Zhu, Ji Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models excel in general tasks, yet assessing their reliability in logic-heavy, precision-critical domains like finance, law, and healthcare remains challenging. To address this, we introduce BizFinBench, the first benchmark specifically designed to evaluate LLMs in real-world financial applications. BizFinBench consists of 6,781 well-annotated queries in Chinese, spanning five dimensions: numerical calculation, reasoning, information extraction, prediction recognition, and knowledge-based question answering, grouped into nine fine-grained categories. The benchmark includes both objective and subjective metrics. We also introduce IteraJudge, a novel LLM evaluation method that reduces bias when LLMs serve as evaluators in objective metrics. We benchmark 25 models, including both proprietary and open-source systems. Extensive experiments show that no model dominates across all tasks. Our evaluation reveals distinct capability patterns: (1) In Numerical Calculation, Claude-3.5-Sonnet (63.18) and DeepSeek-R1 (64.04) lead, while smaller models like Qwen2.5-VL-3B (15.92) lag significantly; (2) In Reasoning, proprietary models dominate (ChatGPT-o3: 83.58, Gemini-2.0-Flash: 81.15), with open-source models trailing by up to 19.49 points; (3) In Information Extraction, the performance spread is the largest, with DeepSeek-R1 scoring 71.46, while Qwen3-1.7B scores 11.23; (4) In Prediction Recognition, performance variance is minimal, with top models scoring between 39.16 and 50.00. We find that while current LLMs handle routine finance queries competently, they struggle with complex scenarios requiring cross-concept reasoning. BizFinBench offers a rigorous, business-aligned benchmark for future research. The code and dataset are available at https://github.com/HiThink-Research/BizFinBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19457</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 03:23:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GraLoRA: Granular Low-Rank Adaptation for Parameter-Efficient   Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20355</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20355.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yeonjoon Jung, Daehyun Ahn, Hyungjun Kim, Taesu Kim, Eunhyeok Park&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) is a popular method for parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) of generative models, valued for its simplicity and effectiveness. Despite recent enhancements, LoRA still suffers from a fundamental limitation: overfitting when the bottleneck is widened. It performs best at ranks 32-64, yet its accuracy stagnates or declines at higher ranks, still falling short of full fine-tuning (FFT) performance. We identify the root cause as LoRA's structural bottleneck, which introduces gradient entanglement to the unrelated input channels and distorts gradient propagation. To address this, we introduce a novel structure, Granular Low-Rank Adaptation (GraLoRA) that partitions weight matrices into sub-blocks, each with its own low-rank adapter. With negligible computational or storage cost, GraLoRA overcomes LoRA's limitations, effectively increases the representational capacity, and more closely approximates FFT behavior. Experiments on code generation and commonsense reasoning benchmarks show that GraLoRA consistently outperforms LoRA and other baselines, achieving up to +8.5% absolute gain in Pass@1 on HumanEval+. These improvements hold across model sizes and rank settings, making GraLoRA a scalable and robust solution for PEFT. Code, data, and scripts are available at https://github.com/SqueezeBits/GraLoRA.git&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20355</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 06:48:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SynLogic: Synthesizing Verifiable Reasoning Data at Scale for Learning   Logical Reasoning and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19641</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19641.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junteng Liu, Yuanxiang Fan, Zhuo Jiang, Han Ding, Yongyi Hu, Chi Zhang, Yiqi Shi, Shitong Weng, Aili Chen, Shiqi Chen, Yunan Huang, Mozhi Zhang, Pengyu Zhao, Junjie Yan, Junxian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances such as OpenAI-o1 and DeepSeek R1 have demonstrated the potential of Reinforcement Learning (RL) to enhance reasoning abilities in Large Language Models (LLMs). While open-source replication efforts have primarily focused on mathematical and coding domains, methods and resources for developing general reasoning capabilities remain underexplored. This gap is partly due to the challenge of collecting diverse and verifiable reasoning data suitable for RL. We hypothesize that logical reasoning is critical for developing general reasoning capabilities, as logic forms a fundamental building block of reasoning. In this work, we present SynLogic, a data synthesis framework and dataset that generates diverse logical reasoning data at scale, encompassing 35 diverse logical reasoning tasks. The SynLogic approach enables controlled synthesis of data with adjustable difficulty and quantity. Importantly, all examples can be verified by simple rules, making them ideally suited for RL with verifiable rewards. In our experiments, we validate the effectiveness of RL training on the SynLogic dataset based on 7B and 32B models. SynLogic leads to state-of-the-art logical reasoning performance among open-source datasets, surpassing DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-32B by 6 points on BBEH. Furthermore, mixing SynLogic data with mathematical and coding tasks improves the training efficiency of these domains and significantly enhances reasoning generalization. Notably, our mixed training model outperforms DeepSeek-R1-Zero-Qwen-32B across multiple benchmarks. These findings position SynLogic as a valuable resource for advancing the broader reasoning capabilities of LLMs. We open-source both the data synthesis pipeline and the SynLogic dataset at https://github.com/MiniMax-AI/SynLogic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19641</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 07:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering Trajectory-Aided LLM Reasoning: An Optimization Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19815</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19815.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junnan Liu, Hongwei Liu, Linchen Xiao, Shudong Liu, Taolin Zhang, Zihan Ma, Songyang Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel framework for comprehending the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs) through the perspective of meta-learning. By conceptualizing reasoning trajectories as pseudo-gradient descent updates to the LLM's parameters, we identify parallels between LLM reasoning and various meta-learning paradigms. We formalize the training process for reasoning tasks as a meta-learning setup, with each question treated as an individual task, and reasoning trajectories serving as the inner loop optimization for adapting model parameters. Once trained on a diverse set of questions, the LLM develops fundamental reasoning capabilities that can generalize to previously unseen questions. Extensive empirical evaluations substantiate the strong connection between LLM reasoning and meta-learning, exploring several issues of significant interest from a meta-learning standpoint. Our work not only enhances the understanding of LLM reasoning but also provides practical insights for improving these models through established meta-learning techniques.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19815</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 10:52:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enigmata: Scaling Logical Reasoning in Large Language Models with   Synthetic Verifiable Puzzles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19914</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.19914.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiangjie Chen, Qianyu He, Siyu Yuan, Aili Chen, Zhicheng Cai, Weinan Dai, Hongli Yu, Qiying Yu, Xuefeng Li, Jiaze Chen, Hao Zhou, Mingxuan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs), such as OpenAI's o1 and DeepSeek's R1, excel at advanced reasoning tasks like math and coding via Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR), but still struggle with puzzles solvable by humans without domain knowledge. We introduce Enigmata, the first comprehensive suite tailored for improving LLMs with puzzle reasoning skills. It includes 36 tasks across seven categories, each with 1) a generator that produces unlimited examples with controllable difficulty and 2) a rule-based verifier for automatic evaluation. This generator-verifier design supports scalable, multi-task RL training, fine-grained analysis, and seamless RLVR integration. We further propose Enigmata-Eval, a rigorous benchmark, and develop optimized multi-task RLVR strategies. Our trained model, Qwen2.5-32B-Enigmata, consistently surpasses o3-mini-high and o1 on the puzzle reasoning benchmarks like Enigmata-Eval, ARC-AGI (32.8%), and ARC-AGI 2 (0.6%). It also generalizes well to out-of-domain puzzle benchmarks and mathematical reasoning, with little multi-tasking trade-off. When trained on larger models like Seed1.5-Thinking (20B activated parameters and 200B total parameters), puzzle data from Enigmata further boosts SoTA performance on advanced math and STEM reasoning tasks such as AIME (2024-2025), BeyondAIME and GPQA (Diamond), showing nice generalization benefits of Enigmata. This work offers a unified, controllable framework for advancing logical reasoning in LLMs. Resources of this work can be found at https://seed-enigmata.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19914</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 12:40:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARM: Adaptive Reasoning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20258</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20258.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siye Wu, Jian Xie, Yikai Zhang, Aili Chen, Kai Zhang, Yu Su, Yanghua Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While large reasoning models demonstrate strong performance on complex tasks, they lack the ability to adjust reasoning token usage based on task difficulty. This often leads to the "overthinking" problem -- excessive and unnecessary reasoning -- which, although potentially mitigated by human intervention to control the token budget, still fundamentally contradicts the goal of achieving fully autonomous AI. In this work, we propose Adaptive Reasoning Model (ARM), a reasoning model capable of adaptively selecting appropriate reasoning formats based on the task at hand. These formats include three efficient ones -- Direct Answer, Short CoT, and Code -- as well as a more elaborate format, Long CoT. To train ARM, we introduce Ada-GRPO, an adaptation of Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), which addresses the format collapse issue in traditional GRPO. Ada-GRPO enables ARM to achieve high token efficiency, reducing tokens by an average of 30%, and up to 70%, while maintaining performance comparable to the model that relies solely on Long CoT. Furthermore, not only does it improve inference efficiency through reduced token generation, but it also brings a 2x speedup in training. In addition to the default Adaptive Mode, ARM supports two additional reasoning modes: 1) Instruction-Guided Mode, which allows users to explicitly specify the reasoning format via special tokens -- ideal when the appropriate format is known for a batch of tasks. 2) Consensus-Guided Mode, which aggregates the outputs of the three efficient formats and resorts to Long CoT in case of disagreement, prioritizing performance with higher token usage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20258</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:38:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenS2V-Nexus: A Detailed Benchmark and Million-Scale Dataset for   Subject-to-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20292</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20292.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shenghai Yuan, Xianyi He, Yufan Deng, Yang Ye, Jinfa Huang, Bin Lin, Chongyang Ma, Jiebo Luo, Li Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Subject-to-Video (S2V) generation aims to create videos that faithfully incorporate reference content, providing enhanced flexibility in the production of videos. To establish the infrastructure for S2V generation, we propose OpenS2V-Nexus, consisting of (i) OpenS2V-Eval, a fine-grained benchmark, and (ii) OpenS2V-5M, a million-scale dataset. In contrast to existing S2V benchmarks inherited from VBench that focus on global and coarse-grained assessment of generated videos, OpenS2V-Eval focuses on the model's ability to generate subject-consistent videos with natural subject appearance and identity fidelity. For these purposes, OpenS2V-Eval introduces 180 prompts from seven major categories of S2V, which incorporate both real and synthetic test data. Furthermore, to accurately align human preferences with S2V benchmarks, we propose three automatic metrics, NexusScore, NaturalScore and GmeScore, to separately quantify subject consistency, naturalness, and text relevance in generated videos. Building on this, we conduct a comprehensive evaluation of 16 representative S2V models, highlighting their strengths and weaknesses across different content. Moreover, we create the first open-source large-scale S2V generation dataset OpenS2V-5M, which consists of five million high-quality 720P subject-text-video triples. Specifically, we ensure subject-information diversity in our dataset by (1) segmenting subjects and building pairing information via cross-video associations and (2) prompting GPT-Image-1 on raw frames to synthesize multi-view representations. Through OpenS2V-Nexus, we deliver a robust infrastructure to accelerate future S2V generation research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20292</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 17:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-rebench: An Automated Pipeline for Task Collection and   Decontaminated Evaluation of Software Engineering Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20411</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.20411.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ibragim Badertdinov, Alexander Golubev, Maksim Nekrashevich, Anton Shevtsov, Simon Karasik, Andrei Andriushchenko, Maria Trofimova, Daria Litvintseva, Boris Yangel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 78&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM-based agents have shown promising capabilities in a growing range of software engineering (SWE) tasks. However, advancing this field faces two critical challenges. First, high-quality training data is scarce, especially data that reflects real-world SWE scenarios, where agents must interact with development environments, execute code and adapt behavior based on the outcomes of their actions. Existing datasets are either limited to one-shot code generation or comprise small, manually curated collections of interactive tasks, lacking both scale and diversity. Second, the lack of fresh interactive SWE tasks affects evaluation of rapidly improving models, as static benchmarks quickly become outdated due to contamination issues. To address these limitations, we introduce a novel, automated, and scalable pipeline to continuously extract real-world interactive SWE tasks from diverse GitHub repositories. Using this pipeline, we construct SWE-rebench, a public dataset comprising over 21,000 interactive Python-based SWE tasks, suitable for reinforcement learning of SWE agents at scale. Additionally, we use continuous supply of fresh tasks collected using SWE-rebench methodology to build a contamination-free benchmark for agentic software engineering. We compare results of various LLMs on this benchmark to results on SWE-bench Verified and show that performance of some language models might be inflated due to contamination issues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20411</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 18:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SageAttention2++: A More Efficient Implementation of SageAttention2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21136</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21136.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jintao Zhang, Xiaoming Xu, Jia Wei, Haofeng Huang, Pengle Zhang, Chendong Xiang, Jun Zhu, Jianfei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The efficiency of attention is critical because its time complexity grows quadratically with sequence length. SageAttention2 addresses this by utilizing quantization to accelerate matrix multiplications (Matmul) in attention. To further accelerate SageAttention2, we propose to utilize the faster instruction of FP8 Matmul accumulated in FP16. The instruction is 2x faster than the FP8 Matmul used in SageAttention2. Our experiments show that SageAttention2++ achieves a 3.9x speedup over FlashAttention while maintaining the same attention accuracy as SageAttention2. This means SageAttention2++ effectively accelerates various models, including those for language, image, and video generation, with negligible end-to-end metrics loss. The code will be available at https://github.com/thu-ml/SageAttention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21136</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 12:50:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Latent Capacity of LLMs for One-Step Text Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21189</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21189.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gleb Mezentsev, Ivan Oseledets&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A recent study showed that large language models (LLMs) can reconstruct surprisingly long texts - up to thousands of tokens - via autoregressive generation from just one specially trained input embedding. In this work, we explore whether such reconstruction is possible without autoregression. We show that frozen LLMs can generate hundreds of accurate tokens in just one forward pass, when provided with only two learned embeddings. This reveals a surprising and underexplored capability of LLMs - multi-token generation without iterative decoding. We investigate the behaviour of these embeddings and provide insight into the type of information they encode. We also empirically show that although these representations are not unique for a given text, they form connected and local regions in embedding space - a property that suggests the potential of learning a dedicated encoder into that space.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21189</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 13:39:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MME-Reasoning: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Logical Reasoning in MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21327</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21327.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiakang Yuan, Tianshuo Peng, Yilei Jiang, Yiting Lu, Renrui Zhang, Kaituo Feng, Chaoyou Fu, Tao Chen, Lei Bai, Bo Zhang, Xiangyu Yue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 79&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Logical reasoning is a fundamental aspect of human intelligence and an essential capability for multimodal large language models (MLLMs). Despite the significant advancement in multimodal reasoning, existing benchmarks fail to comprehensively evaluate their reasoning abilities due to the lack of explicit categorization for logical reasoning types and an unclear understanding of reasoning. To address these issues, we introduce MME-Reasoning, a comprehensive benchmark designed to evaluate the reasoning ability of MLLMs, which covers all three types of reasoning (i.e., inductive, deductive, and abductive) in its questions. We carefully curate the data to ensure that each question effectively evaluates reasoning ability rather than perceptual skills or knowledge breadth, and extend the evaluation protocols to cover the evaluation of diverse questions. Our evaluation reveals substantial limitations of state-of-the-art MLLMs when subjected to holistic assessments of logical reasoning capabilities. Even the most advanced MLLMs show limited performance in comprehensive logical reasoning, with notable performance imbalances across reasoning types. In addition, we conducted an in-depth analysis of approaches such as ``thinking mode'' and Rule-based RL, which are commonly believed to enhance reasoning abilities. These findings highlight the critical limitations and performance imbalances of current MLLMs in diverse logical reasoning scenarios, providing comprehensive and systematic insights into the understanding and evaluation of reasoning capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21327</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 15:23:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MME-VideoOCR: Evaluating OCR-Based Capabilities of Multimodal LLMs in   Video Scenarios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21333</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21333.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Shi, Huanqian Wang, Wulin Xie, Huanyao Zhang, Lijie Zhao, Yi-Fan Zhang, Xinfeng Li, Chaoyou Fu, Zhuoer Wen, Wenting Liu, Zhuoran Zhang, Xinlong Chen, Bohan Zeng, Sihan Yang, Yuanxing Zhang, Pengfei Wan, Haotian Wang, Wenjing Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have achieved considerable accuracy in Optical Character Recognition (OCR) from static images. However, their efficacy in video OCR is significantly diminished due to factors such as motion blur, temporal variations, and visual effects inherent in video content. To provide clearer guidance for training practical MLLMs, we introduce the MME-VideoOCR benchmark, which encompasses a comprehensive range of video OCR application scenarios. MME-VideoOCR features 10 task categories comprising 25 individual tasks and spans 44 diverse scenarios. These tasks extend beyond text recognition to incorporate deeper comprehension and reasoning of textual content within videos. The benchmark consists of 1,464 videos with varying resolutions, aspect ratios, and durations, along with 2,000 meticulously curated, manually annotated question-answer pairs. We evaluate 18 state-of-the-art MLLMs on MME-VideoOCR, revealing that even the best-performing model (Gemini-2.5 Pro) achieves an accuracy of only 73.7%. Fine-grained analysis indicates that while existing MLLMs demonstrate strong performance on tasks where relevant texts are contained within a single or few frames, they exhibit limited capability in effectively handling tasks that demand holistic video comprehension. These limitations are especially evident in scenarios that require spatio-temporal reasoning, cross-frame information integration, or resistance to language prior bias. Our findings also highlight the importance of high-resolution visual input and sufficient temporal coverage for reliable OCR in dynamic video scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21333</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 15:27:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R2R: Efficiently Navigating Divergent Reasoning Paths with Small-Large   Model Token Routing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21600</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21600.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Fu, Yi Ge, Yichen You, Enshu Liu, Zhihang Yuan, Guohao Dai, Shengen Yan, Huazhong Yang, Yu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) achieve impressive reasoning capabilities at the cost of substantial inference overhead, posing substantial deployment challenges. Although distilled Small Language Models (SLMs) significantly enhance efficiency, their performance suffers as they fail to follow LLMs' reasoning paths. Luckily, we reveal that only a small fraction of tokens genuinely diverge reasoning paths between LLMs and SLMs. Most generated tokens are either identical or exhibit neutral differences, such as minor variations in abbreviations or expressions. Leveraging this insight, we introduce **Roads to Rome (R2R)**, a neural token routing method that selectively utilizes LLMs only for these critical, path-divergent tokens, while leaving the majority of token generation to the SLM. We also develop an automatic data generation pipeline that identifies divergent tokens and generates token-level routing labels to train the lightweight router. We apply R2R to combine R1-1.5B and R1-32B models from the DeepSeek family, and evaluate on challenging math, coding, and QA benchmarks. With an average activated parameter size of 5.6B, R2R surpasses the average accuracy of R1-7B by 1.6x, outperforming even the R1-14B model. Compared to R1-32B, it delivers a 2.8x wall-clock speedup with comparable performance, advancing the Pareto frontier of test-time scaling efficiency. Our code is available at https://github.com/thu-nics/R2R.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21600</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 16:57:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI-Genie: A Self-Improving Approach for Iteratively Boosting MLLM-based   Mobile GUI Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21496</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21496.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Han Xiao, Guozhi Wang, Yuxiang Chai, Zimu Lu, Weifeng Lin, Hao He, Lue Fan, Liuyang Bian, Rui Hu, Liang Liu, Shuai Ren, Yafei Wen, Xiaoxin Chen, Aojun Zhou, Hongsheng Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce UI-Genie, a self-improving framework addressing two key challenges in GUI agents: verification of trajectory outcome is challenging and high-quality training data are not scalable. These challenges are addressed by a reward model and a self-improving pipeline, respectively. The reward model, UI-Genie-RM, features an image-text interleaved architecture that efficiently pro- cesses historical context and unifies action-level and task-level rewards. To sup- port the training of UI-Genie-RM, we develop deliberately-designed data genera- tion strategies including rule-based verification, controlled trajectory corruption, and hard negative mining. To address the second challenge, a self-improvement pipeline progressively expands solvable complex GUI tasks by enhancing both the agent and reward models through reward-guided exploration and outcome verification in dynamic environments. For training the model, we generate UI- Genie-RM-517k and UI-Genie-Agent-16k, establishing the first reward-specific dataset for GUI agents while demonstrating high-quality synthetic trajectory gen- eration without manual annotation. Experimental results show that UI-Genie achieves state-of-the-art performance across multiple GUI agent benchmarks with three generations of data-model self-improvement. We open-source our complete framework implementation and generated datasets to facilitate further research in https://github.com/Euphoria16/UI-Genie.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21496</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 17:58:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paper2Poster: Towards Multimodal Poster Automation from Scientific   Papers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21497</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.21497.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei Pang, Kevin Qinghong Lin, Xiangru Jian, Xi He, Philip Torr&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 83&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Academic poster generation is a crucial yet challenging task in scientific communication, requiring the compression of long-context interleaved documents into a single, visually coherent page. To address this challenge, we introduce the first benchmark and metric suite for poster generation, which pairs recent conference papers with author-designed posters and evaluates outputs on (i)Visual Quality-semantic alignment with human posters, (ii)Textual Coherence-language fluency, (iii)Holistic Assessment-six fine-grained aesthetic and informational criteria scored by a VLM-as-judge, and notably (iv)PaperQuiz-the poster's ability to convey core paper content as measured by VLMs answering generated quizzes. Building on this benchmark, we propose PosterAgent, a top-down, visual-in-the-loop multi-agent pipeline: the (a)Parser distills the paper into a structured asset library; the (b)Planner aligns text-visual pairs into a binary-tree layout that preserves reading order and spatial balance; and the (c)Painter-Commenter loop refines each panel by executing rendering code and using VLM feedback to eliminate overflow and ensure alignment. In our comprehensive evaluation, we find that GPT-4o outputs-though visually appealing at first glance-often exhibit noisy text and poor PaperQuiz scores, and we find that reader engagement is the primary aesthetic bottleneck, as human-designed posters rely largely on visual semantics to convey meaning. Our fully open-source variants (e.g. based on the Qwen-2.5 series) outperform existing 4o-driven multi-agent systems across nearly all metrics, while using 87% fewer tokens. It transforms a 22-page paper into a finalized yet editable .pptx poster - all for just $0.005. These findings chart clear directions for the next generation of fully automated poster-generation models. The code and datasets are available at https://github.com/Paper2Poster/Paper2Poster.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21497</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 17:58:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork Open Reasoner 1 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22312</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22312.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jujie He, Jiacai Liu, Chris Yuhao Liu, Rui Yan, Chaojie Wang, Peng Cheng, Xiaoyu Zhang, Fuxiang Zhang, Jiacheng Xu, Wei Shen, Siyuan Li, Liang Zeng, Tianwen Wei, Cheng Cheng, Bo An, Yang Liu, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The success of DeepSeek-R1 underscores the significant role of reinforcement learning (RL) in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs). In this work, we present Skywork-OR1, an effective and scalable RL implementation for long Chain-of-Thought (CoT) models. Building on the DeepSeek-R1-Distill model series, our RL approach achieves notable performance gains, increasing average accuracy across AIME24, AIME25, and LiveCodeBench from 57.8% to 72.8% (+15.0%) for the 32B model and from 43.6% to 57.5% (+13.9%) for the 7B model. Our Skywork-OR1-32B model surpasses both DeepSeek-R1 and Qwen3-32B on the AIME24 and AIME25 benchmarks, while achieving comparable results on LiveCodeBench. The Skywork-OR1-7B and Skywork-OR1-Math-7B models demonstrate competitive reasoning capabilities among models of similar size. We perform comprehensive ablation studies on the core components of our training pipeline to validate their effectiveness. Additionally, we thoroughly investigate the phenomenon of entropy collapse, identify key factors affecting entropy dynamics, and demonstrate that mitigating premature entropy collapse is critical for improved test performance. To support community research, we fully open-source our model weights, training code, and training datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22312</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 12:56:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised Post-Training for Multi-Modal LLM Reasoning via GRPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22453</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22453.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lai Wei, Yuting Li, Chen Wang, Yue Wang, Linghe Kong, Weiran Huang, Lichao Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Improving Multi-modal Large Language Models (MLLMs) in the post-training stage typically relies on supervised fine-tuning (SFT) or reinforcement learning (RL). However, these supervised methods require expensive and manually annotated multi-modal data--an ultimately unsustainable resource. While recent efforts have explored unsupervised post-training, their methods are complex and difficult to iterate. In this work, we are the first to investigate the use of GRPO, a stable and scalable online RL algorithm, for enabling continual self-improvement without any external supervision. We propose MM-UPT, a simple yet effective framework for unsupervised post-training of MLLMs. MM-UPT builds upon GRPO, replacing traditional reward signals with a self-rewarding mechanism based on majority voting over multiple sampled responses. Our experiments demonstrate that MM-UPT significantly improves the reasoning ability of Qwen2.5-VL-7B (e.g., 66.3 %rightarrow72.9 % on MathVista, 62.9 %rightarrow68.7 % on We-Math), using standard dataset without ground truth labels. MM-UPT also outperforms prior unsupervised baselines and even approaches the results of supervised GRPO. Furthermore, we show that incorporating synthetic questions, generated solely by MLLM itself, can boost performance as well, highlighting a promising approach for scalable self-improvement. Overall, MM-UPT offers a new paradigm for continual, autonomous enhancement of MLLMs in the absence of external supervision. Our code is available at https://github.com/waltonfuture/MM-UPT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22453</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 15:11:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Entropy Mechanism of Reinforcement Learning for Reasoning Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22617</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22617.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ganqu Cui, Yuchen Zhang, Jiacheng Chen, Lifan Yuan, Zhi Wang, Yuxin Zuo, Haozhan Li, Yuchen Fan, Huayu Chen, Weize Chen, Zhiyuan Liu, Hao Peng, Lei Bai, Wanli Ouyang, Yu Cheng, Bowen Zhou, Ning Ding&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper aims to overcome a major obstacle in scaling RL for reasoning with LLMs, namely the collapse of policy entropy. Such phenomenon is consistently observed across vast RL runs without entropy intervention, where the policy entropy dropped sharply at the early training stage, this diminished exploratory ability is always accompanied with the saturation of policy performance. In practice, we establish a transformation equation R=-a*e^H+b between entropy H and downstream performance R. This empirical law strongly indicates that, the policy performance is traded from policy entropy, thus bottlenecked by its exhaustion, and the ceiling is fully predictable H=0, R=-a+b. Our finding necessitates entropy management for continuous exploration toward scaling compute for RL. To this end, we investigate entropy dynamics both theoretically and empirically. Our derivation highlights that, the change in policy entropy is driven by the covariance between action probability and the change in logits, which is proportional to its advantage when using Policy Gradient-like algorithms. Empirical study shows that, the values of covariance term and entropy differences matched exactly, supporting the theoretical conclusion. Moreover, the covariance term stays mostly positive throughout training, further explaining why policy entropy would decrease monotonically. Through understanding the mechanism behind entropy dynamics, we motivate to control entropy by restricting the update of high-covariance tokens. Specifically, we propose two simple yet effective techniques, namely Clip-Cov and KL-Cov, which clip and apply KL penalty to tokens with high covariances respectively. Experiments show that these methods encourage exploration, thus helping policy escape entropy collapse and achieve better downstream performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22617</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:38:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sherlock: Self-Correcting Reasoning in Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22651</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22651.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi Ding, Ruqi Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reasoning Vision-Language Models (VLMs) have shown promising performance on complex multimodal tasks. However, they still face significant challenges: they are highly sensitive to reasoning errors, require large volumes of annotated data or accurate verifiers, and struggle to generalize beyond specific domains. To address these limitations, we explore self-correction as a strategy to enhance reasoning VLMs. We first conduct an in-depth analysis of reasoning VLMs' self-correction abilities and identify key gaps. Based on our findings, we introduce Sherlock, a self-correction and self-improvement training framework. Sherlock introduces a trajectory-level self-correction objective, a preference data construction method based on visual perturbation, and a dynamic beta for preference tuning. Once the model acquires self-correction capabilities using only 20k randomly sampled annotated data, it continues to self-improve without external supervision. Built on the Llama3.2-Vision-11B model, Sherlock achieves remarkable results across eight benchmarks, reaching an average accuracy of 64.1 with direct generation and 65.4 after self-correction. It outperforms LLaVA-CoT (63.2), Mulberry (63.9), and LlamaV-o1 (63.4) while using less than 20% of the annotated data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22651</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:58:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Climb Carves Wisdom Deeper Than the Summit: On the Noisy Rewards in   Learning to Reason</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22653</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.22653.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ang Lv, Ruobing Xie, Xingwu Sun, Zhanhui Kang, Rui Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent studies on post-training large language models (LLMs) for reasoning through reinforcement learning (RL) typically focus on tasks that can be accurately verified and rewarded, such as solving math problems. In contrast, our research investigates the impact of reward noise, a more practical consideration for real-world scenarios involving the post-training of LLMs using reward models. We found that LLMs demonstrate strong robustness to substantial reward noise. For example, manually flipping 40% of the reward function's outputs in math tasks still allows a Qwen-2.5-7B model to achieve rapid convergence, improving its performance on math tasks from 5% to 72%, compared to the 75% accuracy achieved by a model trained with noiseless rewards. Surprisingly, by only rewarding the appearance of key reasoning phrases (namely reasoning pattern reward, RPR), such as ``first, I need to''-without verifying the correctness of answers, the model achieved peak downstream performance (over 70% accuracy for Qwen-2.5-7B) comparable to models trained with strict correctness verification and accurate rewards. Recognizing the importance of the reasoning process over the final results, we combined RPR with noisy reward models. RPR helped calibrate the noisy reward models, mitigating potential false negatives and enhancing the LLM's performance on open-ended tasks. These findings suggest the importance of improving models' foundational abilities during the pre-training phase while providing insights for advancing post-training techniques. Our code and scripts are available at https://github.com/trestad/Noisy-Rewards-in-Learning-to-Reason.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22653</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Table-R1: Inference-Time Scaling for Table Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23621</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23621.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zheyuan Yang, Lyuhao Chen, Arman Cohan, Yilun Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we present the first study to explore inference-time scaling on table reasoning tasks. We develop and evaluate two post-training strategies to enable inference-time scaling: distillation from frontier model reasoning traces and reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR). For distillation, we introduce a large-scale dataset of reasoning traces generated by DeepSeek-R1, which we use to fine-tune LLMs into the Table-R1-SFT model. For RLVR, we propose task-specific verifiable reward functions and apply the GRPO algorithm to obtain the Table-R1-Zero model. We evaluate our Table-R1-series models across diverse table reasoning tasks, including short-form QA, fact verification, and free-form QA. Notably, the Table-R1-Zero model matches or exceeds the performance of GPT-4.1 and DeepSeek-R1, while using only a 7B-parameter LLM. It also demonstrates strong generalization to out-of-domain datasets. Extensive ablation and qualitative analyses reveal the benefits of instruction tuning, model architecture choices, and cross-task generalization, as well as emergence of essential table reasoning skills during RL training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23621</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 16:28:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VF-Eval: Evaluating Multimodal LLMs for Generating Feedback on AIGC   Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23693</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23693.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tingyu Song, Tongyan Hu, Guo Gan, Yilun Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; MLLMs have been widely studied for video question answering recently. However, most existing assessments focus on natural videos, overlooking synthetic videos, such as AI-generated content (AIGC). Meanwhile, some works in video generation rely on MLLMs to evaluate the quality of generated videos, but the capabilities of MLLMs on interpreting AIGC videos remain largely underexplored. To address this, we propose a new benchmark, VF-Eval, which introduces four tasks-coherence validation, error awareness, error type detection, and reasoning evaluation-to comprehensively evaluate the abilities of MLLMs on AIGC videos. We evaluate 13 frontier MLLMs on VF-Eval and find that even the best-performing model, GPT-4.1, struggles to achieve consistently good performance across all tasks. This highlights the challenging nature of our benchmark. Additionally, to investigate the practical applications of VF-Eval in improving video generation, we conduct an experiment, RePrompt, demonstrating that aligning MLLMs more closely with human feedback can benefit video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23693</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:31:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial-MLLM: Boosting MLLM Capabilities in Visual-based Spatial   Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23747</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23747.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Diankun Wu, Fangfu Liu, Yi-Hsin Hung, Yueqi Duan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 57&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have significantly enhanced performance on 2D visual tasks. However, improving their spatial intelligence remains a challenge. Existing 3D MLLMs always rely on additional 3D or 2.5D data to incorporate spatial awareness, restricting their utility in scenarios with only 2D inputs, such as images or videos. In this paper, we present Spatial-MLLM, a novel framework for visual-based spatial reasoning from purely 2D observations. Unlike conventional video MLLMs which rely on CLIP-based visual encoders optimized for semantic understanding, our key insight is to unleash the strong structure prior from the feed-forward visual geometry foundation model. Specifically, we propose a dual-encoder architecture: a pretrained 2D visual encoder to extract semantic features, and a spatial encoder-initialized from the backbone of the visual geometry model-to extract 3D structure features. A connector then integrates both features into unified visual tokens for enhanced spatial understanding. Furthermore, we propose a space-aware frame sampling strategy at inference time, which selects the spatially informative frames of a video sequence, ensuring that even under limited token length, the model focuses on frames critical for spatial reasoning. Beyond architecture improvements, we construct the Spatial-MLLM-120k dataset and train the model on it using supervised fine-tuning and GRPO. Extensive experiments on various real-world datasets demonstrate that our spatial-MLLM achieves state-of-the-art performance in a wide range of visual-based spatial understanding and reasoning tasks. Project page: https://diankun-wu.github.io/Spatial-MLLM/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23747</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:59:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZeroGUI: Automating Online GUI Learning at Zero Human Cost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23762</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.23762.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenyu Yang, Shiqian Su, Shi Liu, Xuan Dong, Yue Yu, Weijie Su, Xuehui Wang, Zhaoyang Liu, Jinguo Zhu, Hao Li, Wenhai Wang, Yu Qiao, Xizhou Zhu, Jifeng Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of large Vision-Language Models (VLMs) has propelled the development of pure-vision-based GUI Agents, capable of perceiving and operating Graphical User Interfaces (GUI) to autonomously fulfill user instructions. However, existing approaches usually adopt an offline learning framework, which faces two core limitations: (1) heavy reliance on high-quality manual annotations for element grounding and action supervision, and (2) limited adaptability to dynamic and interactive environments. To address these limitations, we propose ZeroGUI, a scalable, online learning framework for automating GUI Agent training at Zero human cost. Specifically, ZeroGUI integrates (i) VLM-based automatic task generation to produce diverse training goals from the current environment state, (ii) VLM-based automatic reward estimation to assess task success without hand-crafted evaluation functions, and (iii) two-stage online reinforcement learning to continuously interact with and learn from GUI environments. Experiments on two advanced GUI Agents (UI-TARS and Aguvis) demonstrate that ZeroGUI significantly boosts performance across OSWorld and AndroidLab environments. The code is available at https://github.com/OpenGVLab/ZeroGUI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23762</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 17:59:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
