<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 00:12:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>SRT-H: A Hierarchical Framework for Autonomous Surgery via Language   Conditioned Imitation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10251</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2505.10251.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ji Woong Kim, Juo-Tung Chen, Pascal Hansen, Lucy X. Shi, Antony Goldenberg, Samuel Schmidgall, Paul Maria Scheikl, Anton Deguet, Brandon M. White, De Ru Tsai, Richard Cha, Jeffrey Jopling, Chelsea Finn, Axel Krieger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Research on autonomous surgery has largely focused on simple task automation in controlled environments. However, real-world surgical applications demand dexterous manipulation over extended durations and generalization to the inherent variability of human tissue. These challenges remain difficult to address using existing logic-based or conventional end-to-end learning approaches. To address this gap, we propose a hierarchical framework for performing dexterous, long-horizon surgical steps. Our approach utilizes a high-level policy for task planning and a low-level policy for generating robot trajectories. The high-level planner plans in language space, generating task-level or corrective instructions that guide the robot through the long-horizon steps and correct for the low-level policy's errors. We validate our framework through ex vivo experiments on cholecystectomy, a commonly-practiced minimally invasive procedure, and conduct ablation studies to evaluate key components of the system. Our method achieves a 100\% success rate across eight unseen ex vivo gallbladders, operating fully autonomously without human intervention. This work demonstrates step-level autonomy in a surgical procedure, marking a milestone toward clinical deployment of autonomous surgical systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10251</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 13:04:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UnMix-NeRF: Spectral Unmixing Meets Neural Radiance Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21884</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21884.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fabian Perez, Sara Rojas, Carlos Hinojosa, Hoover Rueda-Chacón, Bernard Ghanem&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Neural Radiance Field (NeRF)-based segmentation methods focus on object semantics and rely solely on RGB data, lacking intrinsic material properties. This limitation restricts accurate material perception, which is crucial for robotics, augmented reality, simulation, and other applications. We introduce UnMix-NeRF, a framework that integrates spectral unmixing into NeRF, enabling joint hyperspectral novel view synthesis and unsupervised material segmentation. Our method models spectral reflectance via diffuse and specular components, where a learned dictionary of global endmembers represents pure material signatures, and per-point abundances capture their distribution. For material segmentation, we use spectral signature predictions along learned endmembers, allowing unsupervised material clustering. Additionally, UnMix-NeRF enables scene editing by modifying learned endmember dictionaries for flexible material-based appearance manipulation. Extensive experiments validate our approach, demonstrating superior spectral reconstruction and material segmentation to existing methods. Project page: https://www.factral.co/UnMix-NeRF.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21884</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 03:42:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Vision-Language-Action Models for Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.24044</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.24044.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sicong Jiang, Zilin Huang, Kangan Qian, Ziang Luo, Tianze Zhu, Yang Zhong, Yihong Tang, Menglin Kong, Yunlong Wang, Siwen Jiao, Hao Ye, Zihao Sheng, Xin Zhao, Tuopu Wen, Zheng Fu, Sikai Chen, Kun Jiang, Diange Yang, Seongjin Choi, Lijun Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid progress of multimodal large language models (MLLM) has paved the way for Vision-Language-Action (VLA) paradigms, which integrate visual perception, natural language understanding, and control within a single policy. Researchers in autonomous driving are actively adapting these methods to the vehicle domain. Such models promise autonomous vehicles that can interpret high-level instructions, reason about complex traffic scenes, and make their own decisions. However, the literature remains fragmented and is rapidly expanding. This survey offers the first comprehensive overview of VLA for Autonomous Driving (VLA4AD). We (i) formalize the architectural building blocks shared across recent work, (ii) trace the evolution from early explainer to reasoning-centric VLA models, and (iii) compare over 20 representative models according to VLA's progress in the autonomous driving domain. We also consolidate existing datasets and benchmarks, highlighting protocols that jointly measure driving safety, accuracy, and explanation quality. Finally, we detail open challenges - robustness, real-time efficiency, and formal verification - and outline future directions of VLA4AD. This survey provides a concise yet complete reference for advancing interpretable socially aligned autonomous vehicles. Github repo is available at https://github.com/JohnsonJiang1996/Awesome-VLA4AD{SicongJiang/Awesome-VLA4AD}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.24044</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 16:50:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LitBench: A Benchmark and Dataset for Reliable Evaluation of Creative   Writing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00769</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.00769.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daniel Fein, Sebastian Russo, Violet Xiang, Kabir Jolly, Rafael Rafailov, Nick Haber&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating creative writing generated by large language models (LLMs) remains challenging because open-ended narratives lack ground truths. Without performant automated evaluation methods, off-the-shelf (OTS) language models are employed as zero-shot judges, yet their reliability is unclear in this context. In pursuit of robust evaluation for creative writing, we introduce LitBench, the first standardized benchmark and paired dataset for creative writing verification, comprising a held-out test set of 2,480 debiased, human-labeled story comparisons drawn from Reddit and a 43,827-pair training corpus of human preference labels. Using LitBench, we (i) benchmark zero-shot LLM judges, (ii) train Bradley Terry and generative reward models, and (iii) conduct an online human study to validate reward model rankings on newly LLM-generated stories. Our benchmark identifies Claude-3.7-Sonnet as the strongest off-the-shelf judge, reaching 73% agreement with human preferences; among trained reward models, Bradley-Terry and Generative reward models both attain an accuracy of 78%, outperforming all off-the-shelf judges. An online human study further confirms that our trained reward models consistently align with human preferences in novel LLM-generated stories. We release LitBench and reward models at https://huggingface.co/collections/SAA-Lab/litbench-68267b5da3aafe58f9e43461, providing a vetted resource for reliable, automated evaluation and optimization of creative writing systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00769</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 14:10:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Should We Still Pretrain Encoders with Masked Language Modeling?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00994</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.00994.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hippolyte Gisserot-Boukhlef, Nicolas Boizard, Manuel Faysse, Duarte M. Alves, Emmanuel Malherbe, André F. T. Martins, Céline Hudelot, Pierre Colombo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 72&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Learning high-quality text representations is fundamental to a wide range of NLP tasks. While encoder pretraining has traditionally relied on Masked Language Modeling (MLM), recent evidence suggests that decoder models pretrained with Causal Language Modeling (CLM) can be effectively repurposed as encoders, often surpassing traditional encoders on text representation benchmarks. However, it remains unclear whether these gains reflect an inherent advantage of the CLM objective or arise from confounding factors such as model and data scale. In this paper, we address this question through a series of large-scale, carefully controlled pretraining ablations, training a total of 30 models ranging from 210 million to 1 billion parameters, and conducting over 15,000 fine-tuning and evaluation runs. We find that while training with MLM generally yields better performance across text representation tasks, CLM-trained models are more data-efficient and demonstrate improved fine-tuning stability. Building on these findings, we experimentally show that a biphasic training strategy that sequentially applies CLM and then MLM, achieves optimal performance under a fixed computational training budget. Moreover, we demonstrate that this strategy becomes more appealing when initializing from readily available pretrained CLM models (from the existing LLM ecosystem), reducing the computational burden needed to train best-in-class encoder models. We release all project artifacts at https://hf.co/MLMvsCLM to foster further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00994</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 17:45:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdamMeme: Adaptively Probe the Reasoning Capacity of Multimodal Large   Language Models on Harmfulness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01702</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01702.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zixin Chen, Hongzhan Lin, Kaixin Li, Ziyang Luo, Zhen Ye, Guang Chen, Zhiyong Huang, Jing Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The proliferation of multimodal memes in the social media era demands that multimodal Large Language Models (mLLMs) effectively understand meme harmfulness. Existing benchmarks for assessing mLLMs on harmful meme understanding rely on accuracy-based, model-agnostic evaluations using static datasets. These benchmarks are limited in their ability to provide up-to-date and thorough assessments, as online memes evolve dynamically. To address this, we propose AdamMeme, a flexible, agent-based evaluation framework that adaptively probes the reasoning capabilities of mLLMs in deciphering meme harmfulness. Through multi-agent collaboration, AdamMeme provides comprehensive evaluations by iteratively updating the meme data with challenging samples, thereby exposing specific limitations in how mLLMs interpret harmfulness. Extensive experiments show that our framework systematically reveals the varying performance of different target mLLMs, offering in-depth, fine-grained analyses of model-specific weaknesses. Our code is available at https://github.com/Lbotirx/AdamMeme.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01702</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 13:32:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eka-Eval : A Comprehensive Evaluation Framework for Large Language   Models in Indian Languages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01853</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01853.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Samridhi Raj Sinha, Rajvee Sheth, Abhishek Upperwal, Mayank Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of Large Language Models (LLMs) has intensified the need for evaluation frameworks that go beyond English centric benchmarks and address the requirements of linguistically diverse regions such as India. We present EKA-EVAL, a unified and production-ready evaluation framework that integrates over 35 benchmarks, including 10 Indic-specific datasets, spanning categories like reasoning, mathematics, tool use, long-context understanding, and reading comprehension. Compared to existing Indian language evaluation tools, EKA-EVAL offers broader benchmark coverage, with built-in support for distributed inference, quantization, and multi-GPU usage. Our systematic comparison positions EKA-EVAL as the first end-to-end, extensible evaluation suite tailored for both global and Indic LLMs, significantly lowering the barrier to multilingual benchmarking. The framework is open-source and publicly available at https://github.com/lingo-iitgn/ eka-eval and a part of ongoing EKA initiative (https://eka.soket.ai), which aims to scale up to over 100 benchmarks and establish a robust, multilingual evaluation ecosystem for LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01853</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 16:07:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboBrain 2.0 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02029</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.02029.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; BAAI RoboBrain Team, Mingyu Cao, Huajie Tan, Yuheng Ji, Minglan Lin, Zhiyu Li, Zhou Cao, Pengwei Wang, Enshen Zhou, Yi Han, Yingbo Tang, Xiangqi Xu, Wei Guo, Yaoxu Lyu, Yijie Xu, Jiayu Shi, Cheng Chi, Mengdi Zhao, Xiaoshuai Hao, Shanyu Rong, Zhengliang Cai, Bolun Zhang, Shuyi Zhang, Huaihai Lyu, Mengfei Du, Lingfeng Zhang, Xi Feng, Xiaodan Liu, Yance Jiao, Chenrui He, Mengsi Lyu, Zhuo Chen, Yulong Ao, Xue Sun, Zheqi He, Jingshu Zheng, Xi Yang, Donghai Shi, Kunchang Xie, Bochao Zhang, Shaokai Nie, Chunlei Men, Yonghua Lin, Zhongyuan Wang, Tiejun Huang, Shanghang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce RoboBrain 2.0, our latest generation of embodied vision-language foundation models, designed to unify perception, reasoning, and planning for complex embodied tasks in physical environments. It comes in two variants: a lightweight 7B model and a full-scale 32B model, featuring a heterogeneous architecture with a vision encoder and a language model. Despite its compact size, RoboBrain 2.0 achieves strong performance across a wide spectrum of embodied reasoning tasks. On both spatial and temporal benchmarks, the 32B variant achieves leading results, surpassing prior open-source and proprietary models. In particular, it supports key real-world embodied AI capabilities, including spatial understanding (e.g., affordance prediction, spatial referring, trajectory forecasting) and temporal decision-making (e.g., closed-loop interaction, multi-agent long-horizon planning, and scene graph updating). This report details the model architecture, data construction, multi-stage training strategies, infrastructure and practical applications. We hope RoboBrain 2.0 advances embodied AI research and serves as a practical step toward building generalist embodied agents. The code, checkpoint and benchmark are available at https://superrobobrain.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02029</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:05:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Well Does GPT-4o Understand Vision? Evaluating Multimodal Foundation   Models on Standard Computer Vision Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01955</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.01955.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rahul Ramachandran, Ali Garjani, Roman Bachmann, Andrei Atanov, Oğuzhan Fatih Kar, Amir Zamir&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal foundation models, such as GPT-4o, have recently made remarkable progress, but it is not clear where exactly these models stand in terms of understanding vision. In this paper, we benchmark the performance of popular multimodal foundation models (GPT-4o, o4-mini, Gemini 1.5 Pro and Gemini 2.0 Flash, Claude 3.5 Sonnet, Qwen2-VL, Llama 3.2) on standard computer vision tasks (semantic segmentation, object detection, image classification, depth and surface normal prediction) using established datasets (e.g., COCO, ImageNet and its variants, etc).   The main challenges to performing this are: 1) most models are trained to output text and cannot natively express versatile domains, such as segments or 3D geometry, and 2) many leading models are proprietary and accessible only at an API level, i.e., there is no weight access to adapt them. We address these challenges by translating standard vision tasks into equivalent text-promptable and API-compatible tasks via prompt chaining to create a standardized benchmarking framework.   We observe that 1) the models are not close to the state-of-the-art specialist models at any task. However, 2) they are respectable generalists; this is remarkable as they are presumably trained on primarily image-text-based tasks. 3) They perform semantic tasks notably better than geometric ones. 4) While the prompt-chaining techniques affect performance, better models exhibit less sensitivity to prompt variations. 5) GPT-4o performs the best among non-reasoning models, securing the top position in 4 out of 6 tasks, 6) reasoning models, e.g. o3, show improvements in geometric tasks, and 7) a preliminary analysis of models with native image generation, like the latest GPT-4o, shows they exhibit quirks like hallucinations and spatial misalignments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01955</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 17:59:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving Privacy, Increasing Accessibility, and Reducing Cost: An   On-Device Artificial Intelligence Model for Medical Transcription and Note   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03033</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03033.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Johnson Thomas, Ayush Mudgal, Wendao Liu, Nisten Tahiraj, Zeeshaan Mohammed, Dhruv Diddi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Background: Clinical documentation represents a significant burden for healthcare providers, with physicians spending up to 2 hours daily on administrative tasks. Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) offer promising solutions, but privacy concerns and computational requirements limit their adoption in healthcare settings. Objective: To develop and evaluate a privacy-preserving, on-device medical transcription system using a fine-tuned Llama 3.2 1B model capable of generating structured medical notes from medical transcriptions while maintaining complete data sovereignty entirely in the browser. Methods: We fine-tuned a Llama 3.2 1B model using Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning (PEFT) with LoRA on 1,500 synthetic medical transcription-to-structured note pairs. The model was evaluated against the base Llama 3.2 1B on two datasets: 100 endocrinology transcripts and 140 modified ACI benchmark cases. Evaluation employed both statistical metrics (ROUGE, BERTScore, BLEURT) and LLM-as-judge assessments across multiple clinical quality dimensions. Results: The fine-tuned OnDevice model demonstrated substantial improvements over the base model. On the ACI benchmark, ROUGE-1 scores increased from 0.346 to 0.496, while BERTScore F1 improved from 0.832 to 0.866. Clinical quality assessments showed marked reduction in major hallucinations (from 85 to 35 cases) and enhanced factual correctness (2.81 to 3.54 on 5-point scale). Similar improvements were observed on the internal evaluation dataset, with composite scores increasing from 3.13 to 4.43 (+41.5%). Conclusions: Fine-tuning compact LLMs for medical transcription yields clinically meaningful improvements while enabling complete on-device browser deployment. This approach addresses key barriers to AI adoption in healthcare: privacy preservation, cost reduction, and accessibility for resource-constrained environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03033</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 01:51:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lost in Latent Space: An Empirical Study of Latent Diffusion Models for   Physics Emulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02608</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.02608.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; François Rozet, Ruben Ohana, Michael McCabe, Gilles Louppe, François Lanusse, Shirley Ho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The steep computational cost of diffusion models at inference hinders their use as fast physics emulators. In the context of image and video generation, this computational drawback has been addressed by generating in the latent space of an autoencoder instead of the pixel space. In this work, we investigate whether a similar strategy can be effectively applied to the emulation of dynamical systems and at what cost. We find that the accuracy of latent-space emulation is surprisingly robust to a wide range of compression rates (up to 1000x). We also show that diffusion-based emulators are consistently more accurate than non-generative counterparts and compensate for uncertainty in their predictions with greater diversity. Finally, we cover practical design choices, spanning from architectures to optimizers, that we found critical to train latent-space emulators.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02608</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 13:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniDraft: A Cross-vocabulary, Online Adaptive Drafter for On-device   Speculative Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02659</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.02659.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ramchalam Kinattinkara Ramakrishnan, Zhaocong Yuan, Shaojie Zhuo, Chen Feng, Yicheng Lin, Chenzheng Su, Xiaopeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Speculative decoding generally dictates having a small, efficient draft model that is either pretrained or distilled offline to a particular target model series, for instance, Llama or Qwen models. However, within online deployment settings, there are two major challenges: 1) usage of a target model that is incompatible with the draft model; 2) expectation of latency improvements over usage and time. In this work, we propose OmniDraft, a unified framework that enables a single draft model to operate with any target model and adapt dynamically to user data. We introduce an online n-gram cache with hybrid distillation fine-tuning to address the cross-vocabulary mismatch across draft and target models; and further improve decoding speed by leveraging adaptive drafting techniques. OmniDraft is particularly suitable for on-device LLM applications where model cost, efficiency and user customization are the major points of contention. This further highlights the need to tackle the above challenges and motivates the ``one drafter for all'' paradigm. We showcase the proficiency of the OmniDraft framework by performing online learning on math reasoning, coding and text generation tasks. Notably, OmniDraft enables a single Llama-68M model to pair with various target models including Vicuna-7B, Qwen2-7B and Llama3-8B models for speculative decoding; and additionally provides up to 1.5-2x speedup.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02659</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 14:20:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLVER: Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Emotion Rewards for   Empathetic Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03112</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03112.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peisong Wang, Ruotian Ma, Bang Zhang, Xingyu Chen, Zhiwei He, Kang Luo, Qingsong Lv, Qingxuan Jiang, Zheng Xie, Shanyi Wang, Yuan Li, Fanghua Ye, Jian Li, Yifan Yang, Zhaopeng Tu, Xiaolong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) excel at logical and algorithmic reasoning, yet their emotional intelligence (EQ) still lags far behind their cognitive prowess. While reinforcement learning from verifiable rewards (RLVR) has advanced in other domains, its application to dialogue-especially for emotional intelligence-remains underexplored. In this work, we introduce RLVER, the first end-to-end reinforcement learning framework that leverages verifiable emotion rewards from simulated users to cultivate higher-order empathetic abilities in LLMs. Within this framework, self-consistent affective simulated users engage in dialogue rollouts and produce deterministic emotion scores during conversations, serving as reward signals to guide the LLM's learning. Fine-tuning publicly available Qwen2.5-7B-Instruct model with PPO boosts its Sentient-Benchmark score from 13.3 to 79.2 while largely preserving mathematical and coding competence. Extensive experiments reveal that: (i) RLVER consistently improves multiple dialogue capabilities; (ii) Thinking and non-thinking models show distinct trends--thinking models excel in empathy and insight, while non-thinking models favor action; (iii) GRPO often yields stable gains, while PPO can push certain capabilities to a higher ceiling; (iv) More challenging environments are not always better-moderate ones can yield stronger outcomes. Our results show that RLVER is a practical route toward emotionally intelligent and broadly capable language agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03112</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 18:33:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RefineX: Learning to Refine Pre-training Data at Scale from   Expert-Guided Programs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03253</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03253.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Baolong Bi, Shenghua Liu, Xingzhang Ren, Dayiheng Liu, Junyang Lin, Yiwei Wang, Lingrui Mei, Junfeng Fang, Jiafeng Guo, Xueqi Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The foundational capabilities of large language models (LLMs) are deeply influenced by the quality of their pre-training corpora. However, enhancing data quality at scale remains a significant challenge, primarily due to the trade-off between refinement effectiveness and processing efficiency. While rule-based filtering remains the dominant paradigm, it typically operates at the document level and lacks the granularity needed to refine specific content within documents. Inspired by emerging work such as ProX, we propose RefineX, a novel framework for large-scale, surgical refinement of pre-training data through programmatic editing tasks. RefineX enables efficient and fine-grained data refinement while reliably preserving the diversity and naturalness of raw text. The core strength of RefineX lies in distilling high-quality, expert-guided end-to-end refinement results into minimal edit-based deletion programs. This high-precision distillation pipeline is used to train an efficient and reliable refine model that can systematically improve every instance in the corpus at scale. We evaluate RefineX across from-scratch pre-training at multiple model scales and find that it consistently outperforms models trained on raw, filtered, or alternatively refined data across diverse downstream tasks. On the 750M model, RefineX yields 2.6%-7.2% average gains on lighteval tasks, and achieves comparable performance using significantly fewer training tokens. Further analysis shows that RefineX reliably enhances text quality with both high efficiency and precision, outperforming prior approaches such as end-to-end generation and Prox-C. These results position RefineX as a scalable, effective, and reliable solution for optimizing pre-training data in modern LLM pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03253</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 02:19:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disambiguation-Centric Finetuning Makes Enterprise Tool-Calling LLMs   More Realistic and Less Risky</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03336</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03336.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ashutosh Hathidara, Julien Yu, Sebastian Schreiber&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly tasked with invoking enterprise APIs, yet they routinely falter when near-duplicate tools vie for the same user intent or when required arguments are left underspecified. We introduce DiaFORGE (Dialogue Framework for Organic Response Generation &amp; Evaluation), a disambiguation-centric, three-stage pipeline that (i) synthesizes persona-driven, multi-turn dialogues in which the assistant must distinguish among highly similar tools, (ii) performs supervised fine-tuning of open-source models with reasoning traces across 3B - 70B parameters, and (iii) evaluates real-world readiness via a dynamic suite that redeploys each model in a live agentic loop and reports end-to-end goal completion alongside conventional static metrics. On our dynamic benchmark DiaBENCH, models trained with DiaFORGE raise tool-invocation success by 27 pp over GPT-4o and by 49 pp over Claude-3.5-Sonnet, both under optimized prompting. To spur further research, we release an open corpus of 5000 production-grade enterprise API specifications paired with rigorously validated, disambiguation-focused dialogues, offering a practical blueprint for building reliable, enterprise-ready tool-calling agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03336</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 06:49:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BMMR: A Large-Scale Bilingual Multimodal Multi-Discipline Reasoning   Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03483</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03483.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiheng Xi, Guanyu Li, Yutao Fan, Honglin Guo, Yufang Liu, Xiaoran Fan, Jiaqi Liu, Jingchao Ding, Wangmeng Zuo, Zhenfei Yin, Lei Bai, Tao Ji, Tao Gui, Qi Zhang, Xuanjing Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce BMMR, a large-scale bilingual, multimodal, multi-disciplinary reasoning dataset for the community to develop and evaluate large multimodal models (LMMs). BMMR comprises 110k college-level questions spanning 300 UNESCO-defined subjects, spanning diverse formats-multiple-choice, fill-in-the-blank, and open-ended QA-and sourced from both print and digital media such as books, exams, and quizzes. All data are curated and filtered via a human-in-the-loop and scalable framework, and each instance is paired with a high-quality reasoning path. The dataset is organized into two parts: BMMR-Eval that comprises 20,458 high-quality instances to comprehensively assess LMMs' knowledge and reasoning across multiple disciplines in both Chinese and English; and BMMR-Train that contains 88,991 instances to support further research and development, extending the current focus on mathematical reasoning to diverse disciplines and domains. In addition, we propose the process-based multi-discipline verifier (i.e., BMMR-Verifier) for accurate and fine-grained evaluation of reasoning paths. Extensive experiments on 24 models reveal that (i) even SOTA models (e.g., o3 and Gemini-2.5-Pro) leave substantial headroom on BMMR-Eval; (ii) reasoning models exhibit discipline bias and outperform LMMs only on specific subjects; (iii) open-source models still trail their proprietary counterparts; and (iv) fine-tuning on BMMR-Train narrows this gap. Additionally, we conduct reasoning-chain analyses using BMMR-Verifier and other in-depth studies, uncovering the challenges LMMs currently face in multidisciplinary reasoning. We will release the data, and we hope our work can offer insights and contributions to the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03483</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 11:20:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VLAI: A RoBERTa-Based Model for Automated Vulnerability Severity   Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03607</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03607.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cédric Bonhomme, Alexandre Dulaunoy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents VLAI, a transformer-based model that predicts software vulnerability severity levels directly from text descriptions. Built on RoBERTa, VLAI is fine-tuned on over 600,000 real-world vulnerabilities and achieves over 82% accuracy in predicting severity categories, enabling faster and more consistent triage ahead of manual CVSS scoring. The model and dataset are open-source and integrated into the Vulnerability-Lookup service.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03607</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 14:28:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the rankability of visual embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03683</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03683.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ankit Sonthalia, Arnas Uselis, Seong Joon Oh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We study whether visual embedding models capture continuous, ordinal attributes along linear directions, which we term _rank axes_. We define a model as _rankable_ for an attribute if projecting embeddings onto such an axis preserves the attribute's order. Across 7 popular encoders and 9 datasets with attributes like age, crowd count, head pose, aesthetics, and recency, we find that many embeddings are inherently rankable. Surprisingly, a small number of samples, or even just two extreme examples, often suffice to recover meaningful rank axes, without full-scale supervision. These findings open up new use cases for image ranking in vector databases and motivate further study into the structure and learning of rankable embeddings. Our code is available at https://github.com/aktsonthalia/rankable-vision-embeddings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03683</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 16:03:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAMed-2: Selective Memory Enhanced Medical Segment Anything Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03698</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03698.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiling Yan, Sifan Song, Dingjie Song, Yiwei Li, Rong Zhou, Weixiang Sun, Zhennong Chen, Sekeun Kim, Hui Ren, Tianming Liu, Quanzheng Li, Xiang Li, Lifang He, Lichao Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent "segment anything" efforts show promise by learning from large-scale data, but adapting such models directly to medical images remains challenging due to the complexity of medical data, noisy annotations, and continual learning requirements across diverse modalities and anatomical structures. In this work, we propose SAMed-2, a new foundation model for medical image segmentation built upon the SAM-2 architecture. Specifically, we introduce a temporal adapter into the image encoder to capture image correlations and a confidence-driven memory mechanism to store high-certainty features for later retrieval. This memory-based strategy counters the pervasive noise in large-scale medical datasets and mitigates catastrophic forgetting when encountering new tasks or modalities. To train and evaluate SAMed-2, we curate MedBank-100k, a comprehensive dataset spanning seven imaging modalities and 21 medical segmentation tasks. Our experiments on both internal benchmarks and 10 external datasets demonstrate superior performance over state-of-the-art baselines in multi-task scenarios. The code is available at: https://github.com/ZhilingYan/Medical-SAM-Bench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03698</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 16:30:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MemOS: A Memory OS for AI System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03724</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03724.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyu Li, Shichao Song, Chenyang Xi, Hanyu Wang, Chen Tang, Simin Niu, Ding Chen, Jiawei Yang, Chunyu Li, Qingchen Yu, Jihao Zhao, Yezhaohui Wang, Peng Liu, Zehao Lin, Pengyuan Wang, Jiahao Huo, Tianyi Chen, Kai Chen, Kehang Li, Zhen Tao, Junpeng Ren, Huayi Lai, Hao Wu, Bo Tang, Zhenren Wang, Zhaoxin Fan, Ningyu Zhang, Linfeng Zhang, Junchi Yan, Mingchuan Yang, Tong Xu, Wei Xu, Huajun Chen, Haofeng Wang, Hongkang Yang, Wentao Zhang, Zhi-Qin John Xu, Siheng Chen, Feiyu Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 107&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have become an essential infrastructure for Artificial General Intelligence (AGI), yet their lack of well-defined memory management systems hinders the development of long-context reasoning, continual personalization, and knowledge consistency.Existing models mainly rely on static parameters and short-lived contextual states, limiting their ability to track user preferences or update knowledge over extended periods.While Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) introduces external knowledge in plain text, it remains a stateless workaround without lifecycle control or integration with persistent representations.Recent work has modeled the training and inference cost of LLMs from a memory hierarchy perspective, showing that introducing an explicit memory layer between parameter memory and external retrieval can substantially reduce these costs by externalizing specific knowledge. Beyond computational efficiency, LLMs face broader challenges arising from how information is distributed over time and context, requiring systems capable of managing heterogeneous knowledge spanning different temporal scales and sources. To address this challenge, we propose MemOS, a memory operating system that treats memory as a manageable system resource. It unifies the representation, scheduling, and evolution of plaintext, activation-based, and parameter-level memories, enabling cost-efficient storage and retrieval. As the basic unit, a MemCube encapsulates both memory content and metadata such as provenance and versioning. MemCubes can be composed, migrated, and fused over time, enabling flexible transitions between memory types and bridging retrieval with parameter-based learning. MemOS establishes a memory-centric system framework that brings controllability, plasticity, and evolvability to LLMs, laying the foundation for continual learning and personalized modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03724</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 17:21:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FAROS: Fair Graph Generation via Attribute Switching Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03728</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03728.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abdennacer Badaoui, Oussama Kharouiche, Hatim Mrabet, Daniele Malitesta, Fragkiskos D. Malliaros&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in graph diffusion models (GDMs) have enabled the synthesis of realistic network structures, yet ensuring fairness in the generated data remains a critical challenge. Existing solutions attempt to mitigate bias by re-training the GDMs with ad-hoc fairness constraints. Conversely, with this work, we propose FAROS, a novel FAir graph geneRatiOn framework leveraging attribute Switching mechanisms and directly running in the generation process of the pre-trained GDM. Technically, our approach works by altering nodes' sensitive attributes during the generation. To this end, FAROS calculates the optimal fraction of switching nodes, and selects the diffusion step to perform the switch by setting tailored multi-criteria constraints to preserve the node-topology profile from the original distribution (a proxy for accuracy) while ensuring the edge independence on the sensitive attributes for the generated graph (a proxy for fairness). Our experiments on benchmark datasets for link prediction demonstrate that the proposed approach effectively reduces fairness discrepancies while maintaining comparable (or even higher) accuracy performance to other similar baselines. Noteworthy, FAROS is also able to strike a better accuracy-fairness trade-off than other competitors in some of the tested settings under the Pareto optimality concept, demonstrating the effectiveness of the imposed multi-criteria constraints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03728</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 17:31:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StreamDiT: Real-Time Streaming Text-to-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03745</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.03745.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Akio Kodaira, Tingbo Hou, Ji Hou, Masayoshi Tomizuka, Yue Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, great progress has been achieved in text-to-video (T2V) generation by scaling transformer-based diffusion models to billions of parameters, which can generate high-quality videos. However, existing models typically produce only short clips offline, restricting their use cases in interactive and real-time applications. This paper addresses these challenges by proposing StreamDiT, a streaming video generation model. StreamDiT training is based on flow matching by adding a moving buffer. We design mixed training with different partitioning schemes of buffered frames to boost both content consistency and visual quality. StreamDiT modeling is based on adaLN DiT with varying time embedding and window attention. To practice the proposed method, we train a StreamDiT model with 4B parameters. In addition, we propose a multistep distillation method tailored for StreamDiT. Sampling distillation is performed in each segment of a chosen partitioning scheme. After distillation, the total number of function evaluations (NFEs) is reduced to the number of chunks in a buffer. Finally, our distilled model reaches real-time performance at 16 FPS on one GPU, which can generate video streams at 512p resolution. We evaluate our method through both quantitative metrics and human evaluation. Our model enables real-time applications, e.g. streaming generation, interactive generation, and video-to-video. We provide video results and more examples in our project website: &lt;a href="https://cumulo-autumn.github.io/StreamDiT/"&gt;this https URL.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03745</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 18:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Easy Dataset: A Unified and Extensible Framework for Synthesizing LLM   Fine-Tuning Data from Unstructured Documents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04009</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04009.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyang Miao, Qiyu Sun, Jingyuan Wang, Yuchen Gong, Yaowei Zheng, Shiqi Li, Richong Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have shown impressive performance on general-purpose tasks, yet adapting them to specific domains remains challenging due to the scarcity of high-quality domain data. Existing data synthesis tools often struggle to extract reliable fine-tuning data from heterogeneous documents effectively. To address this limitation, we propose Easy Dataset, a unified framework for synthesizing fine-tuning data from unstructured documents via an intuitive graphical user interface (GUI). Specifically, Easy Dataset allows users to easily configure text extraction models and chunking strategies to transform raw documents into coherent text chunks. It then leverages a persona-driven prompting approach to generate diverse question-answer pairs using public-available LLMs. Throughout the pipeline, a human-in-the-loop visual interface facilitates the review and refinement of intermediate outputs to ensure data quality. Experiments on a financial question-answering task show that fine-tuning LLMs on the synthesized dataset significantly improves domain-specific performance while preserving general knowledge. The source code and installable package are available at https://github.com/ConardLi/easy-dataset and have garnered over 9,000 GitHub stars.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04009</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 11:38:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PresentAgent: Multimodal Agent for Presentation Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04036</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04036.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingwei Shi, Zeyu Zhang, Biao Wu, Yanjie Liang, Meng Fang, Ling Chen, Yang Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present PresentAgent, a multimodal agent that transforms long-form documents into narrated presentation videos. While existing approaches are limited to generating static slides or text summaries, our method advances beyond these limitations by producing fully synchronized visual and spoken content that closely mimics human-style presentations. To achieve this integration, PresentAgent employs a modular pipeline that systematically segments the input document, plans and renders slide-style visual frames, generates contextual spoken narration with large language models and Text-to-Speech models, and seamlessly composes the final video with precise audio-visual alignment. Given the complexity of evaluating such multimodal outputs, we introduce PresentEval, a unified assessment framework powered by Vision-Language Models that comprehensively scores videos across three critical dimensions: content fidelity, visual clarity, and audience comprehension through prompt-based evaluation. Our experimental validation on a curated dataset of 30 document-presentation pairs demonstrates that PresentAgent approaches human-level quality across all evaluation metrics. These results highlight the significant potential of controllable multimodal agents in transforming static textual materials into dynamic, effective, and accessible presentation formats. Code will be available at https://github.com/AIGeeksGroup/PresentAgent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04036</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 13:24:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Train Your LLM Web Agent: A Statistical Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04103</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04103.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dheeraj Vattikonda, Santhoshi Ravichandran, Emiliano Penaloza, Hadi Nekoei, Megh Thakkar, Thibault Le Sellier de Chezelles, Nicolas Gontier, Miguel Muñoz-Mármol, Sahar Omidi Shayegan, Stefania Raimondo, Xue Liu, Alexandre Drouin, Laurent Charlin, Alexandre Piché, Alexandre Lacoste, Massimo Caccia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM-based web agents have recently made significant progress, but much of it has occurred in closed-source systems, widening the gap with open-source alternatives. Progress has been held back by two key challenges: first, a narrow focus on single-step tasks that overlooks the complexity of multi-step web interactions; and second, the high compute costs required to post-train LLM-based web agents. To address this, we present the first statistically grounded study on compute allocation for LLM web-agent post-training. Our approach uses a two-stage pipeline, training a Llama 3.1 8B student to imitate a Llama 3.3 70B teacher via supervised fine-tuning (SFT), followed by on-policy reinforcement learning. We find this process highly sensitive to hyperparameter choices, making exhaustive sweeps impractical. To spare others from expensive trial-and-error, we sample 1,370 configurations and use bootstrapping to estimate effective hyperparameters. Our results show that combining SFT with on-policy RL consistently outperforms either approach alone on both WorkArena and MiniWob++. Further, this strategy requires only 55% of the compute to match the peak performance of pure SFT on MiniWob++, effectively pushing the compute-performance Pareto frontier, and is the only strategy that can close the gap with closed-source models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04103</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 17:12:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SeqTex: Generate Mesh Textures in Video Sequence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04285</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04285.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ze Yuan, Xin Yu, Yangtian Sun, Yuan-Chen Guo, Yan-Pei Cao, Ding Liang, Xiaojuan Qi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training native 3D texture generative models remains a fundamental yet challenging problem, largely due to the limited availability of large-scale, high-quality 3D texture datasets. This scarcity hinders generalization to real-world scenarios. To address this, most existing methods finetune foundation image generative models to exploit their learned visual priors. However, these approaches typically generate only multi-view images and rely on post-processing to produce UV texture maps -- an essential representation in modern graphics pipelines. Such two-stage pipelines often suffer from error accumulation and spatial inconsistencies across the 3D surface. In this paper, we introduce SeqTex, a novel end-to-end framework that leverages the visual knowledge encoded in pretrained video foundation models to directly generate complete UV texture maps. Unlike previous methods that model the distribution of UV textures in isolation, SeqTex reformulates the task as a sequence generation problem, enabling the model to learn the joint distribution of multi-view renderings and UV textures. This design effectively transfers the consistent image-space priors from video foundation models into the UV domain. To further enhance performance, we propose several architectural innovations: a decoupled multi-view and UV branch design, geometry-informed attention to guide cross-domain feature alignment, and adaptive token resolution to preserve fine texture details while maintaining computational efficiency. Together, these components allow SeqTex to fully utilize pretrained video priors and synthesize high-fidelity UV texture maps without the need for post-processing. Extensive experiments show that SeqTex achieves state-of-the-art performance on both image-conditioned and text-conditioned 3D texture generation tasks, with superior 3D consistency, texture-geometry alignment, and real-world generalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04285</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 07:58:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOD-X: A Modular Open Decentralized eXchange Framework proposal for   Heterogeneous Interoperable Artificial Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04376</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04376.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Georgios Ioannides, Christos Constantinou, Vinija Jain, Aman Chadha, Aaron Elkins&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As Artificial Intelligence systems evolve from monolithic models to ecosystems of specialized agents, the need for standardized communication protocols becomes increasingly critical. This paper introduces MOD-X (Modular Open Decentralized eXchange), a novel architectural framework proposal for agent interoperability that addresses key limitations of existing protocols. Unlike current approaches, MOD-X proposes a layered architecture with a Universal Message Bus, thorough state management, translation capabilities, and blockchain-based security mechanisms. We present MOD-X's architecture, compare it with existing protocols, and demonstrate its application through a worked example how it enables integration between heterogeneous specialist agents (agents with different architectures, vendors, capabilities, and knowledge representations--including rule-based systems, neural networks, symbolic reasoning engines, and legacy software with agent wrappers). MOD-X's key innovations include a publish-subscribe communication model, semantic capability discovery, and dynamic workflow orchestration--providing a framework that bridges theoretical formalism with practical implementation. This architecture addresses the growing need for truly decentralized, interoperable agent ecosystems that can scale effectively without the need for central coordination.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04376</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 12:46:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DreamVLA: A Vision-Language-Action Model Dreamed with Comprehensive   World Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04447</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04447.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenyao Zhang, Hongsi Liu, Zekun Qi, Yunnan Wang, XinQiang Yu, Jiazhao Zhang, Runpei Dong, Jiawei He, He Wang, Zhizheng Zhang, Li Yi, Wenjun Zeng, Xin Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in vision-language-action (VLA) models have shown promise in integrating image generation with action prediction to improve generalization and reasoning in robot manipulation. However, existing methods are limited to challenging image-based forecasting, which suffers from redundant information and lacks comprehensive and critical world knowledge, including dynamic, spatial and semantic information. To address these limitations, we propose DreamVLA, a novel VLA framework that integrates comprehensive world knowledge forecasting to enable inverse dynamics modeling, thereby establishing a perception-prediction-action loop for manipulation tasks. Specifically, DreamVLA introduces a dynamic-region-guided world knowledge prediction, integrated with the spatial and semantic cues, which provide compact yet comprehensive representations for action planning. This design aligns with how humans interact with the world by first forming abstract multimodal reasoning chains before acting. To mitigate interference among the dynamic, spatial and semantic information during training, we adopt a block-wise structured attention mechanism that masks their mutual attention, preventing information leakage and keeping each representation clean and disentangled. Moreover, to model the conditional distribution over future actions, we employ a diffusion-based transformer that disentangles action representations from shared latent features. Extensive experiments on both real-world and simulation environments demonstrate that DreamVLA achieves 76.7% success rate on real robot tasks and 4.44 average length on the CALVIN ABC-D benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04447</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 16:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating LLMs on Real-World Forecasting Against Human Superforecasters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04562</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04562.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Janna Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities across diverse tasks, but their ability to forecast future events remains understudied. A year ago, large language models struggle to come close to the accuracy of a human crowd. I evaluate state-of-the-art LLMs on 464 forecasting questions from Metaculus, comparing their performance against human superforecasters. Frontier models achieve Brier scores that ostensibly surpass the human crowd but still significantly underperform a group of superforecasters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04562</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 22:26:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nile-Chat: Egyptian Language Models for Arabic and Latin Scripts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04569</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04569.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guokan Shang, Hadi Abdine, Ahmad Chamma, Amr Mohamed, Mohamed Anwar, Abdelaziz Bounhar, Omar El Herraoui, Preslav Nakov, Michalis Vazirgiannis, Eric Xing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Nile-Chat-4B, 3x4B-A6B, and 12B, a collection of LLMs for Egyptian dialect, uniquely designed to understand and generate texts written in both Arabic and Latin scripts. Specifically, with Nile-Chat-3x4B-A6B, we introduce a novel language adaptation approach by leveraging the Branch-Train-MiX strategy to merge script-specialized experts, into a single MoE model. Our Nile-Chat models significantly outperform leading multilingual and Arabic LLMs, such as LLaMa, Jais, and ALLaM, on our newly introduced Egyptian evaluation benchmarks, which span both understanding and generative tasks. Notably, our 12B model yields a 14.4% performance gain over Qwen2.5-14B-Instruct on Latin-script benchmarks. All our resources are publicly available. We believe this work presents a comprehensive methodology for adapting LLMs to dual-script languages, addressing an often overlooked aspect in modern LLM development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04569</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 22:53:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VLM2Vec-V2: Advancing Multimodal Embedding for Videos, Images, and   Visual Documents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04590</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04590.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui Meng, Ziyan Jiang, Ye Liu, Mingyi Su, Xinyi Yang, Yuepeng Fu, Can Qin, Zeyuan Chen, Ran Xu, Caiming Xiong, Yingbo Zhou, Wenhu Chen, Semih Yavuz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal embedding models have been crucial in enabling various downstream tasks such as semantic similarity, information retrieval, and clustering over different modalities. However, existing multimodal embeddings like VLM2Vec, E5-V, GME are predominantly focused on natural images, with limited support for other visual forms such as videos and visual documents. This restricts their applicability in real-world scenarios, including AI agents, multi-modal search and recommendation, and retrieval-augmented generation (RAG). To close this gap, we propose VLM2Vec-V2, a unified framework for learning embeddings across diverse visual forms. First, we introduce MMEB-V2, a comprehensive benchmark that extends MMEB with five new task types: visual document retrieval, video retrieval, temporal grounding, video classification and video question answering - spanning text, image, video, and visual document inputs. Next, we train VLM2Vec-V2, a general-purpose embedding model that supports text, image, video, and visual document inputs. Extensive experiments show that VLM2Vec-V2 achieves strong performance not only on the newly introduced video and document retrieval tasks, but also improves over prior baselines on the original image benchmarks. Through extensive evaluation, our study offers insights into the generalizability of various multimodal embedding models and highlights effective strategies for unified embedding learning, laying the groundwork for more scalable and adaptable representation learning in both research and real-world settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04590</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 00:51:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>any4: Learned 4-bit Numeric Representation for LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04610</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04610.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mostafa Elhoushi, Jeff Johnson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present any4, a learned 4-bit weight quantization solution for large language models (LLMs) providing arbitrary numeric representations without requiring pre-processing of weights or activations. any4 yields higher accuracy compared to other related 4-bit numeric representation types: int4, fp4 and nf4, as evaluated on a range of model sizes, generations and families (Llama 2, Llama 3, Mistral and Mixtral). While any4 does not require preprocessing of weights or activations, it is also competitive with orthogonal techniques that require such preprocessing (e.g., AWQ and GPTQ). We also experiment with any3 and any2 and show competitiveness at lower bits. Additionally, we show that we can calibrate using a single curated diverse sample rather than hundreds of samples from a dataset as done in most quantization approaches. We also open source tinygemm, a latency optimized GPU matrix multiplication library for LLMs, that implements any4 using a GPU-efficient lookup table strategy along with other common quantization methods. We open source our code at https://github.com/facebookresearch/any4 .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04610</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 01:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>R1-RE: Cross-Domain Relationship Extraction with RLVR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04642</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04642.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runpeng Dai, Tong Zheng, Run Yang, Hongtu Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Relationship extraction (RE) is a core task in natural language processing. Traditional approaches typically frame RE as a supervised learning problem, directly mapping context to labels-an approach that often suffers from poor out-of-domain (OOD) generalization. Inspired by the workflow of human annotators, we reframe RE as a reasoning task guided by annotation guidelines and introduce R1-RE, the first reinforcement learning with verifiable reward (RLVR) framework for RE tasks. Our method elicits the reasoning abilities of small language models for annotation tasks, resulting in significantly improved OOD robustness. We evaluate our approach on the public Sem-2010 dataset and a private MDKG dataset. The R1-RE-7B model attains an average OOD accuracy of approximately 70%, on par with leading proprietary models such as GPT-4o. Additionally, our comprehensive analysis provides novel insights into the training dynamics and emergent reasoning behaviors of the RLVR paradigm for RE.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04642</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 03:50:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LOOM-Scope: a comprehensive and efficient LOng-cOntext Model evaluation   framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04723</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04723.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zecheng Tang, Haitian Wang, Quantong Qiu, Baibei Ji, Ruoxi Sun, Keyan Zhou, Juntao Li, Min Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-context processing has become a fundamental capability for large language models~(LLMs). To assess model's long-context performance, numerous long-context evaluation benchmarks have been proposed. However, variations in evaluation settings across these benchmarks lead to inconsistent results, making it difficult to draw reliable comparisons. Besides, the high computational cost of long-context evaluation poses a significant barrier for the community to conduct comprehensive assessments of long-context models. In this paper, we propose LOOM-Scope, a comprehensive and efficient framework for long-context evaluation. LOOM-Scope standardizes evaluation settings across diverse benchmarks, supports deployment of efficient long-context inference acceleration methods, and introduces a holistic yet lightweight benchmark suite to evaluate models comprehensively. Homepage: https://loomscope.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04723</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 07:33:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Semantics Beyond Token Embeddings: Transformer LMs with Frozen   Visual Unicode Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04886</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04886.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; A. Bochkov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding the locus of semantic representation in large language models (LLMs) is crucial for interpretability and architectural innovation. The dominant paradigm posits that trainable input embeddings serve as foundational "meaning vectors." This paper challenges that view. We construct Transformer models where the embedding layer is entirely frozen, with vectors derived not from data, but from the visual structure of Unicode glyphs. These non-semantic, precomputed visual embeddings are fixed throughout training. Our method is compatible with any tokenizer, including a novel Unicode-centric tokenizer we introduce to ensure universal text coverage. Despite the absence of trainable, semantically initialized embeddings, our models converge, generate coherent text, and, critically, outperform architecturally identical models with trainable embeddings on the MMLU reasoning benchmark. We attribute this to "representational interference" in conventional models, where the embedding layer is burdened with learning both structural and semantic features. Our results indicate that high-level semantics are not inherent to input embeddings but are an emergent property of the Transformer's compositional architecture and data scale. This reframes the role of embeddings from meaning containers to structural primitives. We release all code and models to foster further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04886</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 11:17:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ArtifactsBench: Bridging the Visual-Interactive Gap in LLM Code   Generation Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04952</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.04952.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenchen Zhang, Yuhang Li, Can Xu, Jiaheng Liu, Ao Liu, Shihui Hu, Dengpeng Wu, Guanhua Huang, Kejiao Li, Qi Yi, Ruibin Xiong, Haotian Zhu, Yuanxing Zhang, Yuhao Jiang, Yue Zhang, Zenan Xu, Bohui Zhai, Guoxiang He, Hebin Li, Jie Zhao, Le Zhang, Lingyun Tan, Pengyu Guo, Xianshu Pang, Yang Ruan, Zhifeng Zhang, Zhonghu Wang, Ziyan Xu, Zuopu Yin, Wiggin Zhou, Chayse Zhou, Fengzong Lian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The generative capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs) are rapidly expanding from static code to dynamic, interactive visual artifacts. This progress is bottlenecked by a critical evaluation gap: established benchmarks focus on algorithmic correctness and are blind to the visual fidelity and interactive integrity that define modern user experiences. To bridge this gap, we introduce ArtifactsBench, a new benchmark and paradigm for the automated, multimodal evaluation of visual code generation. Our framework programmatically renders each generated artifact and captures its dynamic behavior through temporal screenshots. This visual evidence, alongside the source code, is then assessed by a Multimodal LLM (MLLM)-as-Judge, which is rigorously guided by a fine-grained, per-task checklist to ensure holistic and reproducible scoring. We construct a new benchmark of 1,825 diverse tasks and evaluate over 30 leading LLMs. Our automated evaluation achieves a striking 94.4% ranking consistency with WebDev Arena, the gold-standard for human preference in web development, and over 90% pairwise agreement with human experts. This establishes ArtifactsBench as the first framework to reliably automate the assessment of human-perceived quality at scale. Our analysis provides a high-resolution map of the current SOTA, revealing that generalist models often outperform domain-specific ones. We open-source ArtifactsBench, including the benchmark, evaluation harness, and baseline results at https://artifactsbenchmark.github.io/, to provide the community with a scalable and accurate tool to accelerate the development of user-centric generative models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04952</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 12:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Critical Risks of Amazon's Nova Premier under the   Frontier Model Safety Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06260</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06260.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Satyapriya Krishna, Ninareh Mehrabi, Abhinav Mohanty, Matteo Memelli, Vincent Ponzo, Payal Motwani, Rahul Gupta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Nova Premier is Amazon's most capable multimodal foundation model and teacher for model distillation. It processes text, images, and video with a one-million-token context window, enabling analysis of large codebases, 400-page documents, and 90-minute videos in a single prompt. We present the first comprehensive evaluation of Nova Premier's critical risk profile under the Frontier Model Safety Framework. Evaluations target three high-risk domains -- Chemical, Biological, Radiological &amp; Nuclear (CBRN), Offensive Cyber Operations, and Automated AI R&amp;D -- and combine automated benchmarks, expert red-teaming, and uplift studies to determine whether the model exceeds release thresholds. We summarize our methodology and report core findings. Based on this evaluation, we find that Nova Premier is safe for public release as per our commitments made at the 2025 Paris AI Safety Summit. We will continue to enhance our safety evaluation and mitigation pipelines as new risks and capabilities associated with frontier models are identified.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06260</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 13:33:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PRING: Rethinking Protein-Protein Interaction Prediction from Pairs to   Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05101</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05101.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinzhe Zheng, Hao Du, Fanding Xu, Jinzhe Li, Zhiyuan Liu, Wenkang Wang, Tao Chen, Wanli Ouyang, Stan Z. Li, Yan Lu, Nanqing Dong, Yang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep learning-based computational methods have achieved promising results in predicting protein-protein interactions (PPIs). However, existing benchmarks predominantly focus on isolated pairwise evaluations, overlooking a model's capability to reconstruct biologically meaningful PPI networks, which is crucial for biology research. To address this gap, we introduce PRING, the first comprehensive benchmark that evaluates protein-protein interaction prediction from a graph-level perspective. PRING curates a high-quality, multi-species PPI network dataset comprising 21,484 proteins and 186,818 interactions, with well-designed strategies to address both data redundancy and leakage. Building on this golden-standard dataset, we establish two complementary evaluation paradigms: (1) topology-oriented tasks, which assess intra and cross-species PPI network construction, and (2) function-oriented tasks, including protein complex pathway prediction, GO module analysis, and essential protein justification. These evaluations not only reflect the model's capability to understand the network topology but also facilitate protein function annotation, biological module detection, and even disease mechanism analysis. Extensive experiments on four representative model categories, consisting of sequence similarity-based, naive sequence-based, protein language model-based, and structure-based approaches, demonstrate that current PPI models have potential limitations in recovering both structural and functional properties of PPI networks, highlighting the gap in supporting real-world biological applications. We believe PRING provides a reliable platform to guide the development of more effective PPI prediction models for the community. The dataset and source code of PRING are available at https://github.com/SophieSarceau/PRING.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05101</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 15:21:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviving Cultural Heritage: A Novel Approach for Comprehensive   Historical Document Restoration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05108</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05108.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuyi Zhang, Peirong Zhang, Zhenhua Yang, Pengyu Yan, Yongxin Shi, Pengwei Liu, Fengjun Guo, Lianwen Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Historical documents represent an invaluable cultural heritage, yet have undergone significant degradation over time through tears, water erosion, and oxidation. Existing Historical Document Restoration (HDR) methods primarily focus on single modality or limited-size restoration, failing to meet practical needs. To fill this gap, we present a full-page HDR dataset (FPHDR) and a novel automated HDR solution (AutoHDR). Specifically, FPHDR comprises 1,633 real and 6,543 synthetic images with character-level and line-level locations, as well as character annotations in different damage grades. AutoHDR mimics historians' restoration workflows through a three-stage approach: OCR-assisted damage localization, vision-language context text prediction, and patch autoregressive appearance restoration. The modular architecture of AutoHDR enables seamless human-machine collaboration, allowing for flexible intervention and optimization at each restoration stage. Experiments demonstrate AutoHDR's remarkable performance in HDR. When processing severely damaged documents, our method improves OCR accuracy from 46.83\% to 84.05\%, with further enhancement to 94.25\% through human-machine collaboration. We believe this work represents a significant advancement in automated historical document restoration and contributes substantially to cultural heritage preservation. The model and dataset are available at https://github.com/SCUT-DLVCLab/AutoHDR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05108</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 15:26:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4DSloMo: 4D Reconstruction for High Speed Scene with Asynchronous   Capture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05163</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05163.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yutian Chen, Shi Guo, Tianshuo Yang, Lihe Ding, Xiuyuan Yu, Jinwei Gu, Tianfan Xue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reconstructing fast-dynamic scenes from multi-view videos is crucial for high-speed motion analysis and realistic 4D reconstruction. However, the majority of 4D capture systems are limited to frame rates below 30 FPS (frames per second), and a direct 4D reconstruction of high-speed motion from low FPS input may lead to undesirable results. In this work, we propose a high-speed 4D capturing system only using low FPS cameras, through novel capturing and processing modules. On the capturing side, we propose an asynchronous capture scheme that increases the effective frame rate by staggering the start times of cameras. By grouping cameras and leveraging a base frame rate of 25 FPS, our method achieves an equivalent frame rate of 100-200 FPS without requiring specialized high-speed cameras. On processing side, we also propose a novel generative model to fix artifacts caused by 4D sparse-view reconstruction, as asynchrony reduces the number of viewpoints at each timestamp. Specifically, we propose to train a video-diffusion-based artifact-fix model for sparse 4D reconstruction, which refines missing details, maintains temporal consistency, and improves overall reconstruction quality. Experimental results demonstrate that our method significantly enhances high-speed 4D reconstruction compared to synchronous capture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05163</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 16:18:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critiques of World Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05169</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05169.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Eric Xing, Mingkai Deng, Jinyu Hou, Zhiting Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; World Model, the supposed algorithmic surrogate of the real-world environment which biological agents experience with and act upon, has been an emerging topic in recent years because of the rising needs to develop virtual agents with artificial (general) intelligence. There has been much debate on what a world model really is, how to build it, how to use it, and how to evaluate it. In this essay, starting from the imagination in the famed Sci-Fi classic Dune, and drawing inspiration from the concept of "hypothetical thinking" in psychology literature, we offer critiques of several schools of thoughts on world modeling, and argue the primary goal of a world model to be simulating all actionable possibilities of the real world for purposeful reasoning and acting. Building on the critiques, we propose a new architecture for a general-purpose world model, based on hierarchical, multi-level, and mixed continuous/discrete representations, and a generative and self-supervision learning framework, with an outlook of a Physical, Agentic, and Nested (PAN) AGI system enabled by such a model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05169</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 16:23:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pre-Trained Policy Discriminators are General Reward Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05197</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05197.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shihan Dou, Shichun Liu, Yuming Yang, Yicheng Zou, Yunhua Zhou, Shuhao Xing, Chenhao Huang, Qiming Ge, Demin Song, Haijun Lv, Songyang Gao, Chengqi Lv, Enyu Zhou, Honglin Guo, Zhiheng Xi, Wenwei Zhang, Qipeng Guo, Qi Zhang, Xipeng Qiu, Xuanjing Huang, Tao Gui, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We offer a novel perspective on reward modeling by formulating it as a policy discriminator, which quantifies the difference between two policies to generate a reward signal, guiding the training policy towards a target policy with desired behaviors. Based on this conceptual insight, we propose a scalable pre-training method named Policy Discriminative Learning (POLAR), which trains a reward model (RM) to discern identical policies and discriminate different ones. Unlike traditional reward modeling methods relying on absolute preferences, POLAR captures the relative difference between one policy and an arbitrary target policy, which is a scalable, high-level optimization objective suitable for modeling generic ranking relationships. Leveraging the POLAR pre-training paradigm, we present a series of RMs with parameter scales from 1.8B to 7B. Empirical results show that POLAR substantially outperforms traditional non-pre-trained methods, significantly enhancing RM performance. For instance, POLAR-7B could improve preference accuracy from 54.8% to 81.0% on STEM tasks and from 57.9% to 85.5% on creative writing tasks compared to SOTA baselines. POLAR also shows robust generalization capabilities in RLHF using Reinforcement Fine-tuning (RFT), providing reliable reward signals and markedly enhancing policy performance--improving LLaMa3.1-8B from an average of 47.36% to 56.33% and Qwen2.5-32B from 64.49% to 70.47% on 20 benchmarks. Moreover, scaling experiments reveal a clear power-law relationship between computation and performance, supported by linear correlation coefficients approaching 0.99. The impressive performance, strong generalization, and scaling properties suggest that POLAR is a promising direction for developing general and strong reward models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05197</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 16:56:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedGemma Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05201</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05201.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Andrew Sellergren, Sahar Kazemzadeh, Tiam Jaroensri, Atilla Kiraly, Madeleine Traverse, Timo Kohlberger, Shawn Xu, Fayaz Jamil, Cían Hughes, Charles Lau, Justin Chen, Fereshteh Mahvar, Liron Yatziv, Tiffany Chen, Bram Sterling, Stefanie Anna Baby, Susanna Maria Baby, Jeremy Lai, Samuel Schmidgall, Lu Yang, Kejia Chen, Per Bjornsson, Shashir Reddy, Ryan Brush, Kenneth Philbrick, Howard Hu, Howard Yang, Richa Tiwari, Sunny Jansen, Preeti Singh, Yun Liu, Shekoofeh Azizi, Aishwarya Kamath, Johan Ferret, Shreya Pathak, Nino Vieillard, Ramona Merhej, Sarah Perrin, Tatiana Matejovicova, Alexandre Ramé, Morgane Riviere, Louis Rouillard, Thomas Mesnard, Geoffrey Cideron, Jean-bastien Grill, Sabela Ramos, Edouard Yvinec, Michelle Casbon, Elena Buchatskaya, Jean-Baptiste Alayrac, Dmitry, Lepikhin, Vlad Feinberg, Sebastian Borgeaud, Alek Andreev, Cassidy Hardin, Robert Dadashi, Léonard Hussenot, Armand Joulin, Olivier Bachem, Yossi Matias, Katherine Chou, Avinatan Hassidim, Kavi Goel, Clement Farabet, Joelle Barral, Tris Warkentin, Jonathon Shlens, David Fleet, Victor Cotruta, Omar Sanseviero, Gus Martins, Phoebe Kirk, Anand Rao, Shravya Shetty, David F. Steiner, Can Kirmizibayrak, Rory Pilgrim, Daniel Golden, Lin Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Artificial intelligence (AI) has significant potential in healthcare applications, but its training and deployment faces challenges due to healthcare's diverse data, complex tasks, and the need to preserve privacy. Foundation models that perform well on medical tasks and require less task-specific tuning data are critical to accelerate the development of healthcare AI applications. We introduce MedGemma, a collection of medical vision-language foundation models based on Gemma 3 4B and 27B. MedGemma demonstrates advanced medical understanding and reasoning on images and text, significantly exceeding the performance of similar-sized generative models and approaching the performance of task-specific models, while maintaining the general capabilities of the Gemma 3 base models. For out-of-distribution tasks, MedGemma achieves 2.6-10% improvement on medical multimodal question answering, 15.5-18.1% improvement on chest X-ray finding classification, and 10.8% improvement on agentic evaluations compared to the base models. Fine-tuning MedGemma further improves performance in subdomains, reducing errors in electronic health record information retrieval by 50% and reaching comparable performance to existing specialized state-of-the-art methods for pneumothorax classification and histopathology patch classification. We additionally introduce MedSigLIP, a medically-tuned vision encoder derived from SigLIP. MedSigLIP powers the visual understanding capabilities of MedGemma and as an encoder achieves comparable or better performance than specialized medical image encoders. Taken together, the MedGemma collection provides a strong foundation of medical image and text capabilities, with potential to significantly accelerate medical research and development of downstream applications. The MedGemma collection, including tutorials and model weights, can be found at https://goo.gle/medgemma.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05201</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 17:01:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StreamVLN: Streaming Vision-and-Language Navigation via SlowFast Context   Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05240</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05240.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Meng Wei, Chenyang Wan, Xiqian Yu, Tai Wang, Yuqiang Yang, Xiaohan Mao, Chenming Zhu, Wenzhe Cai, Hanqing Wang, Yilun Chen, Xihui Liu, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-and-Language Navigation (VLN) in real-world settings requires agents to process continuous visual streams and generate actions with low latency grounded in language instructions. While Video-based Large Language Models (Video-LLMs) have driven recent progress, current VLN methods based on Video-LLM often face trade-offs among fine-grained visual understanding, long-term context modeling and computational efficiency. We introduce StreamVLN, a streaming VLN framework that employs a hybrid slow-fast context modeling strategy to support multi-modal reasoning over interleaved vision, language and action inputs. The fast-streaming dialogue context facilitates responsive action generation through a sliding-window of active dialogues, while the slow-updating memory context compresses historical visual states using a 3D-aware token pruning strategy. With this slow-fast design, StreamVLN achieves coherent multi-turn dialogue through efficient KV cache reuse, supporting long video streams with bounded context size and inference cost. Experiments on VLN-CE benchmarks demonstrate state-of-the-art performance with stable low latency, ensuring robustness and efficiency in real-world deployment. The project page is: https://streamvln.github.io/{https://streamvln.github.io/}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05240</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 17:49:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SciMaster: Towards General-Purpose Scientific AI Agents, Part I.   X-Master as Foundation: Can We Lead on Humanity's Last Exam?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05241</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05241.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingyi Chai, Shuo Tang, Rui Ye, Yuwen Du, Xinyu Zhu, Mengcheng Zhou, Yanfeng Wang, Weinan E, Yuzhi Zhang, Linfeng Zhang, Siheng Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancements of AI agents have ignited the long-held ambition of leveraging them to accelerate scientific discovery. Achieving this goal requires a deep understanding of the frontiers of human knowledge. As such, Humanity's Last Exam (HLE) provides an exceptionally challenging touchstone for evaluating scientific AI agents. In this work, we aim to construct the foundational architecture for general-purpose agents and validate the capabilities through leading performance on HLE. To achieve this, we introduce X-Master, a tool-augmented reasoning agent designed to emulate human researchers by interacting flexibly with external tools during its reasoning process. This agent, guided by the conceptualization of code as an interaction language, can flexibly leverage built-in Python libraries and our customized tools to augment the reasoning. We further scale its capabilities through X-Masters, a scattered-and-stacked agentic workflow that systematically enhances breadth and depth of reasoning. Our open-source solution, X-Masters, sets a new state-of-the-art record on HLE with a score of 32.1%, surpassing OpenAI's and Google's Deep Research (26.6% and 26.9%) and becoming the first to exceed the 30% threshold. This work allows us to gain a deeper understanding of complex task-solving and accumulates valuable experience that can inform future advancements, guiding subsequent model training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05241</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 17:50:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Memory in LLM Agents via Incremental Multi-Turn Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05257</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05257.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuanzhe Hu, Yu Wang, Julian McAuley&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent benchmarks for Large Language Model (LLM) agents primarily focus on evaluating reasoning, planning, and execution capabilities, while another critical component-memory, encompassing how agents memorize, update, and retrieve long-term information-is under-evaluated due to the lack of benchmarks. We term agents with memory mechanisms as memory agents. In this paper, we identify four core competencies essential for memory agents: accurate retrieval, test-time learning, long-range understanding, and conflict resolution. Existing datasets either rely on limited context lengths or are tailored for static, long-context settings like book-based QA, which do not reflect the interactive, multi-turn nature of memory agents that incrementally accumulate information. Furthermore, no existing benchmarks cover all four competencies. Therefore, we introduce MemoryAgentBench, a new benchmark specifically designed for memory agents. Our benchmark combines reformulated existing datasets with newly constructed ones, covering the above four memory competencies, providing a systematic and challenging testbed for assessing memory quality. We evaluate a diverse set of memory agents, ranging from simple context-based and retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) systems to advanced agents with external memory modules and tool integration. Empirical results reveal that current methods fall short of mastering all four competencies, underscoring the need for further research into comprehensive memory mechanisms for LLM agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05257</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 17:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Simple Edits: X-Planner for Complex Instruction-Based Image   Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05259</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05259.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chun-Hsiao Yeh, Yilin Wang, Nanxuan Zhao, Richard Zhang, Yuheng Li, Yi Ma, Krishna Kumar Singh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent diffusion-based image editing methods have significantly advanced text-guided tasks but often struggle to interpret complex, indirect instructions. Moreover, current models frequently suffer from poor identity preservation, unintended edits, or rely heavily on manual masks. To address these challenges, we introduce X-Planner, a Multimodal Large Language Model (MLLM)-based planning system that effectively bridges user intent with editing model capabilities. X-Planner employs chain-of-thought reasoning to systematically decompose complex instructions into simpler, clear sub-instructions. For each sub-instruction, X-Planner automatically generates precise edit types and segmentation masks, eliminating manual intervention and ensuring localized, identity-preserving edits. Additionally, we propose a novel automated pipeline for generating large-scale data to train X-Planner which achieves state-of-the-art results on both existing benchmarks and our newly introduced complex editing benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05259</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AXLearn: Modular Large Model Training on Heterogeneous Infrastructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05411</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05411.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mark Lee, Tom Gunter, Chang Lan, John Peebles, Hanzhi Zhou, Kelvin Zou, Sneha Bangalore, Chung-Cheng Chiu, Nan Du, Xianzhi Du, Philipp Dufter, Ruixuan Hou, Haoshuo Huang, Dongseong Hwang, Xiang Kong, Jinhao Lei, Tao Lei, Meng Li, Li Li, Jiarui Lu, Zhiyun Lu, Yiping Ma, David Qiu, Vivek Rathod, Senyu Tong, Zhucheng Tu, Jianyu Wang, Yongqiang Wang, Zirui Wang, Floris Weers, Sam Wiseman, Guoli Yin, Bowen Zhang, Xiyou Zhou, Danyang Zhuo, Cheng Leong, Ruoming Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We design and implement AXLearn, a production deep learning system that facilitates scalable and high-performance training of large deep learning models. Compared to other state-of-the-art deep learning systems, AXLearn has a unique focus on modularity and support for heterogeneous hardware infrastructure. AXLearn's internal interfaces between software components follow strict encapsulation, allowing different components to be assembled to facilitate rapid model development and experimentation on heterogeneous compute infrastructure. We introduce a novel method of quantifying modularity via Lines-of-Code (LoC)-complexity, which demonstrates how our system maintains constant complexity as we scale the components in the system, compared to linear or quadratic complexity in other systems. This allows integrating features such as Rotary Position Embeddings (RoPE) into AXLearn across hundred of modules with just 10 lines of code, compared to hundreds as required in other systems. At the same time, AXLearn maintains equivalent performance compared to state-of-the-art training systems. Finally, we share our experience in the development and operation of AXLearn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05411</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 18:50:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ModelCitizens: Representing Community Voices in Online Safety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05455</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05455.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ashima Suvarna, Christina Chance, Karolina Naranjo, Hamid Palangi, Sophie Hao, Thomas Hartvigsen, Saadia Gabriel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Automatic toxic language detection is critical for creating safe, inclusive online spaces. However, it is a highly subjective task, with perceptions of toxic language shaped by community norms and lived experience. Existing toxicity detection models are typically trained on annotations that collapse diverse annotator perspectives into a single ground truth, erasing important context-specific notions of toxicity such as reclaimed language. To address this, we introduce MODELCITIZENS, a dataset of 6.8K social media posts and 40K toxicity annotations across diverse identity groups. To capture the role of conversational context on toxicity, typical of social media posts, we augment MODELCITIZENS posts with LLM-generated conversational scenarios. State-of-the-art toxicity detection tools (e.g. OpenAI Moderation API, GPT-o4-mini) underperform on MODELCITIZENS, with further degradation on context-augmented posts. Finally, we release LLAMACITIZEN-8B and GEMMACITIZEN-12B, LLaMA- and Gemma-based models finetuned on MODELCITIZENS, which outperform GPT-o4-mini by 5.5% on in-distribution evaluations. Our findings highlight the importance of community-informed annotation and modeling for inclusive content moderation. The data, models and code are available at https://github.com/asuvarna31/modelcitizens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05455</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 20:15:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Solving More Challenging IMO Problems via Decoupled Reasoning   and Proving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06804</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06804.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenwen Liang, Linfeng Song, Yang Li, Tao Yang, Feng Zhang, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Automated Theorem Proving (ATP) in formal languages is a foundational challenge for AI. While Large Language Models (LLMs) have driven remarkable progress, a significant gap remains between their powerful informal reasoning capabilities and their weak formal proving performance. Recent studies show that the informal accuracy exceeds 80% while formal success remains below 8% on benchmarks like PutnamBench. We argue this gap persists because current state-of-the-art provers, by tightly coupling reasoning and proving, are trained with paradigms that inadvertently punish deep reasoning in favor of shallow, tactic-based strategies. To bridge this fundamental gap, we propose a novel framework that decouples high-level reasoning from low-level proof generation. Our approach utilizes two distinct, specialized models: a powerful, general-purpose Reasoner to generate diverse, strategic subgoal lemmas, and an efficient Prover to rigorously verify them. This modular design liberates the model's full reasoning potential and bypasses the pitfalls of end-to-end training. We evaluate our method on a challenging set of post-2000 IMO problems, a problem set on which no prior open-source prover has reported success. Our decoupled framework successfully solves 5 of these problems, demonstrating a significant step towards automated reasoning on exceptionally difficult mathematical challenges. To foster future research, we release our full dataset of generated and verified lemmas for a wide range of IMO problems, available at https://tencent-imo.github.io/ .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06804</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 22:38:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SingLoRA: Low Rank Adaptation Using a Single Matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05566</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05566.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; David Bensaïd, Noam Rotstein, Roy Velich, Daniel Bensaïd, Ron Kimmel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) has significantly advanced parameter-efficient fine-tuning of large pretrained models. LoRA augments the pre-trained weights of a model by adding the product of two smaller matrices that together form a low-rank matrix update. Recent research has shown that scale disparities between these two matrices often cause unstable training dynamics, leading to suboptimal performance. In this paper, we propose SingLoRA, which reformulates low-rank adaptation by learning the weights update as a decomposition of a single low-rank matrix multiplied by its transpose. This simple design inherently removes inter-matrix scale conflicts, ensuring stable optimization, and roughly halves the parameter count. We analyze SingLoRA within the infinite-width neural network framework, showing that it guarantees stable feature learning by construction. Extensive experiments on multiple tasks validate these benefits. In common sense reasoning, fine-tuning LLama 7B on MNLI with SingLoRA achieves 91.3% accuracy - surpassing LoRA (89.1%) and LoRA+ (90.2%) - while using only 60% of their parameter budget. In image generation, fine-tuning Stable Diffusion with SingLoRA significantly improves image fidelity on DreamBooth, achieving a DINO similarity score of 0.151, compared to scores of 0.148 and 0.143 for DoRA and LoRA, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05566</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 01:11:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Landscape of Memorization in LLMs: Mechanisms, Measurement, and   Mitigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05578</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05578.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Xiong, Xuandong Zhao, Aneesh Pappu, Dawn Song&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities across a wide range of tasks, yet they also exhibit memorization of their training data. This phenomenon raises critical questions about model behavior, privacy risks, and the boundary between learning and memorization. Addressing these concerns, this paper synthesizes recent studies and investigates the landscape of memorization, the factors influencing it, and methods for its detection and mitigation. We explore key drivers, including training data duplication, training dynamics, and fine-tuning procedures that influence data memorization. In addition, we examine methodologies such as prefix-based extraction, membership inference, and adversarial prompting, assessing their effectiveness in detecting and measuring memorized content. Beyond technical analysis, we also explore the broader implications of memorization, including the legal and ethical implications. Finally, we discuss mitigation strategies, including data cleaning, differential privacy, and post-training unlearning, while highlighting open challenges in balancing the minimization of harmful memorization with utility. This paper provides a comprehensive overview of the current state of research on LLM memorization across technical, privacy, and performance dimensions, identifying critical directions for future work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05578</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 01:30:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedGen: Unlocking Medical Video Generation by Scaling   Granularly-annotated Medical Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05675</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05675.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rongsheng Wang, Junying Chen, Ke Ji, Zhenyang Cai, Shunian Chen, Yunjin Yang, Benyou Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in video generation have shown remarkable progress in open-domain settings, yet medical video generation remains largely underexplored. Medical videos are critical for applications such as clinical training, education, and simulation, requiring not only high visual fidelity but also strict medical accuracy. However, current models often produce unrealistic or erroneous content when applied to medical prompts, largely due to the lack of large-scale, high-quality datasets tailored to the medical domain. To address this gap, we introduce MedVideoCap-55K, the first large-scale, diverse, and caption-rich dataset for medical video generation. It comprises over 55,000 curated clips spanning real-world medical scenarios, providing a strong foundation for training generalist medical video generation models. Built upon this dataset, we develop MedGen, which achieves leading performance among open-source models and rivals commercial systems across multiple benchmarks in both visual quality and medical accuracy. We hope our dataset and model can serve as a valuable resource and help catalyze further research in medical video generation. Our code and data is available at https://github.com/FreedomIntelligence/MedGen&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05675</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 04:58:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AutoTriton: Automatic Triton Programming with Reinforcement Learning in   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05687</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05687.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shangzhan Li, Zefan Wang, Ye He, Yuxuan Li, Qi Shi, Jianling Li, Yonggang Hu, Wanxiang Che, Xu Han, Zhiyuan Liu, Maosong Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Kernel development in deep learning requires optimizing computational units across hardware while balancing memory management, parallelism, and hardware-specific optimizations through extensive empirical tuning. Although domain-specific languages like Triton simplify GPU programming by abstracting low-level details, developers must still manually tune critical parameters such as tile sizes and memory access patterns through iterative experimentation, creating substantial barriers to optimal performance and wider adoption. In this work, we introduce AutoTriton, the first model dedicated to Triton programming powered by reinforcement learning (RL). AutoTriton performs supervised fine-tuning (SFT) to be equipped with essential Triton programming expertise using a high-quality data gathering pipeline, and conducts RL with Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) algorithm, combining a rule-based reward and an execution-based reward to further improve Triton programming ability, sequentially. Experiments across five evaluation channels of TritonBench and KernelBench illustrate that our 8B model AutoTriton achieves performance comparable to mainstream large models, including Claude-4-Sonnet and DeepSeek-R1-0528. Further experimental analysis demonstrates the crucial role of each module within AutoTriton, including the SFT stage, the RL stage, and the reward design strategy. These findings underscore the promise of RL for automatically generating high-performance kernels, and since high-performance kernels are core components of AI systems, this breakthrough establishes an important foundation for building more efficient AI systems. The model and code will be available at https://github.com/AI9Stars/AutoTriton.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05687</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 05:38:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GTA1: GUI Test-time Scaling Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05791</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05791.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yan Yang, Dongxu Li, Yutong Dai, Yuhao Yang, Ziyang Luo, Zirui Zhao, Zhiyuan Hu, Junzhe Huang, Amrita Saha, Zeyuan Chen, Ran Xu, Liyuan Pan, Caiming Xiong, Junnan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graphical user interface (GUI) agents autonomously operate across platforms (e.g., Linux) to complete tasks by interacting with visual elements. Specifically, a user instruction is decomposed into a sequence of action proposals, each corresponding to an interaction with the GUI. After each action, the agent observes the updated GUI environment to plan the next step. However, two main challenges arise: i) resolving ambiguity in task planning (i.e., the action proposal sequence), where selecting an appropriate plan is non-trivial, as many valid ones may exist; ii) accurately grounding actions in complex and high-resolution interfaces, i.e., precisely interacting with visual targets.   This paper investigates the two aforementioned challenges with our GUI Test-time Scaling Agent, namely GTA1. First, to select the most appropriate action proposal, we introduce a test-time scaling method. At each step, we sample multiple candidate action proposals and leverage a judge model to evaluate and select the most suitable one. It trades off computation for better decision quality by concurrent sampling, shortening task execution steps, and improving overall performance. Second, we propose a model that achieves improved accuracy when grounding the selected action proposal to its corresponding visual elements. Our key insight is that reinforcement learning (RL) facilitates visual grounding through inherent objective alignments, rewarding successful clicks on interface elements.   Experimentally, our method establishes state-of-the-art performance across diverse benchmarks. For example, GTA1-7B achieves 50.1%, 92.4%, and 67.7% accuracies on Screenspot-Pro, Screenspot-V2, and OSWorld-G, respectively. When paired with a planner applying our test-time scaling strategy, it exhibits state-of-the-art agentic performance (e.g., 45.2% task success rate on OSWorld). We open-source our code and models here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05791</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 08:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Resolution Visual Reasoning via Multi-Turn Grounding-Based   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05920</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05920.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinyu Huang, Yuhao Dong, Weiwei Tian, Bo Li, Rui Feng, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; State-of-the-art large multi-modal models (LMMs) face challenges when processing high-resolution images, as these inputs are converted into enormous visual tokens, many of which are irrelevant to the downstream task. In this paper, we propose Multi-turn Grounding-based Policy Optimization (MGPO), an end-to-end reinforcement learning (RL) framework that enables LMMs to iteratively focus on key visual regions by automatically cropping sub-images, based on model-predicted grounding coordinates within a multi-turn conversation framework. Compared to supervised fine-tuning (SFT), which requires costly additional grounding annotations, our approach highlights that LMMs can emerge robust grounding abilities during the RL training process, leveraging only a binary reward function derived from the correctness of the final answer. Additionally, we observe that LMMs struggle to autonomously trigger visual grounding during the rollout process. To address this cold start problem, we design a multi-turn conversational template and restrict policy loss computation to model outputs generated across multiple dialogue rounds, thereby promoting stable optimization. Extensive experiments demonstrate that, when trained on standard visual-question-short answering data without grounding annotations, MGPO effectively elicits stronger grounding capabilities compared to GRPO, leading to 5.4\% improvement on in-distribution MME-Realworld and 5.2\% improvement on the challenging out-of-distribution (OOD) V* Bench. Notably, MGPO post-training on Qwen2.5-VL-7B with 21K samples surpasses OpenAI's o1 and GPT-4o models on the OOD V* Bench. Codes are available at https://github.com/EvolvingLMMs-Lab/MGPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05920</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 12:05:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tora2: Motion and Appearance Customized Diffusion Transformer for   Multi-Entity Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05963</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05963.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenghao Zhang, Junchao Liao, Xiangyu Meng, Long Qin, Weizhi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in diffusion transformer models for motion-guided video generation, such as Tora, have shown significant progress. In this paper, we present Tora2, an enhanced version of Tora, which introduces several design improvements to expand its capabilities in both appearance and motion customization. Specifically, we introduce a decoupled personalization extractor that generates comprehensive personalization embeddings for multiple open-set entities, better preserving fine-grained visual details compared to previous methods. Building on this, we design a gated self-attention mechanism to integrate trajectory, textual description, and visual information for each entity. This innovation significantly reduces misalignment in multimodal conditioning during training. Moreover, we introduce a contrastive loss that jointly optimizes trajectory dynamics and entity consistency through explicit mapping between motion and personalization embeddings. Tora2 is, to our best knowledge, the first method to achieve simultaneous multi-entity customization of appearance and motion for video generation. Experimental results demonstrate that Tora2 achieves competitive performance with state-of-the-art customization methods while providing advanced motion control capabilities, which marks a critical advancement in multi-condition video generation. Project page: https://github.com/alibaba/Tora .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05963</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 13:11:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-LoRA: Single Image Diffusion Model Customization Without Overfitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05964</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05964.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vera Soboleva, Aibek Alanov, Andrey Kuznetsov, Konstantin Sobolev&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 97&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While diffusion model fine-tuning offers a powerful approach for customizing pre-trained models to generate specific objects, it frequently suffers from overfitting when training samples are limited, compromising both generalization capability and output diversity. This paper tackles the challenging yet most impactful task of adapting a diffusion model using just a single concept image, as single-image customization holds the greatest practical potential. We introduce T-LoRA, a Timestep-Dependent Low-Rank Adaptation framework specifically designed for diffusion model personalization. In our work we show that higher diffusion timesteps are more prone to overfitting than lower ones, necessitating a timestep-sensitive fine-tuning strategy. T-LoRA incorporates two key innovations: (1) a dynamic fine-tuning strategy that adjusts rank-constrained updates based on diffusion timesteps, and (2) a weight parametrization technique that ensures independence between adapter components through orthogonal initialization. Extensive experiments show that T-LoRA and its individual components outperform standard LoRA and other diffusion model personalization techniques. They achieve a superior balance between concept fidelity and text alignment, highlighting the potential of T-LoRA in data-limited and resource-constrained scenarios. Code is available at https://github.com/ControlGenAI/T-LoRA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05964</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 13:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RabakBench: Scaling Human Annotations to Construct Localized   Multilingual Safety Benchmarks for Low-Resource Languages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05980</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.05980.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gabriel Chua, Leanne Tan, Ziyu Ge, Roy Ka-Wei Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) and their safety classifiers often perform poorly on low-resource languages due to limited training data and evaluation benchmarks. This paper introduces RabakBench, a new multilingual safety benchmark localized to Singapore's unique linguistic context, covering Singlish, Chinese, Malay, and Tamil. RabakBench is constructed through a scalable three-stage pipeline: (i) Generate - adversarial example generation by augmenting real Singlish web content with LLM-driven red teaming; (ii) Label - semi-automated multi-label safety annotation using majority-voted LLM labelers aligned with human judgments; and (iii) Translate - high-fidelity translation preserving linguistic nuance and toxicity across languages. The final dataset comprises over 5,000 safety-labeled examples across four languages and six fine-grained safety categories with severity levels. Evaluations of 11 popular open-source and closed-source guardrail classifiers reveal significant performance degradation. RabakBench not only enables robust safety evaluation in Southeast Asian multilingual settings but also offers a reproducible framework for building localized safety datasets in low-resource environments. The benchmark dataset, including the human-verified translations, and evaluation code are publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05980</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 13:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeoBabel: A Multilingual Open Tower for Visual Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06137</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06137.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohammad Mahdi Derakhshani, Dheeraj Varghese, Marzieh Fadaee, Cees G. M. Snoek&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-image generation advancements have been predominantly English-centric, creating barriers for non-English speakers and perpetuating digital inequities. While existing systems rely on translation pipelines, these introduce semantic drift, computational overhead, and cultural misalignment. We introduce NeoBabel, a novel multilingual image generation framework that sets a new Pareto frontier in performance, efficiency and inclusivity, supporting six languages: English, Chinese, Dutch, French, Hindi, and Persian. The model is trained using a combination of large-scale multilingual pretraining and high-resolution instruction tuning. To evaluate its capabilities, we expand two English-only benchmarks to multilingual equivalents: m-GenEval and m-DPG. NeoBabel achieves state-of-the-art multilingual performance while retaining strong English capability, scoring 0.75 on m-GenEval and 0.68 on m-DPG. Notably, it performs on par with leading models on English tasks while outperforming them by +0.11 and +0.09 on multilingual benchmarks, even though these models are built on multilingual base LLMs. This demonstrates the effectiveness of our targeted alignment training for preserving and extending crosslingual generalization. We further introduce two new metrics to rigorously assess multilingual alignment and robustness to code-mixed prompts. Notably, NeoBabel matches or exceeds English-only models while being 2-4x smaller. We release an open toolkit, including all code, model checkpoints, a curated dataset of 124M multilingual text-image pairs, and standardized multilingual evaluation protocols, to advance inclusive AI research. Our work demonstrates that multilingual capability is not a trade-off but a catalyst for improved robustness, efficiency, and cultural fidelity in generative AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06137</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 16:19:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coding Triangle: How Does Large Language Model Understand Code?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06138</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06138.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taolin Zhang, Zihan Ma, Maosong Cao, Junnan Liu, Songyang Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have achieved remarkable progress in code generation, yet their true programming competence remains underexplored. We introduce the Code Triangle framework, which systematically evaluates LLMs across three fundamental dimensions: editorial analysis, code implementation, and test case generation. Through extensive experiments on competitive programming benchmarks, we reveal that while LLMs can form a self-consistent system across these dimensions, their solutions often lack the diversity and robustness of human programmers. We identify a significant distribution shift between model cognition and human expertise, with model errors tending to cluster due to training data biases and limited reasoning transfer. Our study demonstrates that incorporating human-generated editorials, solutions, and diverse test cases, as well as leveraging model mixtures, can substantially enhance both the performance and robustness of LLMs. Furthermore, we reveal both the consistency and inconsistency in the cognition of LLMs that may facilitate self-reflection and self-improvement, providing a potential direction for developing more powerful coding models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06138</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 16:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniPart: Part-Aware 3D Generation with Semantic Decoupling and   Structural Cohesion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06165</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06165.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunhan Yang, Yufan Zhou, Yuan-Chen Guo, Zi-Xin Zou, Yukun Huang, Ying-Tian Liu, Hao Xu, Ding Liang, Yan-Pei Cao, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The creation of 3D assets with explicit, editable part structures is crucial for advancing interactive applications, yet most generative methods produce only monolithic shapes, limiting their utility. We introduce OmniPart, a novel framework for part-aware 3D object generation designed to achieve high semantic decoupling among components while maintaining robust structural cohesion. OmniPart uniquely decouples this complex task into two synergistic stages: (1) an autoregressive structure planning module generates a controllable, variable-length sequence of 3D part bounding boxes, critically guided by flexible 2D part masks that allow for intuitive control over part decomposition without requiring direct correspondences or semantic labels; and (2) a spatially-conditioned rectified flow model, efficiently adapted from a pre-trained holistic 3D generator, synthesizes all 3D parts simultaneously and consistently within the planned layout. Our approach supports user-defined part granularity, precise localization, and enables diverse downstream applications. Extensive experiments demonstrate that OmniPart achieves state-of-the-art performance, paving the way for more interpretable, editable, and versatile 3D content.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06165</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 16:46:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skywork-R1V3 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06167</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06167.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei Shen, Jiangbo Pei, Yi Peng, Xuchen Song, Yang Liu, Jian Peng, Haofeng Sun, Yunzhuo Hao, Peiyu Wang, Yahui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Skywork-R1V3, an advanced, open-source vision-language model (VLM) that pioneers a new approach to visual reasoning. Its key innovation lies in effectively transferring reasoning skills from text-only Large Language Models (LLMs) to visual tasks. The strong performance of Skywork-R1V3 primarily stems from our elaborate post-training RL framework, which effectively activates and enhances the model's reasoning ability, without the need for additional continue pre-training. Through this framework, we further uncover the fundamental role of the connector module in achieving robust cross-modal alignment for multimodal reasoning models. In addition, we introduce a unique indicator of reasoning capability, the entropy of critical reasoning tokens, which has proven highly effective for checkpoint selection during RL training. Skywork-R1V3 achieves state-of-the-art results on MMMU, significantly improving from 64.3% to 76.0%. This performance matches entry-level human capabilities. Remarkably, our RL-powered post-training approach enables even the 38B parameter model to rival top closed-source VLMs. The implementation successfully transfers mathematical reasoning to other subject-related reasoning tasks. We also include an analysis of curriculum learning and reinforcement finetuning strategies, along with a broader discussion on multimodal reasoning. Skywork-R1V3 represents a significant leap in multimodal reasoning, showcasing RL as a powerful engine for advancing open-source VLM capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06167</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 16:47:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CriticLean: Critic-Guided Reinforcement Learning for Mathematical   Formalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06181</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06181.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongyuan Peng, Yifan Yao, Kaijing Ma, Shuyue Guo, Yizhe Li, Yichi Zhang, Chenchen Zhang, Yifan Zhang, Zhouliang Yu, Luming Li, Minghao Liu, Yihang Xia, Jiawei Shen, Yuchen Wu, Yixin Cao, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Jiaheng Liu, Ge Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Translating natural language mathematical statements into formal, executable code is a fundamental challenge in automated theorem proving. While prior work has focused on generation and compilation success, little attention has been paid to the critic phase-the evaluation of whether generated formalizations truly capture the semantic intent of the original problem. In this paper, we introduce CriticLean, a novel critic-guided reinforcement learning framework that elevates the role of the critic from a passive validator to an active learning component. Specifically, first, we propose the CriticLeanGPT, trained via supervised fine-tuning and reinforcement learning, to rigorously assess the semantic fidelity of Lean 4 formalizations. Then, we introduce CriticLeanBench, a benchmark designed to measure models' ability to distinguish semantically correct from incorrect formalizations, and demonstrate that our trained CriticLeanGPT models can significantly outperform strong open- and closed-source baselines. Building on the CriticLean framework, we construct FineLeanCorpus, a dataset comprising over 285K problems that exhibits rich domain diversity, broad difficulty coverage, and high correctness based on human evaluation. Overall, our findings highlight that optimizing the critic phase is essential for producing reliable formalizations, and we hope our CriticLean will provide valuable insights for future advances in formal mathematical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06181</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 17:03:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Latent Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06203</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06203.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui-Jie Zhu, Tianhao Peng, Tianhao Cheng, Xingwei Qu, Jinfa Huang, Dawei Zhu, Hao Wang, Kaiwen Xue, Xuanliang Zhang, Yong Shan, Tianle Cai, Taylor Kergan, Assel Kembay, Andrew Smith, Chenghua Lin, Binh Nguyen, Yuqi Pan, Yuhong Chou, Zefan Cai, Zhenhe Wu, Yongchi Zhao, Tianyu Liu, Jian Yang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Chujie Zheng, Chongxuan Li, Yuyin Zhou, Zhoujun Li, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Jiaheng Liu, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Jason Eshraghian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 71&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive reasoning capabilities, especially when guided by explicit chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning that verbalizes intermediate steps. While CoT improves both interpretability and accuracy, its dependence on natural language reasoning limits the model's expressive bandwidth. Latent reasoning tackles this bottleneck by performing multi-step inference entirely in the model's continuous hidden state, eliminating token-level supervision. To advance latent reasoning research, this survey provides a comprehensive overview of the emerging field of latent reasoning. We begin by examining the foundational role of neural network layers as the computational substrate for reasoning, highlighting how hierarchical representations support complex transformations. Next, we explore diverse latent reasoning methodologies, including activation-based recurrence, hidden state propagation, and fine-tuning strategies that compress or internalize explicit reasoning traces. Finally, we discuss advanced paradigms such as infinite-depth latent reasoning via masked diffusion models, which enable globally consistent and reversible reasoning processes. By unifying these perspectives, we aim to clarify the conceptual landscape of latent reasoning and chart future directions for research at the frontier of LLM cognition. An associated GitHub repository collecting the latest papers and repos is available at: https://github.com/multimodal-art-projection/LatentCoT-Horizon/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06203</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 17:29:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differential Mamba</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06204</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06204.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nadav Schneider, Itamar Zimerman, Eliya Nachmani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sequence models like Transformers and RNNs often overallocate attention to irrelevant context, leading to noisy intermediate representations. This degrades LLM capabilities by promoting hallucinations, weakening long-range and retrieval abilities, and reducing robustness. Recent work has shown that differential design can mitigate this issue in Transformers, improving their effectiveness across various applications. In this paper, we explore whether these techniques, originally developed for Transformers, can be applied to Mamba, a recent architecture based on selective state-space layers that achieves Transformer-level performance with greater efficiency. We show that a naive adaptation of differential design to Mamba is insufficient and requires careful architectural modifications. To address this, we introduce a novel differential mechanism for Mamba, empirically validated on language modeling benchmarks, demonstrating improved retrieval capabilities and superior performance over vanilla Mamba. Finally, we conduct extensive ablation studies and empirical analyses to justify our design choices and provide evidence that our approach effectively mitigates the overallocation problem in Mamba-based models. Our code is publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06204</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 17:30:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Diversity All You Need for Scalable Robotic Manipulation?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06219</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06219.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Modi Shi, Li Chen, Jin Chen, Yuxiang Lu, Chiming Liu, Guanghui Ren, Ping Luo, Di Huang, Maoqing Yao, Hongyang Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data scaling has driven remarkable success in foundation models for Natural Language Processing (NLP) and Computer Vision (CV), yet the principles of effective data scaling in robotic manipulation remain insufficiently understood. In this work, we investigate the nuanced role of data diversity in robot learning by examining three critical dimensions-task (what to do), embodiment (which robot to use), and expert (who demonstrates)-challenging the conventional intuition of "more diverse is better". Throughout extensive experiments on various robot platforms, we reveal that (1) task diversity proves more critical than per-task demonstration quantity, benefiting transfer from diverse pre-training tasks to novel downstream scenarios; (2) multi-embodiment pre-training data is optional for cross-embodiment transfer-models trained on high-quality single-embodiment data can efficiently transfer to different platforms, showing more desirable scaling property during fine-tuning than multi-embodiment pre-trained models; and (3) expert diversity, arising from individual operational preferences and stochastic variations in human demonstrations, can be confounding to policy learning, with velocity multimodality emerging as a key contributing factor. Based on this insight, we propose a distribution debiasing method to mitigate velocity ambiguity, the yielding GO-1-Pro achieves substantial performance gains of 15%, equivalent to using 2.5 times pre-training data. Collectively, these findings provide new perspectives and offer practical guidance on how to scale robotic manipulation datasets effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06219</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 17:52:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficiency-Effectiveness Reranking FLOPs for LLM-based Rerankers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06223</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06223.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Peng, Ting-ruen Wei, Tingyu Song, Yilun Zhao, Yi Fang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have recently been applied to reranking tasks in information retrieval, achieving strong performance. However, their high computational demands often hinder practical deployment. Existing studies evaluate the efficiency of LLM-based rerankers using proxy metrics such as latency, the number of forward passes, input tokens, and output tokens. However, these metrics depend on hardware and running-time choices (\eg parallel or not, batch size, etc), and often fail to account for model size, making it difficult to interpret and obscuring the evaluation of the efficiency-effectiveness tradeoff. To address this issue, we propose E2R-FLOPs, for LLM-based rerankers: ranking metrics per PetaFLOP (RPP) for relevance per compute and queries per PetaFLOP (QPP) for hardware-agnostic throughput. Companied with the new metrics, an interpretable FLOPs estimator is built to estimate the FLOPs of an LLM-based reranker even without running any experiments. Based on the proposed metrics, we conduct comprehensive experiments to evaluate a wide range of LLM-based rerankers with different architecture, studying the efficiency-effectiveness trade-off and bringing this issue to the attention of the research community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06223</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 17:56:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent KB: Leveraging Cross-Domain Experience for Agentic Problem Solving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06229</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06229.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangru Tang, Tianrui Qin, Tianhao Peng, Ziyang Zhou, Daniel Shao, Tingting Du, Xinming Wei, Peng Xia, Fang Wu, He Zhu, Ge Zhang, Jiaheng Liu, Xingyao Wang, Sirui Hong, Chenglin Wu, Hao Cheng, Chi Wang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 66&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As language agents tackle increasingly complex tasks, they struggle with effective error correction and experience reuse across domains. We introduce Agent KB, a hierarchical experience framework that enables complex agentic problem solving via a novel Reason-Retrieve-Refine pipeline. Agent KB addresses a core limitation: agents traditionally cannot learn from each other's experiences. By capturing both high-level strategies and detailed execution logs, Agent KB creates a shared knowledge base that enables cross-agent knowledge transfer. Evaluated on the GAIA benchmark, Agent KB improves success rates by up to 16.28 percentage points. On the most challenging tasks, Claude-3 improves from 38.46% to 57.69%, while GPT-4 improves from 53.49% to 73.26% on intermediate tasks. On SWE-bench code repair, Agent KB enables Claude-3 to improve from 41.33% to 53.33%. Our results suggest that Agent KB provides a modular, framework-agnostic infrastructure for enabling agents to learn from past experiences and generalize successful strategies to new tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06229</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 17:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feed-Forward SceneDINO for Unsupervised Semantic Scene Completion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06230</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06230.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aleksandar Jevtić, Christoph Reich, Felix Wimbauer, Oliver Hahn, Christian Rupprecht, Stefan Roth, Daniel Cremers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Semantic scene completion (SSC) aims to infer both the 3D geometry and semantics of a scene from single images. In contrast to prior work on SSC that heavily relies on expensive ground-truth annotations, we approach SSC in an unsupervised setting. Our novel method, SceneDINO, adapts techniques from self-supervised representation learning and 2D unsupervised scene understanding to SSC. Our training exclusively utilizes multi-view consistency self-supervision without any form of semantic or geometric ground truth. Given a single input image, SceneDINO infers the 3D geometry and expressive 3D DINO features in a feed-forward manner. Through a novel 3D feature distillation approach, we obtain unsupervised 3D semantics. In both 3D and 2D unsupervised scene understanding, SceneDINO reaches state-of-the-art segmentation accuracy. Linear probing our 3D features matches the segmentation accuracy of a current supervised SSC approach. Additionally, we showcase the domain generalization and multi-view consistency of SceneDINO, taking the first steps towards a strong foundation for single image 3D scene understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06230</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 17:59:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Growing Transformers: Modular Composition and Layer-wise Expansion on a   Frozen Substrate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07129</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07129.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; A. Bochkov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The prevailing paradigm for scaling large language models (LLMs) involves monolithic, end-to-end training, a resource-intensive process that lacks flexibility. This paper explores an alternative, constructive approach to model development, built upon the foundation of non-trainable, deterministic input embeddings. In prior [1], we established that high-level semantic reasoning can emerge in Transformers using frozen embeddings derived from the visual structure of Unicode glyphs. Here, we demonstrate that this fixed representational substrate acts as a universal "docking port," enabling two powerful and efficient scaling paradigms: seamless modular composition and progressive layer-wise growth.   First, we show that specialist models trained on disparate datasets (e.g., Russian and Chinese text) can be merged into a single, more capable Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) model, post-training, with zero architectural modification. This is achieved by simply averaging their output logits. The resulting MoE model exhibits immediate performance improvements on reasoning benchmarks like MMLU, surpassing its constituent experts without catastrophic forgetting. Second, we introduce a layer-wise constructive training methodology, where a deep Transformer is "grown" by progressively stacking and training one layer at a time. This method demonstrates stable convergence and a clear correlation between model depth and the emergence of complex reasoning abilities, such as those required for SQuAD.   Our findings suggest a paradigm shift from monolithic optimization towards a more biological or constructive model of AI development, where complexity is built incrementally and modules can be composed freely. This opens new avenues for resource-efficient scaling, continual learning, and a more democratized ecosystem for building powerful AI systems. We release all code and models to facilitate further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07129</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 20:01:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PERK: Long-Context Reasoning as Parameter-Efficient Test-Time Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06415</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06415.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zeming Chen, Angelika Romanou, Gail Weiss, Antoine Bosselut&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Long-context reasoning requires accurately identifying relevant information in extensive, noisy input contexts. Previous research shows that using test-time learning to encode context directly into model parameters can effectively enable reasoning over noisy information. However, meta-learning methods for enabling test-time learning are prohibitively memory-intensive, preventing their application to long context settings. In this work, we propose PERK (Parameter Efficient Reasoning over Knowledge), a scalable approach for learning to encode long input contexts using gradient updates to a lightweight model adapter at test time. Specifically, PERK employs two nested optimization loops in a meta-training phase. The inner loop rapidly encodes contexts into a low-rank adapter (LoRA) that serves as a parameter-efficient memory module for the base model. Concurrently, the outer loop learns to use the updated adapter to accurately recall and reason over relevant information from the encoded long context. Our evaluations on several long-context reasoning tasks show that PERK significantly outperforms the standard prompt-based long-context baseline, achieving average absolute performance gains of up to 90% for smaller models (GPT-2) and up to 27% for our largest evaluated model, Qwen-2.5-0.5B. In general, PERK is more robust to reasoning complexity, length extrapolation, and the locations of relevant information in contexts. Finally, we show that while PERK is memory-intensive during training, it scales more efficiently at inference time than prompt-based long-context inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06415</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 21:38:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perception-Aware Policy Optimization for Multimodal Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06448</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06448.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenhailong Wang, Xuehang Guo, Sofia Stoica, Haiyang Xu, Hongru Wang, Hyeonjeong Ha, Xiusi Chen, Yangyi Chen, Ming Yan, Fei Huang, Heng Ji&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has proven to be a highly effective strategy for endowing Large Language Models (LLMs) with robust multi-step reasoning abilities. However, its design and optimizations remain tailored to purely textual domains, resulting in suboptimal performance when applied to multimodal reasoning tasks. In particular, we observe that a major source of error in current multimodal reasoning lies in the perception of visual inputs. To address this bottleneck, we propose Perception-Aware Policy Optimization (PAPO), a simple yet effective extension of GRPO that encourages the model to learn to perceive while learning to reason, entirely from internal supervision signals. Notably, PAPO does not rely on additional data curation, external reward models, or proprietary models. Specifically, we introduce the Implicit Perception Loss in the form of a KL divergence term to the GRPO objective, which, despite its simplicity, yields significant overall improvements (4.4%) on diverse multimodal benchmarks. The improvements are more pronounced, approaching 8.0%, on tasks with high vision dependency. We also observe a substantial reduction (30.5%) in perception errors, indicating improved perceptual capabilities with PAPO. We conduct comprehensive analysis of PAPO and identify a unique loss hacking issue, which we rigorously analyze and mitigate through a Double Entropy Loss. Overall, our work introduces a deeper integration of perception-aware supervision into RLVR learning objectives and lays the groundwork for a new RL framework that encourages visually grounded reasoning. Project page: https://mikewangwzhl.github.io/PAPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06448</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 23:22:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Systematic Analysis of Hybrid Linear Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06457</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06457.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dustin Wang, Rui-Jie Zhu, Steven Abreu, Yong Shan, Taylor Kergan, Yuqi Pan, Yuhong Chou, Zheng Li, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Jason Eshraghian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Transformers face quadratic complexity and memory issues with long sequences, prompting the adoption of linear attention mechanisms using fixed-size hidden states. However, linear models often suffer from limited recall performance, leading to hybrid architectures that combine linear and full attention layers. Despite extensive hybrid architecture research, the choice of linear attention component has not been deeply explored. We systematically evaluate various linear attention models across generations - vector recurrences to advanced gating mechanisms - both standalone and hybridized. To enable this comprehensive analysis, we trained and open-sourced 72 models: 36 at 340M parameters (20B tokens) and 36 at 1.3B parameters (100B tokens), covering six linear attention variants across five hybridization ratios. Benchmarking on standard language modeling and recall tasks reveals that superior standalone linear models do not necessarily excel in hybrids. While language modeling remains stable across linear-to-full attention ratios, recall significantly improves with increased full attention layers, particularly below a 3:1 ratio. Our study highlights selective gating, hierarchical recurrence, and controlled forgetting as critical for effective hybrid models. We recommend architectures such as HGRN-2 or GatedDeltaNet with a linear-to-full ratio between 3:1 and 6:1 to achieve Transformer-level recall efficiently. Our models are open-sourced at https://huggingface.co/collections/m-a-p/hybrid-linear-attention-research-686c488a63d609d2f20e2b1e.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06457</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 23:54:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LangSplatV2: High-dimensional 3D Language Gaussian Splatting with 450+   FPS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07136</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07136.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wanhua Li, Yujie Zhao, Minghan Qin, Yang Liu, Yuanhao Cai, Chuang Gan, Hanspeter Pfister&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce LangSplatV2, which achieves high-dimensional feature splatting at 476.2 FPS and 3D open-vocabulary text querying at 384.6 FPS for high-resolution images, providing a 42 times speedup and a 47 times boost over LangSplat respectively, along with improved query accuracy. LangSplat employs Gaussian Splatting to embed 2D CLIP language features into 3D, significantly enhancing speed and learning a precise 3D language field with SAM semantics. Such advancements in 3D language fields are crucial for applications that require language interaction within complex scenes. However, LangSplat does not yet achieve real-time inference performance (8.2 FPS), even with advanced A100 GPUs, severely limiting its broader application. In this paper, we first conduct a detailed time analysis of LangSplat, identifying the heavyweight decoder as the primary speed bottleneck. Our solution, LangSplatV2 assumes that each Gaussian acts as a sparse code within a global dictionary, leading to the learning of a 3D sparse coefficient field that entirely eliminates the need for a heavyweight decoder. By leveraging this sparsity, we further propose an efficient sparse coefficient splatting method with CUDA optimization, rendering high-dimensional feature maps at high quality while incurring only the time cost of splatting an ultra-low-dimensional feature. Our experimental results demonstrate that LangSplatV2 not only achieves better or competitive query accuracy but is also significantly faster. Codes and demos are available at our project page: https://langsplat-v2.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07136</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:19:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video-RTS: Rethinking Reinforcement Learning and Test-Time Scaling for   Efficient and Enhanced Video Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06485</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06485.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyang Wang, Jaehong Yoon, Shoubin Yu, Md Mohaiminul Islam, Gedas Bertasius, Mohit Bansal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite advances in reinforcement learning (RL)-based video reasoning with large language models (LLMs), data collection and finetuning remain significant challenges. These methods often rely on large-scale supervised fine-tuning (SFT) with extensive video data and long Chain-of-Thought (CoT) annotations, making them costly and hard to scale. To address this, we present Video-RTS, a new approach to improve video reasoning capability with drastically improved data efficiency by combining data-efficient RL with a video-adaptive test-time scaling (TTS) strategy. Based on observations about the data scaling of RL samples, we skip the resource-intensive SFT step and employ efficient pure-RL training with output-based rewards, requiring no additional annotations or extensive fine-tuning. Furthermore, to utilize computational resources more efficiently, we introduce a sparse-to-dense video TTS strategy that improves inference by iteratively adding frames based on output consistency. We validate our approach on multiple video reasoning benchmarks, showing that Video-RTS surpasses existing video reasoning models by an average of 2.4% in accuracy using only 3.6% training samples. For example, Video-RTS achieves a 4.2% improvement on Video-Holmes, a recent and challenging video reasoning benchmark, and a 2.6% improvement on MMVU. Notably, our pure RL training and adaptive video TTS offer complementary strengths, enabling Video-RTS's strong reasoning performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06485</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 02:06:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Token Bottleneck: One Token to Remember Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06543</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06543.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taekyung Kim, Dongyoon Han, Byeongho Heo, Jeongeun Park, Sangdoo Yun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deriving compact and temporally aware visual representations from dynamic scenes is essential for successful execution of sequential scene understanding tasks such as visual tracking and robotic manipulation. In this paper, we introduce Token Bottleneck (ToBo), a simple yet intuitive self-supervised learning pipeline that squeezes a scene into a bottleneck token and predicts the subsequent scene using minimal patches as hints. The ToBo pipeline facilitates the learning of sequential scene representations by conservatively encoding the reference scene into a compact bottleneck token during the squeeze step. In the expansion step, we guide the model to capture temporal dynamics by predicting the target scene using the bottleneck token along with few target patches as hints. This design encourages the vision backbone to embed temporal dependencies, thereby enabling understanding of dynamic transitions across scenes. Extensive experiments in diverse sequential tasks, including video label propagation and robot manipulation in simulated environments demonstrate the superiority of ToBo over baselines. Moreover, deploying our pre-trained model on physical robots confirms its robustness and effectiveness in real-world environments. We further validate the scalability of ToBo across different model scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06543</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 04:57:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoder-Hybrid-Decoder Architecture for Efficient Reasoning with Long   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06607</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06607.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liliang Ren, Congcong Chen, Haoran Xu, Young Jin Kim, Adam Atkinson, Zheng Zhan, Jiankai Sun, Baolin Peng, Liyuan Liu, Shuohang Wang, Hao Cheng, Jianfeng Gao, Weizhu Chen, Yelong Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in language modeling have demonstrated the effectiveness of State Space Models (SSMs) for efficient sequence modeling. While hybrid architectures such as Samba and the decoder-decoder architecture, YOCO, have shown promising performance gains over Transformers, prior works have not investigated the efficiency potential of representation sharing between SSM layers. In this paper, we introduce the Gated Memory Unit (GMU), a simple yet effective mechanism for efficient memory sharing across layers. We apply it to create SambaY, a decoder-hybrid-decoder architecture that incorporates GMUs in the cross-decoder to share memory readout states from a Samba-based self-decoder. SambaY significantly enhances decoding efficiency, preserves linear pre-filling time complexity, and boosts long-context performance, all while eliminating the need for explicit positional encoding. Through extensive scaling experiments, we demonstrate that our model exhibits a significantly lower irreducible loss compared to a strong YOCO baseline, indicating superior performance scalability under large-scale compute regimes. Our largest model enhanced with Differential Attention, Phi4-mini-Flash-Reasoning, achieves significantly better performance than Phi4-mini-Reasoning on reasoning tasks such as Math500, AIME24/25, and GPQA Diamond without any reinforcement learning, while delivering up to 10x higher decoding throughput on 2K-length prompts with 32K generation length under the vLLM inference framework. We release our training codebase on open-source data at https://github.com/microsoft/ArchScale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06607</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 07:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiffSpectra: Molecular Structure Elucidation from Spectra using   Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06853</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06853.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liang Wang, Yu Rong, Tingyang Xu, Zhenyi Zhong, Zhiyuan Liu, Pengju Wang, Deli Zhao, Qiang Liu, Shu Wu, Liang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Molecular structure elucidation from spectra is a foundational problem in chemistry, with profound implications for compound identification, synthesis, and drug development. Traditional methods rely heavily on expert interpretation and lack scalability. Pioneering machine learning methods have introduced retrieval-based strategies, but their reliance on finite libraries limits generalization to novel molecules. Generative models offer a promising alternative, yet most adopt autoregressive SMILES-based architectures that overlook 3D geometry and struggle to integrate diverse spectral modalities. In this work, we present DiffSpectra, a generative framework that directly infers both 2D and 3D molecular structures from multi-modal spectral data using diffusion models. DiffSpectra formulates structure elucidation as a conditional generation process. Its denoising network is parameterized by Diffusion Molecule Transformer, an SE(3)-equivariant architecture that integrates topological and geometric information. Conditioning is provided by SpecFormer, a transformer-based spectral encoder that captures intra- and inter-spectral dependencies from multi-modal spectra. Extensive experiments demonstrate that DiffSpectra achieves high accuracy in structure elucidation, recovering exact structures with 16.01% top-1 accuracy and 96.86% top-20 accuracy through sampling. The model benefits significantly from 3D geometric modeling, SpecFormer pre-training, and multi-modal conditioning. These results highlight the effectiveness of spectrum-conditioned diffusion modeling in addressing the challenge of molecular structure elucidation. To our knowledge, DiffSpectra is the first framework to unify multi-modal spectral reasoning and joint 2D/3D generative modeling for de novo molecular structure elucidation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06853</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 13:57:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Verification for LLM Code Generation: From Generation to   Testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06920</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.06920.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihan Ma, Taolin Zhang, Maosong Cao, Wenwei Zhang, Minnan Luo, Songyang Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have recently achieved notable success in code-generation benchmarks such as HumanEval and LiveCodeBench. However, a detailed examination reveals that these evaluation suites often comprise only a limited number of homogeneous test cases, resulting in subtle faults going undetected. This not only artificially inflates measured performance but also compromises accurate reward estimation in reinforcement learning frameworks utilizing verifiable rewards (RLVR). To address these critical shortcomings, we systematically investigate the test-case generation (TCG) task by proposing multi-dimensional metrics designed to rigorously quantify test-suite thoroughness. Furthermore, we introduce a human-LLM collaborative method (SAGA), leveraging human programming expertise with LLM reasoning capability, aimed at significantly enhancing both the coverage and the quality of generated test cases. In addition, we develop a TCGBench to facilitate the study of the TCG task. Experiments show that SAGA achieves a detection rate of 90.62% and a verifier accuracy of 32.58% on TCGBench. The Verifier Accuracy (Verifier Acc) of the code generation evaluation benchmark synthesized by SAGA is 10.78% higher than that of LiveCodeBench-v6. These results demonstrate the effectiveness of our proposed method. We hope this work contributes to building a scalable foundation for reliable LLM code evaluation, further advancing RLVR in code generation, and paving the way for automated adversarial test synthesis and adaptive benchmark integration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06920</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 14:58:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Return, Entropy-Eliciting Explore</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07017</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07017.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Zheng, Tianshun Xing, Qingshui Gu, Taoran Liang, Xingwei Qu, Xin Zhou, Yizhi Li, Zhoufutu Wen, Chenghua Lin, Wenhao Huang, Qian Liu, Ge Zhang, Zejun Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning from Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) improves the reasoning abilities of Large Language Models (LLMs) but it struggles with unstable exploration. We propose FR3E (First Return, Entropy-Eliciting Explore), a structured exploration framework that identifies high-uncertainty decision points in reasoning trajectories and performs targeted rollouts to construct semantically grounded intermediate feedback. Our method provides targeted guidance without relying on dense supervision. Empirical results on mathematical reasoning benchmarks(AIME24) show that FR3E promotes more stable training, produces longer and more coherent responses, and increases the proportion of fully correct trajectories. These results highlight the framework's effectiveness in improving LLM reasoning through more robust and structured exploration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07017</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 16:45:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlexOlmo: Open Language Models for Flexible Data Use</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07024</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07024.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weijia Shi, Akshita Bhagia, Kevin Farhat, Niklas Muennighoff, Pete Walsh, Jacob Morrison, Dustin Schwenk, Shayne Longpre, Jake Poznanski, Allyson Ettinger, Daogao Liu, Margaret Li, Dirk Groeneveld, Mike Lewis, Wen-tau Yih, Luca Soldaini, Kyle Lo, Noah A. Smith, Luke Zettlemoyer, Pang Wei Koh, Hannaneh Hajishirzi, Ali Farhadi, Sewon Min&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce FlexOlmo, a new class of language models (LMs) that supports (1) distributed training without data sharing, where different model parameters are independently trained on closed datasets, and (2) data-flexible inference, where these parameters along with their associated data can be flexibly included or excluded from model inferences with no further training. FlexOlmo employs a mixture-of-experts (MoE) architecture where each expert is trained independently on closed datasets and later integrated through a new domain-informed routing without any joint training. FlexOlmo is trained on FlexMix, a corpus we curate comprising publicly available datasets alongside seven domain-specific sets, representing realistic approximations of closed sets. We evaluate models with up to 37 billion parameters (20 billion active) on 31 diverse downstream tasks. We show that a general expert trained on public data can be effectively combined with independently trained experts from other data owners, leading to an average 41% relative improvement while allowing users to opt out of certain data based on data licensing or permission requirements. Our approach also outperforms prior model merging methods by 10.1% on average and surpasses the standard MoE trained without data restrictions using the same training FLOPs. Altogether, this research presents a solution for both data owners and researchers in regulated industries with sensitive or protected data. FlexOlmo enables benefiting from closed data while respecting data owners' preferences by keeping their data local and supporting fine-grained control of data access during inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07024</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 16:54:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Go to Zero: Towards Zero-shot Motion Generation with Million-scale Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07095</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07095.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ke Fan, Shunlin Lu, Minyue Dai, Runyi Yu, Lixing Xiao, Zhiyang Dou, Junting Dong, Lizhuang Ma, Jingbo Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating diverse and natural human motion sequences based on textual descriptions constitutes a fundamental and challenging research area within the domains of computer vision, graphics, and robotics. Despite significant advancements in this field, current methodologies often face challenges regarding zero-shot generalization capabilities, largely attributable to the limited size of training datasets. Moreover, the lack of a comprehensive evaluation framework impedes the advancement of this task by failing to identify directions for improvement. In this work, we aim to push text-to-motion into a new era, that is, to achieve the generalization ability of zero-shot. To this end, firstly, we develop an efficient annotation pipeline and introduce MotionMillion-the largest human motion dataset to date, featuring over 2,000 hours and 2 million high-quality motion sequences. Additionally, we propose MotionMillion-Eval, the most comprehensive benchmark for evaluating zero-shot motion generation. Leveraging a scalable architecture, we scale our model to 7B parameters and validate its performance on MotionMillion-Eval. Our results demonstrate strong generalization to out-of-domain and complex compositional motions, marking a significant step toward zero-shot human motion generation. The code is available at https://github.com/VankouF/MotionMillion-Codes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07095</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 17:52:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Data Scaling Lead to Visual Compositional Generalization?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07102</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07102.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Arnas Uselis, Andrea Dittadi, Seong Joon Oh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Compositional understanding is crucial for human intelligence, yet it remains unclear whether contemporary vision models exhibit it. The dominant machine learning paradigm is built on the premise that scaling data and model sizes will improve out-of-distribution performance, including compositional generalization. We test this premise through controlled experiments that systematically vary data scale, concept diversity, and combination coverage. We find that compositional generalization is driven by data diversity, not mere data scale. Increased combinatorial coverage forces models to discover a linearly factored representational structure, where concepts decompose into additive components. We prove this structure is key to efficiency, enabling perfect generalization from few observed combinations. Evaluating pretrained models (DINO, CLIP), we find above-random yet imperfect performance, suggesting partial presence of this structure. Our work motivates stronger emphasis on constructing diverse datasets for compositional generalization, and considering the importance of representational structure that enables efficient compositional learning. Code available at https://github.com/oshapio/visual-compositional-generalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07102</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 17:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4KAgent: Agentic Any Image to 4K Super-Resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07105</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07105.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yushen Zuo, Qi Zheng, Mingyang Wu, Xinrui Jiang, Renjie Li, Jian Wang, Yide Zhang, Gengchen Mai, Lihong V. Wang, James Zou, Xiaoyu Wang, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Zhengzhong Tu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 71&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present 4KAgent, a unified agentic super-resolution generalist system designed to universally upscale any image to 4K resolution (and even higher, if applied iteratively). Our system can transform images from extremely low resolutions with severe degradations, for example, highly distorted inputs at 256x256, into crystal-clear, photorealistic 4K outputs. 4KAgent comprises three core components: (1) Profiling, a module that customizes the 4KAgent pipeline based on bespoke use cases; (2) A Perception Agent, which leverages vision-language models alongside image quality assessment experts to analyze the input image and make a tailored restoration plan; and (3) A Restoration Agent, which executes the plan, following a recursive execution-reflection paradigm, guided by a quality-driven mixture-of-expert policy to select the optimal output for each step. Additionally, 4KAgent embeds a specialized face restoration pipeline, significantly enhancing facial details in portrait and selfie photos. We rigorously evaluate our 4KAgent across 11 distinct task categories encompassing a total of 26 diverse benchmarks, setting new state-of-the-art on a broad spectrum of imaging domains. Our evaluations cover natural images, portrait photos, AI-generated content, satellite imagery, fluorescence microscopy, and medical imaging like fundoscopy, ultrasound, and X-ray, demonstrating superior performance in terms of both perceptual (e.g., NIQE, MUSIQ) and fidelity (e.g., PSNR) metrics. By establishing a novel agentic paradigm for low-level vision tasks, we aim to catalyze broader interest and innovation within vision-centric autonomous agents across diverse research communities. We will release all the code, models, and results at: https://4kagent.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07105</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 17:59:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Multimodal Understanding via Stable Diffusion as a Task-Aware   Feature Extractor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vatsal Agarwal, Matthew Gwilliam, Gefen Kohavi, Eshan Verma, Daniel Ulbricht, Abhinav Shrivastava&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have enabled image-based question-answering capabilities. However, a key limitation is the use of CLIP as the visual encoder; while it can capture coarse global information, it often can miss fine-grained details that are relevant to the input query. To address these shortcomings, this work studies whether pre-trained text-to-image diffusion models can serve as instruction-aware visual encoders. Through an analysis of their internal representations, we find diffusion features are both rich in semantics and can encode strong image-text alignment. Moreover, we find that we can leverage text conditioning to focus the model on regions relevant to the input question. We then investigate how to align these features with large language models and uncover a leakage phenomenon, where the LLM can inadvertently recover information from the original diffusion prompt. We analyze the causes of this leakage and propose a mitigation strategy. Based on these insights, we explore a simple fusion strategy that utilizes both CLIP and conditional diffusion features. We evaluate our approach on both general VQA and specialized MLLM benchmarks, demonstrating the promise of diffusion models for visual understanding, particularly in vision-centric tasks that require spatial and compositional reasoning. Our project page can be found https://vatsalag99.github.io/mustafar/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07106</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 17:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Survey on Long-Video Storytelling Generation: Architectures,   Consistency, and Cinematic Quality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07202</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07202.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohamed Elmoghany, Ryan Rossi, Seunghyun Yoon, Subhojyoti Mukherjee, Eslam Bakr, Puneet Mathur, Gang Wu, Viet Dac Lai, Nedim Lipka, Ruiyi Zhang, Varun Manjunatha, Chien Nguyen, Daksh Dangi, Abel Salinas, Mohammad Taesiri, Hongjie Chen, Xiaolei Huang, Joe Barrow, Nesreen Ahmed, Hoda Eldardiry, Namyong Park, Yu Wang, Jaemin Cho, Anh Totti Nguyen, Zhengzhong Tu, Thien Nguyen, Dinesh Manocha, Mohamed Elhoseiny, Franck Dernoncourt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the significant progress that has been made in video generative models, existing state-of-the-art methods can only produce videos lasting 5-16 seconds, often labeled "long-form videos". Furthermore, videos exceeding 16 seconds struggle to maintain consistent character appearances and scene layouts throughout the narrative. In particular, multi-subject long videos still fail to preserve character consistency and motion coherence. While some methods can generate videos up to 150 seconds long, they often suffer from frame redundancy and low temporal diversity. Recent work has attempted to produce long-form videos featuring multiple characters, narrative coherence, and high-fidelity detail. We comprehensively studied 32 papers on video generation to identify key architectural components and training strategies that consistently yield these qualities. We also construct a comprehensive novel taxonomy of existing methods and present comparative tables that categorize papers by their architectural designs and performance characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07202</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 18:20:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Bullshit: Characterizing the Emergent Disregard for Truth in   Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07484</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07484.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaiqu Liang, Haimin Hu, Xuandong Zhao, Dawn Song, Thomas L. Griffiths, Jaime Fernández Fisac&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Bullshit, as conceptualized by philosopher Harry Frankfurt, refers to statements made without regard to their truth value. While previous work has explored large language model (LLM) hallucination and sycophancy, we propose machine bullshit as an overarching conceptual framework that can allow researchers to characterize the broader phenomenon of emergent loss of truthfulness in LLMs and shed light on its underlying mechanisms. We introduce the Bullshit Index, a novel metric quantifying LLMs' indifference to truth, and propose a complementary taxonomy analyzing four qualitative forms of bullshit: empty rhetoric, paltering, weasel words, and unverified claims. We conduct empirical evaluations on the Marketplace dataset, the Political Neutrality dataset, and our new BullshitEval benchmark (2,400 scenarios spanning 100 AI assistants) explicitly designed to evaluate machine bullshit. Our results demonstrate that model fine-tuning with reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF) significantly exacerbates bullshit and inference-time chain-of-thought (CoT) prompting notably amplify specific bullshit forms, particularly empty rhetoric and paltering. We also observe prevalent machine bullshit in political contexts, with weasel words as the dominant strategy. Our findings highlight systematic challenges in AI alignment and provide new insights toward more truthful LLM behavior.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07484</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 07:11:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Linear Separability Ceiling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07574</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07574.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Enrico Vompa, Tanel Tammet, Mohit Vaishnav&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Most state-of-the-art Visual-Language Models (VLMs) are seemingly limited by the linear separabilty of their visual embeddings on abstract reasoning tasks. This work investigates this "linear reasoning bottleneck" by introducing the Linear Separability Ceiling (LSC), the performance of a simple linear classifier on a VLM's visual embeddings. We find this bottleneck is widespread and stems not from poor perception, but from failures in the language model's reasoning pathways. We demonstrate this is a solvable alignment issue. The required intervention, however, is task-dependent: activating existing pathways suffices for semantic concepts, while complex relational reasoning requires adapting core model weights. Using postfix tuning as a methodological control, we find strong evidence for powerful, dormant reasoning pathways within VLMs. However, for complex relational tasks requiring deeper adaptation, explicitly improving representation quality causes the model to fail on new prompt formats despite its embeddings remaining well separated. Ultimately, this work provides a new lens for VLM analysis, showing that robust reasoning is a matter of targeted alignment, not simply improved representation learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07574</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 09:23:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re-Bottleneck: Latent Re-Structuring for Neural Audio Autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07867</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07867.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dimitrios Bralios, Jonah Casebeer, Paris Smaragdis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Neural audio codecs and autoencoders have emerged as versatile models for audio compression, transmission, feature-extraction, and latent-space generation. However, a key limitation is that most are trained to maximize reconstruction fidelity, often neglecting the specific latent structure necessary for optimal performance in diverse downstream applications. We propose a simple, post-hoc framework to address this by modifying the bottleneck of a pre-trained autoencoder. Our method introduces a "Re-Bottleneck", an inner bottleneck trained exclusively through latent space losses to instill user-defined structure. We demonstrate the framework's effectiveness in three experiments. First, we enforce an ordering on latent channels without sacrificing reconstruction quality. Second, we align latents with semantic embeddings, analyzing the impact on downstream diffusion modeling. Third, we introduce equivariance, ensuring that a filtering operation on the input waveform directly corresponds to a specific transformation in the latent space. Ultimately, our Re-Bottleneck framework offers a flexible and efficient way to tailor representations of neural audio models, enabling them to seamlessly meet the varied demands of different applications with minimal additional training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07867</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 15:47:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Chunking for End-to-End Hierarchical Sequence Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07955</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07955.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sukjun Hwang, Brandon Wang, Albert Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite incredible progress in language models (LMs) in recent years, largely resulting from moving away from specialized models designed for specific tasks to general models based on powerful architectures (e.g. the Transformer) that learn everything from raw data, pre-processing steps such as tokenization remain a barrier to true end-to-end foundation models. We introduce a collection of new techniques that enable a dynamic chunking mechanism which automatically learns content -- and context -- dependent segmentation strategies learned jointly with the rest of the model. Incorporating this into an explicit hierarchical network (H-Net) allows replacing the (implicitly hierarchical) tokenization-LM-detokenization pipeline with a single model learned fully end-to-end. When compute- and data- matched, an H-Net with one stage of hierarchy operating at the byte level outperforms a strong Transformer language model operating over BPE tokens. Iterating the hierarchy to multiple stages further increases its performance by modeling multiple levels of abstraction, demonstrating significantly better scaling with data and matching a token-based Transformer of twice its size. H-Nets pretrained on English show significantly increased character-level robustness, and qualitatively learn meaningful data-dependent chunking strategies without any heuristics or explicit supervision. Finally, the H-Net's improvement over tokenized pipelines is further increased in languages and modalities with weaker tokenization heuristics, such as Chinese and code, or DNA sequences (nearly 4x improvement in data efficiency over baselines), showing the potential of true end-to-end models that learn and scale better from unprocessed data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07955</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:39:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MIRIX: Multi-Agent Memory System for LLM-Based Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07957</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07957.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Wang, Xi Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although memory capabilities of AI agents are gaining increasing attention, existing solutions remain fundamentally limited. Most rely on flat, narrowly scoped memory components, constraining their ability to personalize, abstract, and reliably recall user-specific information over time. To this end, we introduce MIRIX, a modular, multi-agent memory system that redefines the future of AI memory by solving the field's most critical challenge: enabling language models to truly remember. Unlike prior approaches, MIRIX transcends text to embrace rich visual and multimodal experiences, making memory genuinely useful in real-world scenarios. MIRIX consists of six distinct, carefully structured memory types: Core, Episodic, Semantic, Procedural, Resource Memory, and Knowledge Vault, coupled with a multi-agent framework that dynamically controls and coordinates updates and retrieval. This design enables agents to persist, reason over, and accurately retrieve diverse, long-term user data at scale. We validate MIRIX in two demanding settings. First, on ScreenshotVQA, a challenging multimodal benchmark comprising nearly 20,000 high-resolution computer screenshots per sequence, requiring deep contextual understanding and where no existing memory systems can be applied, MIRIX achieves 35% higher accuracy than the RAG baseline while reducing storage requirements by 99.9%. Second, on LOCOMO, a long-form conversation benchmark with single-modal textual input, MIRIX attains state-of-the-art performance of 85.4%, far surpassing existing baselines. These results show that MIRIX sets a new performance standard for memory-augmented LLM agents. To allow users to experience our memory system, we provide a packaged application powered by MIRIX. It monitors the screen in real time, builds a personalized memory base, and offers intuitive visualization and secure local storage to ensure privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07957</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:40:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling RL to Long Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07966</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07966.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yukang Chen, Wei Huang, Baifeng Shi, Qinghao Hu, Hanrong Ye, Ligeng Zhu, Zhijian Liu, Pavlo Molchanov, Jan Kautz, Xiaojuan Qi, Sifei Liu, Hongxu Yin, Yao Lu, Song Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 112&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce a full-stack framework that scales up reasoning in vision-language models (VLMs) to long videos, leveraging reinforcement learning. We address the unique challenges of long video reasoning by integrating three critical components: (1) a large-scale dataset, LongVideo-Reason, comprising 52K long video QA pairs with high-quality reasoning annotations across diverse domains such as sports, games, and vlogs; (2) a two-stage training pipeline that extends VLMs with chain-of-thought supervised fine-tuning (CoT-SFT) and reinforcement learning (RL); and (3) a training infrastructure for long video RL, named Multi-modal Reinforcement Sequence Parallelism (MR-SP), which incorporates sequence parallelism and a vLLM-based engine tailored for long video, using cached video embeddings for efficient rollout and prefilling. In experiments, LongVILA-R1-7B achieves strong performance on long video QA benchmarks such as VideoMME. It also outperforms Video-R1-7B and even matches Gemini-1.5-Pro across temporal reasoning, goal and purpose reasoning, spatial reasoning, and plot reasoning on our LongVideo-Reason-eval benchmark. Notably, our MR-SP system achieves up to 2.1x speedup on long video RL training. LongVILA-R1 demonstrates consistent performance gains as the number of input video frames scales. LongVILA-R1 marks a firm step towards long video reasoning in VLMs. In addition, we release our training system for public availability that supports RL training on various modalities (video, text, and audio), various models (VILA and Qwen series), and even image and video generation models. On a single A100 node (8 GPUs), it supports RL training on hour-long videos (e.g., 3,600 frames / around 256k tokens).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07966</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:47:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry Forcing: Marrying Video Diffusion and 3D Representation for   Consistent World Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07982</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07982.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoyu Wu, Diankun Wu, Tianyu He, Junliang Guo, Yang Ye, Yueqi Duan, Jiang Bian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Videos inherently represent 2D projections of a dynamic 3D world. However, our analysis suggests that video diffusion models trained solely on raw video data often fail to capture meaningful geometric-aware structure in their learned representations. To bridge this gap between video diffusion models and the underlying 3D nature of the physical world, we propose Geometry Forcing, a simple yet effective method that encourages video diffusion models to internalize latent 3D representations. Our key insight is to guide the model's intermediate representations toward geometry-aware structure by aligning them with features from a pretrained geometric foundation model. To this end, we introduce two complementary alignment objectives: Angular Alignment, which enforces directional consistency via cosine similarity, and Scale Alignment, which preserves scale-related information by regressing unnormalized geometric features from normalized diffusion representation. We evaluate Geometry Forcing on both camera view-conditioned and action-conditioned video generation tasks. Experimental results demonstrate that our method substantially improves visual quality and 3D consistency over the baseline methods. Project page: https://GeometryForcing.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07982</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:55:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OST-Bench: Evaluating the Capabilities of MLLMs in Online   Spatio-temporal Scene Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07984</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07984.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; JingLi Lin, Chenming Zhu, Runsen Xu, Xiaohan Mao, Xihui Liu, Tai Wang, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have shown remarkable capabilities in integrating vision and language for complex reasoning. While most existing benchmarks evaluate models under offline settings with a fixed set of pre-recorded inputs, we introduce OST-Bench, a benchmark designed to evaluate Online Spatio-Temporal understanding from the perspective of an agent actively exploring a scene. The Online aspect emphasizes the need to process and reason over incrementally acquired observations, while the Spatio-Temporal component requires integrating current visual inputs with historical memory to support dynamic spatial reasoning. OST-Bench better reflects the challenges of real-world embodied perception. Built on an efficient data collection pipeline, OST-Bench consists of 1.4k scenes and 10k question-answer pairs collected from ScanNet, Matterport3D, and ARKitScenes. We evaluate several leading MLLMs on OST-Bench and observe that they fall short on tasks requiring complex spatio-temporal reasoning. Under the online setting, their accuracy declines as the exploration horizon extends and the memory grows. Through further experimental analysis, we identify common error patterns across models and find that both complex clue-based spatial reasoning demands and long-term memory retrieval requirements significantly drop model performance along two separate axes, highlighting the core challenges that must be addressed to improve online embodied reasoning. To foster further research and development in the field, our codes, dataset, and benchmark are available. Our project page is: https://rbler1234.github.io/OSTBench.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07984</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:56:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Granular Spatio-Temporal Token Merging for Training-Free   Acceleration of Video LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07990</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07990.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jeongseok Hyun, Sukjun Hwang, Su Ho Han, Taeoh Kim, Inwoong Lee, Dongyoon Wee, Joon-Young Lee, Seon Joo Kim, Minho Shim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video large language models (LLMs) achieve strong video understanding by leveraging a large number of spatio-temporal tokens, but suffer from quadratic computational scaling with token count. To address this, we propose a training-free spatio-temporal token merging method, named STTM. Our key insight is to exploit local spatial and temporal redundancy in video data which has been overlooked in prior work. STTM first transforms each frame into multi-granular spatial tokens using a coarse-to-fine search over a quadtree structure, then performs directed pairwise merging across the temporal dimension. This decomposed merging approach outperforms existing token reduction methods across six video QA benchmarks. Notably, STTM achieves a 2times speed-up with only a 0.5% accuracy drop under a 50% token budget, and a 3times speed-up with just a 2% drop under a 30% budget. Moreover, STTM is query-agnostic, allowing KV cache reuse across different questions for the same video. The project page is available at https://www.jshyun.me/projects/sttm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07990</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skip a Layer or Loop it? Test-Time Depth Adaptation of Pretrained LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07996</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07996.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyue Li, Yang Li, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Can a pretrained neural network adapt its architecture to different inputs without any finetuning? Do we need all layers for simple tasks, and are they adequate for challenging tasks? We found that the layers of a pretrained large language model (LLM) can be manipulated as separate modules to build a better and even shallower model customized for each test sample. In particular, each layer from the pretrained model can be skipped/pruned or repeated multiple times as recurrent neural networks (RNN), and stacked with others in arbitrary orders, yielding a chain-of-layers (CoLa) per sample. This compositional space greatly expands the scope of existing works on looped/recurrent pretrained modules, layer pruning, or early-exit networks. We develop a Monte Carlo Tree Search (MCTS) protocol to explore and identify the optimal CoLa for each sample from math and commonsense reasoning benchmarks. Compared to a static model of a fixed depth, CoLa allows shortcut paths (fast thinking), recurrence of the same layer(s) (slow thinking), and combining both, offering more flexible, dynamic architectures for different inputs. We conduct an extensive analysis of the MCTS-optimized CoLa, which leads to two key findings: (1) For &gt;75% of samples with correct predictions by the original LLM, we can find shorter CoLa, suggesting a large space for improving inference efficiency; (2) For &gt;60% of samples with originally incorrect predictions, we can identify CoLa achieving correct predictions, suggesting a large space of performance enhancement. Our results highlight the shortcomings of using a fixed architecture of pre-trained LLMs for inference on different samples and pave the way to unlock the generalization power of test-time depth adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07996</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PyVision: Agentic Vision with Dynamic Tooling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07998</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07998.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shitian Zhao, Haoquan Zhang, Shaoheng Lin, Ming Li, Qilong Wu, Kaipeng Zhang, Chen Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLMs are increasingly deployed as agents, systems capable of planning, reasoning, and dynamically calling external tools. However, in visual reasoning, prior approaches largely remain limited by predefined workflows and static toolsets. In this report, we present PyVision, an interactive, multi-turn framework that enables MLLMs to autonomously generate, execute, and refine Python-based tools tailored to the task at hand, unlocking flexible and interpretable problem-solving. We develop a taxonomy of the tools created by PyVision and analyze their usage across a diverse set of benchmarks. Quantitatively, PyVision achieves consistent performance gains, boosting GPT-4.1 by +7.8% on V* and Claude-4.0-Sonnet by +31.1% on VLMsAreBlind-mini. These results point to a broader shift: dynamic tooling allows models not just to use tools, but to invent them, advancing toward more agentic visual reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07998</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Traceable Evidence Enhanced Visual Grounded Reasoning: Evaluation and   Methodology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07999</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.07999.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haochen Wang, Xiangtai Li, Zilong Huang, Anran Wang, Jiacong Wang, Tao Zhang, Jiani Zheng, Sule Bai, Zijian Kang, Jiashi Feng, Zhuochen Wang, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Models like OpenAI-o3 pioneer visual grounded reasoning by dynamically referencing visual regions, just like human "thinking with images". However, no benchmark exists to evaluate these capabilities holistically. To bridge this gap, we propose TreeBench (Traceable Evidence Evaluation Benchmark), a diagnostic benchmark built on three principles: (1) focused visual perception of subtle targets in complex scenes, (2) traceable evidence via bounding box evaluation, and (3) second-order reasoning to test object interactions and spatial hierarchies beyond simple object localization. Prioritizing images with dense objects, we initially sample 1K high-quality images from SA-1B, and incorporate eight LMM experts to manually annotate questions, candidate options, and answers for each image. After three stages of quality control, TreeBench consists of 405 challenging visual question-answering pairs, even the most advanced models struggle with this benchmark, where none of them reach 60% accuracy, e.g., OpenAI-o3 scores only 54.87. Furthermore, we introduce TreeVGR (Traceable Evidence Enhanced Visual Grounded Reasoning), a training paradigm to supervise localization and reasoning jointly with reinforcement learning, enabling accurate localizations and explainable reasoning pathways. Initialized from Qwen2.5-VL-7B, it improves V* Bench (+16.8), MME-RealWorld (+12.6), and TreeBench (+13.4), proving traceability is key to advancing vision-grounded reasoning. The code is available at https://github.com/Haochen-Wang409/TreeVGR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07999</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
