<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:13:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>MeshSplatting: Differentiable Rendering with Opaque Meshes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06818</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.06818.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jan Held, Sanghyun Son, Renaud Vandeghen, Daniel Rebain, Matheus Gadelha, Yi Zhou, Anthony Cioppa, Ming C. Lin, Marc Van Droogenbroeck, Andrea Tagliasacchi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Primitive-based splatting methods like 3D Gaussian Splatting have revolutionized novel view synthesis with real-time rendering. However, their point-based representations remain incompatible with mesh-based pipelines that power AR/VR and game engines. We present MeshSplatting, a mesh-based reconstruction approach that jointly optimizes geometry and appearance through differentiable rendering. By enforcing connectivity via restricted Delaunay triangulation and refining surface consistency, MeshSplatting creates end-to-end smooth, visually high-quality meshes that render efficiently in real-time 3D engines. On Mip-NeRF360, it boosts PSNR by +0.69 dB over the current state-of-the-art MiLo for mesh-based novel view synthesis, while training 2x faster and using 2x less memory, bridging neural rendering and interactive 3D graphics for seamless real-time scene interaction. The project page is available at https://meshsplatting.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06818</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 12:31:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aesthetic Alignment Risks Assimilation: How Image Generation and Reward Models Reinforce Beauty Bias and Ideological "Censorship"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11883</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11883.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenqi Marshall Guo, Qingyun Qian, Khalad Hasan, Shan Du&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Over-aligning image generation models to a generalized aesthetic preference conflicts with user intent, particularly when ``anti-aesthetic" outputs are requested for artistic or critical purposes. This adherence prioritizes developer-centered values, compromising user autonomy and aesthetic pluralism. We test this bias by constructing a wide-spectrum aesthetics dataset and evaluating state-of-the-art generation and reward models. We find that aesthetic-aligned generation models frequently default to conventionally beautiful outputs, failing to respect instructions for low-quality or negative imagery. Crucially, reward models penalize anti-aesthetic images even when they perfectly match the explicit user prompt. We confirm this systemic bias through image-to-image editing and evaluation against real abstract artworks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11883</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:24:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EgoX: Egocentric Video Generation from a Single Exocentric Video</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08269</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.08269.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taewoong Kang, Kinam Kim, Dohyeon Kim, Minho Park, Junha Hyung, Jaegul Choo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 101&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Egocentric perception enables humans to experience and understand the world directly from their own point of view. Translating exocentric (third-person) videos into egocentric (first-person) videos opens up new possibilities for immersive understanding but remains highly challenging due to extreme camera pose variations and minimal view overlap. This task requires faithfully preserving visible content while synthesizing unseen regions in a geometrically consistent manner. To achieve this, we present EgoX, a novel framework for generating egocentric videos from a single exocentric input. EgoX leverages the pretrained spatio temporal knowledge of large-scale video diffusion models through lightweight LoRA adaptation and introduces a unified conditioning strategy that combines exocentric and egocentric priors via width and channel wise concatenation. Additionally, a geometry-guided self-attention mechanism selectively attends to spatially relevant regions, ensuring geometric coherence and high visual fidelity. Our approach achieves coherent and realistic egocentric video generation while demonstrating strong scalability and robustness across unseen and in-the-wild videos.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.08269</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 05:53:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VLSA: Vision-Language-Action Models with Plug-and-Play Safety Constraint Layer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11891</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11891.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Songqiao Hu, Zeyi Liu, Shuang Liu, Jun Cen, Zihan Meng, Xiao He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in generalizing across diverse robotic manipulation tasks. However, deploying these models in unstructured environments remains challenging due to the critical need for simultaneous task compliance and safety assurance, particularly in preventing potential collisions during physical interactions. In this work, we introduce a Vision-Language-Safe Action (VLSA) architecture, named AEGIS, which contains a plug-and-play safety constraint (SC) layer formulated via control barrier functions. AEGIS integrates directly with existing VLA models to improve safety with theoretical guarantees, while maintaining their original instruction-following performance. To evaluate the efficacy of our architecture, we construct a comprehensive safety-critical benchmark SafeLIBERO, spanning distinct manipulation scenarios characterized by varying degrees of spatial complexity and obstacle intervention. Extensive experiments demonstrate the superiority of our method over state-of-the-art baselines. Notably, AEGIS achieves a 59.16% improvement in obstacle avoidance rate while substantially increasing the task execution success rate by 17.25%. To facilitate reproducibility and future research, we make our code, models, and the benchmark datasets publicly available at https://vlsa-aegis.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11891</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 16:53:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VABench: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Audio-Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09299</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09299.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Daili Hua, Xizhi Wang, Bohan Zeng, Xinyi Huang, Hao Liang, Junbo Niu, Xinlong Chen, Quanqing Xu, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in video generation have been remarkable, enabling models to produce visually compelling videos with synchronized audio. While existing video generation benchmarks provide comprehensive metrics for visual quality, they lack convincing evaluations for audio-video generation, especially for models aiming to generate synchronized audio-video outputs. To address this gap, we introduce VABench, a comprehensive and multi-dimensional benchmark framework designed to systematically evaluate the capabilities of synchronous audio-video generation. VABench encompasses three primary task types: text-to-audio-video (T2AV), image-to-audio-video (I2AV), and stereo audio-video generation. It further establishes two major evaluation modules covering 15 dimensions. These dimensions specifically assess pairwise similarities (text-video, text-audio, video-audio), audio-video synchronization, lip-speech consistency, and carefully curated audio and video question-answering (QA) pairs, among others. Furthermore, VABench covers seven major content categories: animals, human sounds, music, environmental sounds, synchronous physical sounds, complex scenes, and virtual worlds. We provide a systematic analysis and visualization of the evaluation results, aiming to establish a new standard for assessing video generation models with synchronous audio capabilities and to promote the comprehensive advancement of the field.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09299</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 03:57:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLaDA2.0: Scaling Up Diffusion Language Models to 100B</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15745</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15745.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tiwei Bie, Maosong Cao, Kun Chen, Lun Du, Mingliang Gong, Zhuochen Gong, Yanmei Gu, Jiaqi Hu, Zenan Huang, Zhenzhong Lan, Chengxi Li, Chongxuan Li, Jianguo Li, Zehuan Li, Huabin Liu, Ling Liu, Guoshan Lu, Xiaocheng Lu, Yuxin Ma, Jianfeng Tan, Lanning Wei, Ji-Rong Wen, Yipeng Xing, Xiaolu Zhang, Junbo Zhao, Da Zheng, Jun Zhou, Junlin Zhou, Zhanchao Zhou, Liwang Zhu, Yihong Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 58&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents LLaDA2.0 -- a tuple of discrete diffusion large language models (dLLM) scaling up to 100B total parameters through systematic conversion from auto-regressive (AR) models -- establishing a new paradigm for frontier-scale deployment. Instead of costly training from scratch, LLaDA2.0 upholds knowledge inheritance, progressive adaption and efficiency-aware design principle, and seamless converts a pre-trained AR model into dLLM with a novel 3-phase block-level WSD based training scheme: progressive increasing block-size in block diffusion (warm-up), large-scale full-sequence diffusion (stable) and reverting back to compact-size block diffusion (decay). Along with post-training alignment with SFT and DPO, we obtain LLaDA2.0-mini (16B) and LLaDA2.0-flash (100B), two instruction-tuned Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) variants optimized for practical deployment. By preserving the advantages of parallel decoding, these models deliver superior performance and efficiency at the frontier scale. Both models were open-sourced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15745</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 09:26:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MentraSuite: Post-Training Large Language Models for Mental Health Reasoning and Assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09636</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.09636.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengxi Xiao, Kailai Yang, Pengde Zhao, Enze Zhang, Ziyan Kuang, Zhiwei Liu, Weiguang Han, Shu Liao, Lianting Huang, Jinpeng Hu, Min Peng, Qianqian Xie, Sophia Ananiadou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Mental health disorders affect hundreds of millions globally, and the Web now serves as a primary medium for accessing support, information, and assessment. Large language models (LLMs) offer scalable and accessible assistance, yet their deployment in mental-health settings remains risky when their reasoning is incomplete, inconsistent, or ungrounded. Existing psychological LLMs emphasize emotional understanding or knowledge recall but overlook the step-wise, clinically aligned reasoning required for appraisal, diagnosis, intervention planning, abstraction, and verification. To address these issues, we introduce MentraSuite, a unified framework for advancing reliable mental-health reasoning. We propose MentraBench, a comprehensive benchmark spanning five core reasoning aspects, six tasks, and 13 datasets, evaluating both task performance and reasoning quality across five dimensions: conciseness, coherence, hallucination avoidance, task understanding, and internal consistency. We further present Mindora, a post-trained model optimized through a hybrid SFT-RL framework with an inconsistency-detection reward to enforce faithful and coherent reasoning. To support training, we construct high-quality trajectories using a novel reasoning trajectory generation strategy, that strategically filters difficult samples and applies a structured, consistency-oriented rewriting process to produce concise, readable, and well-balanced trajectories. Across 20 evaluated LLMs, Mindora achieves the highest average performance on MentraBench and shows remarkable performances in reasoning reliability, demonstrating its effectiveness for complex mental-health scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09636</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 13:26:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Openpi Comet: Competition Solution For 2025 BEHAVIOR Challenge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10071</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10071.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junjie Bai, Yu-Wei Chao, Qizhi Chen, Jinwei Gu, Moo Jin Kim, Zhaoshuo Li, Xuan Li, Tsung-Yi Lin, Ming-Yu Liu, Nic Ma, Kaichun Mo, Delin Qu, Shangkun Sun, Hongchi Xia, Fangyin Wei, Xiaohui Zeng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The 2025 BEHAVIOR Challenge is designed to rigorously track progress toward solving long-horizon tasks by physical agents in simulated environments. BEHAVIOR-1K focuses on everyday household tasks that people most want robots to assist with and these tasks introduce long-horizon mobile manipulation challenges in realistic settings, bridging the gap between current research and real-world, human-centric applications. This report presents our solution to the 2025 BEHAVIOR Challenge in a very close 2nd place and substantially outperforms the rest of the submissions. Building on π_{0.5}, we focus on systematically building our solution by studying the effects of training techniques and data. Through careful ablations, we show the scaling power in pre-training and post-training phases for competitive performance. We summarize our practical lessons and design recommendations that we hope will provide actionable insights for the broader embodied AI community when adapting powerful foundation models to complex embodied scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10071</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 20:46:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliding Window Attention Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10411</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10411.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yijiong Yu, Jiale Liu, Qingyun Wu, Huazheng Wang, Ji Pei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The self-attention mechanism in Transformer-based Large Language Models (LLMs) scales quadratically with input length, making long-context inference expensive. Sliding window attention (SWA) reduces this cost to linear complexity, but naively enabling complete SWA at inference-time for models pretrained with full attention (FA) causes severe long-context performance degradation due to training-inference mismatch. This makes us wonder: Can FA-pretrained LLMs be well adapted to SWA without pretraining? We investigate this by proposing Sliding Window Attention Adaptation (SWAA), a set of practical recipes that combine five methods for better adaptation: (1) applying SWA only during prefilling; (2) preserving "sink" tokens; (3) interleaving FA/SWA layers; (4) chain-of-thought (CoT); and (5) fine-tuning. Our experiments show that SWA adaptation is feasible while non-trivial: no single method suffices, yet specific synergistic combinations effectively recover the original long-context performance. We further analyze the performance-efficiency trade-offs of different SWAA configurations and provide recommended recipes for diverse scenarios. Our code is available at https://github.com/yuyijiong/sliding-window-attention-adaptation&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10411</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 08:21:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAPTAIN: Semantic Feature Injection for Memorization Mitigation in Text-to-Image Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10655</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10655.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tong Zhang, Carlos Hinojosa, Bernard Ghanem&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion models can unintentionally reproduce training examples, raising privacy and copyright concerns as these systems are increasingly deployed at scale. Existing inference-time mitigation methods typically manipulate classifier-free guidance (CFG) or perturb prompt embeddings; however, they often struggle to reduce memorization without compromising alignment with the conditioning prompt. We introduce CAPTAIN, a training-free framework that mitigates memorization by directly modifying latent features during denoising. CAPTAIN first applies frequency-based noise initialization to reduce the tendency to replicate memorized patterns early in the denoising process. It then identifies the optimal denoising timesteps for feature injection and localizes memorized regions. Finally, CAPTAIN injects semantically aligned features from non-memorized reference images into localized latent regions, suppressing memorization while preserving prompt fidelity and visual quality. Our experiments show that CAPTAIN achieves substantial reductions in memorization compared to CFG-based baselines while maintaining strong alignment with the intended prompt.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10655</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 14:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp Monocular View Synthesis in Less Than a Second</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10685</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10685.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lars Mescheder, Wei Dong, Shiwei Li, Xuyang Bai, Marcel Santos, Peiyun Hu, Bruno Lecouat, Mingmin Zhen, Amaël Delaunoy, Tian Fang, Yanghai Tsin, Stephan R. Richter, Vladlen Koltun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present SHARP, an approach to photorealistic view synthesis from a single image. Given a single photograph, SHARP regresses the parameters of a 3D Gaussian representation of the depicted scene. This is done in less than a second on a standard GPU via a single feedforward pass through a neural network. The 3D Gaussian representation produced by SHARP can then be rendered in real time, yielding high-resolution photorealistic images for nearby views. The representation is metric, with absolute scale, supporting metric camera movements. Experimental results demonstrate that SHARP delivers robust zero-shot generalization across datasets. It sets a new state of the art on multiple datasets, reducing LPIPS by 25-34% and DISTS by 21-43% versus the best prior model, while lowering the synthesis time by three orders of magnitude. Code and weights are provided at https://github.com/apple/ml-sharp&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10685</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 14:34:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What matters for Representation Alignment: Global Information or Spatial Structure?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10794</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10794.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jaskirat Singh, Xingjian Leng, Zongze Wu, Liang Zheng, Richard Zhang, Eli Shechtman, Saining Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Representation alignment (REPA) guides generative training by distilling representations from a strong, pretrained vision encoder to intermediate diffusion features. We investigate a fundamental question: what aspect of the target representation matters for generation, its global semantic information (e.g., measured by ImageNet-1K accuracy) or its spatial structure (i.e. pairwise cosine similarity between patch tokens)? Prevalent wisdom holds that stronger global semantic performance leads to better generation as a target representation. To study this, we first perform a large-scale empirical analysis across 27 different vision encoders and different model scales. The results are surprising; spatial structure, rather than global performance, drives the generation performance of a target representation. To further study this, we introduce two straightforward modifications, which specifically accentuate the transfer of spatial information. We replace the standard MLP projection layer in REPA with a simple convolution layer and introduce a spatial normalization layer for the external representation. Surprisingly, our simple method (implemented in &lt;4 lines of code), termed iREPA, consistently improves convergence speed of REPA, across a diverse set of vision encoders, model sizes, and training variants (such as REPA, REPA-E, Meanflow, JiT etc). %, etc. Our work motivates revisiting the fundamental working mechanism of representational alignment and how it can be leveraged for improved training of generative models. The code and project page are available at https://end2end-diffusion.github.io/irepa&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10794</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 16:39:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMSI-Video-Bench: A Holistic Benchmark for Video-Based Spatial Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10863</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.10863.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingli Lin, Runsen Xu, Shaohao Zhu, Sihan Yang, Peizhou Cao, Yunlong Ran, Miao Hu, Chenming Zhu, Yiman Xie, Yilin Long, Wenbo Hu, Dahua Lin, Tai Wang, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatial understanding over continuous visual input is crucial for MLLMs to evolve into general-purpose assistants in physical environments. Yet there is still no comprehensive benchmark that holistically assesses the progress toward this goal. In this work, we introduce MMSI-Video-Bench, a fully human-annotated benchmark for video-based spatial intelligence in MLLMs. It operationalizes a four-level framework, Perception, Planning, Prediction, and Cross-Video Reasoning, through 1,106 questions grounded in 1,278 clips from 25 datasets and in-house videos. Each item is carefully designed and reviewed by 3DV experts with explanatory rationales to ensure precise, unambiguous grounding. Leveraging its diverse data sources and holistic task coverage, MMSI-Video-Bench also supports three domain-oriented sub-benchmarks (Indoor Scene Perception Bench, Robot Bench and Grounding Bench) for targeted capability assessment. We evaluate 25 strong open-source and proprietary MLLMs, revealing a striking human--AI gap: many models perform near chance, and the best reasoning model lags humans by nearly 60%. We further find that spatially fine-tuned models still fail to generalize effectively on our benchmark. Fine-grained error analysis exposes systematic failures in geometric reasoning, motion grounding, long-horizon prediction, and cross-video correspondence. We also show that typical frame-sampling strategies transfer poorly to our reasoning-intensive benchmark, and that neither 3D spatial cues nor chain-of-thought prompting yields meaningful gains. We expect our benchmark to establish a solid testbed for advancing video-based spatial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10863</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 17:57:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insight Miner: A Time Series Analysis Dataset for Cross-Domain Alignment with Natural Language</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11251</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11251.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunkai Zhang, Yawen Zhang, Ming Zheng, Kezhen Chen, Chongyang Gao, Ruian Ge, Siyuan Teng, Amine Jelloul, Jinmeng Rao, Xiaoyuan Guo, Chiang-Wei Fang, Zeyu Zheng, Jie Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Time-series data is critical across many scientific and industrial domains, including environmental analysis, agriculture, transportation, and finance. However, mining insights from this data typically requires deep domain expertise, a process that is both time-consuming and labor-intensive. In this paper, we propose Insight Miner, a large-scale multimodal model (LMM) designed to generate high-quality, comprehensive time-series descriptions enriched with domain-specific knowledge. To facilitate this, we introduce TS-InsightsAvailable at \href{https://huggingface.co/datasets/zhykoties/time-series-language-alignment{https://huggingface.co/datasets/zhykoties/time-series-language-alignment}.}, the first general-domain dataset for time series and language alignment. TS-Insights contains 100k time-series windows sampled from 20 forecasting datasets. We construct this dataset using a novel agentic workflow, where we use statistical tools to extract features from raw time series before synthesizing them into coherent trend descriptions with GPT-4. Following instruction tuning on TS-Insights, Insight Miner outperforms state-of-the-art multimodal models, such as LLaVA liu2023llava and GPT-4, in generating time-series descriptions and insights. Our findings suggest a promising direction for leveraging LMMs in time series analysis, and serve as a foundational step toward enabling LLMs to interpret time series as a native input modality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11251</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 03:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PersonaLive! Expressive Portrait Image Animation for Live Streaming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11253</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11253.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiyuan Li, Chi-Man Pun, Chen Fang, Jue Wang, Xiaodong Cun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current diffusion-based portrait animation models predominantly focus on enhancing visual quality and expression realism, while overlooking generation latency and real-time performance, which restricts their application range in the live streaming scenario. We propose PersonaLive, a novel diffusion-based framework towards streaming real-time portrait animation with multi-stage training recipes. Specifically, we first adopt hybrid implicit signals, namely implicit facial representations and 3D implicit keypoints, to achieve expressive image-level motion control. Then, a fewer-step appearance distillation strategy is proposed to eliminate appearance redundancy in the denoising process, greatly improving inference efficiency. Finally, we introduce an autoregressive micro-chunk streaming generation paradigm equipped with a sliding training strategy and a historical keyframe mechanism to enable low-latency and stable long-term video generation. Extensive experiments demonstrate that PersonaLive achieves state-of-the-art performance with up to 7-22x speedup over prior diffusion-based portrait animation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11253</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 03:24:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring MLLM-Diffusion Information Transfer with MetaCanvas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11464</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11464.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Han Lin, Xichen Pan, Ziqi Huang, Ji Hou, Jialiang Wang, Weifeng Chen, Zecheng He, Felix Juefei-Xu, Junzhe Sun, Zhipeng Fan, Ali Thabet, Mohit Bansal, Chu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal learning has rapidly advanced visual understanding, largely via multimodal large language models (MLLMs) that use powerful LLMs as cognitive cores. In visual generation, however, these powerful core models are typically reduced to global text encoders for diffusion models, leaving most of their reasoning and planning ability unused. This creates a gap: current multimodal LLMs can parse complex layouts, attributes, and knowledge-intensive scenes, yet struggle to generate images or videos with equally precise and structured control. We propose MetaCanvas, a lightweight framework that lets MLLMs reason and plan directly in spatial and spatiotemporal latent spaces and interface tightly with diffusion generators. We empirically implement MetaCanvas on three different diffusion backbones and evaluate it across six tasks, including text-to-image generation, text/image-to-video generation, image/video editing, and in-context video generation, each requiring precise layouts, robust attribute binding, and reasoning-intensive control. MetaCanvas consistently outperforms global-conditioning baselines, suggesting that treating MLLMs as latent-space planners is a promising direction for narrowing the gap between multimodal understanding and generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11464</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 11:07:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Expert Trajectory Utilization in LLM Post-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11470</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11470.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bowen Ding, Yuhan Chen, Jiayang Lv, Jiyao Yuan, Qi Zhu, Shuangshuang Tian, Dantong Zhu, Futing Wang, Heyuan Deng, Fei Mi, Lifeng Shang, Tao Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While effective post-training integrates Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) and Reinforcement Learning (RL), the optimal mechanism for utilizing expert trajectories remains unresolved. We propose the Plasticity-Ceiling Framework to theoretically ground this landscape, decomposing performance into foundational SFT performance and the subsequent RL plasticity. Through extensive benchmarking, we establish the Sequential SFT-then-RL pipeline as the superior standard, overcoming the stability deficits of synchronized approaches. Furthermore, we derive precise scaling guidelines: (1) Transitioning to RL at the SFT Stable or Mild Overfitting Sub-phase maximizes the final ceiling by securing foundational SFT performance without compromising RL plasticity; (2) Refuting ``Less is More'' in the context of SFT-then-RL scaling, we demonstrate that Data Scale determines the primary post-training potential, while Trajectory Difficulty acts as a performance multiplier; and (3) Identifying that the Minimum SFT Validation Loss serves as a robust indicator for selecting the expert trajectories that maximize the final performance ceiling. Our findings provide actionable guidelines for maximizing the value extracted from expert trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11470</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 11:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DentalGPT: Incentivizing Multimodal Complex Reasoning in Dentistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11558</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11558.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenyang Cai, Jiaming Zhang, Junjie Zhao, Ziyi Zeng, Yanchao Li, Jingyi Liang, Junying Chen, Yunjin Yang, Jiajun You, Shuzhi Deng, Tongfei Wang, Wanting Chen, Chunxiu Hao, Ruiqi Xie, Zhenwei Wen, Xiangyi Feng, Zou Ting, Jin Zou Lin, Jianquan Li, Guangjun Yu, Liangyi Chen, Junwen Wang, Shan Jiang, Benyou Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reliable interpretation of multimodal data in dentistry is essential for automated oral healthcare, yet current multimodal large language models (MLLMs) struggle to capture fine-grained dental visual details and lack sufficient reasoning ability for precise diagnosis. To address these limitations, we present DentalGPT, a specialized dental MLLM developed through high-quality domain knowledge injection and reinforcement learning. Specifically, the largest annotated multimodal dataset for dentistry to date was constructed by aggregating over 120k dental images paired with detailed descriptions that highlight diagnostically relevant visual features, making it the multimodal dataset with the most extensive collection of dental images to date. Training on this dataset significantly enhances the MLLM's visual understanding of dental conditions, while the subsequent reinforcement learning stage further strengthens its capability for multimodal complex reasoning. Comprehensive evaluations on intraoral and panoramic benchmarks, along with dental subsets of medical VQA benchmarks, show that DentalGPT achieves superior performance in disease classification and dental VQA tasks, outperforming many state-of-the-art MLLMs despite having only 7B parameters. These results demonstrate that high-quality dental data combined with staged adaptation provides an effective pathway for building capable and domain-specialized dental MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11558</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 13:42:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SVG-T2I: Scaling Up Text-to-Image Latent Diffusion Model Without Variational Autoencoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11749</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11749.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minglei Shi, Haolin Wang, Borui Zhang, Wenzhao Zheng, Bohan Zeng, Ziyang Yuan, Xiaoshi Wu, Yuanxing Zhang, Huan Yang, Xintao Wang, Pengfei Wan, Kun Gai, Jie Zhou, Jiwen Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual generation grounded in Visual Foundation Model (VFM) representations offers a highly promising unified pathway for integrating visual understanding, perception, and generation. Despite this potential, training large-scale text-to-image diffusion models entirely within the VFM representation space remains largely unexplored. To bridge this gap, we scale the SVG (Self-supervised representations for Visual Generation) framework, proposing SVG-T2I to support high-quality text-to-image synthesis directly in the VFM feature domain. By leveraging a standard text-to-image diffusion pipeline, SVG-T2I achieves competitive performance, reaching 0.75 on GenEval and 85.78 on DPG-Bench. This performance validates the intrinsic representational power of VFMs for generative tasks. We fully open-source the project, including the autoencoder and generation model, together with their training, inference, evaluation pipelines, and pre-trained weights, to facilitate further research in representation-driven visual generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11749</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 17:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure From Tracking: Distilling Structure-Preserving Motion for Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11792</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11792.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Fei, George Stoica, Jingyuan Liu, Qifeng Chen, Ranjay Krishna, Xiaojuan Wang, Benlin Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reality is a dance between rigid constraints and deformable structures. For video models, that means generating motion that preserves fidelity as well as structure. Despite progress in diffusion models, producing realistic structure-preserving motion remains challenging, especially for articulated and deformable objects such as humans and animals. Scaling training data alone, so far, has failed to resolve physically implausible transitions. Existing approaches rely on conditioning with noisy motion representations, such as optical flow or skeletons extracted using an external imperfect model. To address these challenges, we introduce an algorithm to distill structure-preserving motion priors from an autoregressive video tracking model (SAM2) into a bidirectional video diffusion model (CogVideoX). With our method, we train SAM2VideoX, which contains two innovations: (1) a bidirectional feature fusion module that extracts global structure-preserving motion priors from a recurrent model like SAM2; (2) a Local Gram Flow loss that aligns how local features move together. Experiments on VBench and in human studies show that SAM2VideoX delivers consistent gains (+2.60\% on VBench, 21-22\% lower FVD, and 71.4\% human preference) over prior baselines. Specifically, on VBench, we achieve 95.51\%, surpassing REPA (92.91\%) by 2.60\%, and reduce FVD to 360.57, a 21.20\% and 22.46\% improvement over REPA- and LoRA-finetuning, respectively. The project website can be found at https://sam2videox.github.io/ .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11792</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 18:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V-RGBX: Video Editing with Accurate Controls over Intrinsic Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11799</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11799.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ye Fang, Tong Wu, Valentin Deschaintre, Duygu Ceylan, Iliyan Georgiev, Chun-Hao Paul Huang, Yiwei Hu, Xuelin Chen, Tuanfeng Yang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large-scale video generation models have shown remarkable potential in modeling photorealistic appearance and lighting interactions in real-world scenes. However, a closed-loop framework that jointly understands intrinsic scene properties (e.g., albedo, normal, material, and irradiance), leverages them for video synthesis, and supports editable intrinsic representations remains unexplored. We present V-RGBX, the first end-to-end framework for intrinsic-aware video editing. V-RGBX unifies three key capabilities: (1) video inverse rendering into intrinsic channels, (2) photorealistic video synthesis from these intrinsic representations, and (3) keyframe-based video editing conditioned on intrinsic channels. At the core of V-RGBX is an interleaved conditioning mechanism that enables intuitive, physically grounded video editing through user-selected keyframes, supporting flexible manipulation of any intrinsic modality. Extensive qualitative and quantitative results show that V-RGBX produces temporally consistent, photorealistic videos while propagating keyframe edits across sequences in a physically plausible manner. We demonstrate its effectiveness in diverse applications, including object appearance editing and scene-level relighting, surpassing the performance of prior methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11799</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 18:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V-REX: Benchmarking Exploratory Visual Reasoning via Chain-of-Questions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11995</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.11995.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenrui Fan, Yijun Liang, Shweta Bhardwaj, Kwesi Cobbina, Ming Li, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While many vision-language models (VLMs) are developed to answer well-defined, straightforward questions with highly specified targets, as in most benchmarks, they often struggle in practice with complex open-ended tasks, which usually require multiple rounds of exploration and reasoning in the visual space. Such visual thinking paths not only provide step-by-step exploration and verification as an AI detective but also produce better interpretations of the final answers. However, these paths are challenging to evaluate due to the large exploration space of intermediate steps. To bridge the gap, we develop an evaluation suite, ``Visual Reasoning with multi-step EXploration (V-REX)'', which is composed of a benchmark of challenging visual reasoning tasks requiring native multi-step exploration and an evaluation protocol. V-REX covers rich application scenarios across diverse domains. V-REX casts the multi-step exploratory reasoning into a Chain-of-Questions (CoQ) and disentangles VLMs' capability to (1) Planning: breaking down an open-ended task by selecting a chain of exploratory questions; and (2) Following: answering curated CoQ sequentially to collect information for deriving the final answer. By curating finite options of questions and answers per step, V-REX achieves a reliable quantitative and fine-grained analysis of the intermediate steps. By assessing SOTA proprietary and open-sourced VLMs, we reveal consistent scaling trends, significant differences between planning and following abilities, and substantial room for improvement in multi-step exploratory reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11995</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 19:18:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VOYAGER: A Training Free Approach for Generating Diverse Datasets using LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12072</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12072.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Avinash Amballa, Yashas Malur Saidutta, Chi-Heng Lin, Vivek Kulkarni, Srinivas Chappidi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly being used to generate synthetic datasets for the evaluation and training of downstream models. However, prior work has noted that such generated data lacks diversity. In this paper, we propose Voyager, a novel principled approach to generate diverse datasets. Our approach is iterative and directly optimizes a mathematical quantity that optimizes the diversity of the dataset using the machinery of determinantal point processes. Furthermore, our approach is training-free, applicable to closed-source models, and scalable. In addition to providing theoretical justification for the working of our method, we also demonstrate through comprehensive experiments that Voyager significantly outperforms popular baseline approaches by providing a 1.5-3x improvement in diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12072</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 22:39:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-Free Linear Attention is a Free Lunch: Exact Solution from Continuous-Time Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12602</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12602.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingdi Lei, Di Zhang, Soujanya Poria&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Linear-time attention and State Space Models (SSMs) promise to solve the quadratic cost bottleneck in long-context language models employing softmax attention. We introduce Error-Free Linear Attention (EFLA), a numerically stable, fully parallelism and generalized formulation of the delta rule. Specifically, we formulate the online learning update as a continuous-time dynamical system and prove that its exact solution is not only attainable but also computable in linear time with full parallelism. By leveraging the rank-1 structure of the dynamics matrix, we directly derive the exact closed-form solution effectively corresponding to the infinite-order Runge-Kutta method. This attention mechanism is theoretically free from error accumulation, perfectly capturing the continuous dynamics while preserving the linear-time complexity. Through an extensive suite of experiments, we show that EFLA enables robust performance in noisy environments, achieving lower language modeling perplexity and superior downstream benchmark performance than DeltaNet without introducing additional parameters. Our work provides a new theoretical foundation for building high-fidelity, scalable linear-time attention models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12602</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 08:51:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scone: Bridging Composition and Distinction in Subject-Driven Image Generation via Unified Understanding-Generation Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12675</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12675.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuran Wang, Bohan Zeng, Chengzhuo Tong, Wenxuan Liu, Yang Shi, Xiaochen Ma, Hao Liang, Yuanxing Zhang, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Subject-driven image generation has advanced from single- to multi-subject composition, while neglecting distinction, the ability to identify and generate the correct subject when inputs contain multiple candidates. This limitation restricts effectiveness in complex, realistic visual settings. We propose Scone, a unified understanding-generation method that integrates composition and distinction. Scone enables the understanding expert to act as a semantic bridge, conveying semantic information and guiding the generation expert to preserve subject identity while minimizing interference. A two-stage training scheme first learns composition, then enhances distinction through semantic alignment and attention-based masking. We also introduce SconeEval, a benchmark for evaluating both composition and distinction across diverse scenarios. Experiments demonstrate that Scone outperforms existing open-source models in composition and distinction tasks on two benchmarks. Our model, benchmark, and training data are available at: https://github.com/Ryann-Ran/Scone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12675</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 12:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebOperator: Action-Aware Tree Search for Autonomous Agents in Web Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12692</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12692.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mahir Labib Dihan, Tanzima Hashem, Mohammed Eunus Ali, Md Rizwan Parvez&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM-based agents often operate in a greedy, step-by-step manner, selecting actions solely based on the current observation without considering long-term consequences or alternative paths. This lack of foresight is particularly problematic in web environments, which are only partially observable-limited to browser-visible content (e.g., DOM and UI elements)-where a single misstep often requires complex and brittle navigation to undo. Without an explicit backtracking mechanism, agents struggle to correct errors or systematically explore alternative paths. Tree-search methods provide a principled framework for such structured exploration, but existing approaches lack mechanisms for safe backtracking, making them prone to unintended side effects. They also assume that all actions are reversible, ignoring the presence of irreversible actions-limitations that reduce their effectiveness in realistic web tasks. To address these challenges, we introduce WebOperator, a tree-search framework that enables reliable backtracking and strategic exploration. Our method incorporates a best-first search strategy that ranks actions by both reward estimates and safety considerations, along with a robust backtracking mechanism that verifies the feasibility of previously visited paths before replaying them, preventing unintended side effects. To further guide exploration, WebOperator generates action candidates from multiple, varied reasoning contexts to ensure diverse and robust exploration, and subsequently curates a high-quality action set by filtering out invalid actions pre-execution and merging semantically equivalent ones. Experimental results on WebArena and WebVoyager demonstrate the effectiveness of WebOperator. On WebArena, WebOperator achieves a state-of-the-art 54.6% success rate with gpt-4o, underscoring the critical advantage of integrating strategic foresight with safe execution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12692</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 13:56:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NL2Repo-Bench: Towards Long-Horizon Repository Generation Evaluation of Coding Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12730</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12730.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingzhe Ding, Shengda Long, Changxin Pu, Huan Zhou, Hongwan Gao, Xiang Gao, Chao He, Yue Hou, Fei Hu, Zhaojian Li, Weiran Shi, Zaiyuan Wang, Daoguang Zan, Chenchen Zhang, Xiaoxu Zhang, Qizhi Chen, Xianfu Cheng, Bo Deng, Qingshui Gu, Kai Hua, Juntao Lin, Pai Liu, Mingchen Li, Xuanguang Pan, Zifan Peng, Yujia Qin, Yong Shan, Zhewen Tan, Weihao Xie, Zihan Wang, Yishuo Yuan, Jiayu Zhang, Enduo Zhao, Yunfei Zhao, He Zhu, Chenyang Zou, Ming Ding, Jianpeng Jiao, Jiaheng Liu, Minghao Liu, Qian Liu, Chongyao Tao, Jian Yang, Tong Yang, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Xinjie Chen, Wenhao Huang, Ge Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in coding agents suggest rapid progress toward autonomous software development, yet existing benchmarks fail to rigorously evaluate the long-horizon capabilities required to build complete software systems. Most prior evaluations focus on localized code generation, scaffolded completion, or short-term repair tasks, leaving open the question of whether agents can sustain coherent reasoning, planning, and execution over the extended horizons demanded by real-world repository construction. To address this gap, we present NL2Repo Bench, a benchmark explicitly designed to evaluate the long-horizon repository generation ability of coding agents. Given only a single natural-language requirements document and an empty workspace, agents must autonomously design the architecture, manage dependencies, implement multi-module logic, and produce a fully installable Python library. Our experiments across state-of-the-art open- and closed-source models reveal that long-horizon repository generation remains largely unsolved: even the strongest agents achieve below 40% average test pass rates and rarely complete an entire repository correctly. Detailed analysis uncovers fundamental long-horizon failure modes, including premature termination, loss of global coherence, fragile cross-file dependencies, and inadequate planning over hundreds of interaction steps. NL2Repo Bench establishes a rigorous, verifiable testbed for measuring sustained agentic competence and highlights long-horizon reasoning as a central bottleneck for the next generation of autonomous coding agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12730</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 15:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DrivePI: Spatial-aware 4D MLLM for Unified Autonomous Driving Understanding, Perception, Prediction and Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12799</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12799.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhe Liu, Runhui Huang, Rui Yang, Siming Yan, Zining Wang, Lu Hou, Di Lin, Xiang Bai, Hengshuang Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although multi-modal large language models (MLLMs) have shown strong capabilities across diverse domains, their application in generating fine-grained 3D perception and prediction outputs in autonomous driving remains underexplored. In this paper, we propose DrivePI, a novel spatial-aware 4D MLLM that serves as a unified Vision-Language-Action (VLA) framework that is also compatible with vision-action (VA) models. Our method jointly performs spatial understanding, 3D perception (i.e., 3D occupancy), prediction (i.e., occupancy flow), and planning (i.e., action outputs) in parallel through end-to-end optimization. To obtain both precise geometric information and rich visual appearance, our approach integrates point clouds, multi-view images, and language instructions within a unified MLLM architecture. We further develop a data engine to generate text-occupancy and text-flow QA pairs for 4D spatial understanding. Remarkably, with only a 0.5B Qwen2.5 model as MLLM backbone, DrivePI as a single unified model matches or exceeds both existing VLA models and specialized VA models. Specifically, compared to VLA models, DrivePI outperforms OpenDriveVLA-7B by 2.5% mean accuracy on nuScenes-QA and reduces collision rate by 70% over ORION (from 0.37% to 0.11%) on nuScenes. Against specialized VA models, DrivePI surpasses FB-OCC by 10.3 RayIoU for 3D occupancy on OpenOcc, reduces the mAVE from 0.591 to 0.509 for occupancy flow on OpenOcc, and achieves 32% lower L2 error than VAD (from 0.72m to 0.49m) for planning on nuScenes. Code will be available at https://github.com/happinesslz/DrivePI&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12799</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 18:45:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QwenLong-L1.5: Post-Training Recipe for Long-Context Reasoning and Memory Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12967</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12967.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weizhou Shen, Ziyi Yang, Chenliang Li, Zhiyuan Lu, Miao Peng, Huashan Sun, Yingcheng Shi, Shengyi Liao, Shaopeng Lai, Bo Zhang, Dayiheng Liu, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou, Ming Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 97&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce QwenLong-L1.5, a model that achieves superior long-context reasoning capabilities through systematic post-training innovations. The key technical breakthroughs of QwenLong-L1.5 are as follows: (1) Long-Context Data Synthesis Pipeline: We develop a systematic synthesis framework that generates challenging reasoning tasks requiring multi-hop grounding over globally distributed evidence. By deconstructing documents into atomic facts and their underlying relationships, and then programmatically composing verifiable reasoning questions, our approach creates high-quality training data at scale, moving substantially beyond simple retrieval tasks to enable genuine long-range reasoning capabilities. (2) Stabilized Reinforcement Learning for Long-Context Training: To overcome the critical instability in long-context RL, we introduce task-balanced sampling with task-specific advantage estimation to mitigate reward bias, and propose Adaptive Entropy-Controlled Policy Optimization (AEPO) that dynamically regulates exploration-exploitation trade-offs. (3) Memory-Augmented Architecture for Ultra-Long Contexts: Recognizing that even extended context windows cannot accommodate arbitrarily long sequences, we develop a memory management framework with multi-stage fusion RL training that seamlessly integrates single-pass reasoning with iterative memory-based processing for tasks exceeding 4M tokens. Based on Qwen3-30B-A3B-Thinking, QwenLong-L1.5 achieves performance comparable to GPT-5 and Gemini-2.5-Pro on long-context reasoning benchmarks, surpassing its baseline by 9.90 points on average. On ultra-long tasks (1M~4M tokens), QwenLong-L1.5's memory-agent framework yields a 9.48-point gain over the agent baseline. Additionally, the acquired long-context reasoning ability translates to enhanced performance in general domains like scientific reasoning, memory tool using, and extended dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12967</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 04:11:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reveal Hidden Pitfalls and Navigate Next Generation of Vector Similarity Search from Task-Centric Views</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12980</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.12980.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tingyang Chen, Cong Fu, Jiahua Wu, Haotian Wu, Hua Fan, Xiangyu Ke, Yunjun Gao, Yabo Ni, Anxiang Zeng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vector Similarity Search (VSS) in high-dimensional spaces is rapidly emerging as core functionality in next-generation database systems for numerous data-intensive services -- from embedding lookups in large language models (LLMs), to semantic information retrieval and recommendation engines. Current benchmarks, however, evaluate VSS primarily on the recall-latency trade-off against a ground truth defined solely by distance metrics, neglecting how retrieval quality ultimately impacts downstream tasks. This disconnect can mislead both academic research and industrial practice.   We present Iceberg, a holistic benchmark suite for end-to-end evaluation of VSS methods in realistic application contexts. From a task-centric view, Iceberg uncovers the Information Loss Funnel, which identifies three principal sources of end-to-end performance degradation: (1) Embedding Loss during feature extraction; (2) Metric Misuse, where distances poorly reflect task relevance; (3) Data Distribution Sensitivity, highlighting index robustness across skews and modalities. For a more comprehensive assessment, Iceberg spans eight diverse datasets across key domains such as image classification, face recognition, text retrieval, and recommendation systems. Each dataset, ranging from 1M to 100M vectors, includes rich, task-specific labels and evaluation metrics, enabling assessment of retrieval algorithms within the full application pipeline rather than in isolation. Iceberg benchmarks 13 state-of-the-art VSS methods and re-ranks them based on application-level metrics, revealing substantial deviations from traditional rankings derived purely from recall-latency evaluations. Building on these insights, we define a set of task-centric meta-features and derive an interpretable decision tree to guide practitioners in selecting and tuning VSS methods for their specific workloads.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12980</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 04:49:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial-Aware VLA Pretraining through Visual-Physical Alignment from Human Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13080</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13080.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yicheng Feng, Wanpeng Zhang, Ye Wang, Hao Luo, Haoqi Yuan, Sipeng Zheng, Zongqing Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models provide a promising paradigm for robot learning by integrating visual perception with language-guided policy learning. However, most existing approaches rely on 2D visual inputs to perform actions in 3D physical environments, creating a significant gap between perception and action grounding. To bridge this gap, we propose a Spatial-Aware VLA Pretraining paradigm that performs explicit alignment between visual space and physical space during pretraining, enabling models to acquire 3D spatial understanding before robot policy learning. Starting from pretrained vision-language models, we leverage large-scale human demonstration videos to extract 3D visual and 3D action annotations, forming a new source of supervision that aligns 2D visual observations with 3D spatial reasoning. We instantiate this paradigm with VIPA-VLA, a dual-encoder architecture that incorporates a 3D visual encoder to augment semantic visual representations with 3D-aware features. When adapted to downstream robot tasks, VIPA-VLA achieves significantly improved grounding between 2D vision and 3D action, resulting in more robust and generalizable robotic policies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13080</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 08:31:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finch: Benchmarking Finance &amp; Accounting across Spreadsheet-Centric Enterprise Workflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13168</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13168.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoyu Dong, Pengkun Zhang, Yan Gao, Xuanyu Dong, Yilin Cheng, Mingzhe Lu, Adina Yakefu, Shuxin Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce a finance &amp; accounting benchmark (Finch) for evaluating AI agents on real-world, enterprise-grade professional workflows -- interleaving data entry, structuring, formatting, web search, cross-file retrieval, calculation, modeling, validation, translation, visualization, and reporting. Finch is sourced from authentic enterprise workspaces at Enron (15,000 spreadsheets and 500,000 emails from 150 employees) and other financial institutions, preserving in-the-wild messiness across multimodal artifacts (text, tables, formulas, charts, code, and images) and spanning diverse domains such as budgeting, trading, and asset management.   We propose a workflow construction process that combines LLM-assisted discovery with expert annotation: (1) LLM-assisted, expert-verified derivation of workflows from real-world email threads and version histories of spreadsheet files, and (2) meticulous expert annotation for workflows, requiring over 700 hours of domain-expert effort. This yields 172 composite workflows with 384 tasks, involving 1,710 spreadsheets with 27 million cells, along with PDFs and other artifacts, capturing the intrinsically messy, long-horizon, knowledge-intensive, and collaborative nature of real-world enterprise work.   We conduct both human and automated evaluations of frontier AI systems including GPT 5.1, Claude Sonnet 4.5, Gemini 3 Pro, Grok 4, and Qwen 3 Max, and GPT 5.1 Pro spends 48 hours in total yet passes only 38.4% of workflows, while Claude Sonnet 4.5 passes just 25.0%. Comprehensive case studies further surface the challenges that real-world enterprise workflows pose for AI agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13168</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 10:28:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Ambulatory Vision: Learning Visually-Grounded Active View Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13250</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13250.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Juil Koo, Daehyeon Choi, Sangwoo Youn, Phillip Y. Lee, Minhyuk Sung&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision Language Models (VLMs) excel at visual question answering (VQA) but remain limited to snapshot vision, reasoning from static images. In contrast, embodied agents require ambulatory vision, actively moving to obtain more informative views. We introduce Visually Grounded Active View Selection (VG-AVS), a task that selects the most informative next viewpoint using only the visual information in the current image, without relying on scene memory or external knowledge. To support this task, we construct a synthetic dataset with automatically generated paired query-target views and question-answer prompts. We also propose a framework that fine-tunes pretrained VLMs through supervised fine-tuning (SFT) followed by RL-based policy optimization. Our approach achieves strong question answering performance based on viewpoint selection and generalizes robustly to unseen synthetic and real scenes. Furthermore, incorporating our learned VG-AVS framework into existing scene-exploration-based EQA systems improves downstream question-answering accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13250</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:04:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video Reality Test: Can AI-Generated ASMR Videos fool VLMs and Humans?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13281</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13281.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Wang, Weijia Wu, Yi Zhan, Rui Zhao, Ming Hu, James Cheng, Wei Liu, Philip Torr, Kevin Qinghong Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in video generation have produced vivid content that are often indistinguishable from real videos, making AI-generated video detection an emerging societal challenge. Prior AIGC detection benchmarks mostly evaluate video without audio, target broad narrative domains, and focus on classification solely. Yet it remains unclear whether state-of-the-art video generation models can produce immersive, audio-paired videos that reliably deceive humans and VLMs. To this end, we introduce Video Reality Test, an ASMR-sourced video benchmark suite for testing perceptual realism under tight audio-visual coupling, featuring the following dimensions: (i) Immersive ASMR video-audio sources. Built on carefully curated real ASMR videos, the benchmark targets fine-grained action-object interactions with diversity across objects, actions, and backgrounds. (ii) Peer-Review evaluation. An adversarial creator-reviewer protocol where video generation models act as creators aiming to fool reviewers, while VLMs serve as reviewers seeking to identify fakeness. Our experimental findings show: The best creator Veo3.1-Fast even fools most VLMs: the strongest reviewer (Gemini 2.5-Pro) achieves only 56\% accuracy (random 50\%), far below that of human experts (81.25\%). Adding audio improves real-fake discrimination, yet superficial cues such as watermarks can still significantly mislead models. These findings delineate the current boundary of video generation realism and expose limitations of VLMs in perceptual fidelity and audio-visual consistency. Our code is available at https://github.com/video-reality-test/video-reality-test.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13281</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:41:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ShowTable: Unlocking Creative Table Visualization with Collaborative Reflection and Refinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13303</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13303.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhihang Liu, Xiaoyi Bao, Pandeng Li, Junjie Zhou, Zhaohe Liao, Yefei He, Kaixun Jiang, Chen-Wei Xie, Yun Zheng, Hongtao Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While existing generation and unified models excel at general image generation, they struggle with tasks requiring deep reasoning, planning, and precise data-to-visual mapping abilities beyond general scenarios. To push beyond the existing limitations, we introduce a new and challenging task: creative table visualization, requiring the model to generate an infographic that faithfully and aesthetically visualizes the data from a given table. To address this challenge, we propose ShowTable, a pipeline that synergizes MLLMs with diffusion models via a progressive self-correcting process. The MLLM acts as the central orchestrator for reasoning the visual plan and judging visual errors to provide refined instructions, the diffusion execute the commands from MLLM, achieving high-fidelity results. To support this task and our pipeline, we introduce three automated data construction pipelines for training different modules. Furthermore, we introduce TableVisBench, a new benchmark with 800 challenging instances across 5 evaluation dimensions, to assess performance on this task. Experiments demonstrate that our pipeline, instantiated with different models, significantly outperforms baselines, highlighting its effective multi-modal reasoning, generation, and error correction capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13303</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 13:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KlingAvatar 2.0 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13313</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13313.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kling Team, Jialu Chen, Yikang Ding, Zhixue Fang, Kun Gai, Yuan Gao, Kang He, Jingyun Hua, Boyuan Jiang, Mingming Lao, Xiaohan Li, Hui Liu, Jiwen Liu, Xiaoqiang Liu, Yuan Liu, Shun Lu, Yongsen Mao, Yingchao Shao, Huafeng Shi, Xiaoyu Shi, Peiqin Sun, Songlin Tang, Pengfei Wan, Chao Wang, Xuebo Wang, Haoxian Zhang, Yuanxing Zhang, Yan Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Avatar video generation models have achieved remarkable progress in recent years. However, prior work exhibits limited efficiency in generating long-duration high-resolution videos, suffering from temporal drifting, quality degradation, and weak prompt following as video length increases. To address these challenges, we propose KlingAvatar 2.0, a spatio-temporal cascade framework that performs upscaling in both spatial resolution and temporal dimension. The framework first generates low-resolution blueprint video keyframes that capture global semantics and motion, and then refines them into high-resolution, temporally coherent sub-clips using a first-last frame strategy, while retaining smooth temporal transitions in long-form videos. To enhance cross-modal instruction fusion and alignment in extended videos, we introduce a Co-Reasoning Director composed of three modality-specific large language model (LLM) experts. These experts reason about modality priorities and infer underlying user intent, converting inputs into detailed storylines through multi-turn dialogue. A Negative Director further refines negative prompts to improve instruction alignment. Building on these components, we extend the framework to support ID-specific multi-character control. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our model effectively addresses the challenges of efficient, multimodally aligned long-form high-resolution video generation, delivering enhanced visual clarity, realistic lip-teeth rendering with accurate lip synchronization, strong identity preservation, and coherent multimodal instruction following.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13313</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 13:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentiable Evolutionary Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13399</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13399.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sitao Cheng, Tianle Li, Xuhan Huang, Xunjian Yin, Difan Zou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The design of effective reward functions presents a central and often arduous challenge in reinforcement learning (RL), particularly when developing autonomous agents for complex reasoning tasks. While automated reward optimization approaches exist, they typically rely on derivative-free evolutionary heuristics that treat the reward function as a black box, failing to capture the causal relationship between reward structure and task performance. To bridge this gap, we propose Differentiable Evolutionary Reinforcement Learning (DERL), a bilevel framework that enables the autonomous discovery of optimal reward signals. In DERL, a Meta-Optimizer evolves a reward function (i.e., Meta-Reward) by composing structured atomic primitives, guiding the training of an inner-loop policy. Crucially, unlike previous evolution, DERL is differentiable in its metaoptimization: it treats the inner-loop validation performance as a signal to update the Meta-Optimizer via reinforcement learning. This allows DERL to approximate the "meta-gradient" of task success, progressively learning to generate denser and more actionable feedback. We validate DERL across three distinct domains: robotic agent (ALFWorld), scientific simulation (ScienceWorld), and mathematical reasoning (GSM8k, MATH). Experimental results show that DERL achieves state-of-the-art performance on ALFWorld and ScienceWorld, significantly outperforming methods relying on heuristic rewards, especially in out-of-distribution scenarios. Analysis of the evolutionary trajectory demonstrates that DERL successfully captures the intrinsic structure of tasks, enabling selfimproving agent alignment without human intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13399</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 14:50:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seedance 1.5 pro: A Native Audio-Visual Joint Generation Foundation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13507</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13507.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Heyi Chen, Siyan Chen, Xin Chen, Yanfei Chen, Ying Chen, Zhuo Chen, Feng Cheng, Tianheng Cheng, Xinqi Cheng, Xuyan Chi, Jian Cong, Jing Cui, Qinpeng Cui, Qide Dong, Junliang Fan, Jing Fang, Zetao Fang, Chengjian Feng, Han Feng, Mingyuan Gao, Yu Gao, Dong Guo, Qiushan Guo, Boyang Hao, Qingkai Hao, Bibo He, Qian He, Tuyen Hoang, Ruoqing Hu, Xi Hu, Weilin Huang, Zhaoyang Huang, Zhongyi Huang, Donglei Ji, Siqi Jiang, Wei Jiang, Yunpu Jiang, Zhuo Jiang, Ashley Kim, Jianan Kong, Zhichao Lai, Shanshan Lao, Yichong Leng, Ai Li, Feiya Li, Gen Li, Huixia Li, JiaShi Li, Liang Li, Ming Li, Shanshan Li, Tao Li, Xian Li, Xiaojie Li, Xiaoyang Li, Xingxing Li, Yameng Li, Yifu Li, Yiying Li, Chao Liang, Han Liang, Jianzhong Liang, Ying Liang, Zhiqiang Liang, Wang Liao, Yalin Liao, Heng Lin, Kengyu Lin, Shanchuan Lin, Xi Lin, Zhijie Lin, Feng Ling, Fangfang Liu, Gaohong Liu, Jiawei Liu, Jie Liu, Jihao Liu, Shouda Liu, Shu Liu, Sichao Liu, Songwei Liu, Xin Liu, Xue Liu, Yibo Liu, Zikun Liu, Zuxi Liu, Junlin Lyu, Lecheng Lyu, Qian Lyu, Han Mu, Xiaonan Nie, Jingzhe Ning, Xitong Pan, Yanghua Peng, Lianke Qin, Xueqiong Qu, Yuxi Ren, Kai Shen, Guang Shi, Lei Shi, Yan Song, Yinglong Song, Fan Sun, Li Sun, Renfei Sun, Yan Sun, Zeyu Sun, Wenjing Tang, Yaxue Tang, Zirui Tao, Feng Wang, Furui Wang, Jinran Wang, Junkai Wang, Ke Wang, Kexin Wang, Qingyi Wang, Rui Wang, Sen Wang, Shuai Wang, Tingru Wang, Weichen Wang, Xin Wang, Yanhui Wang, Yue Wang, Yuping Wang, Yuxuan Wang, Ziyu Wang, Guoqiang Wei, Wanru Wei, Di Wu, Guohong Wu, Hanjie Wu, Jian Wu, Jie Wu, Ruolan Wu, Xinglong Wu, Yonghui Wu, Ruiqi Xia, Liang Xiang, Fei Xiao, XueFeng Xiao, Pan Xie, Shuangyi Xie, Shuang Xu, Jinlan Xue, Shen Yan, Bangbang Yang, Ceyuan Yang, Jiaqi Yang, Runkai Yang, Tao Yang, Yang Yang, Yihang Yang, ZhiXian Yang, Ziyan Yang, Songting Yao, Yifan Yao, Zilyu Ye, Bowen Yu, Jian Yu, Chujie Yuan, Linxiao Yuan, Sichun Zeng, Weihong Zeng, Xuejiao Zeng, Yan Zeng, Chuntao Zhang, Heng Zhang, Jingjie Zhang, Kuo Zhang, Liang Zhang, Liying Zhang, Manlin Zhang, Ting Zhang, Weida Zhang, Xiaohe Zhang, Xinyan Zhang, Yan Zhang, Yuan Zhang, Zixiang Zhang, Fengxuan Zhao, Huating Zhao, Yang Zhao, Hao Zheng, Jianbin Zheng, Xiaozheng Zheng, Yangyang Zheng, Yijie Zheng, Jiexin Zhou, Jiahui Zhu, Kuan Zhu, Shenhan Zhu, Wenjia Zhu, Benhui Zou, Feilong Zuo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent strides in video generation have paved the way for unified audio-visual generation. In this work, we present Seedance 1.5 pro, a foundational model engineered specifically for native, joint audio-video generation. Leveraging a dual-branch Diffusion Transformer architecture, the model integrates a cross-modal joint module with a specialized multi-stage data pipeline, achieving exceptional audio-visual synchronization and superior generation quality. To ensure practical utility, we implement meticulous post-training optimizations, including Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) on high-quality datasets and Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback (RLHF) with multi-dimensional reward models. Furthermore, we introduce an acceleration framework that boosts inference speed by over 10X. Seedance 1.5 pro distinguishes itself through precise multilingual and dialect lip-syncing, dynamic cinematic camera control, and enhanced narrative coherence, positioning it as a robust engine for professional-grade content creation. Seedance 1.5 pro is now accessible on Volcano Engine at https://console.volcengine.com/ark/region:ark+cn-beijing/experience/vision?type=GenVideo.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13507</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 16:36:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Memory in the Age of AI Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13564</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13564.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuyang Hu, Shichun Liu, Yanwei Yue, Guibin Zhang, Boyang Liu, Fangyi Zhu, Jiahang Lin, Honglin Guo, Shihan Dou, Zhiheng Xi, Senjie Jin, Jiejun Tan, Yanbin Yin, Jiongnan Liu, Zeyu Zhang, Zhongxiang Sun, Yutao Zhu, Hao Sun, Boci Peng, Zhenrong Cheng, Xuanbo Fan, Jiaxin Guo, Xinlei Yu, Zhenhong Zhou, Zewen Hu, Jiahao Huo, Junhao Wang, Yuwei Niu, Yu Wang, Zhenfei Yin, Xiaobin Hu, Yue Liao, Qiankun Li, Kun Wang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Yixin Liu, Dawei Cheng, Qi Zhang, Tao Gui, Shirui Pan, Yan Zhang, Philip Torr, Zhicheng Dou, Ji-Rong Wen, Xuanjing Huang, Yu-Gang Jiang, Shuicheng Yan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 101&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Memory has emerged, and will continue to remain, a core capability of foundation model-based agents. As research on agent memory rapidly expands and attracts unprecedented attention, the field has also become increasingly fragmented. Existing works that fall under the umbrella of agent memory often differ substantially in their motivations, implementations, and evaluation protocols, while the proliferation of loosely defined memory terminologies has further obscured conceptual clarity. Traditional taxonomies such as long/short-term memory have proven insufficient to capture the diversity of contemporary agent memory systems. This work aims to provide an up-to-date landscape of current agent memory research. We begin by clearly delineating the scope of agent memory and distinguishing it from related concepts such as LLM memory, retrieval augmented generation (RAG), and context engineering. We then examine agent memory through the unified lenses of forms, functions, and dynamics. From the perspective of forms, we identify three dominant realizations of agent memory, namely token-level, parametric, and latent memory. From the perspective of functions, we propose a finer-grained taxonomy that distinguishes factual, experiential, and working memory. From the perspective of dynamics, we analyze how memory is formed, evolved, and retrieved over time. To support practical development, we compile a comprehensive summary of memory benchmarks and open-source frameworks. Beyond consolidation, we articulate a forward-looking perspective on emerging research frontiers, including memory automation, reinforcement learning integration, multimodal memory, multi-agent memory, and trustworthiness issues. We hope this survey serves not only as a reference for existing work, but also as a conceptual foundation for rethinking memory as a first-class primitive in the design of future agentic intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13564</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 17:22:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReFusion: A Diffusion Large Language Model with Parallel Autoregressive Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13586</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13586.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jia-Nan Li, Jian Guan, Wei Wu, Chongxuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 87&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive models (ARMs) are hindered by slow sequential inference. While masked diffusion models (MDMs) offer a parallel alternative, they suffer from critical drawbacks: high computational overhead from precluding Key-Value (KV) caching, and incoherent generation arising from learning dependencies over an intractable space of token combinations. To address these limitations, we introduce ReFusion, a novel masked diffusion model that achieves superior performance and efficiency by elevating parallel decoding from the token level to a higher slot level, where each slot is a fixed-length, contiguous sub-sequence. This is achieved through an iterative ``plan-and-infill'' decoding process: a diffusion-based planning step first identifies a set of weakly dependent slots, and an autoregressive infilling step then decodes these selected slots in parallel. The slot-based design simultaneously unlocks full KV cache reuse with a unified causal framework and reduces the learning complexity from the token combination space to a manageable slot-level permutation space. Extensive experiments on seven diverse benchmarks show that ReFusion not only overwhelmingly surpasses prior MDMs with 34% performance gains and an over 18times speedup on average, but also bridges the performance gap to strong ARMs while maintaining a 2.33times average speedup.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13586</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 17:41:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Image Diffusion Preview with Consistency Solver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13592</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13592.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fu-Yun Wang, Hao Zhou, Liangzhe Yuan, Sanghyun Woo, Boqing Gong, Bohyung Han, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Han Zhang, Yukun Zhu, Ting Liu, Long Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The slow inference process of image diffusion models significantly degrades interactive user experiences. To address this, we introduce Diffusion Preview, a novel paradigm employing rapid, low-step sampling to generate preliminary outputs for user evaluation, deferring full-step refinement until the preview is deemed satisfactory. Existing acceleration methods, including training-free solvers and post-training distillation, struggle to deliver high-quality previews or ensure consistency between previews and final outputs. We propose ConsistencySolver derived from general linear multistep methods, a lightweight, trainable high-order solver optimized via Reinforcement Learning, that enhances preview quality and consistency. Experimental results demonstrate that ConsistencySolver significantly improves generation quality and consistency in low-step scenarios, making it ideal for efficient preview-and-refine workflows. Notably, it achieves FID scores on-par with Multistep DPM-Solver using 47% fewer steps, while outperforming distillation baselines. Furthermore, user studies indicate our approach reduces overall user interaction time by nearly 50% while maintaining generation quality. Code is available at https://github.com/G-U-N/consolver.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13592</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 17:47:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongVie 2: Multimodal Controllable Ultra-Long Video World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13604</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13604.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianxiong Gao, Zhaoxi Chen, Xian Liu, Junhao Zhuang, Chengming Xu, Jianfeng Feng, Yu Qiao, Yanwei Fu, Chenyang Si, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Building video world models upon pretrained video generation systems represents an important yet challenging step toward general spatiotemporal intelligence. A world model should possess three essential properties: controllability, long-term visual quality, and temporal consistency. To this end, we take a progressive approach-first enhancing controllability and then extending toward long-term, high-quality generation. We present LongVie 2, an end-to-end autoregressive framework trained in three stages: (1) Multi-modal guidance, which integrates dense and sparse control signals to provide implicit world-level supervision and improve controllability; (2) Degradation-aware training on the input frame, bridging the gap between training and long-term inference to maintain high visual quality; and (3) History-context guidance, which aligns contextual information across adjacent clips to ensure temporal consistency. We further introduce LongVGenBench, a comprehensive benchmark comprising 100 high-resolution one-minute videos covering diverse real-world and synthetic environments. Extensive experiments demonstrate that LongVie 2 achieves state-of-the-art performance in long-range controllability, temporal coherence, and visual fidelity, and supports continuous video generation lasting up to five minutes, marking a significant step toward unified video world modeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13604</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nemotron-Cascade: Scaling Cascaded Reinforcement Learning for General-Purpose Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13607</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13607.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Boxin Wang, Chankyu Lee, Nayeon Lee, Sheng-Chieh Lin, Wenliang Dai, Yang Chen, Yangyi Chen, Zhuolin Yang, Zihan Liu, Mohammad Shoeybi, Bryan Catanzaro, Wei Ping&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Building general-purpose reasoning models with reinforcement learning (RL) entails substantial cross-domain heterogeneity, including large variation in inference-time response lengths and verification latency. Such variability complicates the RL infrastructure, slows training, and makes training curriculum (e.g., response length extension) and hyperparameter selection challenging. In this work, we propose cascaded domain-wise reinforcement learning (Cascade RL) to develop general-purpose reasoning models, Nemotron-Cascade, capable of operating in both instruct and deep thinking modes. Departing from conventional approaches that blend heterogeneous prompts from different domains, Cascade RL orchestrates sequential, domain-wise RL, reducing engineering complexity and delivering state-of-the-art performance across a wide range of benchmarks. Notably, RLHF for alignment, when used as a pre-step, boosts the model's reasoning ability far beyond mere preference optimization, and subsequent domain-wise RLVR stages rarely degrade the benchmark performance attained in earlier domains and may even improve it (see an illustration in Figure 1). Our 14B model, after RL, outperforms its SFT teacher, DeepSeek-R1-0528, on LiveCodeBench v5/v6/Pro and achieves silver-medal performance in the 2025 International Olympiad in Informatics (IOI). We transparently share our training and data recipes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13607</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:02:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboTracer: Mastering Spatial Trace with Reasoning in Vision-Language Models for Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13660</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13660.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Enshen Zhou, Cheng Chi, Yibo Li, Jingkun An, Jiayuan Zhang, Shanyu Rong, Yi Han, Yuheng Ji, Mengzhen Liu, Pengwei Wang, Zhongyuan Wang, Lu Sheng, Shanghang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spatial tracing, as a fundamental embodied interaction ability for robots, is inherently challenging as it requires multi-step metric-grounded reasoning compounded with complex spatial referring and real-world metric measurement. However, existing methods struggle with this compositional task. To this end, we propose RoboTracer, a 3D-aware VLM that first achieves both 3D spatial referring and measuring via a universal spatial encoder and a regression-supervised decoder to enhance scale awareness during supervised fine-tuning (SFT). Moreover, RoboTracer advances multi-step metric-grounded reasoning via reinforcement fine-tuning (RFT) with metric-sensitive process rewards, supervising key intermediate perceptual cues to accurately generate spatial traces. To support SFT and RFT training, we introduce TraceSpatial, a large-scale dataset of 30M QA pairs, spanning outdoor/indoor/tabletop scenes and supporting complex reasoning processes (up to 9 steps). We further present TraceSpatial-Bench, a challenging benchmark filling the gap to evaluate spatial tracing. Experimental results show that RoboTracer surpasses baselines in spatial understanding, measuring, and referring, with an average success rate of 79.1%, and also achieves SOTA performance on TraceSpatial-Bench by a large margin, exceeding Gemini-2.5-Pro by 36% accuracy. Notably, RoboTracer can be integrated with various control policies to execute long-horizon, dynamic tasks across diverse robots (UR5, G1 humanoid) in cluttered real-world scenes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13660</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:52:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Interactive Intelligence for Digital Humans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13674</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13674.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiyi Cai, Xuangeng Chu, Xiwei Gao, Sitong Gong, Yifei Huang, Caixin Kang, Kunhang Li, Haiyang Liu, Ruicong Liu, Yun Liu, Dianwen Ng, Zixiong Su, Erwin Wu, Yuhan Wu, Dingkun Yan, Tianyu Yan, Chang Zeng, Bo Zheng, You Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Interactive Intelligence, a novel paradigm of digital human that is capable of personality-aligned expression, adaptive interaction, and self-evolution. To realize this, we present Mio (Multimodal Interactive Omni-Avatar), an end-to-end framework composed of five specialized modules: Thinker, Talker, Face Animator, Body Animator, and Renderer. This unified architecture integrates cognitive reasoning with real-time multimodal embodiment to enable fluid, consistent interaction. Furthermore, we establish a new benchmark to rigorously evaluate the capabilities of interactive intelligence. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our framework achieves superior performance compared to state-of-the-art methods across all evaluated dimensions. Together, these contributions move digital humans beyond superficial imitation toward intelligent interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13674</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:57:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feedforward 3D Editing via Text-Steerable Image-to-3D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13678</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13678.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziqi Ma, Hongqiao Chen, Yisong Yue, Georgia Gkioxari&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in image-to-3D has opened up immense possibilities for design, AR/VR, and robotics. However, to use AI-generated 3D assets in real applications, a critical requirement is the capability to edit them easily. We present a feedforward method, Steer3D, to add text steerability to image-to-3D models, which enables editing of generated 3D assets with language. Our approach is inspired by ControlNet, which we adapt to image-to-3D generation to enable text steering directly in a forward pass. We build a scalable data engine for automatic data generation, and develop a two-stage training recipe based on flow-matching training and Direct Preference Optimization (DPO). Compared to competing methods, Steer3D more faithfully follows the language instruction and maintains better consistency with the original 3D asset, while being 2.4x to 28.5x faster. Steer3D demonstrates that it is possible to add a new modality (text) to steer the generation of pretrained image-to-3D generative models with 100k data. Project website: https://glab-caltech.github.io/steer3d/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13678</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:58:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Scalable Pre-training of Visual Tokenizers for Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13687</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13687.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingfeng Yao, Yuda Song, Yucong Zhou, Xinggang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 89&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The quality of the latent space in visual tokenizers (e.g., VAEs) is crucial for modern generative models. However, the standard reconstruction-based training paradigm produces a latent space that is biased towards low-level information, leading to a foundation flaw: better pixel-level accuracy does not lead to higher-quality generation. This implies that pouring extensive compute into visual tokenizer pre-training translates poorly to improved performance in generation. We identify this as the ``pre-training scaling problem`` and suggest a necessary shift: to be effective for generation, a latent space must concisely represent high-level semantics. We present VTP, a unified visual tokenizer pre-training framework, pioneering the joint optimization of image-text contrastive, self-supervised, and reconstruction losses. Our large-scale study reveals two principal findings: (1) understanding is a key driver of generation, and (2) much better scaling properties, where generative performance scales effectively with compute, parameters, and data allocated to the pretraining of the visual tokenizer. After large-scale pre-training, our tokenizer delivers a competitive profile (78.2 zero-shot accuracy and 0.36 rFID on ImageNet) and 4.1 times faster convergence on generation compared to advanced distillation methods. More importantly, it scales effectively: without modifying standard DiT training specs, solely investing more FLOPS in pretraining VTP achieves 65.8\% FID improvement in downstream generation, while conventional autoencoder stagnates very early at 1/10 FLOPS. Our pre-trained models are available at https://github.com/MiniMax-AI/VTP.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13687</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:59:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LitePT: Lighter Yet Stronger Point Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13689</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13689.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuanwen Yue, Damien Robert, Jianyuan Wang, Sunghwan Hong, Jan Dirk Wegner, Christian Rupprecht, Konrad Schindler&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern neural architectures for 3D point cloud processing contain both convolutional layers and attention blocks, but the best way to assemble them remains unclear. We analyse the role of different computational blocks in 3D point cloud networks and find an intuitive behaviour: convolution is adequate to extract low-level geometry at high-resolution in early layers, where attention is expensive without bringing any benefits; attention captures high-level semantics and context in low-resolution, deep layers more efficiently. Guided by this design principle, we propose a new, improved 3D point cloud backbone that employs convolutions in early stages and switches to attention for deeper layers. To avoid the loss of spatial layout information when discarding redundant convolution layers, we introduce a novel, training-free 3D positional encoding, PointROPE. The resulting LitePT model has 3.6times fewer parameters, runs 2times faster, and uses 2times less memory than the state-of-the-art Point Transformer V3, but nonetheless matches or even outperforms it on a range of tasks and datasets. Code and models are available at: https://github.com/prs-eth/LitePT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13689</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAGE: Training Smart Any-Horizon Agents for Long Video Reasoning with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13874</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13874.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jitesh Jain, Jialuo Li, Zixian Ma, Jieyu Zhang, Chris Dongjoo Kim, Sangho Lee, Rohun Tripathi, Tanmay Gupta, Christopher Clark, Humphrey Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As humans, we are natural any-horizon reasoners, i.e., we can decide whether to iteratively skim long videos or watch short ones in full when necessary for a given task. With this in mind, one would expect video reasoning models to reason flexibly across different durations. However, SOTA models are still trained to predict answers in a single turn while processing a large number of frames, akin to watching an entire long video, requiring significant resources. This raises the question: Is it possible to develop performant any-horizon video reasoning systems? Inspired by human behavior, we first propose SAGE, an agent system that performs multi-turn reasoning on long videos while handling simpler problems in a single turn. Secondly, we introduce an easy synthetic data generation pipeline using Gemini-2.5-Flash to train the orchestrator, SAGE-MM, which lies at the core of SAGE. We further propose an effective RL post-training recipe essential for instilling any-horizon reasoning ability in SAGE-MM. Thirdly, we curate SAGE-Bench with an average duration of greater than 700 seconds for evaluating video reasoning ability in real-world entertainment use cases. Lastly, we empirically validate the effectiveness of our system, data, and RL recipe, observing notable improvements of up to 6.1% on open-ended video reasoning tasks, as well as an impressive 8.2% improvement on videos longer than 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13874</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 20:14:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FiNERweb: Datasets and Artifacts for Scalable Multilingual Named Entity Recognition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13884</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13884.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jonas Golde, Patrick Haller, Alan Akbik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent multilingual named entity recognition (NER) work has shown that large language models (LLMs) can provide effective synthetic supervision, yet such datasets have mostly appeared as by-products of broader experiments rather than as systematic, reusable resources. We introduce FiNERweb, a dataset-creation pipeline that scales the teacher-student paradigm to 91 languages and 25 scripts. Building on FineWeb-Edu, our approach trains regression models to identify NER-relevant passages and annotates them with multilingual LLMs, resulting in about 225k passages with 235k distinct entity labels. Our experiments show that the regression model achieves more than 84 F1, and that models trained on FiNERweb obtain comparable or improved performance in zero shot transfer settings on English, Thai, and Swahili, despite being trained on 19x less data than strong baselines. In addition, we assess annotation quality using LLM-as-a-judge and observe consistently high scores for both faithfulness (3.99 out of 5) and completeness (4.05 out of 5), indicating reliable and informative annotations. Further, we release the dataset with both English labels and translated label sets in the respective target languages because we observe that the performance of current state-of-the-art models drops by 0.02 to 0.09 F1 when evaluated using target language labels instead of English ones. We release FiNERweb together with all accompanying artifacts to the research community in order to facilitate more effective student-teacher training for multilingual named entity recognition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13884</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 20:36:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Olmo 3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13961</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.13961.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Team Olmo, Allyson Ettinger, Amanda Bertsch, Bailey Kuehl, David Graham, David Heineman, Dirk Groeneveld, Faeze Brahman, Finbarr Timbers, Hamish Ivison, Jacob Morrison, Jake Poznanski, Kyle Lo, Luca Soldaini, Matt Jordan, Mayee Chen, Michael Noukhovitch, Nathan Lambert, Pete Walsh, Pradeep Dasigi, Robert Berry, Saumya Malik, Saurabh Shah, Scott Geng, Shane Arora, Shashank Gupta, Taira Anderson, Teng Xiao, Tyler Murray, Tyler Romero, Victoria Graf, Akari Asai, Akshita Bhagia, Alexander Wettig, Alisa Liu, Aman Rangapur, Chloe Anastasiades, Costa Huang, Dustin Schwenk, Harsh Trivedi, Ian Magnusson, Jaron Lochner, Jiacheng Liu, Lester James V. Miranda, Maarten Sap, Malia Morgan, Michael Schmitz, Michal Guerquin, Michael Wilson, Regan Huff, Ronan Le Bras, Rui Xin, Rulin Shao, Sam Skjonsberg, Shannon Zejiang Shen, Shuyue Stella Li, Tucker Wilde, Valentina Pyatkin, Will Merrill, Yapei Chang, Yuling Gu, Zhiyuan Zeng, Ashish Sabharwal, Luke Zettlemoyer, Pang Wei Koh, Ali Farhadi, Noah A. Smith, Hannaneh Hajishirzi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Olmo 3, a family of state-of-the-art, fully-open language models at the 7B and 32B parameter scales. Olmo 3 model construction targets long-context reasoning, function calling, coding, instruction following, general chat, and knowledge recall. This release includes the entire model flow, i.e., the full lifecycle of the family of models, including every stage, checkpoint, data point, and dependency used to build it. Our flagship model, Olmo 3 Think 32B, is the strongest fully-open thinking model released to-date.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13961</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 23:41:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sparse-LaViDa: Sparse Multimodal Discrete Diffusion Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14008</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14008.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shufan Li, Jiuxiang Gu, Kangning Liu, Zhe Lin, Zijun Wei, Aditya Grover, Jason Kuen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Masked Discrete Diffusion Models (MDMs) have achieved strong performance across a wide range of multimodal tasks, including image understanding, generation, and editing. However, their inference speed remains suboptimal due to the need to repeatedly process redundant masked tokens at every sampling step. In this work, we propose Sparse-LaViDa, a novel modeling framework that dynamically truncates unnecessary masked tokens at each inference step to accelerate MDM sampling. To preserve generation quality, we introduce specialized register tokens that serve as compact representations for the truncated tokens. Furthermore, to ensure consistency between training and inference, we design a specialized attention mask that faithfully matches the truncated sampling procedure during training. Built upon the state-of-the-art unified MDM LaViDa-O, Sparse-LaViDa achieves up to a 2x speedup across diverse tasks including text-to-image generation, image editing, and mathematical reasoning, while maintaining generation quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14008</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 02:06:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenDataArena: A Fair and Open Arena for Benchmarking Post-Training Dataset Value</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14051</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14051.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengzhang Cai, Xin Gao, Yu Li, Honglin Lin, Zheng Liu, Zhuoshi Pan, Qizhi Pei, Xiaoran Shang, Mengyuan Sun, Zinan Tang, Xiaoyang Wang, Zhanping Zhong, Yun Zhu, Dahua Lin, Conghui He, Lijun Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid evolution of Large Language Models (LLMs) is predicated on the quality and diversity of post-training datasets. However, a critical dichotomy persists: while models are rigorously benchmarked, the data fueling them remains a black box--characterized by opaque composition, uncertain provenance, and a lack of systematic evaluation. This opacity hinders reproducibility and obscures the causal link between data characteristics and model behaviors. To bridge this gap, we introduce OpenDataArena (ODA), a holistic and open platform designed to benchmark the intrinsic value of post-training data. ODA establishes a comprehensive ecosystem comprising four key pillars: (i) a unified training-evaluation pipeline that ensures fair, open comparisons across diverse models (e.g., Llama, Qwen) and domains; (ii) a multi-dimensional scoring framework that profiles data quality along tens of distinct axes; (iii) an interactive data lineage explorer to visualize dataset genealogy and dissect component sources; and (iv) a fully open-source toolkit for training, evaluation, and scoring to foster data research. Extensive experiments on ODA--covering over 120 training datasets across multiple domains on 22 benchmarks, validated by more than 600 training runs and 40 million processed data points--reveal non-trivial insights. Our analysis uncovers the inherent trade-offs between data complexity and task performance, identifies redundancy in popular benchmarks through lineage tracing, and maps the genealogical relationships across datasets. We release all results, tools, and configurations to democratize access to high-quality data evaluation. Rather than merely expanding a leaderboard, ODA envisions a shift from trial-and-error data curation to a principled science of Data-Centric AI, paving the way for rigorous studies on data mixing laws and the strategic composition of foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14051</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 03:33:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HyperVL: An Efficient and Dynamic Multimodal Large Language Model for Edge Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14052</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14052.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; HyperAI Team, Yuchen Liu, Kaiyang Han, Zhiqiang Xia, Yuhang Dong, Chen Song, Kangyu Tang, Jiaming Xu, Xiushi Feng, WenXuan Yu, Li Peng, Mingyang Wang, Kai Wang, Changpeng Yang, Yang Li, Haoyu Lu, Hao Wang, Bingna Xu, Guangyao Liu, Long Huang, Kaibin Guo, Jinyang Wu, Dan Wu, Hongzhen Wang, Peng Zhou, Shuai Nie, Shande Wang, Runyu Shi, Ying Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current multimodal large lanauge models possess strong perceptual and reasoning capabilities, however high computational and memory requirements make them difficult to deploy directly on on-device environments. While small-parameter models are progressively endowed with strong general capabilities, standard Vision Transformer (ViT) encoders remain a critical bottleneck, suffering from excessive latency and memory consumption when processing high-resolution inputs.To address these challenges, we introduce HyperVL, an efficient multimodal large language model tailored for on-device inference. HyperVL adopts an image-tiling strategy to cap peak memory usage and incorporates two novel techniques: (1) a Visual Resolution Compressor (VRC) that adaptively predicts optimal encoding resolutions to eliminate redundant computation, and (2) Dual Consistency Learning (DCL), which aligns multi-scale ViT encoders within a unified framework, enabling dynamic switching between visual branches under a shared LLM. Extensive experiments demonstrate that HyperVL achieves state-of-the-art performance among models of comparable size across multiple benchmarks. Furthermore, it significantly significantly reduces latency and power consumption on real mobile devices, demonstrating its practicality for on-device multimodal inference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14052</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 03:36:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient-DLM: From Autoregressive to Diffusion Language Models, and Beyond in Speed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14067</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14067.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yonggan Fu, Lexington Whalen, Zhifan Ye, Xin Dong, Shizhe Diao, Jingyu Liu, Chengyue Wu, Hao Zhang, Enze Xie, Song Han, Maksim Khadkevich, Jan Kautz, Yingyan Celine Lin, Pavlo Molchanov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion language models (dLMs) have emerged as a promising paradigm that enables parallel, non-autoregressive generation, but their learning efficiency lags behind that of autoregressive (AR) language models when trained from scratch. To this end, we study AR-to-dLM conversion to transform pretrained AR models into efficient dLMs that excel in speed while preserving AR models' task accuracy. We achieve this by identifying limitations in the attention patterns and objectives of existing AR-to-dLM methods and then proposing principles and methodologies for more effective AR-to-dLM conversion. Specifically, we first systematically compare different attention patterns and find that maintaining pretrained AR weight distributions is critical for effective AR-to-dLM conversion. As such, we introduce a continuous pretraining scheme with a block-wise attention pattern, which remains causal across blocks while enabling bidirectional modeling within each block. We find that this approach can better preserve pretrained AR models' weight distributions than fully bidirectional modeling, in addition to its known benefit of enabling KV caching, and leads to a win-win in accuracy and efficiency. Second, to mitigate the training-test gap in mask token distributions (uniform vs. highly left-to-right), we propose a position-dependent token masking strategy that assigns higher masking probabilities to later tokens during training to better mimic test-time behavior. Leveraging this framework, we conduct extensive studies of dLMs' attention patterns, training dynamics, and other design choices, providing actionable insights into scalable AR-to-dLM conversion. These studies lead to the Efficient-DLM family, which outperforms state-of-the-art AR models and dLMs, e.g., our Efficient-DLM 8B achieves +5.4%/+2.7% higher accuracy with 4.5x/2.7x higher throughput compared to Dream 7B and Qwen3 4B, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14067</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 04:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zoom-Zero: Reinforced Coarse-to-Fine Video Understanding via Temporal Zoom-in</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14273</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14273.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoqian Shen, Min-Hung Chen, Yu-Chiang Frank Wang, Mohamed Elhoseiny, Ryo Hachiuma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Grounded video question answering (GVQA) aims to localize relevant temporal segments in videos and generate accurate answers to a given question; however, large video-language models (LVLMs) exhibit limited temporal awareness. Although existing approaches based on Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) attempt to improve temporal grounding, they still struggle to faithfully ground their answers in the relevant video evidence, leading to temporal mislocalization and hallucinations. In this work, we present Zoom-Zero, a coarse-to-fine framework that first localizes query-relevant segments and then temporally zooms into the most salient frames for finer-grained visual verification. Our method addresses the limits of GRPO for the GVQA task with two key innovations: (i) a zoom-in accuracy reward that validates the fidelity of temporal grounding prediction and facilitates fine-grained visual verification on grounded frames; (ii) token-selective credit assignment, which attributes rewards to the tokens responsible for temporal localization or answer generation, mitigating GRPO's issue in handling multi-faceted reward signals. Our proposed method advances grounded video question answering, improving temporal grounding by 5.2\% on NExT-GQA and 4.6\% on ReXTime, while also enhancing average answer accuracy by 2.4\%. Additionally, the coarse-to-fine zoom-in during inference further benefits long-form video understanding by preserving critical visual details without compromising global context, yielding an average improvement of 6.4\% on long-video benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14273</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 10:34:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SS4D: Native 4D Generative Model via Structured Spacetime Latents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14284</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14284.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhibing Li, Mengchen Zhang, Tong Wu, Jing Tan, Jiaqi Wang, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present SS4D, a native 4D generative model that synthesizes dynamic 3D objects directly from monocular video. Unlike prior approaches that construct 4D representations by optimizing over 3D or video generative models, we train a generator directly on 4D data, achieving high fidelity, temporal coherence, and structural consistency. At the core of our method is a compressed set of structured spacetime latents. Specifically, (1) To address the scarcity of 4D training data, we build on a pre-trained single-image-to-3D model, preserving strong spatial consistency. (2) Temporal consistency is enforced by introducing dedicated temporal layers that reason across frames. (3) To support efficient training and inference over long video sequences, we compress the latent sequence along the temporal axis using factorized 4D convolutions and temporal downsampling blocks. In addition, we employ a carefully designed training strategy to enhance robustness against occlusion&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14284</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 10:45:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector Prism: Animating Vector Graphics by Stratifying Semantic Structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14336</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14336.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jooyeol Yun, Jaegul Choo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) are central to modern web design, and the demand to animate them continues to grow as web environments become increasingly dynamic. Yet automating the animation of vector graphics remains challenging for vision-language models (VLMs) despite recent progress in code generation and motion planning. VLMs routinely mis-handle SVGs, since visually coherent parts are often fragmented into low-level shapes that offer little guidance of which elements should move together. In this paper, we introduce a framework that recovers the semantic structure required for reliable SVG animation and reveals the missing layer that current VLM systems overlook. This is achieved through a statistical aggregation of multiple weak part predictions, allowing the system to stably infer semantics from noisy predictions. By reorganizing SVGs into semantic groups, our approach enables VLMs to produce animations with far greater coherence. Our experiments demonstrate substantial gains over existing approaches, suggesting that semantic recovery is the key step that unlocks robust SVG animation and supports more interpretable interactions between VLMs and vector graphics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14336</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 12:03:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RePo: Language Models with Context Re-Positioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14391</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14391.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huayang Li, Tianyu Zhao, Richard Sproat&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In-context learning is fundamental to modern Large Language Models (LLMs); however, prevailing architectures impose a rigid and fixed contextual structure by assigning linear or constant positional indices. Drawing on Cognitive Load Theory (CLT), we argue that this uninformative structure increases extraneous cognitive load, consuming finite working memory capacity that should be allocated to deep reasoning and attention allocation. To address this, we propose RePo, a novel mechanism that reduces extraneous load via context re-positioning. Unlike standard approaches, RePo utilizes a differentiable module, f_φ, to assign token positions that capture contextual dependencies, rather than replying on pre-defined integer range. By continually pre-training on the OLMo-2 1B backbone, we demonstrate that RePo significantly enhances performance on tasks involving noisy contexts, structured data, and longer context length, while maintaining competitive performance on general short-context tasks. Detailed analysis reveals that RePo successfully allocate higher attention to distant but relevant information, assign positions in dense and non-linear space, and capture the intrinsic structure of the input context. Our code is available at https://github.com/SakanaAI/repo.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14391</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 13:30:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A4-Agent: An Agentic Framework for Zero-Shot Affordance Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14442</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14442.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zixin Zhang, Kanghao Chen, Hanqing Wang, Hongfei Zhang, Harold Haodong Chen, Chenfei Liao, Litao Guo, Ying-Cong Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Affordance prediction, which identifies interaction regions on objects based on language instructions, is critical for embodied AI. Prevailing end-to-end models couple high-level reasoning and low-level grounding into a single monolithic pipeline and rely on training over annotated datasets, which leads to poor generalization on novel objects and unseen environments. In this paper, we move beyond this paradigm by proposing A4-Agent, a training-free agentic framework that decouples affordance prediction into a three-stage pipeline. Our framework coordinates specialized foundation models at test time: (1) a Dreamer that employs generative models to visualize how an interaction would look; (2) a Thinker that utilizes large vision-language models to decide what object part to interact with; and (3) a Spotter that orchestrates vision foundation models to precisely locate where the interaction area is. By leveraging the complementary strengths of pre-trained models without any task-specific fine-tuning, our zero-shot framework significantly outperforms state-of-the-art supervised methods across multiple benchmarks and demonstrates robust generalization to real-world settings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14442</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 14:27:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RecGPT-V2 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14503</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14503.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chao Yi, Dian Chen, Gaoyang Guo, Jiakai Tang, Jian Wu, Jing Yu, Mao Zhang, Wen Chen, Wenjun Yang, Yujie Luo, Yuning Jiang, Zhujin Gao, Bo Zheng, Binbin Cao, Changfa Wu, Dixuan Wang, Han Wu, Haoyi Hu, Kewei Zhu, Lang Tian, Lin Yang, Qiqi Huang, Siqi Yang, Wenbo Su, Xiaoxiao He, Xin Tong, Xu Chen, Xunke Xi, Xiaowei Huang, Yaxuan Wu, Yeqiu Yang, Yi Hu, Yujin Yuan, Yuliang Yan, Zile Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable potential in transforming recommender systems from implicit behavioral pattern matching to explicit intent reasoning. While RecGPT-V1 successfully pioneered this paradigm by integrating LLM-based reasoning into user interest mining and item tag prediction, it suffers from four fundamental limitations: (1) computational inefficiency and cognitive redundancy across multiple reasoning routes; (2) insufficient explanation diversity in fixed-template generation; (3) limited generalization under supervised learning paradigms; and (4) simplistic outcome-focused evaluation that fails to match human standards.   To address these challenges, we present RecGPT-V2 with four key innovations. First, a Hierarchical Multi-Agent System restructures intent reasoning through coordinated collaboration, eliminating cognitive duplication while enabling diverse intent coverage. Combined with Hybrid Representation Inference that compresses user-behavior contexts, our framework reduces GPU consumption by 60% and improves exclusive recall from 9.39% to 10.99%. Second, a Meta-Prompting framework dynamically generates contextually adaptive prompts, improving explanation diversity by +7.3%. Third, constrained reinforcement learning mitigates multi-reward conflicts, achieving +24.1% improvement in tag prediction and +13.0% in explanation acceptance. Fourth, an Agent-as-a-Judge framework decomposes assessment into multi-step reasoning, improving human preference alignment. Online A/B tests on Taobao demonstrate significant improvements: +2.98% CTR, +3.71% IPV, +2.19% TV, and +11.46% NER. RecGPT-V2 establishes both the technical feasibility and commercial viability of deploying LLM-powered intent reasoning at scale, bridging the gap between cognitive exploration and industrial utility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14503</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 15:40:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VersatileFFN: Achieving Parameter Efficiency in LLMs via Adaptive Wide-and-Deep Reuse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14531</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14531.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ying Nie, Kai Han, Hongguang Li, Hang Zhou, Tianyu Guo, Enhua Wu, Xinghao Chen, Yunhe Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid scaling of Large Language Models (LLMs) has achieved remarkable performance, but it also leads to prohibitive memory costs. Existing parameter-efficient approaches such as pruning and quantization mainly compress pretrained models without enhancing architectural capacity, thereby hitting the representational ceiling of the base model. In this work, we propose VersatileFFN, a novel feed-forward network (FFN) that enables flexible reuse of parameters in both width and depth dimensions within a fixed parameter budget. Inspired by the dual-process theory of cognition, VersatileFFN comprises two adaptive pathways: a width-versatile path that generates a mixture of sub-experts from a single shared FFN, mimicking sparse expert routing without increasing parameters, and a depth-versatile path that recursively applies the same FFN to emulate deeper processing for complex tokens. A difficulty-aware gating dynamically balances the two pathways, steering "easy" tokens through the efficient width-wise route and allocating deeper iterative refinement to "hard" tokens. Crucially, both pathways reuse the same parameters, so all additional capacity comes from computation rather than memory. Experiments across diverse benchmarks and model scales demonstrate the effectiveness of the method. The code will be available at https://github.com/huawei-noah/noah-research/tree/master/VersatileFFN.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14531</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 16:08:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WorldPlay: Towards Long-Term Geometric Consistency for Real-Time Interactive World Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14614</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14614.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenqiang Sun, Haiyu Zhang, Haoyuan Wang, Junta Wu, Zehan Wang, Zhenwei Wang, Yunhong Wang, Jun Zhang, Tengfei Wang, Chunchao Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents WorldPlay, a streaming video diffusion model that enables real-time, interactive world modeling with long-term geometric consistency, resolving the trade-off between speed and memory that limits current methods. WorldPlay draws power from three key innovations. 1) We use a Dual Action Representation to enable robust action control in response to the user's keyboard and mouse inputs. 2) To enforce long-term consistency, our Reconstituted Context Memory dynamically rebuilds context from past frames and uses temporal reframing to keep geometrically important but long-past frames accessible, effectively alleviating memory attenuation. 3) We also propose Context Forcing, a novel distillation method designed for memory-aware model. Aligning memory context between the teacher and student preserves the student's capacity to use long-range information, enabling real-time speeds while preventing error drift. Taken together, WorldPlay generates long-horizon streaming 720p video at 24 FPS with superior consistency, comparing favorably with existing techniques and showing strong generalization across diverse scenes. Project page and online demo can be found: https://3d-models.hunyuan.tencent.com/world/ and https://3d.hunyuan.tencent.com/sceneTo3D.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14614</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 17:22:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EVOLVE-VLA: Test-Time Training from Environment Feedback for Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14666</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14666.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zechen Bai, Chen Gao, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Achieving truly adaptive embodied intelligence requires agents that learn not just by imitating static demonstrations, but by continuously improving through environmental interaction, which is akin to how humans master skills through practice. Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models have advanced robotic manipulation by leveraging large language models, yet remain fundamentally limited by Supervised Finetuning (SFT): requiring hundreds of demonstrations per task, rigidly memorizing trajectories, and failing to adapt when deployment conditions deviate from training. We introduce EVOLVE-VLA, a test-time training framework enabling VLAs to continuously adapt through environment interaction with minimal or zero task-specific demonstrations. The key technical challenge is replacing oracle reward signals (unavailable at test time) with autonomous feedback. We address this through a learned progress estimator providing dense feedback, and critically, we design our framework to ``tame'' this inherently noisy signal via two mechanisms: (1) an accumulative progress estimation mechanism smoothing noisy point-wise estimates, and (2) a progressive horizon extension strategy enabling gradual policy evolution. EVOLVE-VLA achieves substantial gains: +8.6\% on long-horizon tasks, +22.0\% in 1-shot learning, and enables cross-task generalization -- achieving 20.8\% success on unseen tasks without task-specific demonstrations training (vs. 0\% for pure SFT). Qualitative analysis reveals emergent capabilities absent in demonstrations, including error recovery and novel strategies. This work represents a critical step toward VLAs that truly learn and adapt, moving beyond static imitation toward continuous self-improvements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14666</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:26:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast and Accurate Causal Parallel Decoding using Jacobi Forcing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14681</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14681.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lanxiang Hu, Siqi Kou, Yichao Fu, Samyam Rajbhandari, Tajana Rosing, Yuxiong He, Zhijie Deng, Hao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-token generation has emerged as a promising paradigm for accelerating transformer-based large model inference. Recent efforts primarily explore diffusion Large Language Models (dLLMs) for parallel decoding to reduce inference latency. To achieve AR-level generation quality, many techniques adapt AR models into dLLMs to enable parallel decoding. However, they suffer from limited speedup compared to AR models due to a pretrain-to-posttrain mismatch. Specifically, the masked data distribution in post-training deviates significantly from the real-world data distribution seen during pretraining, and dLLMs rely on bidirectional attention, which conflicts with the causal prior learned during pretraining and hinders the integration of exact KV cache reuse. To address this, we introduce Jacobi Forcing, a progressive distillation paradigm where models are trained on their own generated parallel decoding trajectories, smoothly shifting AR models into efficient parallel decoders while preserving their pretrained causal inference property. The models trained under this paradigm, Jacobi Forcing Model, achieves 3.8x wall-clock speedup on coding and math benchmarks with minimal loss in performance. Based on Jacobi Forcing Models' trajectory characteristics, we introduce multi-block decoding with rejection recycling, which enables up to 4.5x higher token acceptance count per iteration and nearly 4.0x wall-clock speedup, effectively trading additional compute for lower inference latency. Our code is available at https://github.com/hao-ai-lab/JacobiForcing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14681</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:45:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMGR: Multi-Modal Generative Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14691</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14691.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zefan Cai, Haoyi Qiu, Tianyi Ma, Haozhe Zhao, Gengze Zhou, Kung-Hsiang Huang, Parisa Kordjamshidi, Minjia Zhang, Xiao Wen, Jiuxiang Gu, Nanyun Peng, Junjie Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 112&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video foundation models generate visually realistic and temporally coherent content, but their reliability as world simulators depends on whether they capture physical, logical, and spatial constraints. Existing metrics such as Frechet Video Distance (FVD) emphasize perceptual quality and overlook reasoning failures, including violations of causality, physics, and global consistency. We introduce MMGR (Multi-Modal Generative Reasoning Evaluation and Benchmark), a principled evaluation framework based on five reasoning abilities: Physical, Logical, 3D Spatial, 2D Spatial, and Temporal. MMGR evaluates generative reasoning across three domains: Abstract Reasoning (ARC-AGI, Sudoku), Embodied Navigation (real-world 3D navigation and localization), and Physical Commonsense (sports and compositional interactions). MMGR applies fine-grained metrics that require holistic correctness across both video and image generation. We benchmark leading video models (Veo-3, Sora-2, Wan-2.2) and image models (Nano-banana, Nano-banana Pro, GPT-4o-image, Qwen-image), revealing strong performance gaps across domains. Models show moderate success on Physical Commonsense tasks but perform poorly on Abstract Reasoning (below 10 percent accuracy on ARC-AGI) and struggle with long-horizon spatial planning in embodied settings. Our analysis highlights key limitations in current models, including overreliance on perceptual data, weak global state consistency, and objectives that reward visual plausibility over causal correctness. MMGR offers a unified diagnostic benchmark and a path toward reasoning-aware generative world models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14691</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Reasoning Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14693</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14693.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zitian Gao, Lynx Chen, Yihao Xiao, He Xing, Ran Tao, Haoming Luo, Joey Zhou, Bryan Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal transformers (UTs) have been widely used for complex reasoning tasks such as ARC-AGI and Sudoku, yet the specific sources of their performance gains remain underexplored. In this work, we systematically analyze UTs variants and show that improvements on ARC-AGI primarily arise from the recurrent inductive bias and strong nonlinear components of Transformer, rather than from elaborate architectural designs. Motivated by this finding, we propose the Universal Reasoning Model (URM), which enhances the UT with short convolution and truncated backpropagation. Our approach substantially improves reasoning performance, achieving state-of-the-art 53.8% pass@1 on ARC-AGI 1 and 16.0% pass@1 on ARC-AGI 2. Our code is avaliable at https://github.com/zitian-gao/URM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14693</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CRISP: Contact-Guided Real2Sim from Monocular Video with Planar Scene Primitives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14696</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14696.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihan Wang, Jiashun Wang, Jeff Tan, Yiwen Zhao, Jessica Hodgins, Shubham Tulsiani, Deva Ramanan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce CRISP, a method that recovers simulatable human motion and scene geometry from monocular video. Prior work on joint human-scene reconstruction relies on data-driven priors and joint optimization with no physics in the loop, or recovers noisy geometry with artifacts that cause motion tracking policies with scene interactions to fail. In contrast, our key insight is to recover convex, clean, and simulation-ready geometry by fitting planar primitives to a point cloud reconstruction of the scene, via a simple clustering pipeline over depth, normals, and flow. To reconstruct scene geometry that might be occluded during interactions, we make use of human-scene contact modeling (e.g., we use human posture to reconstruct the occluded seat of a chair). Finally, we ensure that human and scene reconstructions are physically-plausible by using them to drive a humanoid controller via reinforcement learning. Our approach reduces motion tracking failure rates from 55.2\% to 6.9\% on human-centric video benchmarks (EMDB, PROX), while delivering a 43\% faster RL simulation throughput. We further validate it on in-the-wild videos including casually-captured videos, Internet videos, and even Sora-generated videos. This demonstrates CRISP's ability to generate physically-valid human motion and interaction environments at scale, greatly advancing real-to-sim applications for robotics and AR/VR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14696</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:59:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spherical Leech Quantization for Visual Tokenization and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14697</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14697.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yue Zhao, Hanwen Jiang, Zhenlin Xu, Chutong Yang, Ehsan Adeli, Philipp Krähenbühl&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Non-parametric quantization has received much attention due to its efficiency on parameters and scalability to a large codebook. In this paper, we present a unified formulation of different non-parametric quantization methods through the lens of lattice coding. The geometry of lattice codes explains the necessity of auxiliary loss terms when training auto-encoders with certain existing lookup-free quantization variants such as BSQ. As a step forward, we explore a few possible candidates, including random lattices, generalized Fibonacci lattices, and densest sphere packing lattices. Among all, we find the Leech lattice-based quantization method, which is dubbed as Spherical Leech Quantization (Λ_{24}-SQ), leads to both a simplified training recipe and an improved reconstruction-compression tradeoff thanks to its high symmetry and even distribution on the hypersphere. In image tokenization and compression tasks, this quantization approach achieves better reconstruction quality across all metrics than BSQ, the best prior art, while consuming slightly fewer bits. The improvement also extends to state-of-the-art auto-regressive image generation frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14697</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TimeLens: Rethinking Video Temporal Grounding with Multimodal LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14698</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14698.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jun Zhang, Teng Wang, Yuying Ge, Yixiao Ge, Xinhao Li, Ying Shan, Limin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper does not introduce a novel method but instead establishes a straightforward, incremental, yet essential baseline for video temporal grounding (VTG), a core capability in video understanding. While multimodal large language models (MLLMs) excel at various video understanding tasks, the recipes for optimizing them for VTG remain under-explored. In this paper, we present TimeLens, a systematic investigation into building MLLMs with strong VTG ability, along two primary dimensions: data quality and algorithmic design. We first expose critical quality issues in existing VTG benchmarks and introduce TimeLens-Bench, comprising meticulously re-annotated versions of three popular benchmarks with strict quality criteria. Our analysis reveals dramatic model re-rankings compared to legacy benchmarks, confirming the unreliability of prior evaluation standards. We also address noisy training data through an automated re-annotation pipeline, yielding TimeLens-100K, a large-scale, high-quality training dataset. Building on our data foundation, we conduct in-depth explorations of algorithmic design principles, yielding a series of meaningful insights and effective yet efficient practices. These include interleaved textual encoding for time representation, a thinking-free reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) approach as the training paradigm, and carefully designed recipes for RLVR training. These efforts culminate in TimeLens models, a family of MLLMs with state-of-the-art VTG performance among open-source models and even surpass proprietary models such as GPT-5 and Gemini-2.5-Flash. All codes, data, and models will be released to facilitate future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14698</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MemFlow: Flowing Adaptive Memory for Consistent and Efficient Long Video Narratives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14699</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14699.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sihui Ji, Xi Chen, Shuai Yang, Xin Tao, Pengfei Wan, Hengshuang Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The core challenge for streaming video generation is maintaining the content consistency in long context, which poses high requirement for the memory design. Most existing solutions maintain the memory by compressing historical frames with predefined strategies. However, different to-generate video chunks should refer to different historical cues, which is hard to satisfy with fixed strategies. In this work, we propose MemFlow to address this problem. Specifically, before generating the coming chunk, we dynamically update the memory bank by retrieving the most relevant historical frames with the text prompt of this chunk. This design enables narrative coherence even if new event happens or scenario switches in future frames. In addition, during generation, we only activate the most relevant tokens in the memory bank for each query in the attention layers, which effectively guarantees the generation efficiency. In this way, MemFlow achieves outstanding long-context consistency with negligible computation burden (7.9% speed reduction compared with the memory-free baseline) and keeps the compatibility with any streaming video generation model with KV cache.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14699</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Puzzle Curriculum GRPO for Vision-Centric Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14944</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.14944.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ahmadreza Jeddi, Hakki Can Karaimer, Hue Nguyen, Zhongling Wang, Ke Zhao, Javad Rajabi, Ran Zhang, Raghav Goyal, Babak Taati, Radek Grzeszczuk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reinforcement learning (RL) approaches like outcome-supervised GRPO have advanced chain-of-thought reasoning in Vision Language Models (VLMs), yet key issues linger: (i) reliance on costly and noisy hand-curated annotations or external verifiers; (ii) flat and sparse reward schemes in GRPO; and (iii) logical inconsistency between a chain's reasoning and its final answer. We present Puzzle Curriculum GRPO (PC-GRPO), a supervision-free recipe for RL with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) that strengthens visual reasoning in VLMs without annotations or external verifiers. PC-GRPO replaces labels with three self-supervised puzzle environments: PatchFit, Rotation (with binary rewards) and Jigsaw (with graded partial credit mitigating reward sparsity). To counter flat rewards and vanishing group-relative advantages, we introduce a difficulty-aware curriculum that dynamically weights samples and peaks at medium difficulty. We further monitor Reasoning-Answer Consistency (RAC) during post-training: mirroring reports for vanilla GRPO in LLMs, RAC typically rises early then degrades; our curriculum delays this decline, and consistency-enforcing reward schemes further boost RAC. RAC correlates with downstream accuracy. Across diverse benchmarks and on Qwen-7B and Qwen-3B backbones, PC-GRPO improves reasoning quality, training stability, and end-task accuracy, offering a practical path to scalable, verifiable, and interpretable RL post-training for VLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14944</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 22:17:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Nano Banana Pro a Low-Level Vision All-Rounder? A Comprehensive Evaluation on 14 Tasks and 40 Datasets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15110</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15110.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jialong Zuo, Haoyou Deng, Hanyu Zhou, Jiaxin Zhu, Yicheng Zhang, Yiwei Zhang, Yongxin Yan, Kaixing Huang, Weisen Chen, Yongtai Deng, Rui Jin, Nong Sang, Changxin Gao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid evolution of text-to-image generation models has revolutionized visual content creation. While commercial products like Nano Banana Pro have garnered significant attention, their potential as generalist solvers for traditional low-level vision challenges remains largely underexplored. In this study, we investigate the critical question: Is Nano Banana Pro a Low-Level Vision All-Rounder? We conducted a comprehensive zero-shot evaluation across 14 distinct low-level tasks spanning 40 diverse datasets. By utilizing simple textual prompts without fine-tuning, we benchmarked Nano Banana Pro against state-of-the-art specialist models. Our extensive analysis reveals a distinct performance dichotomy: while Nano Banana Pro demonstrates superior subjective visual quality, often hallucinating plausible high-frequency details that surpass specialist models, it lags behind in traditional reference-based quantitative metrics. We attribute this discrepancy to the inherent stochasticity of generative models, which struggle to maintain the strict pixel-level consistency required by conventional metrics. This report identifies Nano Banana Pro as a capable zero-shot contender for low-level vision tasks, while highlighting that achieving the high fidelity of domain specialists remains a significant hurdle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15110</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 06:02:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DEER: Draft with Diffusion, Verify with Autoregressive Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15176</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15176.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zicong Cheng, Guo-Wei Yang, Jia Li, Zhijie Deng, Meng-Hao Guo, Shi-Min Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Efficiency, as a critical practical challenge for LLM-driven agentic and reasoning systems, is increasingly constrained by the inherent latency of autoregressive (AR) decoding. Speculative decoding mitigates this cost through a draft-verify scheme, yet existing approaches rely on AR draft models (a.k.a., drafters), which introduce two fundamental issues: (1) step-wise uncertainty accumulation leads to a progressive collapse of trust between the target model and the drafter, and (2) inherently sequential decoding of AR drafters. Together, these factors cause limited speedups. In this paper, we show that a diffusion large language model (dLLM) drafters can naturally overcome these issues through its fundamentally different probabilistic modeling and efficient parallel decoding strategy. Building on this insight, we introduce DEER, an efficient speculative decoding framework that drafts with diffusion and verifies with AR models. To enable high-quality drafting, DEER employs a two-stage training pipeline to align the dLLM-based drafters with the target AR model, and further adopts single-step decoding to generate long draft segments. Experiments show DEER reaches draft acceptance lengths of up to 32 tokens, far surpassing the 10 tokens achieved by EAGLE-3. Moreover, on HumanEval with Qwen3-30B-A3B, DEER attains a 5.54x speedup, while EAGLE-3 achieves only 2.41x. Code, model, demo, etc, will be available at https://czc726.github.io/DEER/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15176</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 08:19:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust and Calibrated Detection of Authentic Multimedia Content</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15182</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15182.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sarim Hashmi, Abdelrahman Elsayed, Mohammed Talha Alam, Samuele Poppi, Nils Lukas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative models can synthesize highly realistic content, so-called deepfakes, that are already being misused at scale to undermine digital media authenticity. Current deepfake detection methods are unreliable for two reasons: (i) distinguishing inauthentic content post-hoc is often impossible (e.g., with memorized samples), leading to an unbounded false positive rate (FPR); and (ii) detection lacks robustness, as adversaries can adapt to known detectors with near-perfect accuracy using minimal computational resources. To address these limitations, we propose a resynthesis framework to determine if a sample is authentic or if its authenticity can be plausibly denied. We make two key contributions focusing on the high-precision, low-recall setting against efficient (i.e., compute-restricted) adversaries. First, we demonstrate that our calibrated resynthesis method is the most reliable approach for verifying authentic samples while maintaining controllable, low FPRs. Second, we show that our method achieves adversarial robustness against efficient adversaries, whereas prior methods are easily evaded under identical compute budgets. Our approach supports multiple modalities and leverages state-of-the-art inversion techniques.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15182</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 08:31:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step-GUI Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15431</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15431.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haolong Yan, Jia Wang, Xin Huang, Yeqing Shen, Ziyang Meng, Zhimin Fan, Kaijun Tan, Jin Gao, Lieyu Shi, Mi Yang, Shiliang Yang, Zhirui Wang, Brian Li, Kang An, Chenyang Li, Lei Lei, Mengmeng Duan, Danxun Liang, Guodong Liu, Hang Cheng, Hao Wu, Jie Dong, Junhao Huang, Mei Chen, Renjie Yu, Shunshan Li, Xu Zhou, Yiting Dai, Yineng Deng, Yingdan Liang, Zelin Chen, Wen Sun, Chengxu Yan, Chunqin Xu, Dong Li, Fengqiong Xiao, Guanghao Fan, Guopeng Li, Guozhen Peng, Hongbing Li, Hang Li, Hongming Chen, Jingjing Xie, Jianyong Li, Jingyang Zhang, Jiaju Ren, Jiayu Yuan, Jianpeng Yin, Kai Cao, Liang Zhao, Liguo Tan, Liying Shi, Mengqiang Ren, Min Xu, Manjiao Liu, Mao Luo, Mingxin Wan, Na Wang, Nan Wu, Ning Wang, Peiyao Ma, Qingzhou Zhang, Qiao Wang, Qinlin Zeng, Qiong Gao, Qiongyao Li, Shangwu Zhong, Shuli Gao, Shaofan Liu, Shisi Gao, Shuang Luo, Xingbin Liu, Xiaojia Liu, Xiaojie Hou, Xin Liu, Xuanti Feng, Xuedan Cai, Xuan Wen, Xianwei Zhu, Xin Liang, Xin Liu, Xin Zhou, Yingxiu Zhao, Yukang Shi, Yunfang Xu, Yuqing Zeng, Yixun Zhang, Zejia Weng, Zhonghao Yan, Zhiguo Huang, Zhuoyu Wang, Zheng Ge, Jing Li, Yibo Zhu, Binxing Jiao, Xiangyu Zhang, Daxin Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 118&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal large language models unlock unprecedented opportunities for GUI automation. However, a fundamental challenge remains: how to efficiently acquire high-quality training data while maintaining annotation reliability? We introduce a self-evolving training pipeline powered by the Calibrated Step Reward System, which converts model-generated trajectories into reliable training signals through trajectory-level calibration, achieving &gt;90% annotation accuracy with 10-100x lower cost. Leveraging this pipeline, we introduce Step-GUI, a family of models (4B/8B) that achieves state-of-the-art GUI performance (8B: 80.2% AndroidWorld, 48.5% OSWorld, 62.6% ScreenShot-Pro) while maintaining robust general capabilities. As GUI agent capabilities improve, practical deployment demands standardized interfaces across heterogeneous devices while protecting user privacy. To this end, we propose GUI-MCP, the first Model Context Protocol for GUI automation with hierarchical architecture that combines low-level atomic operations and high-level task delegation to local specialist models, enabling high-privacy execution where sensitive data stays on-device. Finally, to assess whether agents can handle authentic everyday usage, we introduce AndroidDaily, a benchmark grounded in real-world mobile usage patterns with 3146 static actions and 235 end-to-end tasks across high-frequency daily scenarios (8B: static 89.91%, end-to-end 52.50%). Our work advances the development of practical GUI agents and demonstrates strong potential for real-world deployment in everyday digital interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15431</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 13:26:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qwen-Image-Layered: Towards Inherent Editability via Layer Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15603</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15603.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shengming Yin, Zekai Zhang, Zecheng Tang, Kaiyuan Gao, Xiao Xu, Kun Yan, Jiahao Li, Yilei Chen, Yuxiang Chen, Heung-Yeung Shum, Lionel M. Ni, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin, Chenfei Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent visual generative models often struggle with consistency during image editing due to the entangled nature of raster images, where all visual content is fused into a single canvas. In contrast, professional design tools employ layered representations, allowing isolated edits while preserving consistency. Motivated by this, we propose Qwen-Image-Layered, an end-to-end diffusion model that decomposes a single RGB image into multiple semantically disentangled RGBA layers, enabling inherent editability, where each RGBA layer can be independently manipulated without affecting other content. To support variable-length decomposition, we introduce three key components: (1) an RGBA-VAE to unify the latent representations of RGB and RGBA images; (2) a VLD-MMDiT (Variable Layers Decomposition MMDiT) architecture capable of decomposing a variable number of image layers; and (3) a Multi-stage Training strategy to adapt a pretrained image generation model into a multilayer image decomposer. Furthermore, to address the scarcity of high-quality multilayer training images, we build a pipeline to extract and annotate multilayer images from Photoshop documents (PSD). Experiments demonstrate that our method significantly surpasses existing approaches in decomposition quality and establishes a new paradigm for consistent image editing. Our code and models are released on https://github.com/QwenLM/Qwen-Image-Layered{https://github.com/QwenLM/Qwen-Image-Layered}&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15603</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 17:12:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IC-Effect: Precise and Efficient Video Effects Editing via In-Context Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15635</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15635.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuanhang Li, Yiren Song, Junzhe Bai, Xinran Liang, Hu Yang, Libiao Jin, Qi Mao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose IC-Effect, an instruction-guided, DiT-based framework for few-shot video VFX editing that synthesizes complex effects (\eg flames, particles and cartoon characters) while strictly preserving spatial and temporal consistency. Video VFX editing is highly challenging because injected effects must blend seamlessly with the background, the background must remain entirely unchanged, and effect patterns must be learned efficiently from limited paired data. However, existing video editing models fail to satisfy these requirements. IC-Effect leverages the source video as clean contextual conditions, exploiting the contextual learning capability of DiT models to achieve precise background preservation and natural effect injection. A two-stage training strategy, consisting of general editing adaptation followed by effect-specific learning via Effect-LoRA, ensures strong instruction following and robust effect modeling. To further improve efficiency, we introduce spatiotemporal sparse tokenization, enabling high fidelity with substantially reduced computation. We also release a paired VFX editing dataset spanning 15 high-quality visual styles. Extensive experiments show that IC-Effect delivers high-quality, controllable, and temporally consistent VFX editing, opening new possibilities for video creation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15635</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 17:47:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VTCBench: Can Vision-Language Models Understand Long Context with Vision-Text Compression?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15649</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15649.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongbo Zhao, Meng Wang, Fei Zhu, Wenzhuo Liu, Bolin Ni, Fanhu Zeng, Gaofeng Meng, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The computational and memory overheads associated with expanding the context window of LLMs severely limit their scalability. A noteworthy solution is vision-text compression (VTC), exemplified by frameworks like DeepSeek-OCR and Glyph, which convert long texts into dense 2D visual representations, thereby achieving token compression ratios of 3x-20x. However, the impact of this high information density on the core long-context capabilities of vision-language models (VLMs) remains under-investigated. To address this gap, we introduce the first benchmark for VTC and systematically assess the performance of VLMs across three long-context understanding settings: VTC-Retrieval, which evaluates the model's ability to retrieve and aggregate information; VTC-Reasoning, which requires models to infer latent associations to locate facts with minimal lexical overlap; and VTC-Memory, which measures comprehensive question answering within long-term dialogue memory. Furthermore, we establish the VTCBench-Wild to simulate diverse input scenarios.We comprehensively evaluate leading open-source and proprietary models on our benchmarks. The results indicate that, despite being able to decode textual information (e.g., OCR) well, most VLMs exhibit a surprisingly poor long-context understanding ability with VTC-compressed information, failing to capture long associations or dependencies in the context.This study provides a deep understanding of VTC and serves as a foundation for designing more efficient and scalable VLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15649</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 17:58:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can LLMs Guide Their Own Exploration? Gradient-Guided Reinforcement Learning for LLM Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15687</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15687.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenwen Liang, Sidi Lu, Wenhao Yu, Kishan Panaganti, Yujun Zhou, Haitao Mi, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning has become essential for strengthening the reasoning abilities of large language models, yet current exploration mechanisms remain fundamentally misaligned with how these models actually learn. Entropy bonuses and external semantic comparators encourage surface level variation but offer no guarantee that sampled trajectories differ in the update directions that shape optimization. We propose G2RL, a gradient guided reinforcement learning framework in which exploration is driven not by external heuristics but by the model own first order update geometry. For each response, G2RL constructs a sequence level feature from the model final layer sensitivity, obtainable at negligible cost from a standard forward pass, and measures how each trajectory would reshape the policy by comparing these features within a sampled group. Trajectories that introduce novel gradient directions receive a bounded multiplicative reward scaler, while redundant or off manifold updates are deemphasized, yielding a self referential exploration signal that is naturally aligned with PPO style stability and KL control. Across math and general reasoning benchmarks (MATH500, AMC, AIME24, AIME25, GPQA, MMLUpro) on Qwen3 base 1.7B and 4B models, G2RL consistently improves pass@1, maj@16, and pass@k over entropy based GRPO and external embedding methods. Analyzing the induced geometry, we find that G2RL expands exploration into substantially more orthogonal and often opposing gradient directions while maintaining semantic coherence, revealing that a policy own update space provides a far more faithful and effective basis for guiding exploration in large language model reinforcement learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15687</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 18:44:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skyra: AI-Generated Video Detection via Grounded Artifact Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15693</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15693.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifei Li, Wenzhao Zheng, Yanran Zhang, Runze Sun, Yu Zheng, Lei Chen, Jie Zhou, Jiwen Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The misuse of AI-driven video generation technologies has raised serious social concerns, highlighting the urgent need for reliable AI-generated video detectors. However, most existing methods are limited to binary classification and lack the necessary explanations for human interpretation. In this paper, we present Skyra, a specialized multimodal large language model (MLLM) that identifies human-perceivable visual artifacts in AI-generated videos and leverages them as grounded evidence for both detection and explanation. To support this objective, we construct ViF-CoT-4K for Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT), which represents the first large-scale AI-generated video artifact dataset with fine-grained human annotations. We then develop a two-stage training strategy that systematically enhances our model's spatio-temporal artifact perception, explanation capability, and detection accuracy. To comprehensively evaluate Skyra, we introduce ViF-Bench, a benchmark comprising 3K high-quality samples generated by over ten state-of-the-art video generators. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Skyra surpasses existing methods across multiple benchmarks, while our evaluation yields valuable insights for advancing explainable AI-generated video detection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15693</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 18:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End-to-End Training for Autoregressive Video Diffusion via Self-Resampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15702</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15702.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuwei Guo, Ceyuan Yang, Hao He, Yang Zhao, Meng Wei, Zhenheng Yang, Weilin Huang, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autoregressive video diffusion models hold promise for world simulation but are vulnerable to exposure bias arising from the train-test mismatch. While recent works address this via post-training, they typically rely on a bidirectional teacher model or online discriminator. To achieve an end-to-end solution, we introduce Resampling Forcing, a teacher-free framework that enables training autoregressive video models from scratch and at scale. Central to our approach is a self-resampling scheme that simulates inference-time model errors on history frames during training. Conditioned on these degraded histories, a sparse causal mask enforces temporal causality while enabling parallel training with frame-level diffusion loss. To facilitate efficient long-horizon generation, we further introduce history routing, a parameter-free mechanism that dynamically retrieves the top-k most relevant history frames for each query. Experiments demonstrate that our approach achieves performance comparable to distillation-based baselines while exhibiting superior temporal consistency on longer videos owing to native-length training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15702</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 18:53:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiffusionVL: Translating Any Autoregressive Models into Diffusion Vision Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15713</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15713.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lunbin Zeng, Jingfeng Yao, Bencheng Liao, Hongyuan Tao, Wenyu Liu, Xinggang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In recent multimodal research, the diffusion paradigm has emerged as a promising alternative to the autoregressive paradigm (AR), owing to its unique decoding advantages. However, due to the capability limitations of the base diffusion language model, the performance of the diffusion vision language model (dVLM) still lags significantly behind that of mainstream models. This leads to a simple yet fundamental question: Is it possible to construct dVLMs based on existing powerful AR models? In response, we propose DiffusionVL, a dVLM family that could be translated from any powerful AR models. Through simple fine-tuning, we successfully adapt AR pre-trained models into the diffusion paradigm. This approach yields two key observations: (1) The paradigm shift from AR-based multimodal models to diffusion is remarkably effective. (2) Direct conversion of an AR language model to a dVLM is also feasible, achieving performance competitive with LLaVA-style visual-instruction-tuning. Further, we introduce a block-decoding design into dVLMs that supports arbitrary-length generation and KV cache reuse, achieving a significant inference speedup. We conduct a large number of experiments. Despite training with less than 5% of the data required by prior methods, DiffusionVL achieves a comprehensive performance improvement-a 34.4% gain on the MMMU-Pro (vision) bench and 37.5% gain on the MME (Cog.) bench-alongside a 2x inference speedup. The model and code are released at https://github.com/hustvl/DiffusionVL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15713</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 18:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In Pursuit of Pixel Supervision for Visual Pre-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15715</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.15715.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lihe Yang, Shang-Wen Li, Yang Li, Xinjie Lei, Dong Wang, Abdelrahman Mohamed, Hengshuang Zhao, Hu Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; At the most basic level, pixels are the source of the visual information through which we perceive the world. Pixels contain information at all levels, ranging from low-level attributes to high-level concepts. Autoencoders represent a classical and long-standing paradigm for learning representations from pixels or other raw inputs. In this work, we demonstrate that autoencoder-based self-supervised learning remains competitive today and can produce strong representations for downstream tasks, while remaining simple, stable, and efficient. Our model, codenamed "Pixio", is an enhanced masked autoencoder (MAE) with more challenging pre-training tasks and more capable architectures. The model is trained on 2B web-crawled images with a self-curation strategy with minimal human curation. Pixio performs competitively across a wide range of downstream tasks in the wild, including monocular depth estimation (e.g., Depth Anything), feed-forward 3D reconstruction (i.e., MapAnything), semantic segmentation, and robot learning, outperforming or matching DINOv3 trained at similar scales. Our results suggest that pixel-space self-supervised learning can serve as a promising alternative and a complement to latent-space approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.15715</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 18:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptation of Agentic AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16301</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16301.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengcheng Jiang, Jiacheng Lin, Zhiyi Shi, Zifeng Wang, Luxi He, Yichen Wu, Ming Zhong, Peiyang Song, Qizheng Zhang, Heng Wang, Xueqiang Xu, Hanwen Xu, Pengrui Han, Dylan Zhang, Jiashuo Sun, Chaoqi Yang, Kun Qian, Tian Wang, Changran Hu, Manling Li, Quanzheng Li, Hao Peng, Sheng Wang, Jingbo Shang, Chao Zhang, Jiaxuan You, Liyuan Liu, Pan Lu, Yu Zhang, Heng Ji, Yejin Choi, Dawn Song, Jimeng Sun, Jiawei Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Cutting-edge agentic AI systems are built on foundation models that can be adapted to plan, reason, and interact with external tools to perform increasingly complex and specialized tasks. As these systems grow in capability and scope, adaptation becomes a central mechanism for improving performance, reliability, and generalization. In this paper, we unify the rapidly expanding research landscape into a systematic framework that spans both agent adaptations and tool adaptations. We further decompose these into tool-execution-signaled and agent-output-signaled forms of agent adaptation, as well as agent-agnostic and agent-supervised forms of tool adaptation. We demonstrate that this framework helps clarify the design space of adaptation strategies in agentic AI, makes their trade-offs explicit, and provides practical guidance for selecting or switching among strategies during system design. We then review the representative approaches in each category, analyze their strengths and limitations, and highlight key open challenges and future opportunities. Overall, this paper aims to offer a conceptual foundation and practical roadmap for researchers and practitioners seeking to build more capable, efficient, and reliable agentic AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16301</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 08:38:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VenusBench-GD: A Comprehensive Multi-Platform GUI Benchmark for Diverse Grounding Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16501</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16501.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Beitong Zhou, Zhexiao Huang, Yuan Guo, Zhangxuan Gu, Tianyu Xia, Zichen Luo, Fei Tang, Dehan Kong, Yanyi Shang, Suling Ou, Zhenlin Guo, Changhua Meng, Shuheng Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; GUI grounding is a critical component in building capable GUI agents. However, existing grounding benchmarks suffer from significant limitations: they either provide insufficient data volume and narrow domain coverage, or focus excessively on a single platform and require highly specialized domain knowledge. In this work, we present VenusBench-GD, a comprehensive, bilingual benchmark for GUI grounding that spans multiple platforms, enabling hierarchical evaluation for real-word applications. VenusBench-GD contributes as follows: (i) we introduce a large-scale, cross-platform benchmark with extensive coverage of applications, diverse UI elements, and rich annotated data, (ii) we establish a high-quality data construction pipeline for grounding tasks, achieving higher annotation accuracy than existing benchmarks, and (iii) we extend the scope of element grounding by proposing a hierarchical task taxonomy that divides grounding into basic and advanced categories, encompassing six distinct subtasks designed to evaluate models from complementary perspectives. Our experimental findings reveal critical insights: general-purpose multimodal models now match or even surpass specialized GUI models on basic grounding tasks. In contrast, advanced tasks, still favor GUI-specialized models, though they exhibit significant overfitting and poor robustness. These results underscore the necessity of comprehensive, multi-tiered evaluation frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16501</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 13:09:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>N3D-VLM: Native 3D Grounding Enables Accurate Spatial Reasoning in Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16561</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16561.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxin Wang, Lei Ke, Boqiang Zhang, Tianyuan Qu, Hanxun Yu, Zhenpeng Huang, Meng Yu, Dan Xu, Dong Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While current multimodal models can answer questions based on 2D images, they lack intrinsic 3D object perception, limiting their ability to comprehend spatial relationships and depth cues in 3D scenes. In this work, we propose N3D-VLM, a novel unified framework that seamlessly integrates native 3D object perception with 3D-aware visual reasoning, enabling both precise 3D grounding and interpretable spatial understanding. Unlike conventional end-to-end models that directly predict answers from RGB/RGB-D inputs, our approach equips the model with native 3D object perception capabilities, enabling it to directly localize objects in 3D space based on textual descriptions. Building upon accurate 3D object localization, the model further performs explicit reasoning in 3D, achieving more interpretable and structured spatial understanding. To support robust training for these capabilities, we develop a scalable data construction pipeline that leverages depth estimation to lift large-scale 2D annotations into 3D space, significantly increasing the diversity and coverage for 3D object grounding data, yielding over six times larger than the largest existing single-image 3D detection dataset. Moreover, the pipeline generates spatial question-answering datasets that target chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning in 3D, facilitating joint training for both 3D object localization and 3D spatial reasoning. Experimental results demonstrate that our unified framework not only achieves state-of-the-art performance on 3D grounding tasks, but also consistently surpasses existing methods in 3D spatial reasoning in vision-language model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16561</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 14:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeContext as Defense: Safe Image Editing in Diffusion Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16625</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16625.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Linghui Shen, Mingyue Cui, Xingyi Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In-context diffusion models allow users to modify images with remarkable ease and realism. However, the same power raises serious privacy concerns: personal images can be easily manipulated for identity impersonation, misinformation, or other malicious uses, all without the owner's consent. While prior work has explored input perturbations to protect against misuse in personalized text-to-image generation, the robustness of modern, large-scale in-context DiT-based models remains largely unexamined. In this paper, we propose DeContext, a new method to safeguard input images from unauthorized in-context editing. Our key insight is that contextual information from the source image propagates to the output primarily through multimodal attention layers. By injecting small, targeted perturbations that weaken these cross-attention pathways, DeContext breaks this flow, effectively decouples the link between input and output. This simple defense is both efficient and robust. We further show that early denoising steps and specific transformer blocks dominate context propagation, which allows us to concentrate perturbations where they matter most. Experiments on Flux Kontext and Step1X-Edit show that DeContext consistently blocks unwanted image edits while preserving visual quality. These results highlight the effectiveness of attention-based perturbations as a powerful defense against image manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16625</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 15:01:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>REGLUE Your Latents with Global and Local Semantics for Entangled Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16636</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16636.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Giorgos Petsangourakis, Christos Sgouropoulos, Bill Psomas, Theodoros Giannakopoulos, Giorgos Sfikas, Ioannis Kakogeorgiou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Latent diffusion models (LDMs) achieve state-of-the-art image synthesis, yet their reconstruction-style denoising objective provides only indirect semantic supervision: high-level semantics emerge slowly, requiring longer training and limiting sample quality. Recent works inject semantics from Vision Foundation Models (VFMs) either externally via representation alignment or internally by jointly modeling only a narrow slice of VFM features inside the diffusion process, under-utilizing the rich, nonlinear, multi-layer spatial semantics available. We introduce REGLUE (Representation Entanglement with Global-Local Unified Encoding), a unified latent diffusion framework that jointly models (i) VAE image latents, (ii) compact local (patch-level) VFM semantics, and (iii) a global (image-level) [CLS] token within a single SiT backbone. A lightweight convolutional semantic compressor nonlinearly aggregates multi-layer VFM features into a low-dimensional, spatially structured representation, which is entangled with the VAE latents in the diffusion process. An external alignment loss further regularizes internal representations toward frozen VFM targets. On ImageNet 256x256, REGLUE consistently improves FID and accelerates convergence over SiT-B/2 and SiT-XL/2 baselines, as well as over REPA, ReDi, and REG. Extensive experiments show that (a) spatial VFM semantics are crucial, (b) non-linear compression is key to unlocking their full benefit, and (c) global tokens and external alignment act as complementary, lightweight enhancements within our global-local-latent joint modeling framework. The code is available at https://github.com/giorgospets/reglue .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16636</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 15:10:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JustRL: Scaling a 1.5B LLM with a Simple RL Recipe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16649</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16649.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bingxiang He, Zekai Qu, Zeyuan Liu, Yinghao Chen, Yuxin Zuo, Cheng Qian, Kaiyan Zhang, Weize Chen, Chaojun Xiao, Ganqu Cui, Ning Ding, Zhiyuan Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in reinforcement learning for large language models have converged on increasing complexity: multi-stage training pipelines, dynamic hyperparameter schedules, and curriculum learning strategies. This raises a fundamental question: Is this complexity necessary? We present JustRL, a minimal approach using single-stage training with fixed hyperparameters that achieves state-of-the-art performance on two 1.5B reasoning models (54.9\% and 64.3\% average accuracy across nine mathematical benchmarks) while using 2times less compute than sophisticated approaches. The same hyperparameters transfer across both models without tuning, and training exhibits smooth, monotonic improvement over 4,000+ steps without the collapses or plateaus that typically motivate interventions. Critically, ablations reveal that adding ``standard tricks'' like explicit length penalties and robust verifiers may degrade performance by collapsing exploration. These results suggest that the field may be adding complexity to solve problems that disappear with a stable, scaled-up baseline. We release our models and code to establish a simple, validated baseline for the community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16649</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 15:21:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision-Language-Action Models for Autonomous Driving: Past, Present, and Future</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16760</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16760.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianshuai Hu, Xiaolu Liu, Song Wang, Yiyao Zhu, Ao Liang, Lingdong Kong, Guoyang Zhao, Zeying Gong, Jun Cen, Zhiyu Huang, Xiaoshuai Hao, Linfeng Li, Hang Song, Xiangtai Li, Jun Ma, Shaojie Shen, Jianke Zhu, Dacheng Tao, Ziwei Liu, Junwei Liang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Autonomous driving has long relied on modular "Perception-Decision-Action" pipelines, where hand-crafted interfaces and rule-based components often break down in complex or long-tailed scenarios. Their cascaded design further propagates perception errors, degrading downstream planning and control. Vision-Action (VA) models address some limitations by learning direct mappings from visual inputs to actions, but they remain opaque, sensitive to distribution shifts, and lack structured reasoning or instruction-following capabilities. Recent progress in Large Language Models (LLMs) and multimodal learning has motivated the emergence of Vision-Language-Action (VLA) frameworks, which integrate perception with language-grounded decision making. By unifying visual understanding, linguistic reasoning, and actionable outputs, VLAs offer a pathway toward more interpretable, generalizable, and human-aligned driving policies. This work provides a structured characterization of the emerging VLA landscape for autonomous driving. We trace the evolution from early VA approaches to modern VLA frameworks and organize existing methods into two principal paradigms: End-to-End VLA, which integrates perception, reasoning, and planning within a single model, and Dual-System VLA, which separates slow deliberation (via VLMs) from fast, safety-critical execution (via planners). Within these paradigms, we further distinguish subclasses such as textual vs. numerical action generators and explicit vs. implicit guidance mechanisms. We also summarize representative datasets and benchmarks for evaluating VLA-based driving systems and highlight key challenges and open directions, including robustness, interpretability, and instruction fidelity. Overall, this work aims to establish a coherent foundation for advancing human-compatible autonomous driving systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16760</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 16:57:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kling-Omni Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16776</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16776.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kling Team, Jialu Chen, Yuanzheng Ci, Xiangyu Du, Zipeng Feng, Kun Gai, Sainan Guo, Feng Han, Jingbin He, Kang He, Xiao Hu, Xiaohua Hu, Boyuan Jiang, Fangyuan Kong, Hang Li, Jie Li, Qingyu Li, Shen Li, Xiaohan Li, Yan Li, Jiajun Liang, Borui Liao, Yiqiao Liao, Weihong Lin, Quande Liu, Xiaokun Liu, Yilun Liu, Yuliang Liu, Shun Lu, Hangyu Mao, Yunyao Mao, Haodong Ouyang, Wenyu Qin, Wanqi Shi, Xiaoyu Shi, Lianghao Su, Haozhi Sun, Peiqin Sun, Pengfei Wan, Chao Wang, Chenyu Wang, Meng Wang, Qiulin Wang, Runqi Wang, Xintao Wang, Xuebo Wang, Zekun Wang, Min Wei, Tiancheng Wen, Guohao Wu, Xiaoshi Wu, Zhenhua Wu, Da Xie, Yingtong Xiong, Yulong Xu, Sile Yang, Zikang Yang, Weicai Ye, Ziyang Yuan, Shenglong Zhang, Shuaiyu Zhang, Yuanxing Zhang, Yufan Zhang, Wenzheng Zhao, Ruiliang Zhou, Yan Zhou, Guosheng Zhu, Yongjie Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 135&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Kling-Omni, a generalist generative framework designed to synthesize high-fidelity videos directly from multimodal visual language inputs. Adopting an end-to-end perspective, Kling-Omni bridges the functional separation among diverse video generation, editing, and intelligent reasoning tasks, integrating them into a holistic system. Unlike disjointed pipeline approaches, Kling-Omni supports a diverse range of user inputs, including text instructions, reference images, and video contexts, processing them into a unified multimodal representation to deliver cinematic-quality and highly-intelligent video content creation. To support these capabilities, we constructed a comprehensive data system that serves as the foundation for multimodal video creation. The framework is further empowered by efficient large-scale pre-training strategies and infrastructure optimizations for inference. Comprehensive evaluations reveal that Kling-Omni demonstrates exceptional capabilities in in-context generation, reasoning-based editing, and multimodal instruction following. Moving beyond a content creation tool, we believe Kling-Omni is a pivotal advancement toward multimodal world simulators capable of perceiving, reasoning, generating and interacting with the dynamic and complex worlds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16776</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 17:08:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RePlan: Reasoning-guided Region Planning for Complex Instruction-based Image Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16864</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16864.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyuan Qu, Lei Ke, Xiaohang Zhan, Longxiang Tang, Yuqi Liu, Bohao Peng, Bei Yu, Dong Yu, Jiaya Jia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Instruction-based image editing enables natural-language control over visual modifications, yet existing models falter under Instruction-Visual Complexity (IV-Complexity), where intricate instructions meet cluttered or ambiguous scenes. We introduce RePlan (Region-aligned Planning), a plan-then-execute framework that couples a vision-language planner with a diffusion editor. The planner decomposes instructions via step-by-step reasoning and explicitly grounds them to target regions; the editor then applies changes using a training-free attention-region injection mechanism, enabling precise, parallel multi-region edits without iterative inpainting. To strengthen planning, we apply GRPO-based reinforcement learning using 1K instruction-only examples, yielding substantial gains in reasoning fidelity and format reliability. We further present IV-Edit, a benchmark focused on fine-grained grounding and knowledge-intensive edits. Across IV-Complex settings, RePlan consistently outperforms strong baselines trained on far larger datasets, improving regional precision and overall fidelity. Our project page: https://replan-iv-edit.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16864</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:34:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal RewardBench 2: Evaluating Omni Reward Models for Interleaved Text and Image</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16899</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16899.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yushi Hu, Reyhane Askari-Hemmat, Melissa Hall, Emily Dinan, Luke Zettlemoyer, Marjan Ghazvininejad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward models (RMs) are essential for training large language models (LLMs), but remain underexplored for omni models that handle interleaved image and text sequences. We introduce Multimodal RewardBench 2 (MMRB2), the first comprehensive benchmark for reward models on multimodal understanding and (interleaved) generation. MMRB2 spans four tasks: text-to-image, image editing, interleaved generation, and multimodal reasoning ("thinking-with-images"), providing 1,000 expert-annotated preference pairs per task from 23 models and agents across 21 source tasks. MMRB2 is designed with: (1) practical but challenging prompts; (2) responses from state-of-the-art models and agents; and (3) preference pairs with strong human-expert consensus, curated via an ensemble filtering strategy. Using MMRB2, we study existing judges for each subtask, including multimodal LLM-as-a-judge and models trained with human preferences. The latest Gemini 3 Pro attains 75-80% accuracy. GPT-5 and Gemini 2.5 Pro reach 66-75% accuracy, compared to &gt;90% for humans, yet surpass the widely used GPT-4o (59%). The best performing open-source model Qwen3-VL-32B achieves similar accuracies as Gemini 2.5 Flash (64%). We also show that MMRB2 performance strongly correlates with downstream task success using Best-of-N sampling and conduct an in-depth analysis that shows key areas to improve the reward models going forward.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16899</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:56:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlashPortrait: 6x Faster Infinite Portrait Animation with Adaptive Latent Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16900</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16900.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuyuan Tu, Yueming Pan, Yinming Huang, Xintong Han, Zhen Xing, Qi Dai, Kai Qiu, Chong Luo, Zuxuan Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current diffusion-based acceleration methods for long-portrait animation struggle to ensure identity (ID) consistency. This paper presents FlashPortrait, an end-to-end video diffusion transformer capable of synthesizing ID-preserving, infinite-length videos while achieving up to 6x acceleration in inference speed. In particular, FlashPortrait begins by computing the identity-agnostic facial expression features with an off-the-shelf extractor. It then introduces a Normalized Facial Expression Block to align facial features with diffusion latents by normalizing them with their respective means and variances, thereby improving identity stability in facial modeling. During inference, FlashPortrait adopts a dynamic sliding-window scheme with weighted blending in overlapping areas, ensuring smooth transitions and ID consistency in long animations. In each context window, based on the latent variation rate at particular timesteps and the derivative magnitude ratio among diffusion layers, FlashPortrait utilizes higher-order latent derivatives at the current timestep to directly predict latents at future timesteps, thereby skipping several denoising steps and achieving 6x speed acceleration. Experiments on benchmarks show the effectiveness of FlashPortrait both qualitatively and quantitatively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16900</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:56:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alchemist: Unlocking Efficiency in Text-to-Image Model Training via Meta-Gradient Data Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16905</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16905.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaixin Ding, Yang Zhou, Xi Chen, Miao Yang, Jiarong Ou, Rui Chen, Xin Tao, Hengshuang Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Text-to-Image (T2I) generative models, such as Imagen, Stable Diffusion, and FLUX, have led to remarkable improvements in visual quality. However, their performance is fundamentally limited by the quality of training data. Web-crawled and synthetic image datasets often contain low-quality or redundant samples, which lead to degraded visual fidelity, unstable training, and inefficient computation. Hence, effective data selection is crucial for improving data efficiency. Existing approaches rely on costly manual curation or heuristic scoring based on single-dimensional features in Text-to-Image data filtering. Although meta-learning based method has been explored in LLM, there is no adaptation for image modalities. To this end, we propose **Alchemist**, a meta-gradient-based framework to select a suitable subset from large-scale text-image data pairs. Our approach automatically learns to assess the influence of each sample by iteratively optimizing the model from a data-centric perspective. Alchemist consists of two key stages: data rating and data pruning. We train a lightweight rater to estimate each sample's influence based on gradient information, enhanced with multi-granularity perception. We then use the Shift-Gsampling strategy to select informative subsets for efficient model training. Alchemist is the first automatic, scalable, meta-gradient-based data selection framework for Text-to-Image model training. Experiments on both synthetic and web-crawled datasets demonstrate that Alchemist consistently improves visual quality and downstream performance. Training on an Alchemist-selected 50% of the data can outperform training on the full dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16905</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:57:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploration v.s. Exploitation: Rethinking RLVR through Clipping, Entropy, and Spurious Reward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16912</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16912.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peter Chen, Xiaopeng Li, Ziniu Li, Wotao Yin, Xi Chen, Tianyi Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper examines the exploration-exploitation trade-off in reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR), a framework for improving the reasoning of Large Language Models (LLMs). Recent studies suggest that RLVR can elicit strong mathematical reasoning in LLMs through two seemingly paradoxical mechanisms: spurious rewards, which suppress exploitation by rewarding outcomes unrelated to the ground truth, and entropy minimization, which suppresses exploration by pushing the model toward more confident and deterministic outputs, highlighting a puzzling dynamic: both discouraging exploitation and discouraging exploration improve reasoning performance, yet the underlying principles that reconcile these effects remain poorly understood. We focus on two fundamental questions: (i) how policy entropy relates to performance, and (ii) whether spurious rewards yield gains, potentially through the interplay of clipping bias and model contamination. Our results show that clipping bias under spurious rewards reduces policy entropy, leading to more confident and deterministic outputs, while entropy minimization alone is insufficient for improvement. We further propose a reward-misalignment model explaining why spurious rewards can enhance performance beyond contaminated settings. Our findings clarify the mechanisms behind spurious-reward benefits and provide principles for more effective RLVR training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16912</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depth Any Panoramas: A Foundation Model for Panoramic Depth Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16913</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16913.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xin Lin, Meixi Song, Dizhe Zhang, Wenxuan Lu, Haodong Li, Bo Du, Ming-Hsuan Yang, Truong Nguyen, Lu Qi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we present a panoramic metric depth foundation model that generalizes across diverse scene distances. We explore a data-in-the-loop paradigm from the view of both data construction and framework design. We collect a large-scale dataset by combining public datasets, high-quality synthetic data from our UE5 simulator and text-to-image models, and real panoramic images from the web. To reduce domain gaps between indoor/outdoor and synthetic/real data, we introduce a three-stage pseudo-label curation pipeline to generate reliable ground truth for unlabeled images. For the model, we adopt DINOv3-Large as the backbone for its strong pre-trained generalization, and introduce a plug-and-play range mask head, sharpness-centric optimization, and geometry-centric optimization to improve robustness to varying distances and enforce geometric consistency across views. Experiments on multiple benchmarks (e.g., Stanford2D3D, Matterport3D, and Deep360) demonstrate strong performance and zero-shot generalization, with particularly robust and stable metric predictions in diverse real-world scenes. The project page can be found at: https://insta360-research-team.github.io/DAP_website/ {https://insta360-research-team.github.io/DAP\_website/}&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16913</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StereoPilot: Learning Unified and Efficient Stereo Conversion via Generative Priors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16915</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16915.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guibao Shen, Yihua Du, Wenhang Ge, Jing He, Chirui Chang, Donghao Zhou, Zhen Yang, Luozhou Wang, Xin Tao, Ying-Cong Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid growth of stereoscopic displays, including VR headsets and 3D cinemas, has led to increasing demand for high-quality stereo video content. However, producing 3D videos remains costly and complex, while automatic Monocular-to-Stereo conversion is hindered by the limitations of the multi-stage ``Depth-Warp-Inpaint'' (DWI) pipeline. This paradigm suffers from error propagation, depth ambiguity, and format inconsistency between parallel and converged stereo configurations. To address these challenges, we introduce UniStereo, the first large-scale unified dataset for stereo video conversion, covering both stereo formats to enable fair benchmarking and robust model training. Building upon this dataset, we propose StereoPilot, an efficient feed-forward model that directly synthesizes the target view without relying on explicit depth maps or iterative diffusion sampling. Equipped with a learnable domain switcher and a cycle consistency loss, StereoPilot adapts seamlessly to different stereo formats and achieves improved consistency. Extensive experiments demonstrate that StereoPilot significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods in both visual fidelity and computational efficiency. Project page: https://hit-perfect.github.io/StereoPilot/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16915</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdaTooler-V: Adaptive Tool-Use for Images and Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16918</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16918.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaoyang Wang, Kaituo Feng, Dongyang Chen, Zhongyu Wang, Zhixun Li, Sicheng Gao, Meng Meng, Xu Zhou, Manyuan Zhang, Yuzhang Shang, Xiangyu Yue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances have shown that multimodal large language models (MLLMs) benefit from multimodal interleaved chain-of-thought (CoT) with vision tool interactions. However, existing open-source models often exhibit blind tool-use reasoning patterns, invoking vision tools even when they are unnecessary, which significantly increases inference overhead and degrades model performance. To this end, we propose AdaTooler-V, an MLLM that performs adaptive tool-use by determining whether a visual problem truly requires tools. First, we introduce AT-GRPO, a reinforcement learning algorithm that adaptively adjusts reward scales based on the Tool Benefit Score of each sample, encouraging the model to invoke tools only when they provide genuine improvements. Moreover, we construct two datasets to support training: AdaTooler-V-CoT-100k for SFT cold start and AdaTooler-V-300k for RL with verifiable rewards across single-image, multi-image, and video data. Experiments across twelve benchmarks demonstrate the strong reasoning capability of AdaTooler-V, outperforming existing methods in diverse visual reasoning tasks. Notably, AdaTooler-V-7B achieves an accuracy of 89.8\% on the high-resolution benchmark V*, surpassing the commercial proprietary model GPT-4o and Gemini 1.5 Pro. All code, models, and data are released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16918</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differences That Matter: Auditing Models for Capability Gap Discovery and Rectification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16921</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16921.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qihao Liu, Chengzhi Mao, Yaojie Liu, Alan Yuille, Wen-Sheng Chu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Conventional evaluation methods for multimodal LLMs (MLLMs) lack interpretability and are often insufficient to fully disclose significant capability gaps across models. To address this, we introduce AuditDM, an automated framework that actively discovers and rectifies MLLM failure modes by auditing their divergence. AuditDM fine-tunes an MLLM as an auditor via reinforcement learning to generate challenging questions and counterfactual images that maximize disagreement among target models. Once trained, the auditor uncovers diverse, interpretable exemplars that reveal model weaknesses and serve as annotation-free data for rectification. When applied to SoTA models like Gemma-3 and PaliGemma-2, AuditDM discovers more than 20 distinct failure types. Fine-tuning on these discoveries consistently improves all models across 16 benchmarks, and enables a 3B model to surpass its 28B counterpart. Our results suggest that as data scaling hits diminishing returns, targeted model auditing offers an effective path to model diagnosis and improvement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16921</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EasyV2V: A High-quality Instruction-based Video Editing Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16920</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16920.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinjie Mai, Chaoyang Wang, Guocheng Gordon Qian, Willi Menapace, Sergey Tulyakov, Bernard Ghanem, Peter Wonka, Ashkan Mirzaei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While image editing has advanced rapidly, video editing remains less explored, facing challenges in consistency, control, and generalization. We study the design space of data, architecture, and control, and introduce EasyV2V, a simple and effective framework for instruction-based video editing. On the data side, we compose existing experts with fast inverses to build diverse video pairs, lift image edit pairs into videos via single-frame supervision and pseudo pairs with shared affine motion, mine dense-captioned clips for video pairs, and add transition supervision to teach how edits unfold. On the model side, we observe that pretrained text-to-video models possess editing capability, motivating a simplified design. Simple sequence concatenation for conditioning with light LoRA fine-tuning suffices to train a strong model. For control, we unify spatiotemporal control via a single mask mechanism and support optional reference images. Overall, EasyV2V works with flexible inputs, e.g., video+text, video+mask+text, video+mask+reference+text, and achieves state-of-the-art video editing results, surpassing concurrent and commercial systems. Project page: https://snap-research.github.io/easyv2v/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16920</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next-Embedding Prediction Makes Strong Vision Learners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16922</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16922.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sihan Xu, Ziqiao Ma, Wenhao Chai, Xuweiyi Chen, Weiyang Jin, Joyce Chai, Saining Xie, Stella X. Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Inspired by the success of generative pretraining in natural language, we ask whether the same principles can yield strong self-supervised visual learners. Instead of training models to output features for downstream use, we train them to generate embeddings to perform predictive tasks directly. This work explores such a shift from learning representations to learning models. Specifically, models learn to predict future patch embeddings conditioned on past ones, using causal masking and stop gradient, which we refer to as Next-Embedding Predictive Autoregression (NEPA). We demonstrate that a simple Transformer pretrained on ImageNet-1k with next embedding prediction as its sole learning objective is effective - no pixel reconstruction, discrete tokens, contrastive loss, or task-specific heads. This formulation retains architectural simplicity and scalability, without requiring additional design complexity. NEPA achieves strong results across tasks, attaining 83.8% and 85.3% top-1 accuracy on ImageNet-1K with ViT-B and ViT-L backbones after fine-tuning, and transferring effectively to semantic segmentation on ADE20K. We believe generative pretraining from embeddings provides a simple, scalable, and potentially modality-agnostic alternative to visual self-supervised learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16922</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The World is Your Canvas: Painting Promptable Events with Reference Images, Trajectories, and Text</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16924</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16924.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hanlin Wang, Hao Ouyang, Qiuyu Wang, Yue Yu, Yihao Meng, Wen Wang, Ka Leong Cheng, Shuailei Ma, Qingyan Bai, Yixuan Li, Cheng Chen, Yanhong Zeng, Xing Zhu, Yujun Shen, Qifeng Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present WorldCanvas, a framework for promptable world events that enables rich, user-directed simulation by combining text, trajectories, and reference images. Unlike text-only approaches and existing trajectory-controlled image-to-video methods, our multimodal approach combines trajectories -- encoding motion, timing, and visibility -- with natural language for semantic intent and reference images for visual grounding of object identity, enabling the generation of coherent, controllable events that include multi-agent interactions, object entry/exit, reference-guided appearance and counterintuitive events. The resulting videos demonstrate not only temporal coherence but also emergent consistency, preserving object identity and scene despite temporary disappearance. By supporting expressive world events generation, WorldCanvas advances world models from passive predictors to interactive, user-shaped simulators. Our project page is available at: https://worldcanvas.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16924</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative Refocusing: Flexible Defocus Control from a Single Image</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16923</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2512.16923.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chun-Wei Tuan Mu, Jia-Bin Huang, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Depth-of-field control is essential in photography, but getting the perfect focus often takes several tries or special equipment. Single-image refocusing is still difficult. It involves recovering sharp content and creating realistic bokeh. Current methods have significant drawbacks. They need all-in-focus inputs, depend on synthetic data from simulators, and have limited control over aperture. We introduce Generative Refocusing, a two-step process that uses DeblurNet to recover all-in-focus images from various inputs and BokehNet for creating controllable bokeh. Our main innovation is semi-supervised training. This method combines synthetic paired data with unpaired real bokeh images, using EXIF metadata to capture real optical characteristics beyond what simulators can provide. Our experiments show we achieve top performance in defocus deblurring, bokeh synthesis, and refocusing benchmarks. Additionally, our Generative Refocusing allows text-guided adjustments and custom aperture shapes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16923</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
