<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:02:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>ZARA: Zero-shot Motion Time-Series Analysis via Knowledge and Retrieval   Driven LLM Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04038</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04038.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zechen Li, Baiyu Chen, Hao Xue, Flora D. Salim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Motion sensor time-series are central to human activity recognition (HAR), with applications in health, sports, and smart devices. However, existing methods are trained for fixed activity sets and require costly retraining when new behaviours or sensor setups appear. Recent attempts to use large language models (LLMs) for HAR, typically by converting signals into text or images, suffer from limited accuracy and lack verifiable interpretability. We propose ZARA, the first agent-based framework for zero-shot, explainable HAR directly from raw motion time-series. ZARA integrates an automatically derived pair-wise feature knowledge base that captures discriminative statistics for every activity pair, a multi-sensor retrieval module that surfaces relevant evidence, and a hierarchical agent pipeline that guides the LLM to iteratively select features, draw on this evidence, and produce both activity predictions and natural-language explanations. ZARA enables flexible and interpretable HAR without any fine-tuning or task-specific classifiers. Extensive experiments on 8 HAR benchmarks show that ZARA achieves SOTA zero-shot performance, delivering clear reasoning while exceeding the strongest baselines by 2.53x in macro F1. Ablation studies further confirm the necessity of each module, marking ZARA as a promising step toward trustworthy, plug-and-play motion time-series analysis. Our codes are available at https://github.com/zechenli03/ZARA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04038</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 02:57:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TempFlow-GRPO: When Timing Matters for GRPO in Flow Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04324</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04324.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoxuan He, Siming Fu, Yuke Zhao, Wanli Li, Jian Yang, Dacheng Yin, Fengyun Rao, Bo Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent flow matching models for text-to-image generation have achieved remarkable quality, yet their integration with reinforcement learning for human preference alignment remains suboptimal, hindering fine-grained reward-based optimization. We observe that the key impediment to effective GRPO training of flow models is the temporal uniformity assumption in existing approaches: sparse terminal rewards with uniform credit assignment fail to capture the varying criticality of decisions across generation timesteps, resulting in inefficient exploration and suboptimal convergence. To remedy this shortcoming, we introduce TempFlow-GRPO (Temporal Flow GRPO), a principled GRPO framework that captures and exploits the temporal structure inherent in flow-based generation. TempFlow-GRPO introduces two key innovations: (i) a trajectory branching mechanism that provides process rewards by concentrating stochasticity at designated branching points, enabling precise credit assignment without requiring specialized intermediate reward models; and (ii) a noise-aware weighting scheme that modulates policy optimization according to the intrinsic exploration potential of each timestep, prioritizing learning during high-impact early stages while ensuring stable refinement in later phases. These innovations endow the model with temporally-aware optimization that respects the underlying generative dynamics, leading to state-of-the-art performance in human preference alignment and standard text-to-image benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04324</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 11:10:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiance Fields in XR: A Survey on How Radiance Fields are Envisioned   and Addressed for XR Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04326</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.04326.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ke Li, Mana Masuda, Susanne Schmidt, Shohei Mori&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The development of radiance fields (RF), such as 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) and Neural Radiance Fields (NeRF), has revolutionized interactive photorealistic view synthesis and presents enormous opportunities for XR research and applications. However, despite the exponential growth of RF research, RF-related contributions to the XR community remain sparse. To better understand this research gap, we performed a systematic survey of current RF literature to analyze (i) how RF is envisioned for XR applications, (ii) how they have already been implemented, and (iii) the remaining research gaps. We collected 365 RF contributions related to XR from computer vision, computer graphics, robotics, multimedia, human-computer interaction, and XR communities, seeking to answer the above research questions. Among the 365 papers, we performed an analysis of 66 papers that already addressed a detailed aspect of RF research for XR. With this survey, we extended and positioned XR-specific RF research topics in the broader RF research field and provide a helpful resource for the XR community to navigate within the rapid development of RF research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.04326</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 11:14:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chain-of-Agents: End-to-End Agent Foundation Models via Multi-Agent   Distillation and Agentic RL</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13167</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13167.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weizhen Li, Jianbo Lin, Zhuosong Jiang, Jingyi Cao, Xinpeng Liu, Jiayu Zhang, Zhenqiang Huang, Qianben Chen, Weichen Sun, Qiexiang Wang, Hongxuan Lu, Tianrui Qin, Chenghao Zhu, Yi Yao, Shuying Fan, Xiaowan Li, Tiannan Wang, Pai Liu, King Zhu, He Zhu, Dingfeng Shi, Piaohong Wang, Yeyi Guan, Xiangru Tang, Minghao Liu, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Jian Yang, Jiaheng Liu, Ge Zhang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 65&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) and multi-agent systems have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in complex problem-solving tasks such as deep research, vibe coding, and mathematical reasoning. However, most existing multi-agent systems are built upon manual prompt/workflow engineering with sophisticated agent frameworks, making them computationally inefficient, less capable, and can not benefit from data-centric learning. In this work, we introduce Chain-of-Agents (CoA), a novel paradigm of LLM reasoning that enables native end-to-end complex problem-solving in the same way as a multi-agent system (i.e., multi-turn problem solving with multiple tools and multiple agents) within one model. In chain-of-agents problem-solving, the model dynamically activates different tool agents and role-playing agents to simulate multi-agent collaboration in an end-to-end fashion. To elicit end-to-end chain-of-agents problem-solving abilities in LLMs, we introduce a multi-agent distillation framework to distill state-of-the-art multi-agent systems into chain-of-agents trajectories for agentic supervised fine-tuning. We then use agentic reinforcement learning on verifiable agentic tasks to further improve the models' capabilities on chain-of-agents problem solving. We call the resulting models Agent Foundation Models (AFMs). Our empirical studies demonstrate that AFM establishes new state-of-the-art performance across diverse benchmarks in both web agent and code agent settings. We make the entire research, including the model weights, code for training and evaluation, and the training data, fully open-sourced, which offers a solid starting point for future research on agent models and agentic RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13167</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 17:01:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MultiRef: Controllable Image Generation with Multiple Visual References</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06905</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.06905.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruoxi Chen, Dongping Chen, Siyuan Wu, Sinan Wang, Shiyun Lang, Petr Sushko, Gaoyang Jiang, Yao Wan, Ranjay Krishna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual designers naturally draw inspiration from multiple visual references, combining diverse elements and aesthetic principles to create artwork. However, current image generative frameworks predominantly rely on single-source inputs -- either text prompts or individual reference images. In this paper, we focus on the task of controllable image generation using multiple visual references. We introduce MultiRef-bench, a rigorous evaluation framework comprising 990 synthetic and 1,000 real-world samples that require incorporating visual content from multiple reference images. The synthetic samples are synthetically generated through our data engine RefBlend, with 10 reference types and 33 reference combinations. Based on RefBlend, we further construct a dataset MultiRef containing 38k high-quality images to facilitate further research. Our experiments across three interleaved image-text models (i.e., OmniGen, ACE, and Show-o) and six agentic frameworks (e.g., ChatDiT and LLM + SD) reveal that even state-of-the-art systems struggle with multi-reference conditioning, with the best model OmniGen achieving only 66.6% in synthetic samples and 79.0% in real-world cases on average compared to the golden answer. These findings provide valuable directions for developing more flexible and human-like creative tools that can effectively integrate multiple sources of visual inspiration. The dataset is publicly available at: https://multiref.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06905</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 09:36:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Podcast Recommendations with Profile-Aware LLM-as-a-Judge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08777</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.08777.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Francesco Fabbri, Gustavo Penha, Edoardo D'Amico, Alice Wang, Marco De Nadai, Jackie Doremus, Paul Gigioli, Andreas Damianou, Oskar Stal, Mounia Lalmas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating personalized recommendations remains a central challenge, especially in long-form audio domains like podcasts, where traditional offline metrics suffer from exposure bias and online methods such as A/B testing are costly and operationally constrained. In this paper, we propose a novel framework that leverages Large Language Models (LLMs) as offline judges to assess the quality of podcast recommendations in a scalable and interpretable manner. Our two-stage profile-aware approach first constructs natural-language user profiles distilled from 90 days of listening history. These profiles summarize both topical interests and behavioral patterns, serving as compact, interpretable representations of user preferences. Rather than prompting the LLM with raw data, we use these profiles to provide high-level, semantically rich context-enabling the LLM to reason more effectively about alignment between a user's interests and recommended episodes. This reduces input complexity and improves interpretability. The LLM is then prompted to deliver fine-grained pointwise and pairwise judgments based on the profile-episode match. In a controlled study with 47 participants, our profile-aware judge matched human judgments with high fidelity and outperformed or matched a variant using raw listening histories. The framework enables efficient, profile-aware evaluation for iterative testing and model selection in recommender systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08777</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 09:23:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training-Free Text-Guided Color Editing with Multi-Modal Diffusion   Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09131</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09131.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zixin Yin, Xili Dai, Ling-Hao Chen, Deyu Zhou, Jianan Wang, Duomin Wang, Gang Yu, Lionel M. Ni, Lei Zhang, Heung-Yeung Shum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-guided color editing in images and videos is a fundamental yet unsolved problem, requiring fine-grained manipulation of color attributes, including albedo, light source color, and ambient lighting, while preserving physical consistency in geometry, material properties, and light-matter interactions. Existing training-free methods offer broad applicability across editing tasks but struggle with precise color control and often introduce visual inconsistency in both edited and non-edited regions. In this work, we present ColorCtrl, a training-free color editing method that leverages the attention mechanisms of modern Multi-Modal Diffusion Transformers (MM-DiT). By disentangling structure and color through targeted manipulation of attention maps and value tokens, our method enables accurate and consistent color editing, along with word-level control of attribute intensity. Our method modifies only the intended regions specified by the prompt, leaving unrelated areas untouched. Extensive experiments on both SD3 and FLUX.1-dev demonstrate that ColorCtrl outperforms existing training-free approaches and achieves state-of-the-art performances in both edit quality and consistency. Furthermore, our method surpasses strong commercial models such as FLUX.1 Kontext Max and GPT-4o Image Generation in terms of consistency. When extended to video models like CogVideoX, our approach exhibits greater advantages, particularly in maintaining temporal coherence and editing stability. Finally, our method also generalizes to instruction-based editing diffusion models such as Step1X-Edit and FLUX.1 Kontext dev, further demonstrating its versatility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09131</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 17:57:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Describe What You See with Multimodal Large Language Models to Enhance   Video Recommendations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09789</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.09789.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marco De Nadai, Andreas Damianou, Mounia Lalmas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing video recommender systems rely primarily on user-defined metadata or on low-level visual and acoustic signals extracted by specialised encoders. These low-level features describe what appears on the screen but miss deeper semantics such as intent, humour, and world knowledge that make clips resonate with viewers. For example, is a 30-second clip simply a singer on a rooftop, or an ironic parody filmed amid the fairy chimneys of Cappadocia, Turkey? Such distinctions are critical to personalised recommendations yet remain invisible to traditional encoding pipelines. In this paper, we introduce a simple, recommendation system-agnostic zero-finetuning framework that injects high-level semantics into the recommendation pipeline by prompting an off-the-shelf Multimodal Large Language Model (MLLM) to summarise each clip into a rich natural-language description (e.g. "a superhero parody with slapstick fights and orchestral stabs"), bridging the gap between raw content and user intent. We use MLLM output with a state-of-the-art text encoder and feed it into standard collaborative, content-based, and generative recommenders. On the MicroLens-100K dataset, which emulates user interactions with TikTok-style videos, our framework consistently surpasses conventional video, audio, and metadata features in five representative models. Our findings highlight the promise of leveraging MLLMs as on-the-fly knowledge extractors to build more intent-aware video recommenders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09789</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 13:19:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semantic IDs for Joint Generative Search and Recommendation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10478</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10478.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gustavo Penha, Edoardo D'Amico, Marco De Nadai, Enrico Palumbo, Alexandre Tamborrino, Ali Vardasbi, Max Lefarov, Shawn Lin, Timothy Heath, Francesco Fabbri, Hugues Bouchard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative models powered by Large Language Models (LLMs) are emerging as a unified solution for powering both recommendation and search tasks. A key design choice in these models is how to represent items, traditionally through unique identifiers (IDs) and more recently with Semantic IDs composed of discrete codes, obtained from embeddings. While task-specific embedding models can improve performance for individual tasks, they may not generalize well in a joint setting. In this paper, we explore how to construct Semantic IDs that perform well both in search and recommendation when using a unified model. We compare a range of strategies to construct Semantic IDs, looking into task-specific and cross-tasks approaches, and also whether each task should have its own semantic ID tokens in a joint search and recommendation generative model. Our results show that using a bi-encoder model fine-tuned on both search and recommendation tasks to obtain item embeddings, followed by the construction of a unified Semantic ID space provides an effective trade-off, enabling strong performance in both tasks. We hope these findings spark follow-up work on generalisable, semantically grounded ID schemes and inform the next wave of unified generative recommender architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10478</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 09:28:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MM-BrowseComp: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Multimodal Browsing Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13186</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13186.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shilong Li, Xingyuan Bu, Wenjie Wang, Jiaheng Liu, Jun Dong, Haoyang He, Hao Lu, Haozhe Zhang, Chenchen Jing, Zhen Li, Chuanhao Li, Jiayi Tian, Chenchen Zhang, Tianhao Peng, Yancheng He, Jihao Gu, Yuanxing Zhang, Jian Yang, Ge Zhang, Wenhao Huang, Wangchunshu Zhou, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Ruizhe Ding, Shilei Wen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI agents with advanced reasoning and tool use capabilities have demonstrated impressive performance in web browsing for deep search. While existing benchmarks such as BrowseComp evaluate these browsing abilities, they primarily focus on textual information, overlooking the prevalence of multimodal content. To bridge this gap, we introduce MM-BrowseComp, a novel benchmark comprising 224 challenging, hand-crafted questions specifically designed to assess agents' multimodal retrieval and reasoning capabilities. These questions often incorporate images in prompts, and crucial information encountered during the search and reasoning process may also be embedded within images or videos on webpages. Consequently, methods relying solely on text prove insufficient for our benchmark. Additionally, we provide a verified checklist for each question, enabling fine-grained analysis of multimodal dependencies and reasoning paths. Our comprehensive evaluation of state-of-the-art models on MM-BrowseComp reveals that even top models like OpenAI o3 with tools achieve only 29.02\% accuracy, highlighting the suboptimal multimodal capabilities and lack of native multimodal reasoning in current models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13186</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 13:46:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advances in Speech Separation: Techniques, Challenges, and Future Trends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10830</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.10830.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kai Li, Guo Chen, Wendi Sang, Yi Luo, Zhuo Chen, Shuai Wang, Shulin He, Zhong-Qiu Wang, Andong Li, Zhiyong Wu, Xiaolin Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The field of speech separation, addressing the "cocktail party problem", has seen revolutionary advances with DNNs. Speech separation enhances clarity in complex acoustic environments and serves as crucial pre-processing for speech recognition and speaker recognition. However, current literature focuses narrowly on specific architectures or isolated approaches, creating fragmented understanding. This survey addresses this gap by providing systematic examination of DNN-based speech separation techniques. Our work differentiates itself through: (I) Comprehensive perspective: We systematically investigate learning paradigms, separation scenarios with known/unknown speakers, comparative analysis of supervised/self-supervised/unsupervised frameworks, and architectural components from encoders to estimation strategies. (II) Timeliness: Coverage of cutting-edge developments ensures access to current innovations and benchmarks. (III) Unique insights: Beyond summarization, we evaluate technological trajectories, identify emerging patterns, and highlight promising directions including domain-robust frameworks, efficient architectures, multimodal integration, and novel self-supervised paradigms. (IV) Fair evaluation: We provide quantitative evaluations on standard datasets, revealing true capabilities and limitations of different methods. This comprehensive survey serves as an accessible reference for experienced researchers and newcomers navigating speech separation's complex landscape.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10830</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 16:54:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedSAMix: A Training-Free Model Merging Approach for Medical Image   Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11032</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11032.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanwu Yang, Guinan Su, Jiesi Hu, Francesco Sammarco, Jonas Geiping, Thomas Wolfers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal medical image segmentation models have emerged as a promising paradigm due to their strong generalizability across diverse tasks, showing great potential for a wide range of clinical applications. This potential has been partly driven by the success of general-purpose vision models such as the Segment Anything Model (SAM), which has inspired the development of various fine-tuned variants for medical segmentation tasks. However, fine-tuned variants like MedSAM are trained on comparatively limited medical imaging data that often suffers from heterogeneity, scarce annotations, and distributional shifts. These challenges limit their ability to generalize across a wide range of medical segmentation tasks. In this regard, we propose MedSAMix, a training-free model merging method that integrates the strengths of both generalist models (e.g., SAM) and specialist models (e.g., MedSAM) for medical image segmentation. In contrast to traditional model merging approaches that rely on manual configuration and often result in suboptimal outcomes, we propose a zero-order optimization method to automatically discover optimal layer-wise merging solutions. Furthermore, for clinical applications, we develop two regimes to meet the demand of domain-specificity and generalizability in different scenarios by single-task optimization and multi-objective optimization respectively. Extensive evaluations on 25 medical segmentation tasks demonstrate that MedSAMix effectively mitigates model bias and consistently improves performance in both domain-specific accuracy and generalization, achieving improvements of 6.67% on specialized tasks and 4.37% on multi-task evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11032</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 19:35:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrieval-augmented reasoning with lean language models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11386</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11386.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ryan Sze-Yin Chan, Federico Nanni, Tomas Lazauskas, Rosie Wood, Penelope Yong, Lionel Tarassenko, Mark Girolami, James Geddes, Andrew Duncan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This technical report details a novel approach to combining reasoning and retrieval augmented generation (RAG) within a single, lean language model architecture. While existing RAG systems typically rely on large-scale models and external APIs, our work addresses the increasing demand for performant and privacy-preserving solutions deployable in resource-constrained or secure environments. Building on recent developments in test-time scaling and small-scale reasoning models, we develop a retrieval augmented conversational agent capable of interpreting complex, domain-specific queries using a lightweight backbone model. Our system integrates a dense retriever with fine-tuned Qwen2.5-Instruct models, using synthetic query generation and reasoning traces derived from frontier models (e.g., DeepSeek-R1) over a curated corpus, in this case, the NHS A-to-Z condition pages. We explore the impact of summarisation-based document compression, synthetic data design, and reasoning-aware fine-tuning on model performance. Evaluation against both non-reasoning and general-purpose lean models demonstrates that our domain-specific fine-tuning approach yields substantial gains in answer accuracy and consistency, approaching frontier-level performance while remaining feasible for local deployment. All implementation details and code are publicly released to support reproducibility and adaptation across domains.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11386</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 10:38:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Copyright Protection for Large Language Models: A Survey of Methods,   Challenges, and Trends</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11548</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.11548.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenhua Xu, Xubin Yue, Zhebo Wang, Qichen Liu, Xixiang Zhao, Jingxuan Zhang, Wenjun Zeng, Wengpeng Xing, Dezhang Kong, Changting Lin, Meng Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Copyright protection for large language models is of critical importance, given their substantial development costs, proprietary value, and potential for misuse. Existing surveys have predominantly focused on techniques for tracing LLM-generated content-namely, text watermarking-while a systematic exploration of methods for protecting the models themselves (i.e., model watermarking and model fingerprinting) remains absent. Moreover, the relationships and distinctions among text watermarking, model watermarking, and model fingerprinting have not been comprehensively clarified. This work presents a comprehensive survey of the current state of LLM copyright protection technologies, with a focus on model fingerprinting, covering the following aspects: (1) clarifying the conceptual connection from text watermarking to model watermarking and fingerprinting, and adopting a unified terminology that incorporates model watermarking into the broader fingerprinting framework; (2) providing an overview and comparison of diverse text watermarking techniques, highlighting cases where such methods can function as model fingerprinting; (3) systematically categorizing and comparing existing model fingerprinting approaches for LLM copyright protection; (4) presenting, for the first time, techniques for fingerprint transfer and fingerprint removal; (5) summarizing evaluation metrics for model fingerprints, including effectiveness, harmlessness, robustness, stealthiness, and reliability; and (6) discussing open challenges and future research directions. This survey aims to offer researchers a thorough understanding of both text watermarking and model fingerprinting technologies in the era of LLMs, thereby fostering further advances in protecting their intellectual property.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.11548</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 15:50:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mind the Generation Process: Fine-Grained Confidence Estimation During   LLM Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12040</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12040.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinyi Han, Tingyun Li, Shisong Chen, Jie Shi, Xinyi Wang, Guanglei Yue, Jiaqing Liang, Xin Lin, Liqian Wen, Zulong Chen, Yanghua Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable performance across diverse tasks, they fundamentally lack self-awareness and frequently exhibit overconfidence, assigning high confidence scores to incorrect predictions. Accurate confidence estimation is therefore critical for enhancing the trustworthiness and reliability of LLM-generated outputs. However, existing approaches suffer from coarse-grained scoring mechanisms that fail to provide fine-grained, continuous confidence estimates throughout the generation process. To address these limitations, we introduce FineCE, a novel confidence estimation method that delivers accurate, fine-grained confidence scores during text generation. Specifically, we first develop a comprehensive pipeline for constructing training data that effectively captures the underlying probabilistic distribution of LLM responses, and then train a model to predict confidence scores for arbitrary text sequences in a supervised manner. Furthermore, we propose a Backward Confidence Integration (BCI) strategy that leverages information from the subsequent text to enhance confidence estimation for the current sequence during inference. We also introduce three strategies for identifying optimal positions to perform confidence estimation within the generation process. Extensive experiments on multiple benchmark datasets demonstrate that FineCE consistently outperforms existing classical confidence estimation methods. Our code and all baselines used in the paper are available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12040</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 13:29:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CorrSteer: Steering Improves Task Performance and Safety in LLMs through   Correlation-based Sparse Autoencoder Feature Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12535</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12535.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seonglae Cho, Zekun Wu, Adriano Koshiyama&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse Autoencoders (SAEs) can extract interpretable features from large language models (LLMs) without supervision. However, their effectiveness in downstream steering tasks is limited by the requirement for contrastive datasets or large activation storage. To address these limitations, we propose CorrSteer, which selects features by correlating sample correctness with SAE activations from generated tokens at inference time. This approach uses only inference-time activations to extract more relevant features, thereby avoiding spurious correlations. It also obtains steering coefficients from average activations, automating the entire pipeline. Our method shows improved task performance on QA, bias mitigation, jailbreaking prevention, and reasoning benchmarks on Gemma 2 2B and LLaMA 3.1 8B, notably achieving a +4.1% improvement in MMLU performance and a +22.9% improvement in HarmBench with only 4000 samples. Selected features demonstrate semantically meaningful patterns aligned with each task's requirements, revealing the underlying capabilities that drive performance. Our work establishes correlationbased selection as an effective and scalable approach for automated SAE steering across language model applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12535</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:01:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Large Language Models for Predictive Analysis of Human Misery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12669</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12669.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bishanka Seal, Rahul Seetharaman, Aman Bansal, Abhilash Nandy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This study investigates the use of Large Language Models (LLMs) for predicting human-perceived misery scores from natural language descriptions of real-world scenarios. The task is framed as a regression problem, where the model assigns a scalar value from 0 to 100 to each input statement. We evaluate multiple prompting strategies, including zero-shot, fixed-context few-shot, and retrieval-based prompting using BERT sentence embeddings. Few-shot approaches consistently outperform zero-shot baselines, underscoring the value of contextual examples in affective prediction. To move beyond static evaluation, we introduce the "Misery Game Show", a novel gamified framework inspired by a television format. It tests LLMs through structured rounds involving ordinal comparison, binary classification, scalar estimation, and feedback-driven reasoning. This setup enables us to assess not only predictive accuracy but also the model's ability to adapt based on corrective feedback. The gamified evaluation highlights the broader potential of LLMs in dynamic emotional reasoning tasks beyond standard regression. Code and data link: https://github.com/abhi1nandy2/Misery_Data_Exps_GitHub&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12669</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 07:02:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atom-Searcher: Enhancing Agentic Deep Research via Fine-Grained Atomic   Thought Reward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12800</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12800.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yong Deng, Guoqing Wang, Zhenzhe Ying, Xiaofeng Wu, Jinzhen Lin, Wenwen Xiong, Yuqin Dai, Shuo Yang, Zhanwei Zhang, Qiwen Wang, Yang Qin, Changhua Meng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) exhibit remarkable problem-solving abilities, but struggle with complex tasks due to static internal knowledge. Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) enhances access to external information, yet remains limited in multi-hop reasoning and strategic search due to rigid workflows. Recent advancements in agentic deep research empower LLMs to autonomously reason, search, and synthesize information. However, current approaches relying on outcome-based reinforcement learning (RL) face critical issues such as conflicting gradients and reward sparsity, limiting performance gains and training efficiency. To address these, we first propose Atomic Thought, a novel LLM thinking paradigm that decomposes reasoning into fine-grained functional units. These units are supervised by Reasoning Reward Models (RRMs), which provide Atomic Thought Rewards (ATR) for fine-grained guidance. Building on this, we propose Atom-Searcher, a novel RL framework for agentic deep research that integrates Atomic Thought and ATR. Atom-Searcher uses a curriculum-inspired reward schedule, prioritizing process-level ATR early and transitioning to outcome rewards, accelerating convergence on effective reasoning paths. Experiments on seven benchmarks show consistent improvements over the state-of-the-art. Key advantages include: (1) Atom-Searcher scales computation at test-time. (2) Atomic Thought provides supervision anchors for RRMs, bridging deep research tasks and RRMs. (3) Atom-Searcher exhibits more interpretable, human-like reasoning patterns.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12800</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 10:23:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAMAR: Continuous Actions Multi-Agent Routing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12845</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12845.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Artem Pshenitsyn, Aleksandr Panov, Alexey Skrynnik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-agent reinforcement learning (MARL) is a powerful paradigm for solving cooperative and competitive decision-making problems. While many MARL benchmarks have been proposed, few combine continuous state and action spaces with challenging coordination and planning tasks. We introduce CAMAR, a new MARL benchmark designed explicitly for multi-agent pathfinding in environments with continuous actions. CAMAR supports cooperative and competitive interactions between agents and runs efficiently at up to 100,000 environment steps per second. We also propose a three-tier evaluation protocol to better track algorithmic progress and enable deeper analysis of performance. In addition, CAMAR allows the integration of classical planning methods such as RRT and RRT* into MARL pipelines. We use them as standalone baselines and combine RRT* with popular MARL algorithms to create hybrid approaches. We provide a suite of test scenarios and benchmarking tools to ensure reproducibility and fair comparison. Experiments show that CAMAR presents a challenging and realistic testbed for the MARL community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12845</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 11:32:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Stitch in Time Saves Nine: Proactive Self-Refinement for Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12903</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.12903.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinyi Han, Xinyi Wang, Haiquan Zhao, Tingyun li, Zishang Jiang, Sihang Jiang, Jiaqing Liang, Xin Lin, Weikang Zhou, Zeye Sun, Fei Yu, Yanghua Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in self-refinement have demonstrated significant potential for improving the outputs of large language models (LLMs) through iterative refinement. However, most existing self-refinement methods rely on a reactive process with a fixed number of iterations, making it difficult to determine the optimal timing and content of refinement based on the evolving generation context. Inspired by the way humans dynamically refine their thoughts during execution, we propose ProActive Self-Refinement (PASR), a novel method that enables LLMs to refine their outputs during the generation process. Unlike methods that regenerate entire responses, PASR proactively decides whether, when, and how to refine based on the model's internal state and evolving context. We conduct extensive experiments on a diverse set of 10 tasks to evaluate the effectiveness of PASR. Experimental results show that PASR significantly enhances problem-solving performance. In particular, on Qwen3-8B, PASR reduces average token consumption by 41.6 percent compared to standard generation, while also achieving an 8.2 percent improvement in accuracy. Our code and all baselines used in the paper are available in the GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12903</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 13:07:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion2Motion: Cross-topology Motion Transfer with Sparse Correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13139</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13139.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ling-Hao Chen, Yuhong Zhang, Zixin Yin, Zhiyang Dou, Xin Chen, Jingbo Wang, Taku Komura, Lei Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This work studies the challenge of transfer animations between characters whose skeletal topologies differ substantially. While many techniques have advanced retargeting techniques in decades, transfer motions across diverse topologies remains less-explored. The primary obstacle lies in the inherent topological inconsistency between source and target skeletons, which restricts the establishment of straightforward one-to-one bone correspondences. Besides, the current lack of large-scale paired motion datasets spanning different topological structures severely constrains the development of data-driven approaches. To address these limitations, we introduce Motion2Motion, a novel, training-free framework. Simply yet effectively, Motion2Motion works with only one or a few example motions on the target skeleton, by accessing a sparse set of bone correspondences between the source and target skeletons. Through comprehensive qualitative and quantitative evaluations, we demonstrate that Motion2Motion achieves efficient and reliable performance in both similar-skeleton and cross-species skeleton transfer scenarios. The practical utility of our approach is further evidenced by its successful integration in downstream applications and user interfaces, highlighting its potential for industrial applications. Code and data are available at https://lhchen.top/Motion2Motion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13139</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 17:50:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapidly Adapting to New Voice Spoofing: Few-Shot Detection of   Synthesized Speech Under Distribution Shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13320</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13320.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ashi Garg, Zexin Cai, Henry Li Xinyuan, Leibny Paola García-Perera, Kevin Duh, Sanjeev Khudanpur, Matthew Wiesner, Nicholas Andrews&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We address the challenge of detecting synthesized speech under distribution shifts -- arising from unseen synthesis methods, speakers, languages, or audio conditions -- relative to the training data. Few-shot learning methods are a promising way to tackle distribution shifts by rapidly adapting on the basis of a few in-distribution samples. We propose a self-attentive prototypical network to enable more robust few-shot adaptation. To evaluate our approach, we systematically compare the performance of traditional zero-shot detectors and the proposed few-shot detectors, carefully controlling training conditions to introduce distribution shifts at evaluation time. In conditions where distribution shifts hamper the zero-shot performance, our proposed few-shot adaptation technique can quickly adapt using as few as 10 in-distribution samples -- achieving upto 32% relative EER reduction on deepfakes in Japanese language and 20% relative reduction on ASVspoof 2021 Deepfake dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13320</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 19:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniTry: Virtual Try-On Anything without Masks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13632</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13632.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yutong Feng, Linlin Zhang, Hengyuan Cao, Yiming Chen, Xiaoduan Feng, Jian Cao, Yuxiong Wu, Bin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Virtual Try-ON (VTON) is a practical and widely-applied task, for which most of existing works focus on clothes. This paper presents OmniTry, a unified framework that extends VTON beyond garment to encompass any wearable objects, e.g., jewelries and accessories, with mask-free setting for more practical application. When extending to various types of objects, data curation is challenging for obtaining paired images, i.e., the object image and the corresponding try-on result. To tackle this problem, we propose a two-staged pipeline: For the first stage, we leverage large-scale unpaired images, i.e., portraits with any wearable items, to train the model for mask-free localization. Specifically, we repurpose the inpainting model to automatically draw objects in suitable positions given an empty mask. For the second stage, the model is further fine-tuned with paired images to transfer the consistency of object appearance. We observed that the model after the first stage shows quick convergence even with few paired samples. OmniTry is evaluated on a comprehensive benchmark consisting of 12 common classes of wearable objects, with both in-shop and in-the-wild images. Experimental results suggest that OmniTry shows better performance on both object localization and ID-preservation compared with existing methods. The code, model weights, and evaluation benchmark of OmniTry will be made publicly available at https://omnitry.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13632</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 08:47:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Human Judgment: A Bayesian Evaluation of LLMs' Moral Values   Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13804</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13804.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Maciej Skorski, Alina Landowska&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; How do large language models understand moral dimensions compared to humans?   This first large-scale Bayesian evaluation of market-leading language models provides the answer. In contrast to prior work using deterministic ground truth (majority or inclusion rules), we model annotator disagreements to capture both aleatoric uncertainty (inherent human disagreement) and epistemic uncertainty (model domain sensitivity). We evaluate top language models (Claude Sonnet 4, DeepSeek-V3, Llama 4 Maverick) across 250K+ annotations from ~700 annotators on 100K+ texts spanning social media, news, and forums.   Our GPU-optimized Bayesian framework processed 1M+ model queries, revealing that AI models typically rank among the top 25\% of human annotators, achieving much better-than-average balanced accuracy. Importantly, we find that AI produces far fewer false negatives than humans, highlighting their more sensitive moral detection capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13804</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 13:05:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prompt Orchestration Markup Language</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13948</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13948.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuge Zhang, Nan Chen, Jiahang Xu, Yuqing Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) require sophisticated prompting, yet current practices face challenges in structure, data integration, format sensitivity, and tooling. Existing methods lack comprehensive solutions for organizing complex prompts involving diverse data types (documents, tables, images) or managing presentation variations systematically. To address these gaps, we introduce POML (Prompt Orchestration Markup Language). POML employs component-based markup for logical structure (roles, tasks, examples), specialized tags for seamless data integration, and a CSS-like styling system to decouple content from presentation, reducing formatting sensitivity. It includes templating for dynamic prompts and a comprehensive developer toolkit (IDE support, SDKs) to improve version control and collaboration. We validate POML through two case studies demonstrating its impact on complex application integration (PomLink) and accuracy performance (TableQA), as well as a user study assessing its effectiveness in real-world development scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13948</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 15:37:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMAU-Pro: A Challenging and Comprehensive Benchmark for Holistic   Evaluation of Audio General Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13992</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13992.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sonal Kumar, Šimon Sedláček, Vaibhavi Lokegaonkar, Fernando López, Wenyi Yu, Nishit Anand, Hyeonggon Ryu, Lichang Chen, Maxim Plička, Miroslav Hlaváček, William Fineas Ellingwood, Sathvik Udupa, Siyuan Hou, Allison Ferner, Sara Barahona, Cecilia Bolaños, Satish Rahi, Laura Herrera-Alarcón, Satvik Dixit, Siddhi Patil, Soham Deshmukh, Lasha Koroshinadze, Yao Liu, Leibny Paola Garcia Perera, Eleni Zanou, Themos Stafylakis, Joon Son Chung, David Harwath, Chao Zhang, Dinesh Manocha, Alicia Lozano-Diez, Santosh Kesiraju, Sreyan Ghosh, Ramani Duraiswami&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Audio comprehension-including speech, non-speech sounds, and music-is essential for achieving human-level intelligence. Consequently, AI agents must demonstrate holistic audio understanding to qualify as generally intelligent. However, evaluating auditory intelligence comprehensively remains challenging. To address this gap, we introduce MMAU-Pro, the most comprehensive and rigorously curated benchmark for assessing audio intelligence in AI systems. MMAU-Pro contains 5,305 instances, where each instance has one or more audios paired with human expert-generated question-answer pairs, spanning speech, sound, music, and their combinations. Unlike existing benchmarks, MMAU-Pro evaluates auditory intelligence across 49 unique skills and multiple complex dimensions, including long-form audio comprehension, spatial audio reasoning, multi-audio understanding, among others. All questions are meticulously designed to require deliberate multi-hop reasoning, including both multiple-choice and open-ended response formats. Importantly, audio data is sourced directly ``from the wild" rather than from existing datasets with known distributions. We evaluate 22 leading open-source and proprietary multimodal AI models, revealing significant limitations: even state-of-the-art models such as Gemini 2.5 Flash and Audio Flamingo 3 achieve only 59.2% and 51.7% accuracy, respectively, approaching random performance in multiple categories. Our extensive analysis highlights specific shortcomings and provides novel insights, offering actionable perspectives for the community to enhance future AI systems' progression toward audio general intelligence. The benchmark and code is available at https://sonalkum.github.io/mmau-pro.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13992</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 16:33:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embodied-R1: Reinforced Embodied Reasoning for General Robotic   Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13998</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.13998.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifu Yuan, Haiqin Cui, Yaoting Huang, Yibin Chen, Fei Ni, Zibin Dong, Pengyi Li, Yan Zheng, Jianye Hao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generalization in embodied AI is hindered by the "seeing-to-doing gap," which stems from data scarcity and embodiment heterogeneity. To address this, we pioneer "pointing" as a unified, embodiment-agnostic intermediate representation, defining four core embodied pointing abilities that bridge high-level vision-language comprehension with low-level action primitives. We introduce Embodied-R1, a 3B Vision-Language Model (VLM) specifically designed for embodied reasoning and pointing. We use a wide range of embodied and general visual reasoning datasets as sources to construct a large-scale dataset, Embodied-Points-200K, which supports key embodied pointing capabilities. We then train Embodied-R1 using a two-stage Reinforced Fine-tuning (RFT) curriculum with a specialized multi-task reward design. Embodied-R1 achieves state-of-the-art performance on 11 embodied spatial and pointing benchmarks. Critically, it demonstrates robust zero-shot generalization by achieving a 56.2% success rate in the SIMPLEREnv and 87.5% across 8 real-world XArm tasks without any task-specific fine-tuning, representing a 62% improvement over strong baselines. Furthermore, the model exhibits high robustness against diverse visual disturbances. Our work shows that a pointing-centric representation, combined with an RFT training paradigm, offers an effective and generalizable pathway to closing the perception-action gap in robotics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13998</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 16:50:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongSplat: Robust Unposed 3D Gaussian Splatting for Casual Long Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14041</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2508.14041.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chin-Yang Lin, Cheng Sun, Fu-En Yang, Min-Hung Chen, Yen-Yu Lin, Yu-Lun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LongSplat addresses critical challenges in novel view synthesis (NVS) from casually captured long videos characterized by irregular camera motion, unknown camera poses, and expansive scenes. Current methods often suffer from pose drift, inaccurate geometry initialization, and severe memory limitations. To address these issues, we introduce LongSplat, a robust unposed 3D Gaussian Splatting framework featuring: (1) Incremental Joint Optimization that concurrently optimizes camera poses and 3D Gaussians to avoid local minima and ensure global consistency; (2) a robust Pose Estimation Module leveraging learned 3D priors; and (3) an efficient Octree Anchor Formation mechanism that converts dense point clouds into anchors based on spatial density. Extensive experiments on challenging benchmarks demonstrate that LongSplat achieves state-of-the-art results, substantially improving rendering quality, pose accuracy, and computational efficiency compared to prior approaches. Project page: https://linjohnss.github.io/longsplat/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14041</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
