<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:13:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Upsample What Matters: Region-Adaptive Latent Sampling for Accelerated   Diffusion Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08422</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.08422.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wongi Jeong, Kyungryeol Lee, Hoigi Seo, Se Young Chun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion transformers have emerged as an alternative to U-net-based diffusion models for high-fidelity image and video generation, offering superior scalability. However, their heavy computation remains a major obstacle to real-world deployment. Existing acceleration methods primarily exploit the temporal dimension such as reusing cached features across diffusion timesteps. Here, we propose Region-Adaptive Latent Upsampling (RALU), a training-free framework that accelerates inference along spatial dimension. RALU performs mixed-resolution sampling across three stages: 1) low-resolution denoising latent diffusion to efficiently capture global semantic structure, 2) region-adaptive upsampling on specific regions prone to artifacts at full-resolution, and 3) all latent upsampling at full-resolution for detail refinement. To stabilize generations across resolution transitions, we leverage noise-timestep rescheduling to adapt the noise level across varying resolutions. Our method significantly reduces computation while preserving image quality by achieving up to 7.0times speed-up on FLUX and 3.0times on Stable Diffusion 3 with minimal degradation. Furthermore, RALU is complementary to existing temporal accelerations such as caching methods, thus can be seamlessly integrated to further reduce inference latency without compromising generation quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08422</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 09:07:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RedOne: Revealing Domain-specific LLM Post-Training in Social Networking   Services</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10605</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.10605.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fei Zhao, Chonggang Lu, Yue Wang, Zheyong Xie, Ziyan Liu, Haofu Qian, JianZhao Huang, Fangcheng Shi, Zijie Meng, Hongcheng Guo, Mingqian He, Xinze Lyu, Yiming Lu, Ziyang Xiang, Zheyu Ye, Chengqiang Lu, Zhe Xu, Yi Wu, Yao Hu, Yan Gao, Jun Fan, Xiaolong Jiang, Weiting Liu, Boyang Wang, Shaosheng Cao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; As a primary medium for modern information dissemination, social networking services (SNS) have experienced rapid growth, which has proposed significant challenges for platform content management and interaction quality improvement. Recently, the development of large language models (LLMs) has offered potential solutions but existing studies focus on isolated tasks, which not only encounter diminishing benefit from the data scaling within individual scenarios but also fail to flexibly adapt to diverse real-world context. To address these challenges, we introduce RedOne, a domain-specific LLM designed to break the performance bottleneck of single-task baselines and establish a comprehensive foundation for the SNS. RedOne was developed through a three-stage training strategy consisting of continue pretraining, supervised fine-tuning, and preference optimization, using a large-scale real-world dataset. Through extensive experiments, RedOne maintains strong general capabilities, and achieves an average improvement up to 14.02% across 8 major SNS tasks and 7.56% in SNS bilingual evaluation benchmark, compared with base models. Furthermore, through online testing, RedOne reduced the exposure rate in harmful content detection by 11.23% and improved the click page rate in post-view search by 14.95% compared with single-tasks finetuned baseline models. These results establish RedOne as a robust domain-specific LLM for SNS, demonstrating excellent generalization across various tasks and promising applicability in real-world scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10605</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2025 02:22:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GeoDistill: Geometry-Guided Self-Distillation for Weakly Supervised   Cross-View Localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10935</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.10935.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaowen Tong, Zimin Xia, Alexandre Alahi, Xuming He, Yujiao Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Cross-view localization, the task of estimating a camera's 3-degrees-of-freedom (3-DoF) pose by aligning ground-level images with satellite images, is crucial for large-scale outdoor applications like autonomous navigation and augmented reality. Existing methods often rely on fully supervised learning, which requires costly ground-truth pose annotations. In this work, we propose GeoDistill, a Geometry guided weakly supervised self distillation framework that uses teacher-student learning with Field-of-View (FoV)-based masking to enhance local feature learning for robust cross-view localization. In GeoDistill, the teacher model localizes a panoramic image, while the student model predicts locations from a limited FoV counterpart created by FoV-based masking. By aligning the student's predictions with those of the teacher, the student focuses on key features like lane lines and ignores textureless regions, such as roads. This results in more accurate predictions and reduced uncertainty, regardless of whether the query images are panoramas or limited FoV images. Our experiments show that GeoDistill significantly improves localization performance across different frameworks. Additionally, we introduce a novel orientation estimation network that predicts relative orientation without requiring precise planar position ground truth. GeoDistill provides a scalable and efficient solution for real-world cross-view localization challenges. Code and model can be found at https://github.com/tongshw/GeoDistill.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10935</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 03:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust 3D-Masked Part-level Editing in 3D Gaussian Splatting with   Regularized Score Distillation Sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11061</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.11061.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hayeon Kim, Ji Ha Jang, Se Young Chun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in 3D neural representations and instance-level editing models have enabled the efficient creation of high-quality 3D content. However, achieving precise local 3D edits remains challenging, especially for Gaussian Splatting, due to inconsistent multi-view 2D part segmentations and inherently ambiguous nature of Score Distillation Sampling (SDS) loss. To address these limitations, we propose RoMaP, a novel local 3D Gaussian editing framework that enables precise and drastic part-level modifications. First, we introduce a robust 3D mask generation module with our 3D-Geometry Aware Label Prediction (3D-GALP), which uses spherical harmonics (SH) coefficients to model view-dependent label variations and soft-label property, yielding accurate and consistent part segmentations across viewpoints. Second, we propose a regularized SDS loss that combines the standard SDS loss with additional regularizers. In particular, an L1 anchor loss is introduced via our Scheduled Latent Mixing and Part (SLaMP) editing method, which generates high-quality part-edited 2D images and confines modifications only to the target region while preserving contextual coherence. Additional regularizers, such as Gaussian prior removal, further improve flexibility by allowing changes beyond the existing context, and robust 3D masking prevents unintended edits. Experimental results demonstrate that our RoMaP achieves state-of-the-art local 3D editing on both reconstructed and generated Gaussian scenes and objects qualitatively and quantitatively, making it possible for more robust and flexible part-level 3D Gaussian editing. Code is available at https://janeyeon.github.io/romap.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11061</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 07:54:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Devil behind the mask: An emergent safety vulnerability of Diffusion   LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11097</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.11097.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zichen Wen, Jiashu Qu, Dongrui Liu, Zhiyuan Liu, Ruixi Wu, Yicun Yang, Xiangqi Jin, Haoyun Xu, Xuyang Liu, Weijia Li, Chaochao Lu, Jing Shao, Conghui He, Linfeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion-based large language models (dLLMs) have recently emerged as a powerful alternative to autoregressive LLMs, offering faster inference and greater interactivity via parallel decoding and bidirectional modeling. However, despite strong performance in code generation and text infilling, we identify a fundamental safety concern: existing alignment mechanisms fail to safeguard dLLMs against context-aware, masked-input adversarial prompts, exposing novel vulnerabilities. To this end, we present DIJA, the first systematic study and jailbreak attack framework that exploits unique safety weaknesses of dLLMs. Specifically, our proposed DIJA constructs adversarial interleaved mask-text prompts that exploit the text generation mechanisms of dLLMs, i.e., bidirectional modeling and parallel decoding. Bidirectional modeling drives the model to produce contextually consistent outputs for masked spans, even when harmful, while parallel decoding limits model dynamic filtering and rejection sampling of unsafe content. This causes standard alignment mechanisms to fail, enabling harmful completions in alignment-tuned dLLMs, even when harmful behaviors or unsafe instructions are directly exposed in the prompt. Through comprehensive experiments, we demonstrate that DIJA significantly outperforms existing jailbreak methods, exposing a previously overlooked threat surface in dLLM architectures. Notably, our method achieves up to 100% keyword-based ASR on Dream-Instruct, surpassing the strongest prior baseline, ReNeLLM, by up to 78.5% in evaluator-based ASR on JailbreakBench and by 37.7 points in StrongREJECT score, while requiring no rewriting or hiding of harmful content in the jailbreak prompt. Our findings underscore the urgent need for rethinking safety alignment in this emerging class of language models. Code is available at https://github.com/ZichenWen1/DIJA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11097</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 08:44:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elevating 3D Models: High-Quality Texture and Geometry Refinement from a   Low-Quality Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11465</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.11465.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nuri Ryu, Jiyun Won, Jooeun Son, Minsu Gong, Joo-Haeng Lee, Sunghyun Cho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; High-quality 3D assets are essential for various applications in computer graphics and 3D vision but remain scarce due to significant acquisition costs. To address this shortage, we introduce Elevate3D, a novel framework that transforms readily accessible low-quality 3D assets into higher quality. At the core of Elevate3D is HFS-SDEdit, a specialized texture enhancement method that significantly improves texture quality while preserving the appearance and geometry while fixing its degradations. Furthermore, Elevate3D operates in a view-by-view manner, alternating between texture and geometry refinement. Unlike previous methods that have largely overlooked geometry refinement, our framework leverages geometric cues from images refined with HFS-SDEdit by employing state-of-the-art monocular geometry predictors. This approach ensures detailed and accurate geometry that aligns seamlessly with the enhanced texture. Elevate3D outperforms recent competitors by achieving state-of-the-art quality in 3D model refinement, effectively addressing the scarcity of high-quality open-source 3D assets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11465</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 16:36:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Streaming 4D Visual Geometry Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11539</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.11539.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dong Zhuo, Wenzhao Zheng, Jiahe Guo, Yuqi Wu, Jie Zhou, Jiwen Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Perceiving and reconstructing 4D spatial-temporal geometry from videos is a fundamental yet challenging computer vision task. To facilitate interactive and real-time applications, we propose a streaming 4D visual geometry transformer that shares a similar philosophy with autoregressive large language models. We explore a simple and efficient design and employ a causal transformer architecture to process the input sequence in an online manner. We use temporal causal attention and cache the historical keys and values as implicit memory to enable efficient streaming long-term 4D reconstruction. This design can handle real-time 4D reconstruction by incrementally integrating historical information while maintaining high-quality spatial consistency. For efficient training, we propose to distill knowledge from the dense bidirectional visual geometry grounded transformer (VGGT) to our causal model. For inference, our model supports the migration of optimized efficient attention operator (e.g., FlashAttention) from the field of large language models. Extensive experiments on various 4D geometry perception benchmarks demonstrate that our model increases the inference speed in online scenarios while maintaining competitive performance, paving the way for scalable and interactive 4D vision systems. Code is available at: https://github.com/wzzheng/StreamVGGT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11539</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Risk Management in Volatile Markets with an Expectile-Based   Framework for the FTSE Index</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13391</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.13391.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abiodun Finbarrs Oketunji&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This research presents a framework for quantitative risk management in volatile markets, specifically focusing on expectile-based methodologies applied to the FTSE 100 index. Traditional risk measures such as Value-at-Risk (VaR) have demonstrated significant limitations during periods of market stress, as evidenced during the 2008 financial crisis and subsequent volatile periods. This study develops an advanced expectile-based framework that addresses the shortcomings of conventional quantile-based approaches by providing greater sensitivity to tail losses and improved stability in extreme market conditions. The research employs a dataset spanning two decades of FTSE 100 returns, incorporating periods of high volatility, market crashes, and recovery phases. Our methodology introduces novel mathematical formulations for expectile regression models, enhanced threshold determination techniques using time series analysis, and robust backtesting procedures. The empirical results demonstrate that expectile-based Value-at-Risk (EVaR) consistently outperforms traditional VaR measures across various confidence levels and market conditions. The framework exhibits superior performance during volatile periods, with reduced model risk and enhanced predictive accuracy. Furthermore, the study establishes practical implementation guidelines for financial institutions and provides evidence-based recommendations for regulatory compliance and portfolio management. The findings contribute significantly to the literature on financial risk management and offer practical tools for practitioners dealing with volatile market environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13391</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 08:24:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating Object Hallucinations via Sentence-Level Early Intervention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12455</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.12455.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shangpin Peng, Senqiao Yang, Li Jiang, Zhuotao Tian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have revolutionized cross-modal understanding but continue to struggle with hallucinations - fabricated content contradicting visual inputs. Existing hallucination mitigation methods either incur prohibitive computational costs or introduce distribution mismatches between training data and model outputs. We identify a critical insight: hallucinations predominantly emerge at the early stages of text generation and propagate through subsequent outputs. To address this, we propose **SENTINEL** (**S**entence-level **E**arly i**N**tervention **T**hrough **IN**-domain pr**E**ference **L**earning), a framework that eliminates dependency on human annotations. Specifically, we first bootstrap high-quality in-domain preference pairs by iteratively sampling model outputs, validating object existence through cross-checking with two open-vocabulary detectors, and classifying sentences into hallucinated/non-hallucinated categories. Subsequently, we use context-coherent positive samples and hallucinated negative samples to build context-aware preference data iteratively. Finally, we train models using a context-aware preference loss (C-DPO) that emphasizes discriminative learning at the sentence level where hallucinations initially manifest. Experimental results show that SENTINEL can reduce hallucinations by over 90\% compared to the original model and outperforms the previous state-of-the-art method on both hallucination benchmarks and general capabilities benchmarks, demonstrating its superiority and generalization ability. The models, datasets, and code are available at https://github.com/pspdada/SENTINEL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12455</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 17:55:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Serial Scaling Hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12549</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.12549.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxi Liu, Konpat Preechakul, Kananart Kuwaranancharoen, Yutong Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While machine learning has advanced through massive parallelization, we identify a critical blind spot: some problems are fundamentally sequential. These "inherently serial" problems-from mathematical reasoning to physical simulations to sequential decision-making-require dependent computational steps that cannot be parallelized. Drawing from complexity theory, we formalize this distinction and demonstrate that current parallel-centric architectures face fundamental limitations on such tasks. We argue that recognizing the serial nature of computation holds profound implications on machine learning, model design, hardware development. As AI tackles increasingly complex reasoning, deliberately scaling serial computation-not just parallel computation-is essential for continued progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12549</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 18:01:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mono-InternVL-1.5: Towards Cheaper and Faster Monolithic Multimodal   Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12566</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.12566.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gen Luo, Wenhan Dou, Wenhao Li, Zhaokai Wang, Xue Yang, Changyao Tian, Hao Li, Weiyun Wang, Wenhai Wang, Xizhou Zhu, Yu Qiao, Jifeng Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper focuses on monolithic Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs), which integrate visual encoding and language decoding into a single model. Existing structures and pre-training strategies for monolithic MLLMs often suffer from unstable optimization and catastrophic forgetting. To address these challenges, our key idea is to embed a new visual parameter space into a pre-trained LLM, enabling stable learning of visual knowledge from noisy data via delta tuning. Based on this principle, we first introduce Mono-InternVL, an advanced monolithic MLLM that incorporates a set of visual experts through a multimodal mixture-of-experts architecture. In addition, we design an innovative Endogenous Visual Pre-training (EViP) for Mono-InternVL to maximize its visual capabilities via progressive learning. Mono-InternVL achieves competitive performance against existing MLLMs but also leads to relatively expensive data cost. Therefore, we further present Mono-InternVL-1.5, a cheaper and stronger monolithic MLLM equipped with an improved EViP (EViP++). EViP++ introduces additional visual attention experts to Mono-InternVL-1.5 and re-organizes the pre-training process in an efficient manner. During inference, it includes a fused CUDA kernel to speed up its MoE operations. With these designs, Mono-InternVL-1.5 significantly reduces training and inference costs, while still maintaining competitive performance with Mono-InternVL. To evaluate our approach, we conduct extensive experiments across 15 benchmarks. Results demonstrate that Mono-InternVL outperforms existing monolithic MLLMs on 12 out of 15 benchmarks, e.g., +114-point improvement over Emu3 on OCRBench. Compared to its modular counterpart, i.e., InternVL-1.5, Mono-InternVL-1.5 achieves similar multimodal performance while reducing first-token latency by up to 69%. Code and models are released at https://github.com/OpenGVLab/Mono-InternVL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12566</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 18:31:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ParaStudent: Generating and Evaluating Realistic Student Code by   Teaching LLMs to Struggle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12674</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.12674.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mihran Miroyan, Rose Niousha, Joseph E. Gonzalez, Gireeja Ranade, Narges Norouzi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown strong performance on programming tasks, but can they generate student-like code like real students - imperfect, iterative, and stylistically diverse? We present ParaStudent, a systematic study of LLM-based "student-like" code generation in an introductory programming course setting. Using a dataset of timestamped student submissions across multiple semesters, we design low- and high-resolution experiments to model student progress and evaluate code outputs along semantic, functional, and stylistic dimensions. Our results show that fine-tuning significantly improves alignment with real student trajectories and captures error patterns, incremental improvements, and stylistic variations more faithfully. This study shows that modeling realistic student code requires capturing learning dynamics through context-aware generation, temporal modeling, and multi-dimensional evaluation. Code for experiments and evaluation is available at https://github.com/mmiroyan/ParaStudent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12674</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 23:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MCPEval: Automatic MCP-based Deep Evaluation for AI Agent Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12806</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.12806.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhiwei Liu, Jielin Qiu, Shiyu Wang, Jianguo Zhang, Zuxin Liu, Roshan Ram, Haolin Chen, Weiran Yao, Huan Wang, Shelby Heinecke, Silvio Savarese, Caiming Xiong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid rise of Large Language Models (LLMs)-based intelligent agents underscores the need for robust, scalable evaluation frameworks. Existing methods rely on static benchmarks and labor-intensive data collection, limiting practical assessment. We introduce \oursystemname, an open-source Model Context Protocol (MCP)-based framework that automates end-to-end task generation and deep evaluation of LLM agents across diverse domains. MCPEval standardizes metrics, seamlessly integrates with native agent tools, and eliminates manual effort in building evaluation pipelines. Empirical results across five real-world domains show its effectiveness in revealing nuanced, domain-specific performance. We publicly release MCPEval https://github.com/SalesforceAIResearch/MCPEval to promote reproducible and standardized LLM agent evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12806</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 05:46:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Reinforcement Learning Meets Large Language Model Post-Training:   Basics, Advances, and Opportunities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13158</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.13158.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Sun, Mihaela van der Schaar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In the era of Large Language Models (LLMs), alignment has emerged as a fundamental yet challenging problem in the pursuit of more reliable, controllable, and capable machine intelligence. The recent success of reasoning models and conversational AI systems has underscored the critical role of reinforcement learning (RL) in enhancing these systems, driving increased research interest at the intersection of RL and LLM alignment. This paper provides a comprehensive review of recent advances in LLM alignment through the lens of inverse reinforcement learning (IRL), emphasizing the distinctions between RL techniques employed in LLM alignment and those in conventional RL tasks. In particular, we highlight the necessity of constructing neural reward models from human data and discuss the formal and practical implications of this paradigm shift. We begin by introducing fundamental concepts in RL to provide a foundation for readers unfamiliar with the field. We then examine recent advances in this research agenda, discussing key challenges and opportunities in conducting IRL for LLM alignment. Beyond methodological considerations, we explore practical aspects, including datasets, benchmarks, evaluation metrics, infrastructure, and computationally efficient training and inference techniques. Finally, we draw insights from the literature on sparse-reward RL to identify open questions and potential research directions. By synthesizing findings from diverse studies, we aim to provide a structured and critical overview of the field, highlight unresolved challenges, and outline promising future directions for improving LLM alignment through RL and IRL techniques.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13158</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 14:22:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Generative Energy Arena (GEA): Incorporating Energy Awareness in   Large Language Model (LLM) Human Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13302</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.13302.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Carlos Arriaga, Gonzalo Martínez, Eneko Sendin, Javier Conde, Pedro Reviriego&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The evaluation of large language models is a complex task, in which several approaches have been proposed. The most common is the use of automated benchmarks in which LLMs have to answer multiple-choice questions of different topics. However, this method has certain limitations, being the most concerning, the poor correlation with the humans. An alternative approach, is to have humans evaluate the LLMs. This poses scalability issues as there is a large and growing number of models to evaluate making it impractical (and costly) to run traditional studies based on recruiting a number of evaluators and having them rank the responses of the models. An alternative approach is the use of public arenas, such as the popular LM arena, on which any user can freely evaluate models on any question and rank the responses of two models. The results are then elaborated into a model ranking. An increasingly important aspect of LLMs is their energy consumption and, therefore, evaluating how energy awareness influences the decisions of humans in selecting a model is of interest. In this paper, we present GEA, the Generative Energy Arena, an arena that incorporates information on the energy consumption of the model in the evaluation process. Preliminary results obtained with GEA are also presented, showing that for most questions, when users are aware of the energy consumption, they favor smaller and more energy efficient models. This suggests that for most user interactions, the extra cost and energy incurred by the more complex and top-performing models do not provide an increase in the perceived quality of the responses that justifies their use.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13302</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 17:11:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"PhyWorldBench": A Comprehensive Evaluation of Physical Realism in   Text-to-Video Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13428</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.13428.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jing Gu, Xian Liu, Yu Zeng, Ashwin Nagarajan, Fangrui Zhu, Daniel Hong, Yue Fan, Qianqi Yan, Kaiwen Zhou, Ming-Yu Liu, Xin Eric Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video generation models have achieved remarkable progress in creating high-quality, photorealistic content. However, their ability to accurately simulate physical phenomena remains a critical and unresolved challenge. This paper presents PhyWorldBench, a comprehensive benchmark designed to evaluate video generation models based on their adherence to the laws of physics. The benchmark covers multiple levels of physical phenomena, ranging from fundamental principles like object motion and energy conservation to more complex scenarios involving rigid body interactions and human or animal motion. Additionally, we introduce a novel ""Anti-Physics"" category, where prompts intentionally violate real-world physics, enabling the assessment of whether models can follow such instructions while maintaining logical consistency. Besides large-scale human evaluation, we also design a simple yet effective method that could utilize current MLLM to evaluate the physics realism in a zero-shot fashion. We evaluate 12 state-of-the-art text-to-video generation models, including five open-source and five proprietary models, with a detailed comparison and analysis. we identify pivotal challenges models face in adhering to real-world physics. Through systematic testing of their outputs across 1,050 curated prompts-spanning fundamental, composite, and anti-physics scenarios-we identify pivotal challenges these models face in adhering to real-world physics. We then rigorously examine their performance on diverse physical phenomena with varying prompt types, deriving targeted recommendations for crafting prompts that enhance fidelity to physical principles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13428</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 17:54:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Promptomatix: An Automatic Prompt Optimization Framework for Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14241</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14241.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rithesh Murthy, Ming Zhu, Liangwei Yang, Jielin Qiu, Juntao Tan, Shelby Heinecke, Caiming Xiong, Silvio Savarese, Huan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) perform best with well-crafted prompts, yet prompt engineering remains manual, inconsistent, and inaccessible to non-experts. We introduce Promptomatix, an automatic prompt optimization framework that transforms natural language task descriptions into high-quality prompts without requiring manual tuning or domain expertise. Promptomatix supports both a lightweight meta-prompt-based optimizer and a DSPy-powered compiler, with modular design enabling future extension to more advanced frameworks. The system analyzes user intent, generates synthetic training data, selects prompting strategies, and refines prompts using cost-aware objectives. Evaluated across 5 task categories, Promptomatix achieves competitive or superior performance compared to existing libraries, while reducing prompt length and computational overhead making prompt optimization scalable and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14241</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 18:18:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PrefPalette: Personalized Preference Modeling with Latent Attributes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13541</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.13541.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuyue Stella Li, Melanie Sclar, Hunter Lang, Ansong Ni, Jacqueline He, Puxin Xu, Andrew Cohen, Chan Young Park, Yulia Tsvetkov, Asli Celikyilmaz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Personalizing AI systems requires understanding not just what users prefer, but the reasons that underlie those preferences - yet current preference models typically treat human judgment as a black box. We introduce PrefPalette, a framework that decomposes preferences into attribute dimensions and tailors its preference prediction to distinct social community values in a human-interpretable manner. PrefPalette operationalizes a cognitive science principle known as multi-attribute decision making in two ways: (1) a scalable counterfactual attribute synthesis step that involves generating synthetic training data to isolate for individual attribute effects (e.g., formality, humor, cultural values), and (2) attention-based preference modeling that learns how different social communities dynamically weight these attributes. This approach moves beyond aggregate preference modeling to capture the diverse evaluation frameworks that drive human judgment. When evaluated on 45 social communities from the online platform Reddit, PrefPalette outperforms GPT-4o by 46.6% in average prediction accuracy. Beyond raw predictive improvements, PrefPalette also shed light on intuitive, community-specific profiles: scholarly communities prioritize verbosity and stimulation, conflict-oriented communities value sarcasm and directness, and support-based communities emphasize empathy. By modeling the attribute-mediated structure of human judgment, PrefPalette delivers both superior preference modeling and transparent, interpretable insights, and serves as a first step toward more trustworthy, value-aware personalized applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13541</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 21:21:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>nablaNABLA: Neighborhood Adaptive Block-Level Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13546</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.13546.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dmitrii Mikhailov, Aleksey Letunovskiy, Maria Kovaleva, Vladimir Arkhipkin, Vladimir Korviakov, Vladimir Polovnikov, Viacheslav Vasilev, Evelina Sidorova, Denis Dimitrov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in transformer-based architectures has demonstrated remarkable success in video generation tasks. However, the quadratic complexity of full attention mechanisms remains a critical bottleneck, particularly for high-resolution and long-duration video sequences. In this paper, we propose NABLA, a novel Neighborhood Adaptive Block-Level Attention mechanism that dynamically adapts to sparsity patterns in video diffusion transformers (DiTs). By leveraging block-wise attention with adaptive sparsity-driven threshold, NABLA reduces computational overhead while preserving generative quality. Our method does not require custom low-level operator design and can be seamlessly integrated with PyTorch's Flex Attention operator. Experiments demonstrate that NABLA achieves up to 2.7x faster training and inference compared to baseline almost without compromising quantitative metrics (CLIP score, VBench score, human evaluation score) and visual quality drop. The code and model weights are available here: https://github.com/gen-ai-team/Wan2.1-NABLA&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13546</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 21:36:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Data-Centric Framework for Addressing Phonetic and Prosodic Challenges   in Russian Speech Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13563</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.13563.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kirill Borodin, Nikita Vasiliev, Vasiliy Kudryavtsev, Maxim Maslov, Mikhail Gorodnichev, Oleg Rogov, Grach Mkrtchian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Russian speech synthesis presents distinctive challenges, including vowel reduction, consonant devoicing, variable stress patterns, homograph ambiguity, and unnatural intonation. This paper introduces Balalaika, a novel dataset comprising more than 2,000 hours of studio-quality Russian speech with comprehensive textual annotations, including punctuation and stress markings. Experimental results show that models trained on Balalaika significantly outperform those trained on existing datasets in both speech synthesis and enhancement tasks. We detail the dataset construction pipeline, annotation methodology, and results of comparative evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13563</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 22:41:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CSD-VAR: Content-Style Decomposition in Visual Autoregressive Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13984</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.13984.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Quang-Binh Nguyen, Minh Luu, Quang Nguyen, Anh Tran, Khoi Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Disentangling content and style from a single image, known as content-style decomposition (CSD), enables recontextualization of extracted content and stylization of extracted styles, offering greater creative flexibility in visual synthesis. While recent personalization methods have explored the decomposition of explicit content style, they remain tailored for diffusion models. Meanwhile, Visual Autoregressive Modeling (VAR) has emerged as a promising alternative with a next-scale prediction paradigm, achieving performance comparable to that of diffusion models. In this paper, we explore VAR as a generative framework for CSD, leveraging its scale-wise generation process for improved disentanglement. To this end, we propose CSD-VAR, a novel method that introduces three key innovations: (1) a scale-aware alternating optimization strategy that aligns content and style representation with their respective scales to enhance separation, (2) an SVD-based rectification method to mitigate content leakage into style representations, and (3) an Augmented Key-Value (K-V) memory enhancing content identity preservation. To benchmark this task, we introduce CSD-100, a dataset specifically designed for content-style decomposition, featuring diverse subjects rendered in various artistic styles. Experiments demonstrate that CSD-VAR outperforms prior approaches, achieving superior content preservation and stylization fidelity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13984</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 14:45:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UGPL: Uncertainty-Guided Progressive Learning for Evidence-Based   Classification in Computed Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14102</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14102.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shravan Venkatraman, Pavan Kumar S, Rakesh Raj Madavan, Chandrakala S&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Accurate classification of computed tomography (CT) images is essential for diagnosis and treatment planning, but existing methods often struggle with the subtle and spatially diverse nature of pathological features. Current approaches typically process images uniformly, limiting their ability to detect localized abnormalities that require focused analysis. We introduce UGPL, an uncertainty-guided progressive learning framework that performs a global-to-local analysis by first identifying regions of diagnostic ambiguity and then conducting detailed examination of these critical areas. Our approach employs evidential deep learning to quantify predictive uncertainty, guiding the extraction of informative patches through a non-maximum suppression mechanism that maintains spatial diversity. This progressive refinement strategy, combined with an adaptive fusion mechanism, enables UGPL to integrate both contextual information and fine-grained details. Experiments across three CT datasets demonstrate that UGPL consistently outperforms state-of-the-art methods, achieving improvements of 3.29%, 2.46%, and 8.08% in accuracy for kidney abnormality, lung cancer, and COVID-19 detection, respectively. Our analysis shows that the uncertainty-guided component provides substantial benefits, with performance dramatically increasing when the full progressive learning pipeline is implemented. Our code is available at: https://github.com/shravan-18/UGPL&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14102</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 17:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NoHumansRequired: Autonomous High-Quality Image Editing Triplet Mining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14119</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14119.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Maksim Kuprashevich, Grigorii Alekseenko, Irina Tolstykh, Georgii Fedorov, Bulat Suleimanov, Vladimir Dokholyan, Aleksandr Gordeev&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in generative modeling enable image editing assistants that follow natural language instructions without additional user input. Their supervised training requires millions of triplets: original image, instruction, edited image. Yet mining pixel-accurate examples is hard. Each edit must affect only prompt-specified regions, preserve stylistic coherence, respect physical plausibility, and retain visual appeal. The lack of robust automated edit-quality metrics hinders reliable automation at scale. We present an automated, modular pipeline that mines high-fidelity triplets across domains, resolutions, instruction complexities, and styles. Built on public generative models and running without human intervention, our system uses a task-tuned Gemini validator to score instruction adherence and aesthetics directly, removing any need for segmentation or grounding models. Inversion and compositional bootstrapping enlarge the mined set by approximately 2.2x, enabling large-scale high-fidelity training data. By automating the most repetitive annotation steps, the approach allows a new scale of training without human labeling effort. To democratize research in this resource-intensive area, we release NHR-Edit: an open dataset of 358k high-quality triplets. In the largest cross-dataset evaluation, it surpasses all public alternatives. We also release Bagel-NHR-Edit, an open-source fine-tuned Bagel model, which achieves state-of-the-art metrics in our experiments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14119</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenBEATs: A Fully Open-Source General-Purpose Audio Encoder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14129</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14129.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shikhar Bharadwaj, Samuele Cornell, Kwanghee Choi, Satoru Fukayama, Hye-jin Shim, Soham Deshmukh, Shinji Watanabe&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Masked token prediction has emerged as a powerful pre-training objective across language, vision, and speech, offering the potential to unify these diverse modalities through a single pre-training task. However, its application for general audio understanding remains underexplored, with BEATs being the only notable example. BEATs has seen limited modifications due to the absence of open-source pre-training code. Furthermore, BEATs was trained only on AudioSet, restricting its broader downstream applicability. To address these gaps, we present OpenBEATs, an open-source framework that extends BEATs via multi-domain audio pre-training. We conduct comprehensive evaluations across six types of tasks, twenty five datasets, and three audio domains, including audio reasoning tasks such as audio question answering, entailment, and captioning. OpenBEATs achieves state-of-the-art performance on six bioacoustics datasets, two environmental sound datasets and five reasoning datasets, performing better than models exceeding a billion parameters at one-fourth their parameter size. These results demonstrate the effectiveness of multi-domain datasets and masked token prediction task to learn general-purpose audio representations. To promote further research and reproducibility, we release all pre-training and evaluation code, pretrained and fine-tuned checkpoints, and training logs at https://shikhar-s.github.io/OpenBEATs&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14129</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 17:57:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Franca: Nested Matryoshka Clustering for Scalable Visual Representation   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14137</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14137.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shashanka Venkataramanan, Valentinos Pariza, Mohammadreza Salehi, Lukas Knobel, Spyros Gidaris, Elias Ramzi, Andrei Bursuc, Yuki M. Asano&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Franca (pronounced Fran-ka): free one; the first fully open-source (data, code, weights) vision foundation model that matches and in many cases surpasses the performance of state-of-the-art proprietary models, e.g., DINOv2, CLIP, SigLIPv2, etc. Our approach is grounded in a transparent training pipeline inspired by Web-SSL and uses publicly available data: ImageNet-21K and a subset of ReLAION-2B. Beyond model release, we tackle critical limitations in SSL clustering methods. While modern models rely on assigning image features to large codebooks via clustering algorithms like Sinkhorn-Knopp, they fail to account for the inherent ambiguity in clustering semantics. To address this, we introduce a parameter-efficient, multi-head clustering projector based on nested Matryoshka representations. This design progressively refines features into increasingly fine-grained clusters without increasing the model size, enabling both performance and memory efficiency. Additionally, we propose a novel positional disentanglement strategy that explicitly removes positional biases from dense representations, thereby improving the encoding of semantic content. This leads to consistent gains on several downstream benchmarks, demonstrating the utility of cleaner feature spaces. Our contributions establish a new standard for transparent, high-performance vision models and open a path toward more reproducible and generalizable foundation models for the broader AI community. The code and model checkpoints are available at https://github.com/valeoai/Franca.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14137</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 17:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Simple "Try Again" Can Elicit Multi-Turn LLM Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14295</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14295.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Licheng Liu, Zihan Wang, Linjie Li, Chenwei Xu, Yiping Lu, Han Liu, Avirup Sil, Manling Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-turn problem solving is critical yet challenging for Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) to reflect on their reasoning and revise from feedback. Existing Reinforcement Learning (RL) methods train large reasoning models on a single-turn paradigm with verifiable rewards. However, we observe that models trained with existing RL paradigms often lose their ability to solve problems across multiple turns and struggle to revise answers based on contextual feedback, leading to repetitive responses. We ask: can LRMs learn to reflect their answers in a multi-turn context? In this work, we find that training models with multi-turn RL using only unary feedback (e.g., "Let's try again") after wrong answers can improve both single-turn performance and multi-turn reasoning. We introduce Unary Feedback as Observation (UFO) for reinforcement learning, which uses minimal yet common unary user feedback during iterative problem solving. It can be easily applied to existing single-turn RL training setups. Experimental results show that RL training with UFO keeps single-turn performance and improves multi-turn reasoning accuracy by up to 14%, enabling language models to better react to feedback in multi-turn problem solving. To further minimize the number of turns needed for a correct answer while encouraging diverse reasoning when mistakes occur, we design reward structures that guide models to produce careful and deliberate answers in each turn. Code: https://github.com/lichengliu03/unary-feedback&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14295</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 18:07:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Scaling in Test-Time Compute</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14417</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14417.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aryo Pradipta Gema, Alexander Hägele, Runjin Chen, Andy Arditi, Jacob Goldman-Wetzler, Kit Fraser-Taliente, Henry Sleight, Linda Petrini, Julian Michael, Beatrice Alex, Pasquale Minervini, Yanda Chen, Joe Benton, Ethan Perez&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We construct evaluation tasks where extending the reasoning length of Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) deteriorates performance, exhibiting an inverse scaling relationship between test-time compute and accuracy. Our evaluation tasks span four categories: simple counting tasks with distractors, regression tasks with spurious features, deduction tasks with constraint tracking, and advanced AI risks. We identify five distinct failure modes when models reason for longer: 1) Claude models become increasingly distracted by irrelevant information; 2) OpenAI o-series models resist distractors but overfit to problem framings; 3) models shift from reasonable priors to spurious correlations; 4) all models show difficulties in maintaining focus on complex deductive tasks; and 5) extended reasoning may amplify concerning behaviors, with Claude Sonnet 4 showing increased expressions of self-preservation. These findings suggest that while test-time compute scaling remains promising for improving model capabilities, it may inadvertently reinforce problematic reasoning patterns. Our results demonstrate the importance of evaluating models across diverse reasoning lengths to identify and address these failure modes in LRMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14417</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 00:06:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiroMind-M1: An Open-Source Advancement in Mathematical Reasoning via   Context-Aware Multi-Stage Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14683</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14683.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xingxuan Li, Yao Xiao, Dianwen Ng, Hai Ye, Yue Deng, Xiang Lin, Bin Wang, Zhanfeng Mo, Chong Zhang, Yueyi Zhang, Zonglin Yang, Ruilin Li, Lei Lei, Shihao Xu, Han Zhao, Weiling Chen, Feng Ji, Lidong Bing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 109&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models have recently evolved from fluent text generation to advanced reasoning across diverse domains, giving rise to reasoning language models. Among these domains, mathematical reasoning serves as a representative benchmark as it requires precise multi-step logic and abstract reasoning, which can be generalized to other tasks. While closed-source RLMs such as GPT-o3 demonstrate impressive reasoning capabilities, their proprietary nature limits transparency and reproducibility. Although many open-source projects aim to close this gap, most of them lack sufficient openness by omitting critical resources such as datasets and detailed training configurations, which hinders reproducibility. To contribute toward greater transparency in RLM development, we introduce the MiroMind-M1 series, a set of fully open-source RLMs built on the Qwen-2.5 backbone that match or exceed the performance of existing open-source RLMs. Specifically, our models are trained in two stages: SFT on a carefully curated corpus of 719K math-reasoning problems with verified CoT trajectories, followed by RLVR on 62K challenging and verifiable problems. To enhance the robustness and efficiency of the RLVR process, we introduce Context-Aware Multi-Stage Policy Optimization, an algorithm that integrates length-progressive training with an adaptive repetition penalty to encourage context-aware RL training. Our model achieves state-of-the-art or competitive performance and superior token efficiency among Qwen-2.5-based open-source 7B and 32B models on the AIME24, AIME25, and MATH benchmarks. To facilitate reproducibility, we release the complete stack: models (MiroMind-M1-SFT-7B, MiroMind-M1-RL-7B, MiroMind-M1-RL-32B); datasets (MiroMind-M1-SFT-719K, MiroMind-M1-RL-62K); and all training and evaluation configurations. We hope these resources will support further research and foster community advancement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14683</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 16:21:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Invisible Leash: Why RLVR May Not Escape Its Origin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14843</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14843.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fang Wu, Weihao Xuan, Ximing Lu, Zaid Harchaoui, Yejin Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large reasoning models highlight Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) as a promising method for enhancing AI's capabilities, particularly in solving complex logical tasks. However, it remains unclear whether RLVR truly expands a model's reasoning boundary or merely amplifies high-reward outputs that the base model already knows for improved precision. This study presents a theoretical and empirical investigation that provides fresh insights into the potential limits of RLVR. First, we offer a new theoretical perspective that RLVR is constrained by the base model's support-unable to sample solutions with zero initial probability-and operates as a conservative reweighting mechanism that may restrict the discovery of entirely original solutions. We also identify an entropy-reward tradeoff: while RLVR reliably enhances precision, it may progressively narrow exploration and potentially overlook correct yet underrepresented solutions. Extensive empirical experiments validate that while RLVR consistently improves pass@1, the shrinkage of empirical support generally outweighs the expansion of empirical support under larger sampling budgets, failing to recover correct answers that were previously accessible to the base model. Interestingly, we also observe that while RLVR sometimes increases token-level entropy, resulting in greater uncertainty at each generation step, answer-level entropy declines, indicating that these seemingly more uncertain paths ultimately converge onto a smaller set of distinct answers. Taken together, these findings reveal potential limits of RLVR in extending reasoning horizons. Breaking this invisible leash may require future algorithmic innovations such as explicit exploration mechanisms or hybrid strategies that seed probability mass into underrepresented solution regions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14843</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 07:04:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MUR: Momentum Uncertainty guided Reasoning for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14958</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14958.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hang Yan, Fangzhi Xu, Rongman Xu, Yifei Li, Jian Zhang, Haoran Luo, Xiaobao Wu, Luu Anh Tuan, Haiteng Zhao, Qika Lin, Jun Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have achieved impressive performance on reasoning-intensive tasks, yet optimizing their reasoning efficiency remains an open challenge. While Test-Time Scaling (TTS) improves reasoning quality, it often leads to overthinking, wasting tokens on redundant computations. This work investigates how to efficiently and adaptively guide LLM test-time scaling without additional training. Inspired by the concept of momentum in physics, we propose Momentum Uncertainty-guided Reasoning (MUR), which dynamically allocates thinking budgets to critical reasoning steps by tracking and aggregating stepwise uncertainty over time. To support flexible inference-time control, we introduce gamma-control, a simple mechanism that tunes the reasoning budget via a single hyperparameter. We provide in-depth theoretical proof to support the superiority of MUR in terms of stability and biases. MUR is comprehensively evaluated against various TTS methods across four challenging benchmarks (MATH-500, AIME24, AIME25, and GPQA-diamond) using different sizes of recent Qwen3 models (1.7B, 4B, and 8B). Results demonstrate that MUR reduces computation by over 50% on average while improving accuracy by 0.62-3.37%.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14958</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 13:36:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DMOSpeech 2: Reinforcement Learning for Duration Prediction in   Metric-Optimized Speech Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14988</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.14988.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yinghao Aaron Li, Xilin Jiang, Fei Tao, Cheng Niu, Kaifeng Xu, Juntong Song, Nima Mesgarani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion-based text-to-speech (TTS) systems have made remarkable progress in zero-shot speech synthesis, yet optimizing all components for perceptual metrics remains challenging. Prior work with DMOSpeech demonstrated direct metric optimization for speech generation components, but duration prediction remained unoptimized. This paper presents DMOSpeech 2, which extends metric optimization to the duration predictor through a reinforcement learning approach. The proposed system implements a novel duration policy framework using group relative preference optimization (GRPO) with speaker similarity and word error rate as reward signals. By optimizing this previously unoptimized component, DMOSpeech 2 creates a more complete metric-optimized synthesis pipeline. Additionally, this paper introduces teacher-guided sampling, a hybrid approach leveraging a teacher model for initial denoising steps before transitioning to the student model, significantly improving output diversity while maintaining efficiency. Comprehensive evaluations demonstrate superior performance across all metrics compared to previous systems, while reducing sampling steps by half without quality degradation. These advances represent a significant step toward speech synthesis systems with metric optimization across multiple components. The audio samples, code and pre-trained models are available at https://dmospeech2.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14988</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 14:48:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RefCritic: Training Long Chain-of-Thought Critic Models with Refinement   Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15024</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15024.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qiaoyu Tang, Hao Xiang, Le Yu, Bowen Yu, Hongyu Lin, Yaojie Lu, Xianpei Han, Le Sun, Junyang Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the rapid advancement of Large Language Models (LLMs), developing effective critic modules for precise guidance has become crucial yet challenging. In this paper, we initially demonstrate that supervised fine-tuning for building critic modules (which is widely adopted in current solutions) fails to genuinely enhance models' critique abilities, producing superficial critiques with insufficient reflections and verifications. To unlock the unprecedented critique capabilities, we propose RefCritic, a long-chain-of-thought critic module based on reinforcement learning with dual rule-based rewards: (1) instance-level correctness of solution judgments and (2) refinement accuracies of the policy model based on critiques, aiming to generate high-quality evaluations with actionable feedback that effectively guides model refinement. We evaluate RefCritic on Qwen2.5-14B-Instruct and DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-14B across five benchmarks. On critique and refinement settings, RefCritic demonstrates consistent advantages across all benchmarks, e.g., 6.8\% and 7.2\% gains on AIME25 for the respective base models. Notably, under majority voting, policy models filtered by RefCritic show superior scaling with increased voting numbers. Moreover, despite training on solution-level supervision, RefCritic outperforms step-level supervised approaches on ProcessBench, a benchmark to identify erroneous steps in mathematical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15024</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 16:19:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Video Thinking Test: A Holistic Benchmark for Advanced Video   Reasoning and Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15028</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15028.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuanhan Zhang, Yunice Chew, Yuhao Dong, Aria Leo, Bo Hu, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Human intelligence requires correctness and robustness, with the former being foundational for the latter. In video understanding, correctness ensures the accurate interpretation of visual content, and robustness maintains consistent performance in challenging conditions. Despite advances in video large language models (video LLMs), existing benchmarks inadequately reflect the gap between these models and human intelligence in maintaining correctness and robustness in video interpretation. We introduce the Video Thinking Test (Video-TT), to assess if video LLMs can interpret real-world videos as effectively as humans. Video-TT reflects genuine gaps in understanding complex visual narratives, and evaluates robustness against natural adversarial questions. Video-TT comprises 1,000 YouTube Shorts videos, each with one open-ended question and four adversarial questions that probe visual and narrative complexity. Our evaluation shows a significant gap between video LLMs and human performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15028</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 16:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WebShaper: Agentically Data Synthesizing via Information-Seeking   Formalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15061</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15061.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengwei Tao, Jialong Wu, Wenbiao Yin, Junkai Zhang, Baixuan Li, Haiyang Shen, Kuan Li, Liwen Zhang, Xinyu Wang, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The advent of Large Language Model (LLM)-powered agents has revolutionized artificial intelligence by enabling solutions to complex, open-ended tasks through web-based information-seeking (IS) capabilities. The scarcity of high-quality training data has limited the development of IS agents. Existing approaches typically adopt an information-driven paradigm that first collects web data and then generates questions based on the retrieval. However, this may lead to inconsistency between information structure and reasoning structure, question and answer. To mitigate, we propose a formalization-driven IS data synthesis framework WebShaper to construct a dataset. WebShaper systematically formalizes IS tasks through set theory. Central to the formalization is the concept of Knowledge Projections (KP), which enables precise control over reasoning structure by KP operation compositions. During synthesis, we begin by creating seed tasks, then use a multi-step expansion process. At each step, an agentic Expander expands the current formal question more complex with retrieval and validation tools based on our formalization. We train our model on the synthesized dataset. Experiment results demonstrate that WebShaper achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-sourced IS agents on GAIA and WebWalkerQA benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15061</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2025 17:53:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPAR: Scholar Paper Retrieval with LLM-based Agents for Enhanced   Academic Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15245</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15245.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaofeng Shi, Yuduo Li, Qian Kou, Longbin Yu, Jinxin Xie, Hua Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have opened new opportunities for academic literature retrieval. However, existing systems often rely on rigid pipelines and exhibit limited reasoning capabilities. We introduce SPAR, a multi-agent framework that incorporates RefChain-based query decomposition and query evolution to enable more flexible and effective search. To facilitate systematic evaluation, we also construct SPARBench, a challenging benchmark with expert-annotated relevance labels. Experimental results demonstrate that SPAR substantially outperforms strong baselines, achieving up to +56% F1 on AutoScholar and +23% F1 on SPARBench over the best-performing baseline. Together, SPAR and SPARBench provide a scalable, interpretable, and high-performing foundation for advancing research in scholarly retrieval. Code and data will be available at: https://github.com/xiaofengShi/SPAR&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15245</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 05:06:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STITCH: Simultaneous Thinking and Talking with Chunked Reasoning for   Spoken Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15375</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15375.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng-Han Chiang, Xiaofei Wang, Linjie Li, Chung-Ching Lin, Kevin Lin, Shujie Liu, Zhendong Wang, Zhengyuan Yang, Hung-yi Lee, Lijuan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Spoken Language Models (SLMs) are designed to take speech inputs and produce spoken responses. However, current SLMs lack the ability to perform an internal, unspoken thinking process before responding. In contrast, humans typically engage in complex mental reasoning internally, enabling them to communicate ideas clearly and concisely. Thus, integrating an unspoken thought process into SLMs is highly desirable. While naively generating a complete chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning before starting to talk can enable thinking for SLMs, this induces additional latency for the speech response, as the CoT reasoning can be arbitrarily long. To solve this issue, we propose Stitch, a novel generation method that alternates between the generation of unspoken reasoning chunks and spoken response chunks. Since the audio duration of a chunk of spoken response is much longer than the time to generate the tokens in a chunk of spoken response, we use the remaining free time to generate the unspoken reasoning tokens. When a chunk of audio is played to the user, the model continues to generate the next unspoken reasoning chunk, achieving simultaneous thinking and talking. Remarkably, Stitch matches the latency of baselines that cannot generate unspoken CoT by design while outperforming those baselines by 15% on math reasoning datasets; Stitch also performs equally well on non-reasoning datasets as those baseline models. Some animations and demonstrations are on the project page: https://d223302.github.io/STITCH.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15375</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 08:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ObjectGS: Object-aware Scene Reconstruction and Scene Understanding via   Gaussian Splatting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15454</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15454.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruijie Zhu, Mulin Yu, Linning Xu, Lihan Jiang, Yixuan Li, Tianzhu Zhang, Jiangmiao Pang, Bo Dai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D Gaussian Splatting is renowned for its high-fidelity reconstructions and real-time novel view synthesis, yet its lack of semantic understanding limits object-level perception. In this work, we propose ObjectGS, an object-aware framework that unifies 3D scene reconstruction with semantic understanding. Instead of treating the scene as a unified whole, ObjectGS models individual objects as local anchors that generate neural Gaussians and share object IDs, enabling precise object-level reconstruction. During training, we dynamically grow or prune these anchors and optimize their features, while a one-hot ID encoding with a classification loss enforces clear semantic constraints. We show through extensive experiments that ObjectGS not only outperforms state-of-the-art methods on open-vocabulary and panoptic segmentation tasks, but also integrates seamlessly with applications like mesh extraction and scene editing. Project page: https://ruijiezhu94.github.io/ObjectGS_page&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15454</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 10:06:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GR-3 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15493</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15493.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chilam Cheang, Sijin Chen, Zhongren Cui, Yingdong Hu, Liqun Huang, Tao Kong, Hang Li, Yifeng Li, Yuxiao Liu, Xiao Ma, Hao Niu, Wenxuan Ou, Wanli Peng, Zeyu Ren, Haixin Shi, Jiawen Tian, Hongtao Wu, Xin Xiao, Yuyang Xiao, Jiafeng Xu, Yichu Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We report our recent progress towards building generalist robot policies, the development of GR-3. GR-3 is a large-scale vision-language-action (VLA) model. It showcases exceptional capabilities in generalizing to novel objects, environments, and instructions involving abstract concepts. Furthermore, it can be efficiently fine-tuned with minimal human trajectory data, enabling rapid and cost-effective adaptation to new settings. GR-3 also excels in handling long-horizon and dexterous tasks, including those requiring bi-manual manipulation and mobile movement, showcasing robust and reliable performance. These capabilities are achieved through a multi-faceted training recipe that includes co-training with web-scale vision-language data, efficient fine-tuning from human trajectory data collected via VR devices, and effective imitation learning with robot trajectory data. In addition, we introduce ByteMini, a versatile bi-manual mobile robot designed with exceptional flexibility and reliability, capable of accomplishing a wide range of tasks when integrated with GR-3. Through extensive real-world experiments, we show GR-3 surpasses the state-of-the-art baseline method, pi_0, on a wide variety of challenging tasks. We hope GR-3 can serve as a step towards building generalist robots capable of assisting humans in daily life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15493</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 10:54:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhysGym: Benchmarking LLMs in Interactive Physics Discovery with   Controlled Priors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15550</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15550.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yimeng Chen, Piotr Piȩkos, Mateusz Ostaszewski, Firas Laakom, Jürgen Schmidhuber&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating the scientific discovery capabilities of large language model based agents, particularly how they cope with varying environmental complexity and utilize prior knowledge, requires specialized benchmarks currently lacking in the landscape. To address this gap, we introduce PhysGym, a novel benchmark suite and simulation platform for rigorously assessing LLM-based scientific reasoning in interactive physics environments. PhysGym's primary contribution lies in its sophisticated control over the level of prior knowledge provided to the agent. This allows researchers to dissect agent performance along axes including the complexity of the problem and the prior knowledge levels. The benchmark comprises a suite of interactive simulations, where agents must actively probe environments, gather data sequentially under constraints and formulate hypotheses about underlying physical laws. PhysGym provides standardized evaluation protocols and metrics for assessing hypothesis accuracy and model fidelity. We demonstrate the benchmark's utility by presenting results from baseline LLMs, showcasing its ability to differentiate capabilities based on varying priors and task complexity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15550</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 12:28:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SegDT: A Diffusion Transformer-Based Segmentation Model for Medical   Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15595</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15595.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Salah Eddine Bekhouche, Gaby Maroun, Fadi Dornaika, Abdenour Hadid&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Medical image segmentation is crucial for many healthcare tasks, including disease diagnosis and treatment planning. One key area is the segmentation of skin lesions, which is vital for diagnosing skin cancer and monitoring patients. In this context, this paper introduces SegDT, a new segmentation model based on diffusion transformer (DiT). SegDT is designed to work on low-cost hardware and incorporates Rectified Flow, which improves the generation quality at reduced inference steps and maintains the flexibility of standard diffusion models. Our method is evaluated on three benchmarking datasets and compared against several existing works, achieving state-of-the-art results while maintaining fast inference speeds. This makes the proposed model appealing for real-world medical applications. This work advances the performance and capabilities of deep learning models in medical image analysis, enabling faster, more accurate diagnostic tools for healthcare professionals. The code is made publicly available at https://github.com/Bekhouche/SegDT{GitHub}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15595</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 13:18:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Being-H0: Vision-Language-Action Pretraining from Large-Scale Human   Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15597</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15597.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Luo, Yicheng Feng, Wanpeng Zhang, Sipeng Zheng, Ye Wang, Haoqi Yuan, Jiazheng Liu, Chaoyi Xu, Qin Jin, Zongqing Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Being-H0, a dexterous Vision-Language-Action model (VLA) trained on large-scale human videos. Existing VLAs struggle with complex manipulation tasks requiring high dexterity and generalize poorly to novel scenarios and tasks, primarily due to their reliance on synthetic data with significant sim-to-real gaps or teleoperated demonstrations lacking scale and diversity. To address this data bottleneck, we propose leveraging human hands as a foundation manipulator, capitalizing on the rich dexterity and scalability present in web data. Our approach centers on physical instruction tuning, a novel training paradigm that combines large-scale VLA pretraining from human videos, physical space alignment for 3D reasoning, and post-training adaptation for robotic tasks. Additionally, we introduce a part-level motion tokenization method which achieves millimeter-level reconstruction accuracy to model precise hand trajectories for action learning. To support our proposed paradigm, we further develop a comprehensive data curation pipeline that integrates heterogeneous sources -- including motion capture, VR, and RGB-only videos -- into a large-scale dataset with millions of motion-based instructional instances. We empirically show the excellence of Being-H0 in hand motion generation and instruction following, and it also scales well with model and data sizes. Importantly, we observe the expected gains of Being-H0 in real-world robotic manipulation as physical instruction tuning is applied. More details are available at https://beingbeyond.github.io/Being-H0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15597</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 13:19:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian Splatting with Discretized SDF for Relightable Assets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15629</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15629.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zuo-Liang Zhu, Jian Yang, Beibei Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D Gaussian splatting (3DGS) has shown its detailed expressive ability and highly efficient rendering speed in the novel view synthesis (NVS) task. The application to inverse rendering still faces several challenges, as the discrete nature of Gaussian primitives makes it difficult to apply geometry constraints. Recent works introduce the signed distance field (SDF) as an extra continuous representation to regularize the geometry defined by Gaussian primitives. It improves the decomposition quality, at the cost of increasing memory usage and complicating training. Unlike these works, we introduce a discretized SDF to represent the continuous SDF in a discrete manner by encoding it within each Gaussian using a sampled value. This approach allows us to link the SDF with the Gaussian opacity through an SDF-to-opacity transformation, enabling rendering the SDF via splatting and avoiding the computational cost of ray marching.The key challenge is to regularize the discrete samples to be consistent with the underlying SDF, as the discrete representation can hardly apply the gradient-based constraints (\eg Eikonal loss). For this, we project Gaussians onto the zero-level set of SDF and enforce alignment with the surface from splatting, namely a projection-based consistency loss. Thanks to the discretized SDF, our method achieves higher relighting quality, while requiring no extra memory beyond GS and avoiding complex manually designed optimization. The experiments reveal that our method outperforms existing Gaussian-based inverse rendering methods. Our code is available at https://github.com/NK-CS-ZZL/DiscretizedSDF.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15629</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 13:52:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Mixing Agent: Learning to Re-weight Domains for Continual   Pre-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15640</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15640.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kailai Yang, Xiao Liu, Lei Ji, Hao Li, Yeyun Gong, Peng Cheng, Mao Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Continual pre-training on small-scale task-specific data is an effective method for improving large language models in new target fields, yet it risks catastrophic forgetting of their original capabilities. A common solution is to re-weight training data mixtures from source and target fields on a domain space to achieve balanced performance. Previous domain reweighting strategies rely on manual designation with certain heuristics based on human intuition or empirical results. In this work, we prove that more general heuristics can be parameterized by proposing Data Mixing Agent, the first model-based, end-to-end framework that learns to re-weight domains. The agent learns generalizable heuristics through reinforcement learning on large quantities of data mixing trajectories with corresponding feedback from an evaluation environment. Experiments in continual pre-training on math reasoning show that Data Mixing Agent outperforms strong baselines in achieving balanced performance across source and target field benchmarks. Furthermore, it generalizes well across unseen source fields, target models, and domain spaces without retraining. Direct application to the code generation field also indicates its adaptability across target domains. Further analysis showcases the agents' well-aligned heuristics with human intuitions and their efficiency in achieving superior model performance with less source-field data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15640</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 14:01:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TokensGen: Harnessing Condensed Tokens for Long Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15728</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15728.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenqi Ouyang, Zeqi Xiao, Danni Yang, Yifan Zhou, Shuai Yang, Lei Yang, Jianlou Si, Xingang Pan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating consistent long videos is a complex challenge: while diffusion-based generative models generate visually impressive short clips, extending them to longer durations often leads to memory bottlenecks and long-term inconsistency. In this paper, we propose TokensGen, a novel two-stage framework that leverages condensed tokens to address these issues. Our method decomposes long video generation into three core tasks: (1) inner-clip semantic control, (2) long-term consistency control, and (3) inter-clip smooth transition. First, we train To2V (Token-to-Video), a short video diffusion model guided by text and video tokens, with a Video Tokenizer that condenses short clips into semantically rich tokens. Second, we introduce T2To (Text-to-Token), a video token diffusion transformer that generates all tokens at once, ensuring global consistency across clips. Finally, during inference, an adaptive FIFO-Diffusion strategy seamlessly connects adjacent clips, reducing boundary artifacts and enhancing smooth transitions. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach significantly enhances long-term temporal and content coherence without incurring prohibitive computational overhead. By leveraging condensed tokens and pre-trained short video models, our method provides a scalable, modular solution for long video generation, opening new possibilities for storytelling, cinematic production, and immersive simulations. Please see our project page at https://vicky0522.github.io/tokensgen-webpage/ .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15728</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 15:37:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LAPO: Internalizing Reasoning Efficiency via Length-Adaptive Policy   Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15758</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15758.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xingyu Wu, Yuchen Yan, Shangke Lyu, Linjuan Wu, Yiwen Qiu, Yongliang Shen, Weiming Lu, Jian Shao, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models have achieved remarkable performance through extended chain-of-thought sequences, yet this computational freedom leads to excessive token generation even for simple problems. We present Length-Adaptive Policy Optimization (LAPO), a novel framework that transforms reasoning length control from an external constraint into an intrinsic model capability. Unlike existing approaches that impose rigid limits or rely on post-hoc interventions, LAPO enables models to internalize an understanding of appropriate reasoning depth through a two-stage reinforcement learning process. In the first stage, models learn natural reasoning patterns by discovering the statistical distribution of successful solution lengths. The second stage leverages these patterns as meta-cognitive guidance, embedding them directly within the model's reasoning context to ensure inference-time flexibility. Experiments on mathematical reasoning benchmarks demonstrate that LAPO reduces token usage by up to 40.9\% while improving accuracy by 2.3\%. Our analysis reveals that models trained with LAPO develop emergent abilities to allocate computational resources based on problem complexity, achieving efficient reasoning without sacrificing quality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15758</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 16:14:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizing Knowledge, Promoting Reasoning: Dual-Token Constraints for   RLVR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15778</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15778.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiakang Wang, Runze Liu, Fuzheng Zhang, Xiu Li, Guorui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has become an effective post-training method for improving the reasoning abilities of Large Language Models (LLMs), mainly by shaping higher-order behaviors such as reflection and planning. However, previous RLVR algorithms often apply uniform training signals to all tokens, without considering the different roles of low-entropy knowledge-related tokens and high-entropy reasoning-related tokens. Some recent methods try to separate these token types by gradient masking or asynchronous updates, but these approaches may break semantic dependencies in the model output and hinder effective learning. In this work, we propose Archer, an entropy-aware RLVR approach with dual-token constraints and synchronous updates. Specifically, our method applies weaker KL regularization and higher clipping thresholds to reasoning tokens to encourage exploration, while using stronger constraints on knowledge tokens to maintain factual knowledge. Experimental results on several mathematical reasoning and code generation benchmarks show that our approach significantly outperforms previous RLVR methods, reaching or exceeding state-of-the-art performance among models of comparable size. The code is available at https://github.com/wizard-III/ArcherCodeR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15778</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 16:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>True Multimodal In-Context Learning Needs Attention to the Visual   Context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15807</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15807.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuo Chen, Jianzhe Liu, Zhen Han, Yan Xia, Daniel Cremers, Philip Torr, Volker Tresp, Jindong Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs), built on powerful language backbones, have enabled Multimodal In-Context Learning (MICL)-adapting to new tasks from a few multimodal demonstrations consisting of images, questions, and answers. Despite showing noticeable improvement on standard vision-language datasets, current MLLMs struggle to leverage visual information in the demonstrations. Specifically, they tend to neglect visual cues and over-rely on textual patterns, leading to mere text imitation rather than genuine multimodal adaptation. This behavior makes MICL still unimodal and largely restricts its practical utility. More importantly, this limitation is often concealed by the improved performance on tasks that do not require understanding the visual context. As a result, how to effectively enhance MICL ability and reliably evaluate the MICL performance remains underexplored. To address these issues, we first introduce Dynamic Attention Reallocation (DARA), an efficient fine-tuning strategy that encourages models to attend to the visual context by rebalancing attention across visual and textual tokens. In addition, we present TrueMICL, an MICL-dedicated dataset with both support and test sets that explicitly requires the integration of multimodal information-particularly visual content-for correct task completion. Extensive experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our holistic solution, showcasing substantial improvements in the true multimodal in-context learning capabilities. Code and datasets are available at https://chenxshuo.github.io/true-micl-colm .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15807</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 17:08:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLM Economist: Large Population Models and Mechanism Design in   Multi-Agent Generative Simulacra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15815</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15815.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seth Karten, Wenzhe Li, Zihan Ding, Samuel Kleiner, Yu Bai, Chi Jin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present the LLM Economist, a novel framework that uses agent-based modeling to design and assess economic policies in strategic environments with hierarchical decision-making. At the lower level, bounded rational worker agents -- instantiated as persona-conditioned prompts sampled from U.S. Census-calibrated income and demographic statistics -- choose labor supply to maximize text-based utility functions learned in-context. At the upper level, a planner agent employs in-context reinforcement learning to propose piecewise-linear marginal tax schedules anchored to the current U.S. federal brackets. This construction endows economic simulacra with three capabilities requisite for credible fiscal experimentation: (i) optimization of heterogeneous utilities, (ii) principled generation of large, demographically realistic agent populations, and (iii) mechanism design -- the ultimate nudging problem -- expressed entirely in natural language. Experiments with populations of up to one hundred interacting agents show that the planner converges near Stackelberg equilibria that improve aggregate social welfare relative to Saez solutions, while a periodic, persona-level voting procedure furthers these gains under decentralized governance. These results demonstrate that large language model-based agents can jointly model, simulate, and govern complex economic systems, providing a tractable test bed for policy evaluation at the societal scale to help build better civilizations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15815</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 17:21:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Budget Policy Optimization for Adaptive Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15844</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15844.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shangke Lyu, Linjuan Wu, Yuchen Yan, Xingyu Wu, Hao Li, Yongliang Shen, Peisheng Jiang, Weiming Lu, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models achieve remarkable performance through extensive chain-of-thought generation, yet exhibit significant computational inefficiency by applying uniform reasoning strategies regardless of problem complexity. We present Hierarchical Budget Policy Optimization (HBPO), a reinforcement learning framework that enables models to learn problem-specific reasoning depths without sacrificing capability. HBPO addresses the fundamental challenge of exploration space collapse in efficiency-oriented training, where penalties on long output length systematically bias models away from necessary long reasoning paths. Through hierarchical budget exploration, our approach partitions rollout samples into multiple subgroups with distinct token budgets, aiming to enable efficient resource allocation while preventing degradation of capability. We introduce differentiated reward mechanisms that create budget-aware incentives aligned with the complexity of the problem, allowing models to discover natural correspondences between task requirements and computational effort. Extensive experiments demonstrate that HBPO reduces average token usage by up to 60.6% while improving accuracy by 3.14% across four reasoning benchmarks. Unlike existing methods that impose external constraints or rely on discrete mode selection, HBPO exhibits emergent adaptive behavior where models automatically adjust reasoning depth based on problem complexity. Our results suggest that reasoning efficiency and capability are not inherently conflicting, and can be simultaneously optimized through appropriately structured hierarchical training that preserves exploration diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15844</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 17:52:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GUI-G^2: Gaussian Reward Modeling for GUI Grounding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15846</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15846.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fei Tang, Zhangxuan Gu, Zhengxi Lu, Xuyang Liu, Shuheng Shen, Changhua Meng, Wen Wang, Wenqi Zhang, Yongliang Shen, Weiming Lu, Jun Xiao, Yueting Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 118&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graphical User Interface (GUI) grounding maps natural language instructions to precise interface locations for autonomous interaction. Current reinforcement learning approaches use binary rewards that treat elements as hit-or-miss targets, creating sparse signals that ignore the continuous nature of spatial interactions. Motivated by human clicking behavior that naturally forms Gaussian distributions centered on target elements, we introduce GUI Gaussian Grounding Rewards (GUI-G^2), a principled reward framework that models GUI elements as continuous Gaussian distributions across the interface plane. GUI-G^2 incorporates two synergistic mechanisms: Gaussian point rewards model precise localization through exponentially decaying distributions centered on element centroids, while coverage rewards assess spatial alignment by measuring the overlap between predicted Gaussian distributions and target regions. To handle diverse element scales, we develop an adaptive variance mechanism that calibrates reward distributions based on element dimensions. This framework transforms GUI grounding from sparse binary classification to dense continuous optimization, where Gaussian distributions generate rich gradient signals that guide models toward optimal interaction positions. Extensive experiments across ScreenSpot, ScreenSpot-v2, and ScreenSpot-Pro benchmarks demonstrate that GUI-G^2, substantially outperforms state-of-the-art method UI-TARS-72B, with the most significant improvement of 24.7% on ScreenSpot-Pro. Our analysis reveals that continuous modeling provides superior robustness to interface variations and enhanced generalization to unseen layouts, establishing a new paradigm for spatial reasoning in GUI interaction tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15846</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 17:53:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SeC: Advancing Complex Video Object Segmentation via Progressive Concept   Construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15852</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15852.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhixiong Zhang, Shuangrui Ding, Xiaoyi Dong, Songxin He, Jianfan Lin, Junsong Tang, Yuhang Zang, Yuhang Cao, Dahua Lin, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video Object Segmentation (VOS) is a core task in computer vision, requiring models to track and segment target objects across video frames. Despite notable advances with recent efforts, current techniques still lag behind human capabilities in handling drastic visual variations, occlusions, and complex scene changes. This limitation arises from their reliance on appearance matching, neglecting the human-like conceptual understanding of objects that enables robust identification across temporal dynamics. Motivated by this gap, we propose Segment Concept (SeC), a concept-driven segmentation framework that shifts from conventional feature matching to the progressive construction and utilization of high-level, object-centric representations. SeC employs Large Vision-Language Models (LVLMs) to integrate visual cues across diverse frames, constructing robust conceptual priors. During inference, SeC forms a comprehensive semantic representation of the target based on processed frames, realizing robust segmentation of follow-up frames. Furthermore, SeC adaptively balances LVLM-based semantic reasoning with enhanced feature matching, dynamically adjusting computational efforts based on scene complexity. To rigorously assess VOS methods in scenarios demanding high-level conceptual reasoning and robust semantic understanding, we introduce the Semantic Complex Scenarios Video Object Segmentation benchmark (SeCVOS). SeCVOS comprises 160 manually annotated multi-scenario videos designed to challenge models with substantial appearance variations and dynamic scene transformations. In particular, SeC achieves an 11.8-point improvement over SAM 2.1 on SeCVOS, establishing a new state-of-the-art in concept-aware video object segmentation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15852</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Denoising Makes Good Visual Tokenizers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15856</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15856.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiawei Yang, Tianhong Li, Lijie Fan, Yonglong Tian, Yue Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite their fundamental role, it remains unclear what properties could make visual tokenizers more effective for generative modeling. We observe that modern generative models share a conceptually similar training objective -- reconstructing clean signals from corrupted inputs such as Gaussian noise or masking -- a process we term denoising. Motivated by this insight, we propose aligning tokenizer embeddings directly with the downstream denoising objective, encouraging latent embeddings to be more easily reconstructed even when heavily corrupted. To achieve this, we introduce the Latent Denoising Tokenizer (l-DeTok), a simple yet effective tokenizer trained to reconstruct clean images from latent embeddings corrupted by interpolative noise and random masking. Extensive experiments on ImageNet 256x256 demonstrate that our tokenizer consistently outperforms standard tokenizers across six representative generative models. Our findings highlight denoising as a fundamental design principle for tokenizer development, and we hope it could motivate new perspectives for future tokenizer design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15856</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does More Inference-Time Compute Really Help Robustness?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15974</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.15974.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tong Wu, Chong Xiang, Jiachen T. Wang, Weichen Yu, Chawin Sitawarin, Vikash Sehwag, Prateek Mittal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, Zaremba et al. demonstrated that increasing inference-time computation improves robustness in large proprietary reasoning LLMs. In this paper, we first show that smaller-scale, open-source models (e.g., DeepSeek R1, Qwen3, Phi-reasoning) can also benefit from inference-time scaling using a simple budget forcing strategy. More importantly, we reveal and critically examine an implicit assumption in prior work: intermediate reasoning steps are hidden from adversaries. By relaxing this assumption, we identify an important security risk, intuitively motivated and empirically verified as an inverse scaling law: if intermediate reasoning steps become explicitly accessible, increased inference-time computation consistently reduces model robustness. Finally, we discuss practical scenarios where models with hidden reasoning chains are still vulnerable to attacks, such as models with tool-integrated reasoning and advanced reasoning extraction attacks. Our findings collectively demonstrate that the robustness benefits of inference-time scaling depend heavily on the adversarial setting and deployment context. We urge practitioners to carefully weigh these subtle trade-offs before applying inference-time scaling in security-sensitive, real-world applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15974</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 18:08:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovering and using Spelke segments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16038</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16038.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rahul Venkatesh, Klemen Kotar, Lilian Naing Chen, Seungwoo Kim, Luca Thomas Wheeler, Jared Watrous, Ashley Xu, Gia Ancone, Wanhee Lee, Honglin Chen, Daniel Bear, Stefan Stojanov, Daniel Yamins&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Segments in computer vision are often defined by semantic considerations and are highly dependent on category-specific conventions. In contrast, developmental psychology suggests that humans perceive the world in terms of Spelke objects--groupings of physical things that reliably move together when acted on by physical forces. Spelke objects thus operate on category-agnostic causal motion relationships which potentially better support tasks like manipulation and planning. In this paper, we first benchmark the Spelke object concept, introducing the SpelkeBench dataset that contains a wide variety of well-defined Spelke segments in natural images. Next, to extract Spelke segments from images algorithmically, we build SpelkeNet, a class of visual world models trained to predict distributions over future motions. SpelkeNet supports estimation of two key concepts for Spelke object discovery: (1) the motion affordance map, identifying regions likely to move under a poke, and (2) the expected-displacement map, capturing how the rest of the scene will move. These concepts are used for "statistical counterfactual probing", where diverse "virtual pokes" are applied on regions of high motion-affordance, and the resultant expected displacement maps are used define Spelke segments as statistical aggregates of correlated motion statistics. We find that SpelkeNet outperforms supervised baselines like SegmentAnything (SAM) on SpelkeBench. Finally, we show that the Spelke concept is practically useful for downstream applications, yielding superior performance on the 3DEditBench benchmark for physical object manipulation when used in a variety of off-the-shelf object manipulation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16038</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 20:11:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pixels, Patterns, but No Poetry: To See The World like Humans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16863</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16863.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongcheng Gao, Zihao Huang, Lin Xu, Jingyi Tang, Xinhao Li, Yue Liu, Haoyang Li, Taihang Hu, Minhua Lin, Xinlong Yang, Ge Wu, Balong Bi, Hongyu Chen, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Achieving human-like perception and reasoning in Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) remains a central challenge in artificial intelligence. While recent research has primarily focused on enhancing reasoning capabilities in MLLMs, a fundamental question persists: Can Multimodal Large Language Models truly perceive the world as humans do? This paper shifts focus from reasoning to perception. Rather than constructing benchmarks specifically for reasoning, we introduce the Turing Eye Test (TET), a challenging perception-oriented benchmark comprising four diagnostic tasks that evaluate MLLMs' performance on synthetic images that humans process intuitively. Our findings reveal that state-of-the-art MLLMs exhibit catastrophic failures on our perceptual tasks trivial for humans. Both in-context learning and training on language backbone-effective for previous benchmarks-fail to improve performance on our tasks, while fine-tuning the vision tower enables rapid adaptation, suggesting that our benchmark poses challenges for vision tower generalization rather than for the knowledge and reasoning capabilities of the language backbone-a key gap between current MLLMs and human perception. We release a representative subset of TET tasks in this version, and will introduce more diverse tasks and methods to enhance visual generalization in future work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16863</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 21:50:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PUSA V1.0: Surpassing Wan-I2V with $500 Training Cost by Vectorized   Timestep Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16116</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16116.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yaofang Liu, Yumeng Ren, Aitor Artola, Yuxuan Hu, Xiaodong Cun, Xiaotong Zhao, Alan Zhao, Raymond H. Chan, Suiyun Zhang, Rui Liu, Dandan Tu, Jean-Michel Morel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of video diffusion models has been hindered by fundamental limitations in temporal modeling, particularly the rigid synchronization of frame evolution imposed by conventional scalar timestep variables. While task-specific adaptations and autoregressive models have sought to address these challenges, they remain constrained by computational inefficiency, catastrophic forgetting, or narrow applicability. In this work, we present Pusa, a groundbreaking paradigm that leverages vectorized timestep adaptation (VTA) to enable fine-grained temporal control within a unified video diffusion framework. Besides, VTA is a non-destructive adaptation, which means it fully preserves the capabilities of the base model. By finetuning the SOTA Wan2.1-T2V-14B model with VTA, we achieve unprecedented efficiency -- surpassing the performance of Wan-I2V-14B with leq 1/200 of the training cost (\500 vs. \geq 100,000) and leq 1/2500 of the dataset size (4K vs. geq 10M samples). Pusa not only sets a new standard for image-to-video (I2V) generation, achieving a VBench-I2V total score of 87.32\% (vs. 86.86\% of Wan-I2V-14B), but also unlocks many zero-shot multi-task capabilities such as start-end frames and video extension -- all without task-specific training. Meanwhile, Pusa can still perform text-to-video generation. Mechanistic analyses reveal that our approach preserves the foundation model's generative priors while surgically injecting temporal dynamics, avoiding the combinatorial explosion inherent to vectorized timesteps. This work establishes a scalable, efficient, and versatile paradigm for next-generation video synthesis, democratizing high-fidelity video generation for research and industry alike. Code is open-sourced at https://github.com/Yaofang-Liu/Pusa-VidGen&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16116</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:09:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Re:Form -- Reducing Human Priors in Scalable Formal Software   Verification with RL in LLMs: A Preliminary Study on Dafny</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16331</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16331.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chuanhao Yan, Fengdi Che, Xuhan Huang, Xu Xu, Xin Li, Yizhi Li, Xingwei Qu, Jingzhe Shi, Zhuangzhuang He, Chenghua Lin, Yaodong Yang, Binhang Yuan, Hang Zhao, Yu Qiao, Bowen Zhou, Jie Fu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing informal language-based (e.g., human language) Large Language Models (LLMs) trained with Reinforcement Learning (RL) face a significant challenge: their verification processes, which provide crucial training signals, are neither reliable nor scalable. In fact, the prevalent large proprietary models could hardly generate verifiable programs. A promising yet largely uncharted alternative is formal language-based reasoning. Grounding LLMs in rigorous formal systems where generative models operate in formal language spaces (e.g., Dafny) enables the automatic and mathematically provable verification of their reasoning processes and outcomes. This capability is pivotal for achieving large-scale, reliable formal software verification. It is a common practice to employ human-annotated chain-of-thought and other human priors to induce the reasoning and coding capabilities of LLMs. Unfortunately, it becomes unacceptably all-consuming to provide such priors for supervising complex programming tasks. In this work, we systematically explore ways to reduce human priors with the formal language, Dafny, as the main environment for our pilot study. Our pipeline mainly relies on introducing an automatic and scalable data curation pipeline, and careful RL designs integrated with feedback from the formal language verifier. We introduce DafnyComp, a benchmark of compositional formal programs with auto-formalized specifications for specification reasoning. Our supervised fine-tuning (SFT) stage enables even small models (e.g., 0.5B) to generate syntactically valid and verifiable Dafny code, surpassing proprietary models. RL with regularization further improves performance, achieving stronger generalization to out-of-domain tasks and outperforming all strong baselines on the challenging DafnyComp benchmark.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16331</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:13:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EarthCrafter: Scalable 3D Earth Generation via Dual-Sparse Latent   Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16535</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16535.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shang Liu, Chenjie Cao, Chaohui Yu, Wen Qian, Jing Wang, Fan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the remarkable developments achieved by recent 3D generation works, scaling these methods to geographic extents, such as modeling thousands of square kilometers of Earth's surface, remains an open challenge. We address this through a dual innovation in data infrastructure and model architecture. First, we introduce Aerial-Earth3D, the largest 3D aerial dataset to date, consisting of 50k curated scenes (each measuring 600m x 600m) captured across the U.S. mainland, comprising 45M multi-view Google Earth frames. Each scene provides pose-annotated multi-view images, depth maps, normals, semantic segmentation, and camera poses, with explicit quality control to ensure terrain diversity. Building on this foundation, we propose EarthCrafter, a tailored framework for large-scale 3D Earth generation via sparse-decoupled latent diffusion. Our architecture separates structural and textural generation: 1) Dual sparse 3D-VAEs compress high-resolution geometric voxels and textural 2D Gaussian Splats (2DGS) into compact latent spaces, largely alleviating the costly computation suffering from vast geographic scales while preserving critical information. 2) We propose condition-aware flow matching models trained on mixed inputs (semantics, images, or neither) to flexibly model latent geometry and texture features independently. Extensive experiments demonstrate that EarthCrafter performs substantially better in extremely large-scale generation. The framework further supports versatile applications, from semantic-guided urban layout generation to unconditional terrain synthesis, while maintaining geographic plausibility through our rich data priors from Aerial-Earth3D. Our project page is available at https://whiteinblue.github.io/earthcrafter/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16535</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 12:46:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step-Audio 2 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16632</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16632.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Boyong Wu, Chao Yan, Chen Hu, Cheng Yi, Chengli Feng, Fei Tian, Feiyu Shen, Gang Yu, Haoyang Zhang, Jingbei Li, Mingrui Chen, Peng Liu, Wang You, Xiangyu Tony Zhang, Xingyuan Li, Xuerui Yang, Yayue Deng, Yechang Huang, Yuxin Li, Yuxin Zhang, Zhao You, Brian Li, Changyi Wan, Hanpeng Hu, Jiangjie Zhen, Siyu Chen, Song Yuan, Xuelin Zhang, Yimin Jiang, Yu Zhou, Yuxiang Yang, Bingxin Li, Buyun Ma, Changhe Song, Dongqing Pang, Guoqiang Hu, Haiyang Sun, Kang An, Na Wang, Shuli Gao, Wei Ji, Wen Li, Wen Sun, Xuan Wen, Yong Ren, Yuankai Ma, Yufan Lu, Bin Wang, Bo Li, Changxin Miao, Che Liu, Chen Xu, Dapeng Shi, Dingyuan Hu, Donghang Wu, Enle Liu, Guanzhe Huang, Gulin Yan, Han Zhang, Hao Nie, Haonan Jia, Hongyu Zhou, Jianjian Sun, Jiaoren Wu, Jie Wu, Jie Yang, Jin Yang, Junzhe Lin, Kaixiang Li, Lei Yang, Liying Shi, Li Zhou, Longlong Gu, Ming Li, Mingliang Li, Mingxiao Li, Nan Wu, Qi Han, Qinyuan Tan, Shaoliang Pang, Shengjie Fan, Siqi Liu, Tiancheng Cao, Wanying Lu, Wenqing He, Wuxun Xie, Xu Zhao, Xueqi Li, Yanbo Yu, Yang Yang, Yi Liu, Yifan Lu, Yilei Wang, Yuanhao Ding, Yuanwei Liang, Yuanwei Lu, Yuchu Luo, Yuhe Yin, Yumeng Zhan, Yuxiang Zhang, Zidong Yang, Zixin Zhang, Binxing Jiao, Daxin Jiang, Heung-Yeung Shum, Jiansheng Chen, Jing Li, Xiangyu Zhang, Yibo Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents Step-Audio~2, an end-to-end multi-modal large language model designed for industry-strength audio understanding and speech conversation. By integrating a latent audio encoder and reasoning-centric reinforcement learning (RL), Step-Audio 2 achieves promising performance in automatic speech recognition (ASR) and audio understanding. To facilitate genuine end-to-end speech conversation, Step-Audio 2 incorporates the generation of discrete audio tokens into language modeling, significantly enhancing its responsiveness to paralinguistic information such as speaking styles and emotions. To effectively leverage the rich textual and acoustic knowledge in real-world data, Step-Audio 2 integrates retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) and is able to call external tools such as web search to mitigate hallucination and audio search to switch timbres. Trained on millions of hours of speech and audio data, Step-Audio 2 delivers intelligence and expressiveness across diverse conversational scenarios. Evaluation results demonstrate that Step-Audio 2 achieves state-of-the-art performance on various audio understanding and conversational benchmarks compared to other open-source and commercial solutions. Please visit https://github.com/stepfun-ai/Step-Audio2 for more information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16632</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 14:23:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding Dori: Memorization in Text-to-Image Diffusion Models Is Less   Local Than Assumed</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16880</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16880.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Antoni Kowalczuk, Dominik Hintersdorf, Lukas Struppek, Kristian Kersting, Adam Dziedzic, Franziska Boenisch&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Text-to-image diffusion models (DMs) have achieved remarkable success in image generation. However, concerns about data privacy and intellectual property remain due to their potential to inadvertently memorize and replicate training data. Recent mitigation efforts have focused on identifying and pruning weights responsible for triggering replication, based on the assumption that memorization can be localized. Our research assesses the robustness of these pruning-based approaches. We demonstrate that even after pruning, minor adjustments to text embeddings of input prompts are sufficient to re-trigger data replication, highlighting the fragility of these defenses. Furthermore, we challenge the fundamental assumption of memorization locality, by showing that replication can be triggered from diverse locations within the text embedding space, and follows different paths in the model. Our findings indicate that existing mitigation strategies are insufficient and underscore the need for methods that truly remove memorized content, rather than attempting to suppress its retrieval. As a first step in this direction, we introduce a novel adversarial fine-tuning method that iteratively searches for replication triggers and updates the model to increase robustness. Through our research, we provide fresh insights into the nature of memorization in text-to-image DMs and a foundation for building more trustworthy and compliant generative AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16880</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 15:02:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experience is the Best Teacher: Grounding VLMs for Robotics through   Self-Generated Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16713</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16713.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guowei Lan, Kaixian Qu, René Zurbrügg, Changan Chen, Christopher E. Mower, Haitham Bou-Ammar, Marco Hutter&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language models (VLMs) have been widely adopted in robotics to enable autonomous planning. However, grounding VLMs, originally trained on internet data, to diverse real-world robots remains a challenge. This paper presents ExpTeach, a framework that grounds VLMs to physical robots by building a self-generated memory of real-world experiences. In ExpTeach, the VLM autonomously plans actions, verifies outcomes, reflects on failures, and adapts robot behaviors in a closed loop. The self-generated experiences during this process are then summarized into a long-term memory, enabling retrieval of learned knowledge to guide future tasks via retrieval-augmented generation (RAG). Additionally, ExpTeach enhances the spatial understanding of VLMs with an on-demand image annotation module. In experiments, we show that reflection improves success rates from 36% to 84% on four challenging robotic tasks and observe the emergence of intelligent object interactions, including creative tool use. Across extensive tests on 12 real-world scenarios (including eight unseen ones), we find that grounding with long-term memory boosts single-trial success rates from 22% to 80%, demonstrating the effectiveness and generalizability of ExpTeach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16713</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 15:48:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RAVine: Reality-Aligned Evaluation for Agentic Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16725</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16725.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yilong Xu, Xiang Long, Zhi Zheng, Jinhua Gao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic search, as a more autonomous and adaptive paradigm of retrieval augmentation, is driving the evolution of intelligent search systems. However, existing evaluation frameworks fail to align well with the goals of agentic search. First, the complex queries commonly used in current benchmarks often deviate from realistic user search scenarios. Second, prior approaches tend to introduce noise when extracting ground truth for end-to-end evaluations, leading to distorted assessments at a fine-grained level. Third, most current frameworks focus solely on the quality of final answers, neglecting the evaluation of the iterative process inherent to agentic search. To address these limitations, we propose RAVine -- a Reality-Aligned eValuation framework for agentic LLMs with search. RAVine targets multi-point queries and long-form answers that better reflect user intents, and introduces an attributable ground truth construction strategy to enhance the accuracy of fine-grained evaluation. Moreover, RAVine examines model's interaction with search tools throughout the iterative process, and accounts for factors of efficiency. We benchmark a series of models using RAVine and derive several insights, which we hope will contribute to advancing the development of agentic search systems. The code and datasets are available at https://github.com/SwordFaith/RAVine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16725</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 16:08:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zebra-CoT: A Dataset for Interleaved Vision Language Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16746</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16746.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ang Li, Charles Wang, Kaiyu Yue, Zikui Cai, Ollie Liu, Deqing Fu, Peng Guo, Wang Bill Zhu, Vatsal Sharan, Robin Jia, Willie Neiswanger, Furong Huang, Tom Goldstein, Micah Goldblum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humans often use visual aids, for example diagrams or sketches, when solving complex problems. Training multimodal models to do the same, known as Visual Chain of Thought (Visual CoT), is challenging due to: (1) poor off-the-shelf visual CoT performance, which hinders reinforcement learning, and (2) the lack of high-quality visual CoT training data. We introduce Zebra-CoT, a diverse large-scale dataset with 182,384 samples, containing logically coherent interleaved text-image reasoning traces. We focus on four categories of tasks where sketching or visual reasoning is especially natural, spanning scientific questions such as geometry, physics, and algorithms; 2D visual reasoning tasks like visual search and jigsaw puzzles; 3D reasoning tasks including 3D multi-hop inference, embodied and robot planning; visual logic problems and strategic games like chess. Fine-tuning the Anole-7B model on the Zebra-CoT training corpus results in an improvement of +12% in our test-set accuracy and yields up to +13% performance gain on standard VLM benchmark evaluations. Fine-tuning Bagel-7B yields a model that generates high-quality interleaved visual reasoning chains, underscoring Zebra-CoT's effectiveness for developing multimodal reasoning abilities. We open-source our dataset and models to support development and evaluation of visual CoT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16746</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 16:35:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task-Specific Zero-shot Quantization-Aware Training for Object Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16782</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16782.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Changhao Li, Xinrui Chen, Ji Wang, Kang Zhao, Jianfei Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Quantization is a key technique to reduce network size and computational complexity by representing the network parameters with a lower precision. Traditional quantization methods rely on access to original training data, which is often restricted due to privacy concerns or security challenges. Zero-shot Quantization (ZSQ) addresses this by using synthetic data generated from pre-trained models, eliminating the need for real training data. Recently, ZSQ has been extended to object detection. However, existing methods use unlabeled task-agnostic synthetic images that lack the specific information required for object detection, leading to suboptimal performance. In this paper, we propose a novel task-specific ZSQ framework for object detection networks, which consists of two main stages. First, we introduce a bounding box and category sampling strategy to synthesize a task-specific calibration set from the pre-trained network, reconstructing object locations, sizes, and category distributions without any prior knowledge. Second, we integrate task-specific training into the knowledge distillation process to restore the performance of quantized detection networks. Extensive experiments conducted on the MS-COCO and Pascal VOC datasets demonstrate the efficiency and state-of-the-art performance of our method. Our code is publicly available at: https://github.com/DFQ-Dojo/dfq-toolkit .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16782</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:28:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Context Limits: Subconscious Threads for Long-Horizon Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16784</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16784.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hongyin Luo, Nathaniel Morgan, Tina Li, Derek Zhao, Ai Vy Ngo, Philip Schroeder, Lijie Yang, Assaf Ben-Kish, Jack O'Brien, James Glass&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 106&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; To break the context limits of large language models (LLMs) that bottleneck reasoning accuracy and efficiency, we propose the Thread Inference Model (TIM), a family of LLMs trained for recursive and decompositional problem solving, and TIMRUN, an inference runtime enabling long-horizon structured reasoning beyond context limits. Together, TIM hosted on TIMRUN supports virtually unlimited working memory and multi-hop tool calls within a single language model inference, overcoming output limits, positional-embedding constraints, and GPU-memory bottlenecks. Performance is achieved by modeling natural language as reasoning trees measured by both length and depth instead of linear sequences. The reasoning trees consist of tasks with thoughts, recursive subtasks, and conclusions based on the concept we proposed in Schroeder et al, 2025. During generation, we maintain a working memory that retains only the key-value states of the most relevant context tokens, selected by a rule-based subtask-pruning mechanism, enabling reuse of positional embeddings and GPU memory pages throughout reasoning. Experimental results show that our system sustains high inference throughput, even when manipulating up to 90% of the KV cache in GPU memory. It also delivers accurate reasoning on mathematical tasks and handles information retrieval challenges that require long-horizon reasoning and multi-hop tool use.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16784</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:30:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steering Out-of-Distribution Generalization with Concept Ablation   Fine-Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16795</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16795.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Helena Casademunt, Caden Juang, Adam Karvonen, Samuel Marks, Senthooran Rajamanoharan, Neel Nanda&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-tuning large language models (LLMs) can lead to unintended out-of-distribution generalization. Standard approaches to this problem rely on modifying training data, for example by adding data that better specify the intended generalization. However, this is not always practical. We introduce Concept Ablation Fine-Tuning (CAFT), a technique that leverages interpretability tools to control how LLMs generalize from fine-tuning, without needing to modify the training data or otherwise use data from the target distribution. Given a set of directions in an LLM's latent space corresponding to undesired concepts, CAFT works by ablating these concepts with linear projections during fine-tuning, steering the model away from unintended generalizations. We successfully apply CAFT to three fine-tuning tasks, including emergent misalignment, a phenomenon where LLMs fine-tuned on a narrow task generalize to give egregiously misaligned responses to general questions. Without any changes to the fine-tuning data, CAFT reduces misaligned responses by 10x without degrading performance on the training distribution. Overall, CAFT represents a novel approach for steering LLM generalization without modifying training data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16795</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:45:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agentar-Fin-R1: Enhancing Financial Intelligence through Domain   Expertise, Training Efficiency, and Advanced Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16802</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16802.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanjun Zheng, Xiyang Du, Longfei Liao, Xiaoke Zhao, Zhaowen Zhou, Jingze Song, Bo Zhang, Jiawei Liu, Xiang Qi, Zhe Li, Zhiqiang Zhang, Wei Wang, Peng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) exhibit considerable promise in financial applications; however, prevailing models frequently demonstrate limitations when confronted with scenarios that necessitate sophisticated reasoning capabilities, stringent trustworthiness criteria, and efficient adaptation to domain-specific requirements. We introduce the Agentar-Fin-R1 series of financial large language models (8B and 32B parameters), specifically engineered based on the Qwen3 foundation model to enhance reasoning capabilities, reliability, and domain specialization for financial applications. Our optimization approach integrates a high-quality, systematic financial task label system with a comprehensive multi-layered trustworthiness assurance framework. This framework encompasses high-quality trustworthy knowledge engineering, multi-agent trustworthy data synthesis, and rigorous data validation governance. Through label-guided automated difficulty-aware optimization, tow-stage training pipeline, and dynamic attribution systems, we achieve substantial improvements in training efficiency. Our models undergo comprehensive evaluation on mainstream financial benchmarks including Fineva, FinEval, and FinanceIQ, as well as general reasoning datasets such as MATH-500 and GPQA-diamond. To thoroughly assess real-world deployment capabilities, we innovatively propose the Finova evaluation benchmark, which focuses on agent-level financial reasoning and compliance verification. Experimental results demonstrate that Agentar-Fin-R1 not only achieves state-of-the-art performance on financial tasks but also exhibits exceptional general reasoning capabilities, validating its effectiveness as a trustworthy solution for high-stakes financial applications. The Finova bench is available at https://github.com/antgroup/Finova.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16802</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:52:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MegaScience: Pushing the Frontiers of Post-Training Datasets for Science   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16812</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16812.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Run-Ze Fan, Zengzhi Wang, Pengfei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scientific reasoning is critical for developing AI scientists and supporting human researchers in advancing the frontiers of natural science discovery. However, the open-source community has primarily focused on mathematics and coding while neglecting the scientific domain, largely due to the absence of open, large-scale, high-quality, verifiable scientific reasoning datasets. To bridge this gap, we first present TextbookReasoning, an open dataset featuring truthful reference answers extracted from 12k university-level scientific textbooks, comprising 650k reasoning questions spanning 7 scientific disciplines. We further introduce MegaScience, a large-scale mixture of high-quality open-source datasets totaling 1.25 million instances, developed through systematic ablation studies that evaluate various data selection methodologies to identify the optimal subset for each publicly available scientific dataset. Meanwhile, we build a comprehensive evaluation system covering diverse subjects and question types across 15 benchmarks, incorporating comprehensive answer extraction strategies to ensure accurate evaluation metrics. Our experiments demonstrate that our datasets achieve superior performance and training efficiency with more concise response lengths compared to existing open-source scientific datasets. Furthermore, we train Llama3.1, Qwen2.5, and Qwen3 series base models on MegaScience, which significantly outperform the corresponding official instruct models in average performance. In addition, MegaScience exhibits greater effectiveness for larger and stronger models, suggesting a scaling benefit for scientific tuning. We release our data curation pipeline, evaluation system, datasets, and seven trained models to the community to advance scientific reasoning research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16812</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:59:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HOComp: Interaction-Aware Human-Object Composition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16813</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16813.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dong Liang, Jinyuan Jia, Yuhao Liu, Rynson W. H. Lau&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While existing image-guided composition methods may help insert a foreground object onto a user-specified region of a background image, achieving natural blending inside the region with the rest of the image unchanged, we observe that these existing methods often struggle in synthesizing seamless interaction-aware compositions when the task involves human-object interactions. In this paper, we first propose HOComp, a novel approach for compositing a foreground object onto a human-centric background image, while ensuring harmonious interactions between the foreground object and the background person and their consistent appearances. Our approach includes two key designs: (1) MLLMs-driven Region-based Pose Guidance (MRPG), which utilizes MLLMs to identify the interaction region as well as the interaction type (e.g., holding and lefting) to provide coarse-to-fine constraints to the generated pose for the interaction while incorporating human pose landmarks to track action variations and enforcing fine-grained pose constraints; and (2) Detail-Consistent Appearance Preservation (DCAP), which unifies a shape-aware attention modulation mechanism, a multi-view appearance loss, and a background consistency loss to ensure consistent shapes/textures of the foreground and faithful reproduction of the background human. We then propose the first dataset, named Interaction-aware Human-Object Composition (IHOC), for the task. Experimental results on our dataset show that HOComp effectively generates harmonious human-object interactions with consistent appearances, and outperforms relevant methods qualitatively and quantitatively.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16813</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:59:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-off-Policy Reinforcement Learning for Vision-Language Slow-thinking   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16814</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16814.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junhao Shen, Haiteng Zhao, Yuzhe Gu, Songyang Gao, Kuikun Liu, Haian Huang, Jianfei Gao, Dahua Lin, Wenwei Zhang, Kai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Enhancing large vision-language models (LVLMs) with visual slow-thinking reasoning is crucial for solving complex multimodal tasks. However, since LVLMs are mainly trained with vision-language alignment, it is difficult to adopt on-policy reinforcement learning (RL) to develop the slow thinking ability because the rollout space is restricted by its initial abilities. Off-policy RL offers a way to go beyond the current policy, but directly distilling trajectories from external models may cause visual hallucinations due to mismatched visual perception abilities across models. To address these issues, this paper proposes SOPHIA, a simple and scalable Semi-Off-Policy RL for vision-language slow-tHInking reAsoning. SOPHIA builds a semi-off-policy behavior model by combining on-policy visual understanding from a trainable LVLM with off-policy slow-thinking reasoning from a language model, assigns outcome-based rewards to reasoning, and propagates visual rewards backward. Then LVLM learns slow-thinking reasoning ability from the obtained reasoning trajectories using propagated rewards via off-policy RL algorithms. Extensive experiments with InternVL2.5 and InternVL3.0 with 8B and 38B sizes show the effectiveness of SOPHIA. Notably, SOPHIA improves InternVL3.0-38B by 8.50% in average, reaching state-of-the-art performance among open-source LVLMs on multiple multimodal reasoning benchmarks, and even outperforms some closed-source models (e.g., GPT-4.1) on the challenging MathVision and OlympiadBench, achieving 49.08% and 49.95% pass@1 accuracy, respectively. Analysis shows SOPHIA outperforms supervised fine-tuning and direct on-policy RL methods, offering a better policy initialization for further on-policy training.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16814</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:59:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ThinkAct: Vision-Language-Action Reasoning via Reinforced Visual Latent   Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16815</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.16815.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chi-Pin Huang, Yueh-Hua Wu, Min-Hung Chen, Yu-Chiang Frank Wang, Fu-En Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language-action (VLA) reasoning tasks require agents to interpret multimodal instructions, perform long-horizon planning, and act adaptively in dynamic environments. Existing approaches typically train VLA models in an end-to-end fashion, directly mapping inputs to actions without explicit reasoning, which hinders their ability to plan over multiple steps or adapt to complex task variations. In this paper, we propose ThinkAct, a dual-system framework that bridges high-level reasoning with low-level action execution via reinforced visual latent planning. ThinkAct trains a multimodal LLM to generate embodied reasoning plans guided by reinforcing action-aligned visual rewards based on goal completion and trajectory consistency. These reasoning plans are compressed into a visual plan latent that conditions a downstream action model for robust action execution on target environments. Extensive experiments on embodied reasoning and robot manipulation benchmarks demonstrate that ThinkAct enables few-shot adaptation, long-horizon planning, and self-correction behaviors in complex embodied AI tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16815</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 17:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DesignLab: Designing Slides Through Iterative Detection and Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17202</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.17202.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jooyeol Yun, Heng Wang, Yotaro Shimose, Jaegul Choo, Shingo Takamatsu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Designing high-quality presentation slides can be challenging for non-experts due to the complexity involved in navigating various design choices. Numerous automated tools can suggest layouts and color schemes, yet often lack the ability to refine their own output, which is a key aspect in real-world workflows. We propose DesignLab, which separates the design process into two roles, the design reviewer, who identifies design-related issues, and the design contributor who corrects them. This decomposition enables an iterative loop where the reviewer continuously detects issues and the contributor corrects them, allowing a draft to be further polished with each iteration, reaching qualities that were unattainable. We fine-tune large language models for these roles and simulate intermediate drafts by introducing controlled perturbations, enabling the design reviewer learn design errors and the contributor learn how to fix them. Our experiments show that DesignLab outperforms existing design-generation methods, including a commercial tool, by embracing the iterative nature of designing which can result in polished, professional slides.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17202</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 04:49:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HLFormer: Enhancing Partially Relevant Video Retrieval with Hyperbolic   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17402</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.17402.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Li Jun, Wang Jinpeng, Tan Chaolei, Lian Niu, Chen Long, Zhang Min, Wang Yaowei, Xia Shu-Tao, Chen Bin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Partially Relevant Video Retrieval (PRVR) addresses the critical challenge of matching untrimmed videos with text queries describing only partial content. Existing methods suffer from geometric distortion in Euclidean space that sometimes misrepresents the intrinsic hierarchical structure of videos and overlooks certain hierarchical semantics, ultimately leading to suboptimal temporal modeling. To address this issue, we propose the first hyperbolic modeling framework for PRVR, namely HLFormer, which leverages hyperbolic space learning to compensate for the suboptimal hierarchical modeling capabilities of Euclidean space. Specifically, HLFormer integrates the Lorentz Attention Block and Euclidean Attention Block to encode video embeddings in hybrid spaces, using the Mean-Guided Adaptive Interaction Module to dynamically fuse features. Additionally, we introduce a Partial Order Preservation Loss to enforce "text &lt; video" hierarchy through Lorentzian cone constraints. This approach further enhances cross-modal matching by reinforcing partial relevance between video content and text queries. Extensive experiments show that HLFormer outperforms state-of-the-art methods. Code is released at https://github.com/lijun2005/ICCV25-HLFormer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17402</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 10:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can One Domain Help Others? A Data-Centric Study on Multi-Domain   Reasoning via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17512</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.17512.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Li, Zhuoshi Pan, Honglin Lin, Mengyuan Sun, Conghui He, Lijun Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) has emerged as a powerful paradigm for enhancing the reasoning capabilities of LLMs. Existing research has predominantly concentrated on isolated reasoning domains such as mathematical problem-solving, coding tasks, or logical reasoning. However, real world reasoning scenarios inherently demand an integrated application of multiple cognitive skills. Despite this, the interplay among these reasoning skills under reinforcement learning remains poorly understood. To bridge this gap, we present a systematic investigation of multi-domain reasoning within the RLVR framework, explicitly focusing on three primary domains: mathematical reasoning, code generation, and logical puzzle solving. We conduct a comprehensive study comprising four key components: (1) Leveraging the GRPO algorithm and the Qwen-2.5-7B model family, our study thoroughly evaluates the models' in-domain improvements and cross-domain generalization capabilities when trained on single-domain datasets. (2) Additionally, we examine the intricate interactions including mutual enhancements and conflicts that emerge during combined cross-domain training. (3) To further understand the influence of SFT on RL, we also analyze and compare performance differences between base and instruct models under identical RL configurations. (4) Furthermore, we delve into critical RL training details, systematically exploring the impacts of curriculum learning strategies, variations in reward design, and language-specific factors. Through extensive experiments, our results offer significant insights into the dynamics governing domain interactions, revealing key factors influencing both specialized and generalizable reasoning performance. These findings provide valuable guidance for optimizing RL methodologies to foster comprehensive, multi-domain reasoning capabilities in LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17512</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 13:51:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yume: An Interactive World Generation Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17744</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.17744.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaofeng Mao, Shaoheng Lin, Zhen Li, Chuanhao Li, Wenshuo Peng, Tong He, Jiangmiao Pang, Mingmin Chi, Yu Qiao, Kaipeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 62&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Yume aims to use images, text, or videos to create an interactive, realistic, and dynamic world, which allows exploration and control using peripheral devices or neural signals. In this report, we present a preview version of \method, which creates a dynamic world from an input image and allows exploration of the world using keyboard actions. To achieve this high-fidelity and interactive video world generation, we introduce a well-designed framework, which consists of four main components, including camera motion quantization, video generation architecture, advanced sampler, and model acceleration. First, we quantize camera motions for stable training and user-friendly interaction using keyboard inputs. Then, we introduce the Masked Video Diffusion Transformer~(MVDT) with a memory module for infinite video generation in an autoregressive manner. After that, training-free Anti-Artifact Mechanism (AAM) and Time Travel Sampling based on Stochastic Differential Equations (TTS-SDE) are introduced to the sampler for better visual quality and more precise control. Moreover, we investigate model acceleration by synergistic optimization of adversarial distillation and caching mechanisms. We use the high-quality world exploration dataset \sekai to train \method, and it achieves remarkable results in diverse scenes and applications. All data, codebase, and model weights are available on https://github.com/stdstu12/YUME. Yume will update monthly to achieve its original goal. Project page: https://stdstu12.github.io/YUME-Project/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17744</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 17:57:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra3D: Efficient and High-Fidelity 3D Generation with Part Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17745</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.17745.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiwen Chen, Zhihao Li, Yikai Wang, Hu Zhang, Qin Li, Chi Zhang, Guosheng Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in sparse voxel representations have significantly improved the quality of 3D content generation, enabling high-resolution modeling with fine-grained geometry. However, existing frameworks suffer from severe computational inefficiencies due to the quadratic complexity of attention mechanisms in their two-stage diffusion pipelines. In this work, we propose Ultra3D, an efficient 3D generation framework that significantly accelerates sparse voxel modeling without compromising quality. Our method leverages the compact VecSet representation to efficiently generate a coarse object layout in the first stage, reducing token count and accelerating voxel coordinate prediction. To refine per-voxel latent features in the second stage, we introduce Part Attention, a geometry-aware localized attention mechanism that restricts attention computation within semantically consistent part regions. This design preserves structural continuity while avoiding unnecessary global attention, achieving up to 6.7x speed-up in latent generation. To support this mechanism, we construct a scalable part annotation pipeline that converts raw meshes into part-labeled sparse voxels. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Ultra3D supports high-resolution 3D generation at 1024 resolution and achieves state-of-the-art performance in both visual fidelity and user preference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17745</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 17:57:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technical Report of TeleChat2, TeleChat2.5 and T1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18013</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18013.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihan Wang, Xinzhang Liu, Yitong Yao, Chao Wang, Yu Zhao, Zhihao Yang, Wenmin Deng, Kaipeng Jia, Jiaxin Peng, Yuyao Huang, Sishi Xiong, Zhuo Jiang, Kaidong Yu, Xiaohui Hu, Fubei Yao, Ruiyu Fang, Zhuoru Jiang, Ruiting Song, Qiyi Xie, Rui Xue, Xuewei He, Yanlei Xue, Zhu Yuan, Zhaoxi Zhang, Zilu Huang, Shiquan Wang, Xin Wang, Hanming Wu, Mingyuan Wang, Xufeng Zhan, Yuhan Sun, Zhaohu Xing, Yuhao Jiang, Bingkai Yang, Shuangyong Song, Yongxiang Li, Zhongjiang He, Xuelong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce the latest series of TeleChat models: TeleChat2, TeleChat2.5, and T1, offering a significant upgrade over their predecessor, TeleChat. Despite minimal changes to the model architecture, the new series achieves substantial performance gains through enhanced training strategies in both pre-training and post-training stages. The series begins with TeleChat2, which undergoes pretraining on 10 trillion high-quality and diverse tokens. This is followed by Supervised Fine-Tuning (SFT) and Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) to further enhance its capabilities. TeleChat2.5 and T1 expand the pipeline by incorporating a continual pretraining phase with domain-specific datasets, combined with reinforcement learning (RL) to improve performance in code generation and mathematical reasoning tasks. The T1 variant is designed for complex reasoning, supporting long Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning and demonstrating substantial improvements in mathematics and coding. In contrast, TeleChat2.5 prioritizes speed, delivering rapid inference. Both flagship models of T1 and TeleChat2.5 are dense Transformer-based architectures with 115B parameters, showcasing significant advancements in reasoning and general task performance compared to the original TeleChat. Notably, T1-115B outperform proprietary models such as OpenAI's o1-mini and GPT-4o. We publicly release TeleChat2, TeleChat2.5 and T1, including post-trained versions with 35B and 115B parameters, to empower developers and researchers with state-of-the-art language models tailored for diverse applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18013</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 01:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group Sequence Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18071</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18071.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chujie Zheng, Shixuan Liu, Mingze Li, Xiong-Hui Chen, Bowen Yu, Chang Gao, Kai Dang, Yuqiong Liu, Rui Men, An Yang, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 121&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces Group Sequence Policy Optimization (GSPO), our stable, efficient, and performant reinforcement learning algorithm for training large language models. Unlike previous algorithms that adopt token-level importance ratios, GSPO defines the importance ratio based on sequence likelihood and performs sequence-level clipping, rewarding, and optimization. We demonstrate that GSPO achieves superior training efficiency and performance compared to the GRPO algorithm, notably stabilizes Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) RL training, and has the potential for simplifying the design of RL infrastructure. These merits of GSPO have contributed to the remarkable improvements in the latest Qwen3 models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18071</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 03:50:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Pair of GloVes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18103</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18103.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Riley Carlson, John Bauer, Christopher D. Manning&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This report documents, describes, and evaluates new 2024 English GloVe (Global Vectors for Word Representation) models. While the original GloVe models built in 2014 have been widely used and found useful, languages and the world continue to evolve and we thought that current usage could benefit from updated models. Moreover, the 2014 models were not carefully documented as to the exact data versions and preprocessing that were used, and we rectify this by documenting these new models. We trained two sets of word embeddings using Wikipedia, Gigaword, and a subset of Dolma. Evaluation through vocabulary comparison, direct testing, and NER tasks shows that the 2024 vectors incorporate new culturally and linguistically relevant words, perform comparably on structural tasks like analogy and similarity, and demonstrate improved performance on recent, temporally dependent NER datasets such as non-Western newswire data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18103</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 05:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TeEFusion: Blending Text Embeddings to Distill Classifier-Free Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18192</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18192.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minghao Fu, Guo-Hua Wang, Xiaohao Chen, Qing-Guo Chen, Zhao Xu, Weihua Luo, Kaifu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in text-to-image synthesis largely benefit from sophisticated sampling strategies and classifier-free guidance (CFG) to ensure high-quality generation. However, CFG's reliance on two forward passes, especially when combined with intricate sampling algorithms, results in prohibitively high inference costs. To address this, we introduce TeEFusion (Text Embeddings Fusion), a novel and efficient distillation method that directly incorporates the guidance magnitude into the text embeddings and distills the teacher model's complex sampling strategy. By simply fusing conditional and unconditional text embeddings using linear operations, TeEFusion reconstructs the desired guidance without adding extra parameters, simultaneously enabling the student model to learn from the teacher's output produced via its sophisticated sampling approach. Extensive experiments on state-of-the-art models such as SD3 demonstrate that our method allows the student to closely mimic the teacher's performance with a far simpler and more efficient sampling strategy. Consequently, the student model achieves inference speeds up to 6times faster than the teacher model, while maintaining image quality at levels comparable to those obtained through the teacher's complex sampling approach. The code is publicly available at https://github.com/AIDC-AI/TeEFusion{github.com/AIDC-AI/TeEFusion}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18192</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 08:45:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iwin Transformer: Hierarchical Vision Transformer using Interleaved   Windows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18405</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18405.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Simin Huo, Ning Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Iwin Transformer, a novel position-embedding-free hierarchical vision transformer, which can be fine-tuned directly from low to high resolution, through the collaboration of innovative interleaved window attention and depthwise separable convolution. This approach uses attention to connect distant tokens and applies convolution to link neighboring tokens, enabling global information exchange within a single module, overcoming Swin Transformer's limitation of requiring two consecutive blocks to approximate global attention. Extensive experiments on visual benchmarks demonstrate that Iwin Transformer exhibits strong competitiveness in tasks such as image classification (87.4 top-1 accuracy on ImageNet-1K), semantic segmentation and video action recognition. We also validate the effectiveness of the core component in Iwin as a standalone module that can seamlessly replace the self-attention module in class-conditional image generation. The concepts and methods introduced by the Iwin Transformer have the potential to inspire future research, like Iwin 3D Attention in video generation. The code and models are available at https://github.com/cominder/Iwin-Transformer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18405</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 13:45:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DriftMoE: A Mixture of Experts Approach to Handle Concept Drifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18464</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18464.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Miguel Aspis, Sebastián A. Cajas Ordónez, Andrés L. Suárez-Cetrulo, Ricardo Simón Carbajo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Learning from non-stationary data streams subject to concept drift requires models that can adapt on-the-fly while remaining resource-efficient. Existing adaptive ensemble methods often rely on coarse-grained adaptation mechanisms or simple voting schemes that fail to optimally leverage specialized knowledge. This paper introduces DriftMoE, an online Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture that addresses these limitations through a novel co-training framework. DriftMoE features a compact neural router that is co-trained alongside a pool of incremental Hoeffding tree experts. The key innovation lies in a symbiotic learning loop that enables expert specialization: the router selects the most suitable expert for prediction, the relevant experts update incrementally with the true label, and the router refines its parameters using a multi-hot correctness mask that reinforces every accurate expert. This feedback loop provides the router with a clear training signal while accelerating expert specialization. We evaluate DriftMoE's performance across nine state-of-the-art data stream learning benchmarks spanning abrupt, gradual, and real-world drifts testing two distinct configurations: one where experts specialize on data regimes (multi-class variant), and another where they focus on single-class specialization (task-based variant). Our results demonstrate that DriftMoE achieves competitive results with state-of-the-art stream learning adaptive ensembles, offering a principled and efficient approach to concept drift adaptation. All code, data pipelines, and reproducibility scripts are available in our public GitHub repository: https://github.com/miguel-ceadar/drift-moe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18464</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 14:39:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TTS-VAR: A Test-Time Scaling Framework for Visual Auto-Regressive   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18537</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18537.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhekai Chen, Ruihang Chu, Yukang Chen, Shiwei Zhang, Yujie Wei, Yingya Zhang, Xihui Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling visual generation models is essential for real-world content creation, yet requires substantial training and computational expenses. Alternatively, test-time scaling has garnered growing attention due to resource efficiency and promising performance. In this work, we present TTS-VAR, the first general test-time scaling framework for visual auto-regressive (VAR) models, modeling the generation process as a path searching problem. To dynamically balance computational efficiency with exploration capacity, we first introduce an adaptive descending batch size schedule throughout the causal generation process. Besides, inspired by VAR's hierarchical coarse-to-fine multi-scale generation, our framework integrates two key components: (i) At coarse scales, we observe that generated tokens are hard for evaluation, possibly leading to erroneous acceptance of inferior samples or rejection of superior samples. Noticing that the coarse scales contain sufficient structural information, we propose clustering-based diversity search. It preserves structural variety through semantic feature clustering, enabling later selection on samples with higher potential. (ii) In fine scales, resampling-based potential selection prioritizes promising candidates using potential scores, which are defined as reward functions incorporating multi-scale generation history. Experiments on the powerful VAR model Infinity show a notable 8.7% GenEval score improvement (from 0.69 to 0.75). Key insights reveal that early-stage structural features effectively influence final quality, and resampling efficacy varies across generation scales. Code is available at https://github.com/ali-vilab/TTS-VAR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18537</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 16:04:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GLiNER2: An Efficient Multi-Task Information Extraction System with   Schema-Driven Interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18546</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18546.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Urchade Zaratiana, Gil Pasternak, Oliver Boyd, George Hurn-Maloney, Ash Lewis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Information extraction (IE) is fundamental to numerous NLP applications, yet existing solutions often require specialized models for different tasks or rely on computationally expensive large language models. We present GLiNER2, a unified framework that enhances the original GLiNER architecture to support named entity recognition, text classification, and hierarchical structured data extraction within a single efficient model. Built pretrained transformer encoder architecture, GLiNER2 maintains CPU efficiency and compact size while introducing multi-task composition through an intuitive schema-based interface. Our experiments demonstrate competitive performance across extraction and classification tasks with substantial improvements in deployment accessibility compared to LLM-based alternatives. We release GLiNER2 as an open-source pip-installable library with pre-trained models and documentation at https://github.com/fastino-ai/GLiNER2.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18546</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 16:11:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning-Based Age Estimation and Gender Deep Learning-Based Age   Estimation and Gender Classification for Targeted Advertisement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18565</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18565.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muhammad Imran Zaman, Nisar Ahmed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents a novel deep learning-based approach for simultaneous age and gender classification from facial images, designed to enhance the effectiveness of targeted advertising campaigns. We propose a custom Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) architecture, optimized for both tasks, which leverages the inherent correlation between age and gender information present in facial features. Unlike existing methods that often treat these tasks independently, our model learns shared representations, leading to improved performance. The network is trained on a large, diverse dataset of facial images, carefully pre-processed to ensure robustness against variations in lighting, pose, and image quality. Our experimental results demonstrate a significant improvement in gender classification accuracy, achieving 95%, and a competitive mean absolute error of 5.77 years for age estimation. Critically, we analyze the performance across different age groups, identifying specific challenges in accurately estimating the age of younger individuals. This analysis reveals the need for targeted data augmentation and model refinement to address these biases. Furthermore, we explore the impact of different CNN architectures and hyperparameter settings on the overall performance, providing valuable insights for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18565</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 16:41:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Captain Cinema: Towards Short Movie Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18634</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2507.18634.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junfei Xiao, Ceyuan Yang, Lvmin Zhang, Shengqu Cai, Yang Zhao, Yuwei Guo, Gordon Wetzstein, Maneesh Agrawala, Alan Yuille, Lu Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Captain Cinema, a generation framework for short movie generation. Given a detailed textual description of a movie storyline, our approach firstly generates a sequence of keyframes that outline the entire narrative, which ensures long-range coherence in both the storyline and visual appearance (e.g., scenes and characters). We refer to this step as top-down keyframe planning. These keyframes then serve as conditioning signals for a video synthesis model, which supports long context learning, to produce the spatio-temporal dynamics between them. This step is referred to as bottom-up video synthesis. To support stable and efficient generation of multi-scene long narrative cinematic works, we introduce an interleaved training strategy for Multimodal Diffusion Transformers (MM-DiT), specifically adapted for long-context video data. Our model is trained on a specially curated cinematic dataset consisting of interleaved data pairs. Our experiments demonstrate that Captain Cinema performs favorably in the automated creation of visually coherent and narrative consistent short movies in high quality and efficiency. Project page: https://thecinema.ai&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18634</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
