<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:15:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Every Activation Boosted: Scaling General Reasoner to 1 Trillion Open   Language Foundation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22115</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.22115.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ling-Team, Ang Li, Ben Liu, Binbin Hu, Bing Li, Bingwei Zeng, Borui Ye, Caizhi Tang, Changxin Tian, Chao Huang, Chao Zhang, Chen Qian, Chenchen Ju, Chenchen Li, Chengfu Tang, Chili Fu, Chunshao Ren, Chunwei Wu, Cong Zhang, Cunyin Peng, Dafeng Xu, Daixin Wang, Dalong Zhang, Dingnan Jin, Dingyuan Zhu, Dongke Hu, Fangzheng Zhao, Feifan Wu, Feng Zhu, Gangshan Wang, Haitao Zhang, Hailin Zhao, Hanxiao Zhang, Hanzi Wang, Hao Qian, Haoyi Yu, Heng Zhang, Hongliang Zhang, Hongzhi Luan, Huirong Dong, Huizhong Li, Jia Li, Jia Liu, Jialong Zhu, Jian Sha, Jianping Wei, Jiaolong Yang, Jieyue Ma, Jiewei Wu, Jinjing Huang, Jingyun Tian, Jingyuan Zhang, Jinquan Sun, Juanhui Tu, Jun Liu, Jun Xu, Jun Zhou, Junjie Ou, Junpeng Fang, Kaihong Zhang, Kaiqin Hu, Ke Shi, Kun Tang, Kunlong Chen, Lanyin Mei, Lei Liang, Lei Xu, Libo Zhang, Lin Ju, Lin Yuan, Ling Zhong, Lintao Ma, Lu Liu, Lu Yu, Lun Cai, Meiqi Zhu, Mengying Li, Min Chen, Minghao Xue, Minghong Cai, Mingming Yin, Peijie Jiang, Peilong Zhao, Pingping Liu, Qian Zhao, Qing Cui, Qingxiang Huang, Qingyuan Yang, Quankun Yu, Shaowei Wei, Shijie Lian, Shoujian Zheng, Shun Song, Shungen Zhang, Shuo Zhang, Siyuan Li, Song Liu, Ting Guo, Tong Zhao, Wanli Gu, Weichang Wu, Weiguang Han, Wenjing Fang, Wubin Wang, Xiang Shu, Xiao Shi, Xiaoshun Lan, Xiaolu Zhang, Xiaqing Sun, Xin Zhao, Xingyu Lu, Xiong Xu, Xudong Wang, Xudong Wang, Xuemin Yang, Yajie Yang, Yang Xiang, Yanzhe Li, Yi Zhang, Yilong Wang, Yingxue Li, Yongzhen Guo, Yuzhuo Fu, Yuanyuan Wang, Yue Yang, Yue Yu, Yufeng Deng, Yun Zhang, Yunfei Xu, Yuqi Zhang, Yuxiao He, Zengke Gui, Zhaoxin Huan, Zhaoyang Wang, Zhibo Zhu, Zhihao Wang, Zhiqiang Zhang, Zhoufei Wang, Zihang Zeng, Ziqi Liu, Zitao Xuan, Zuoli Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 82&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Ling 2.0, a series reasoning-oriented language foundation built upon the principle that every activation boosts reasoning capability. Designed to scale from tens of billions to one trillion parameters under a unified Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) paradigm, Ling 2.0 emphasizes high sparsity, cross-scale consistency, and efficiency guided by empirical scaling laws. The series includes three non-thinking (instruct) models - Ling-mini-2.0, Ling-flash-2.0, and Ling-1T - ranging from 16B to 1T total parameters and achieving up to 7-fold active-compute efficiency compared with dense counterparts. Ling 2.0 integrates coordinated innovations across model architecture, pre-training, post-training, and infrastructure: a high-sparsity MoE with MTP for efficient reasoning, reasoning-oriented data and mid-training CoT activation, reinforcement-based fine-tuning (DFT, Evo-CoT), and full-scale FP8 training with fine-grained heterogeneous pipelines. At the trillion scale, Ling-1T establishes a new Pareto frontier of reasoning accuracy versus computational efficiency, demonstrating that sparse activation, when properly aligned with reasoning objectives, enables scalable and efficient intelligence. Collectively, Ling 2.0 provides a coherent, open, and efficient foundation for advancing future reasoning and thinking models, including the Ring series built upon the same base.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22115</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 01:51:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OS-Sentinel: Towards Safety-Enhanced Mobile GUI Agents via Hybrid   Validation in Realistic Workflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24411</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.24411.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qiushi Sun, Mukai Li, Zhoumianze Liu, Zhihui Xie, Fangzhi Xu, Zhangyue Yin, Kanzhi Cheng, Zehao Li, Zichen Ding, Qi Liu, Zhiyong Wu, Zhuosheng Zhang, Ben Kao, Lingpeng Kong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Computer-using agents powered by Vision-Language Models (VLMs) have demonstrated human-like capabilities in operating digital environments like mobile platforms. While these agents hold great promise for advancing digital automation, their potential for unsafe operations, such as system compromise and privacy leakage, is raising significant concerns. Detecting these safety concerns across the vast and complex operational space of mobile environments presents a formidable challenge that remains critically underexplored. To establish a foundation for mobile agent safety research, we introduce MobileRisk-Live, a dynamic sandbox environment accompanied by a safety detection benchmark comprising realistic trajectories with fine-grained annotations. Built upon this, we propose OS-Sentinel, a novel hybrid safety detection framework that synergistically combines a Formal Verifier for detecting explicit system-level violations with a VLM-based Contextual Judge for assessing contextual risks and agent actions. Experiments show that OS-Sentinel achieves 10%-30% improvements over existing approaches across multiple metrics. Further analysis provides critical insights that foster the development of safer and more reliable autonomous mobile agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24411</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 13:22:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>World Simulation with Video Foundation Models for Physical AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00062</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00062.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; NVIDIA, Arslan Ali, Junjie Bai, Maciej Bala, Yogesh Balaji, Aaron Blakeman, Tiffany Cai, Jiaxin Cao, Tianshi Cao, Elizabeth Cha, Yu-Wei Chao, Prithvijit Chattopadhyay, Mike Chen, Yongxin Chen, Yu Chen, Shuai Cheng, Yin Cui, Jenna Diamond, Yifan Ding, Jiaojiao Fan, Linxi Fan, Liang Feng, Francesco Ferroni, Sanja Fidler, Xiao Fu, Ruiyuan Gao, Yunhao Ge, Jinwei Gu, Aryaman Gupta, Siddharth Gururani, Imad El Hanafi, Ali Hassani, Zekun Hao, Jacob Huffman, Joel Jang, Pooya Jannaty, Jan Kautz, Grace Lam, Xuan Li, Zhaoshuo Li, Maosheng Liao, Chen-Hsuan Lin, Tsung-Yi Lin, Yen-Chen Lin, Huan Ling, Ming-Yu Liu, Xian Liu, Yifan Lu, Alice Luo, Qianli Ma, Hanzi Mao, Kaichun Mo, Seungjun Nah, Yashraj Narang, Abhijeet Panaskar, Lindsey Pavao, Trung Pham, Morteza Ramezanali, Fitsum Reda, Scott Reed, Xuanchi Ren, Haonan Shao, Yue Shen, Stella Shi, Shuran Song, Bartosz Stefaniak, Shangkun Sun, Shitao Tang, Sameena Tasmeen, Lyne Tchapmi, Wei-Cheng Tseng, Jibin Varghese, Andrew Z. Wang, Hao Wang, Haoxiang Wang, Heng Wang, Ting-Chun Wang, Fangyin Wei, Jiashu Xu, Dinghao Yang, Xiaodong Yang, Haotian Ye, Seonghyeon Ye, Xiaohui Zeng, Jing Zhang, Qinsheng Zhang, Kaiwen Zheng, Andrew Zhu, Yuke Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce [Cosmos-Predict2.5], the latest generation of the Cosmos World Foundation Models for Physical AI. Built on a flow-based architecture, [Cosmos-Predict2.5] unifies Text2World, Image2World, and Video2World generation in a single model and leverages [Cosmos-Reason1], a Physical AI vision-language model, to provide richer text grounding and finer control of world simulation. Trained on 200M curated video clips and refined with reinforcement learning-based post-training, [Cosmos-Predict2.5] achieves substantial improvements over [Cosmos-Predict1] in video quality and instruction alignment, with models released at 2B and 14B scales. These capabilities enable more reliable synthetic data generation, policy evaluation, and closed-loop simulation for robotics and autonomous systems. We further extend the family with [Cosmos-Transfer2.5], a control-net style framework for Sim2Real and Real2Real world translation. Despite being 3.5times smaller than [Cosmos-Transfer1], it delivers higher fidelity and robust long-horizon video generation. Together, these advances establish [Cosmos-Predict2.5] and [Cosmos-Transfer2.5] as versatile tools for scaling embodied intelligence. To accelerate research and deployment in Physical AI, we release source code, pretrained checkpoints, and curated benchmarks under the NVIDIA Open Model License at https://github.com/nvidia-cosmos/cosmos-predict2.5 and https://github.com/nvidia-cosmos/cosmos-transfer2.5. We hope these open resources lower the barrier to adoption and foster innovation in building the next generation of embodied intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00062</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 22:44:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INT v.s. FP: A Comprehensive Study of Fine-Grained Low-bit Quantization   Formats</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25602</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25602.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mengzhao Chen, Meng Wu, Hui Jin, Zhihang Yuan, Jing Liu, Chaoyi Zhang, Yunshui Li, Jie Huang, Jin Ma, Zeyue Xue, Zhiheng Liu, Xingyan Bin, Ping Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 75&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Modern AI hardware, such as Nvidia's Blackwell architecture, is increasingly embracing low-precision floating-point (FP) formats to handle the pervasive activation outliers in Large Language Models (LLMs). Despite this industry trend, a unified comparison of FP and integer (INT) quantization across varying granularities has been missing, leaving algorithm and hardware co-design without clear guidance. This paper fills that gap by systematically investigating the trade-offs between FP and INT formats. We reveal a critical performance crossover: while FP excels in coarse-grained quantization, the comparison at fine-grained (block-wise) levels is more nuanced. Our comprehensive comparison demonstrates that for popular 8-bit fine-grained formats (e.g., MX with block size 32), MXINT8 is superior to its FP counterpart in both algorithmic accuracy and hardware efficiency. However, for 4-bit formats, FP (e.g., MXFP4, NVFP4) often holds an accuracy advantage , though we show that NVINT4 can surpass NVFP4 when outlier-mitigation techniques like Hadamard rotation are applied. We also introduce a symmetric clipping method that resolves gradient bias in fine-grained low-bit INT training, enabling nearly lossless performance for MXINT8 training. These findings challenge the current hardware trajectory, demonstrating that a one-size-fits-all FP approach is suboptimal and advocating that fine-grained INT formats, particularly MXINT8, offer a better balance of accuracy, power, and efficiency for future AI accelerators.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25602</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 15:11:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don't Blind Your VLA: Aligning Visual Representations for OOD   Generalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25616</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25616.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nikita Kachaev, Mikhail Kolosov, Daniil Zelezetsky, Alexey K. Kovalev, Aleksandr I. Panov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 94&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The growing success of Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models stems from the promise that pretrained Vision-Language Models (VLMs) can endow agents with transferable world knowledge and vision-language (VL) grounding, laying a foundation for action models with broader generalization. Yet when these VLMs are adapted to the action modality, it remains unclear to what extent their original VL representations and knowledge are preserved. In this work, we conduct a systematic study of representation retention during VLA fine-tuning, showing that naive action fine-tuning leads to degradation of visual representations. To characterize and measure these effects, we probe VLA's hidden representations and analyze attention maps, further, we design a set of targeted tasks and methods that contrast VLA models with their counterpart VLMs, isolating changes in VL capabilities induced by action fine-tuning. We further evaluate a range of strategies for aligning visual representations and introduce a simple yet effective method that mitigates degradation and yields improved generalization to out-of-distribution (OOD) scenarios. Taken together, our analysis clarifies the trade-off between action fine-tuning and the degradation of VL representations and highlights practical approaches to recover inherited VL capabilities. Code is publicly available: https://blind-vla-paper.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25616</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 15:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>π_RL: Online RL Fine-tuning for Flow-based   Vision-Language-Action Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25889</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.25889.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kang Chen, Zhihao Liu, Tonghe Zhang, Zhen Guo, Si Xu, Hao Lin, Hongzhi Zang, Quanlu Zhang, Zhaofei Yu, Guoliang Fan, Tiejun Huang, Yu Wang, Chao Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models enable robots to understand and perform complex tasks from multimodal input. Although recent work explores using reinforcement learning (RL) to automate the laborious data collection process in scaling supervised fine-tuning (SFT), applying large-scale RL to flow-based VLAs (e.g., pi_0, pi_{0.5}) remains challenging due to intractable action log-likelihoods from iterative denoising.   We address this challenge with pi_{RL}, an open-source framework for training flow-based VLAs in parallel simulation. pi_{RL} implements two RL algorithms: (1) {Flow-Noise} models the denoising process as a discrete-time MDP with a learnable noise network for exact log-likelihood computation. (2) {Flow-SDE} integrates denoising with agent-environment interaction, formulating a two-layer MDP that employs ODE-to-SDE conversion for efficient RL exploration.   We evaluate pi_{RL} on LIBERO and ManiSkill benchmarks. On LIBERO, pi_{RL} boosts few-shot SFT models pi_0 and pi_{0.5} from 57.6% to 97.6% and from 77.1% to 98.3%, respectively. In ManiSkill, we train pi_{RL} in 320 parallel environments, improving pi_0 from 41.6% to 85.7% and pi_{0.5} from 40.0% to 84.8% across 4352 pick-and-place tasks, demonstrating scalable multitask RL under heterogeneous simulation.   Overall, pi_{RL} achieves significant performance gains and stronger generalization over SFT-models, validating the effectiveness of online RL for flow-based VLAs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25889</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 18:37:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing Test-time Compute-optimal Scaling as an Optimizable Graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00086</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.00086.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fali Wang, Jihai Chen, Shuhua Yang, Runxue Bao, Tianxiang Zhao, Zhiwei Zhang, Xianfeng Tang, Hui Liu, Qi He, Suhang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Test-Time Scaling (TTS) improves large language models (LLMs) by allocating additional computation during inference, typically through parallel, sequential, or hybrid scaling. However, prior studies often assume fixed collaboration architectures (e.g., topologies) and single-model usage, overlooking that optimal architectures and model combinations can vary across tasks. Therefore, we study the novel problem of searching for compute-optimal model combinations and architectures in TTS under a fixed budget. We formalize it as a multi-LLM collaboration graph, where nodes encode roles and LLM model assignments, and edges capture information flow. This problem is challenging because (i) the combinatorial search space is prohibitively large, and (ii) task-specific requirements demand tailored designs. To address these, we reformulate the problem as probabilistic graph optimization and, through pilot experiments, derive three empirical insights into TTS collaboration graphs. Guided by these insights, we propose Agent-REINFORCE, an LLM-agent-augmented framework that mirrors the REINFORCE pipeline by mapping sampling-gradient-update to sampling-feedback-update, where feedback serves as a textual gradient to update the probabilistic graph and efficiently search for optimal multi-LLM collaboration graphs. Experiments show that Agent-REINFORCE outperforms both traditional and LLM-based baselines in sample efficiency and search performance, and effectively identifies optimal graphs under joint objectives of accuracy and inference latency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00086</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 22:14:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ThinkMorph: Emergent Properties in Multimodal Interleaved   Chain-of-Thought Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27492</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27492.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiawei Gu, Yunzhuo Hao, Huichen Will Wang, Linjie Li, Michael Qizhe Shieh, Yejin Choi, Ranjay Krishna, Yu Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 80&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal reasoning requires iterative coordination between language and vision, yet it remains unclear what constitutes a meaningful interleaved chain of thought. We posit that text and image thoughts should function as complementary, rather than isomorphic, modalities that mutually advance reasoning. Guided by this principle, we build ThinkMorph, a unified model fine-tuned on 24K high-quality interleaved reasoning traces spanning tasks with varying visual engagement. ThinkMorph learns to generate progressive text-image reasoning steps that concretely manipulate visual content while maintaining coherent verbal logic. It delivers large gains on vision-centric benchmarks (averaging 34.7% over the base model) and generalizes to out-of-domain tasks, matching or surpassing larger and proprietary VLMs. Beyond performance, ThinkMorph exhibits emergent multimodal intelligence, including unseen visual manipulation skills, adaptive switching between reasoning modes, and better test-time scaling through diversified multimodal thoughts.These findings suggest promising directions for characterizing the emergent capabilities of unified models for multimodal reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27492</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:51:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defeating the Training-Inference Mismatch via FP16</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26788</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.26788.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Penghui Qi, Zichen Liu, Xiangxin Zhou, Tianyu Pang, Chao Du, Wee Sun Lee, Min Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) fine-tuning of large language models (LLMs) often suffers from instability due to the numerical mismatch between the training and inference policies. While prior work has attempted to mitigate this issue through algorithmic corrections or engineering alignments, we show that its root cause lies in the floating point precision itself. The widely adopted BF16, despite its large dynamic range, introduces large rounding errors that breaks the consistency between training and inference. In this work, we demonstrate that simply reverting to FP16 effectively eliminates this mismatch. The change is simple, fully supported by modern frameworks with only a few lines of code change, and requires no modification to the model architecture or learning algorithm. Our results suggest that using FP16 uniformly yields more stable optimization, faster convergence, and stronger performance across diverse tasks, algorithms and frameworks. We hope these findings motivate a broader reconsideration of precision trade-offs in RL fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26788</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 17:58:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EBT-Policy: Energy Unlocks Emergent Physical Reasoning Capabilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27545</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27545.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Travis Davies, Yiqi Huang, Alexi Gladstone, Yunxin Liu, Xiang Chen, Heng Ji, Huxian Liu, Luhui Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Implicit policies parameterized by generative models, such as Diffusion Policy, have become the standard for policy learning and Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models in robotics. However, these approaches often suffer from high computational cost, exposure bias, and unstable inference dynamics, which lead to divergence under distribution shifts. Energy-Based Models (EBMs) address these issues by learning energy landscapes end-to-end and modeling equilibrium dynamics, offering improved robustness and reduced exposure bias. Yet, policies parameterized by EBMs have historically struggled to scale effectively. Recent work on Energy-Based Transformers (EBTs) demonstrates the scalability of EBMs to high-dimensional spaces, but their potential for solving core challenges in physically embodied models remains underexplored. We introduce a new energy-based architecture, EBT-Policy, that solves core issues in robotic and real-world settings. Across simulated and real-world tasks, EBT-Policy consistently outperforms diffusion-based policies, while requiring less training and inference computation. Remarkably, on some tasks it converges within just two inference steps, a 50x reduction compared to Diffusion Policy's 100. Moreover, EBT-Policy exhibits emergent capabilities not seen in prior models, such as zero-shot recovery from failed action sequences using only behavior cloning and without explicit retry training. By leveraging its scalar energy for uncertainty-aware inference and dynamic compute allocation, EBT-Policy offers a promising path toward robust, generalizable robot behavior under distribution shifts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27545</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 15:21:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous Autoregressive Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27688</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2510.27688.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenze Shao, Darren Li, Fandong Meng, Jie Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The efficiency of large language models (LLMs) is fundamentally limited by their sequential, token-by-token generation process. We argue that overcoming this bottleneck requires a new design axis for LLM scaling: increasing the semantic bandwidth of each generative step. To this end, we introduce Continuous Autoregressive Language Models (CALM), a paradigm shift from discrete next-token prediction to continuous next-vector prediction. CALM uses a high-fidelity autoencoder to compress a chunk of K tokens into a single continuous vector, from which the original tokens can be reconstructed with over 99.9\% accuracy. This allows us to model language as a sequence of continuous vectors instead of discrete tokens, which reduces the number of generative steps by a factor of K. The paradigm shift necessitates a new modeling toolkit; therefore, we develop a comprehensive likelihood-free framework that enables robust training, evaluation, and controllable sampling in the continuous domain. Experiments show that CALM significantly improves the performance-compute trade-off, achieving the performance of strong discrete baselines at a significantly lower computational cost. More importantly, these findings establish next-vector prediction as a powerful and scalable pathway towards ultra-efficient language models. Code: https://github.com/shaochenze/calm. Project: https://shaochenze.github.io/blog/2025/CALM.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.27688</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 17:58:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ROVER: Benchmarking Reciprocal Cross-Modal Reasoning for Omnimodal   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01163</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01163.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yongyuan Liang, Wei Chow, Feng Li, Ziqiao Ma, Xiyao Wang, Jiageng Mao, Jiuhai Chen, Jiatao Gu, Yue Wang, Furong Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified multimodal models (UMMs) have emerged as a powerful paradigm for seamlessly unifying text and image understanding and generation. However, prevailing evaluations treat these abilities in isolation, such that tasks with multimodal inputs and outputs are scored primarily through unimodal reasoning, i.e., textual benchmarks emphasize language-based reasoning, while visual benchmarks emphasize reasoning outcomes manifested in the pixels. We introduce ROVER to address this pressing need to test reciprocal cross-modal reasoning, the use of one modality to guide, verify, or refine outputs in the other, an ability central to the vision of unified multimodal intelligence. ROVER is a human-annotated benchmark that explicitly targets reciprocal cross-modal reasoning, which contains 1312 tasks grounded in 1876 images, spanning two complementary settings. Verbally-augmented reasoning for visual generation evaluates whether models can use verbal prompts and reasoning chains to guide faithful image synthesis. Visually-augmented reasoning for verbal generation evaluates whether models can generate intermediate visualizations that strengthen their own reasoning processes for question answering. Experiments on 17 unified models reveal two key findings: (i) Cross-modal reasoning determines visual generation quality, with interleaved models significantly outperforming non-interleaved ones; notably, combining strong unimodal models fails to achieve comparable reasoning. (ii) Models show dissociation between physical and symbolic reasoning: they succeed at interpreting perceptual concepts literally but fail to construct visual abstractions for symbolic tasks, where faulty reasoning harms performance. These results highlight reciprocal cross-modal reasoning as a critical frontier for enabling true omnimodal generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01163</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 02:27:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniREditBench: A Unified Reasoning-based Image Editing Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01295</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01295.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Feng Han, Yibin Wang, Chenglin Li, Zheming Liang, Dianyi Wang, Yang Jiao, Zhipeng Wei, Chao Gong, Cheng Jin, Jingjing Chen, Jiaqi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multi-modal generative models have driven substantial improvements in image editing. However, current generative models still struggle with handling diverse and complex image editing tasks that require implicit reasoning, underscoring the need for a comprehensive benchmark to systematically assess their performance across various reasoning scenarios. Existing benchmarks primarily focus on single-object attribute transformation in realistic scenarios, which, while effective, encounter two key challenges: (1) they largely overlook multi-object interactions as well as game-world scenarios that involve human-defined rules, which are common in real-life applications; (2) they only rely on textual references to evaluate the generated images, potentially leading to systematic misjudgments, especially in complex reasoning scenarios. To this end, this work proposes UniREditBench, a unified benchmark for reasoning-based image editing evaluation. It comprises 2,700 meticulously curated samples, covering both real- and game-world scenarios across 8 primary dimensions and 18 sub-dimensions. To improve evaluation reliability, we introduce multimodal dual-reference evaluation, providing both textual and ground-truth image references for each sample assessment. Furthermore, we design an automated multi-scenario data synthesis pipeline and construct UniREdit-Data-100K, a large-scale synthetic dataset with high-quality chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning annotations. We fine-tune Bagel on this dataset and develop UniREdit-Bagel, demonstrating substantial improvements in both in-domain and out-of-distribution settings. Through thorough benchmarking of both open-source and closed-source image editing models, we reveal their strengths and weaknesses across various aspects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01295</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 07:24:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniLumos: Fast and Unified Image and Video Relighting with   Physics-Plausible Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01678</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.01678.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ropeway Liu, Hangjie Yuan, Bo Dong, Jiazheng Xing, Jinwang Wang, Rui Zhao, Yan Xing, Weihua Chen, Fan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Relighting is a crucial task with both practical demand and artistic value, and recent diffusion models have shown strong potential by enabling rich and controllable lighting effects. However, as they are typically optimized in semantic latent space, where proximity does not guarantee physical correctness in visual space, they often produce unrealistic results, such as overexposed highlights, misaligned shadows, and incorrect occlusions. We address this with UniLumos, a unified relighting framework for both images and videos that brings RGB-space geometry feedback into a flow matching backbone. By supervising the model with depth and normal maps extracted from its outputs, we explicitly align lighting effects with the scene structure, enhancing physical plausibility. Nevertheless, this feedback requires high-quality outputs for supervision in visual space, making standard multi-step denoising computationally expensive. To mitigate this, we employ path consistency learning, allowing supervision to remain effective even under few-step training regimes. To enable fine-grained relighting control and supervision, we design a structured six-dimensional annotation protocol capturing core illumination attributes. Building upon this, we propose LumosBench, a disentangled attribute-level benchmark that evaluates lighting controllability via large vision-language models, enabling automatic and interpretable assessment of relighting precision across individual dimensions. Extensive experiments demonstrate that UniLumos achieves state-of-the-art relighting quality with significantly improved physical consistency, while delivering a 20x speedup for both image and video relighting. Code is available at https://github.com/alibaba-damo-academy/Lumos-Custom.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01678</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 15:41:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VCode: a Multimodal Coding Benchmark with SVG as Symbolic Visual   Representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02778</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02778.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kevin Qinghong Lin, Yuhao Zheng, Hangyu Ran, Dantong Zhu, Dongxing Mao, Linjie Li, Philip Torr, Alex Jinpeng Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 101&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Code has emerged as a precise and executable medium for reasoning and action in the agent era. Yet, progress has largely focused on language-centric tasks such as program synthesis and debugging, leaving visual-centric coding underexplored. Inspired by how humans reason over sketches, we advocate SVG code as a compact, interpretable, and executable visual representation. We introduce VCode, a benchmark that reframes multimodal understanding as code generation: given an image, a model must produce SVG that preserves symbolic meaning for downstream reasoning. VCode covers three domains - general commonsense (MM-Vet), professional disciplines (MMMU), and visual-centric perception (CV-Bench). To assess symbolic fidelity, we propose CodeVQA, a novel evaluation protocol in which a policy model answers questions over rendered SVGs; correct answers indicate faithful symbolic preservation. Empirically, frontier VLMs struggle to generate faithful SVGs, revealing a persistent gap between language-centric and visual-centric coding. To close this gap, we introduce VCoder, an agentic framework that augments VLMs along two axes: (i) Thinking with Revision, which iteratively analyzes discrepancies and refines SVG code; and (ii) Acting with Visual Tools, where detectors and parsers supply structured cues such as objects, shapes, and text beyond the model's intrinsic capacity. Across benchmarks, frontier VLMs with strong reasoning capabilities score well overall yet remain limited in professional knowledge and 3D reasoning. VCoder delivers a 12.3-point overall gain over the top-performing Claude-4-Opus. Human studies show that both humans and VLMs perform worse on rendered SVGs, their consistency reveals the promise of symbolic visual representation. The benchmark and code are available at https://github.com/CSU-JPG/VCode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02778</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 18:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Visualizing is the First Step to Reasoning: MIRA, a Benchmark for   Visual Chain-of-Thought</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02779</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.02779.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiyang Zhou, Haoqin Tu, Zijun Wang, Zeyu Wang, Niklas Muennighoff, Fan Nie, Yejin Choi, James Zou, Chaorui Deng, Shen Yan, Haoqi Fan, Cihang Xie, Huaxiu Yao, Qinghao Ye&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose MIRA, a new benchmark designed to evaluate models in scenarios where generating intermediate visual images is essential for successful reasoning. Unlike traditional CoT methods that rely solely on text, tasks in MIRA require models to generate and utilize intermediate images - such as sketches, structural diagrams, or path drawings - to guide their reasoning process. This setup closely mirrors how humans solve complex problems through "drawing to think". To solve this, MIRA focuses on tasks that are intrinsically challenging and involve complex structures, spatial relationships, or reasoning steps that are difficult to express through language alone. To ensure that our evaluation data is of high-quality, we include 546 multimodal problems, annotated with intermediate visual images and final answers. We also propose a unified evaluation protocol for MIRA that spans three levels of evaluation input: direct input with image and question only, text-only CoT input with image and thinking prompts, and Visual-CoT input with both annotated image clues and textual thinking prompts. To probe the upper bound of model capacity on our benchmark, we also report pass@k and majority voting accuracies under different k settings. Experimental results show that existing multimodal large language models, including strongest private models as well as strong open-weight models, perform poorly when relying solely on textual prompts. However, when intermediate visual cues are provided, model performance improves consistently, yielding an average relative gain of 33.7% across all models and tasks. We also probe the upper bound by expanding the search space and designing textual prompts aligned with Visual-CoT, but both yield only limited improvements compared to our Visual-CoT setting. These results underscore the critical role of imagined visual information in enabling successful reasoning on MIRA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02779</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 18:00:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LEGO-Eval: Towards Fine-Grained Evaluation on Synthesizing 3D Embodied   Environments with Tool Augmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03001</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03001.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gyeom Hwangbo, Hyungjoo Chae, Minseok Kang, Hyeonjong Ju, Soohyun Oh, Jinyoung Yeo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite recent progress in using Large Language Models (LLMs) for automatically generating 3D scenes, generated scenes often lack realistic spatial layouts and object attributes found in real-world environments. As this problem stems from insufficiently detailed, coarse-grained instructions, advancing 3D scene synthesis guided by more detailed, fine-grained instructions that reflect real-world environments becomes crucial. Without such realistic scenes, training embodied agents in unrealistic environments can lead them to learn priors that diverge significantly from real-world physics and semantics, degrading their performance when deployed. Thus, verifying the alignment between the fine-grained instruction and the generated scene is essential for effective learning. However, current evaluation methods, such as CLIPScore and vision-language models (VLMs), often fail to reliably assess such alignment. This shortcoming arises primarily from their shallow understanding of 3D scenes, which often leads to improperly grounded scene components. To address this, we introduce LEGO-Eval, an evaluation framework equipped with diverse tools designed to explicitly ground scene components, enabling more accurate alignment assessments. We also present LEGO-Bench, a benchmark of detailed instructions that specify complex layouts and attributes of real-world environments. Experiments demonstrate that LEGO-Eval outperforms VLM-as-a-judge by 0.41 F1 score in assessing scene-instruction alignment. Benchmarking with LEGO-Bench reveals significant limitations in current generation methods. Across all evaluated approaches, success rates reached at most 10% in generating scenes that fully align with fine-grained instructions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 21:13:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Language Models are Super Data Learners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03276</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03276.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinjie Ni, Qian Liu, Longxu Dou, Chao Du, Zili Wang, Hang Yan, Tianyu Pang, Michael Qizhe Shieh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 120&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Under strictly controlled pre-training settings, we observe a Crossover: when unique data is limited, diffusion language models (DLMs) consistently surpass autoregressive (AR) models by training for more epochs. The crossover shifts later with more or higher-quality data, earlier with larger models, and persists across dense and sparse architectures. We attribute the gains to three compounding factors: (1) any-order modeling, (2) super-dense compute from iterative bidirectional denoising, and (3) built-in Monte Carlo augmentation; input or parameter noise improves AR under data constraint but cannot close the gap. At scale, a 1.7B DLM trained with a ~1.5T-token compute budget on 10B unique Python tokens overtakes an AR coder trained with strictly matched settings. In addition, a 1B-parameter DLM achieves &gt; 56% accuracy on HellaSwag and &gt; 33% on MMLU using only 1B tokens, without any special tricks, just by repeating standard pre-training data. We also show that rising validation cross-entropy does not imply degraded downstream performance in this regime.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03276</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 08:17:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniAVGen: Unified Audio and Video Generation with Asymmetric Cross-Modal   Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03334</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03334.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guozhen Zhang, Zixiang Zhou, Teng Hu, Ziqiao Peng, Youliang Zhang, Yi Chen, Yuan Zhou, Qinglin Lu, Limin Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Due to the lack of effective cross-modal modeling, existing open-source audio-video generation methods often exhibit compromised lip synchronization and insufficient semantic consistency. To mitigate these drawbacks, we propose UniAVGen, a unified framework for joint audio and video generation. UniAVGen is anchored in a dual-branch joint synthesis architecture, incorporating two parallel Diffusion Transformers (DiTs) to build a cohesive cross-modal latent space. At its heart lies an Asymmetric Cross-Modal Interaction mechanism, which enables bidirectional, temporally aligned cross-attention, thus ensuring precise spatiotemporal synchronization and semantic consistency. Furthermore, this cross-modal interaction is augmented by a Face-Aware Modulation module, which dynamically prioritizes salient regions in the interaction process. To enhance generative fidelity during inference, we additionally introduce Modality-Aware Classifier-Free Guidance, a novel strategy that explicitly amplifies cross-modal correlation signals. Notably, UniAVGen's robust joint synthesis design enables seamless unification of pivotal audio-video tasks within a single model, such as joint audio-video generation and continuation, video-to-audio dubbing, and audio-driven video synthesis. Comprehensive experiments validate that, with far fewer training samples (1.3M vs. 30.1M), UniAVGen delivers overall advantages in audio-video synchronization, timbre consistency, and emotion consistency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03334</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 10:06:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HaluMem: Evaluating Hallucinations in Memory Systems of Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03506</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03506.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ding Chen, Simin Niu, Kehang Li, Peng Liu, Xiangping Zheng, Bo Tang, Xinchi Li, Feiyu Xiong, Zhiyu Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 91&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Memory systems are key components that enable AI systems such as LLMs and AI agents to achieve long-term learning and sustained interaction. However, during memory storage and retrieval, these systems frequently exhibit memory hallucinations, including fabrication, errors, conflicts, and omissions. Existing evaluations of memory hallucinations are primarily end-to-end question answering, which makes it difficult to localize the operational stage within the memory system where hallucinations arise. To address this, we introduce the Hallucination in Memory Benchmark (HaluMem), the first operation level hallucination evaluation benchmark tailored to memory systems. HaluMem defines three evaluation tasks (memory extraction, memory updating, and memory question answering) to comprehensively reveal hallucination behaviors across different operational stages of interaction. To support evaluation, we construct user-centric, multi-turn human-AI interaction datasets, HaluMem-Medium and HaluMem-Long. Both include about 15k memory points and 3.5k multi-type questions. The average dialogue length per user reaches 1.5k and 2.6k turns, with context lengths exceeding 1M tokens, enabling evaluation of hallucinations across different context scales and task complexities. Empirical studies based on HaluMem show that existing memory systems tend to generate and accumulate hallucinations during the extraction and updating stages, which subsequently propagate errors to the question answering stage. Future research should focus on developing interpretable and constrained memory operation mechanisms that systematically suppress hallucinations and improve memory reliability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03506</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 14:37:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Agent Learning via Experience Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03773</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.03773.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhaorun Chen, Zhuokai Zhao, Kai Zhang, Bo Liu, Qi Qi, Yifan Wu, Tarun Kalluri, Sara Cao, Yuanhao Xiong, Haibo Tong, Huaxiu Yao, Hengduo Li, Jiacheng Zhu, Xian Li, Dawn Song, Bo Li, Jason Weston, Dat Huynh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 77&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While reinforcement learning (RL) can empower large language model (LLM) agents by enabling self-improvement through interaction, its practical adoption remains challenging due to costly rollouts, limited task diversity, unreliable reward signals, and infrastructure complexity, all of which obstruct the collection of scalable experience data. To address these challenges, we introduce DreamGym, the first unified framework designed to synthesize diverse experiences with scalability in mind to enable effective online RL training for autonomous agents. Rather than relying on expensive real-environment rollouts, DreamGym distills environment dynamics into a reasoning-based experience model that derives consistent state transitions and feedback signals through step-by-step reasoning, enabling scalable agent rollout collection for RL. To improve the stability and quality of transitions, DreamGym leverages an experience replay buffer initialized with offline real-world data and continuously enriched with fresh interactions to actively support agent training. To improve knowledge acquisition, DreamGym adaptively generates new tasks that challenge the current agent policy, enabling more effective online curriculum learning. Experiments across diverse environments and agent backbones demonstrate that DreamGym substantially improves RL training, both in fully synthetic settings and in sim-to-real transfer scenarios. On non-RL-ready tasks like WebArena, DreamGym outperforms all baselines by over 30%. And in RL-ready but costly settings, it matches GRPO and PPO performance using only synthetic interactions. When transferring a policy trained purely on synthetic experiences to real-environment RL, DreamGym yields significant additional performance gains while requiring far fewer real-world interactions, providing a scalable warm-start strategy for general-purpose RL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03773</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 18:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V-Thinker: Interactive Thinking with Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04460</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04460.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runqi Qiao, Qiuna Tan, Minghan Yang, Guanting Dong, Peiqing Yang, Shiqiang Lang, Enhui Wan, Xiaowan Wang, Yida Xu, Lan Yang, Chong Sun, Chen Li, Honggang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 94&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Empowering Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) to deeply integrate image interaction with long-horizon reasoning capabilities remains a long-standing challenge in this field. Recent advances in vision-centric reasoning explore a promising "Thinking with Images" paradigm for LMMs, marking a shift from image-assisted reasoning to image-interactive thinking. While this milestone enables models to focus on fine-grained image regions, progress remains constrained by limited visual tool spaces and task-specific workflow designs. To bridge this gap, we present V-Thinker, a general-purpose multimodal reasoning assistant that enables interactive, vision-centric thinking through end-to-end reinforcement learning. V-Thinker comprises two key components: (1) a Data Evolution Flywheel that automatically synthesizes, evolves, and verifies interactive reasoning datasets across three dimensions-diversity, quality, and difficulty; and (2) a Visual Progressive Training Curriculum that first aligns perception via point-level supervision, then integrates interactive reasoning through a two-stage reinforcement learning framework. Furthermore, we introduce VTBench, an expert-verified benchmark targeting vision-centric interactive reasoning tasks. Extensive experiments demonstrate that V-Thinker consistently outperforms strong LMM-based baselines in both general and interactive reasoning scenarios, providing valuable insights for advancing image-interactive reasoning applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04460</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 15:32:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking with Video: Video Generation as a Promising Multimodal   Reasoning Paradigm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04570</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04570.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingqi Tong, Yurong Mou, Hangcheng Li, Mingzhe Li, Yongzhuo Yang, Ming Zhang, Qiguang Chen, Tianyi Liang, Xiaomeng Hu, Yining Zheng, Xinchi Chen, Jun Zhao, Xuanjing Huang, Xipeng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 204&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; "Thinking with Text" and "Thinking with Images" paradigm significantly improve the reasoning ability of large language models (LLMs) and Vision Language Models (VLMs). However, these paradigms have inherent limitations. (1) Images capture only single moments and fail to represent dynamic processes or continuous changes, and (2) The separation of text and vision as distinct modalities, hindering unified multimodal understanding and generation. To overcome these limitations, we introduce "Thinking with Video", a new paradigm that leverages video generation models, such as Sora-2, to bridge visual and textual reasoning in a unified temporal framework. To support this exploration, we developed the Video Thinking Benchmark (VideoThinkBench). VideoThinkBench encompasses two task categories: (1) vision-centric tasks (e.g., Eyeballing Puzzles), and (2) text-centric tasks (e.g., subsets of GSM8K, MMMU). Our evaluation establishes Sora-2 as a capable reasoner. On vision-centric tasks, Sora-2 is generally comparable to state-of-the-art (SOTA) VLMs, and even surpasses VLMs on several tasks, such as Eyeballing Games. On text-centric tasks, Sora-2 achieves 92% accuracy on MATH, and 75.53% accuracy on MMMU. Furthermore, we systematically analyse the source of these abilities. We also find that self-consistency and in-context learning can improve Sora-2's performance. In summary, our findings demonstrate that the video generation model is the potential unified multimodal understanding and generation model, positions "thinking with video" as a unified multimodal reasoning paradigm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04570</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 17:25:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VeriCoT: Neuro-symbolic Chain-of-Thought Validation via Logical   Consistency Checks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04662</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04662.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Feng, Nathaniel Weir, Kaj Bostrom, Sam Bayless, Darion Cassel, Sapana Chaudhary, Benjamin Kiesl-Reiter, Huzefa Rangwala&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLMs can perform multi-step reasoning through Chain-of-Thought (CoT), but they cannot reliably verify their own logic. Even when they reach correct answers, the underlying reasoning may be flawed, undermining trust in high-stakes scenarios. To mitigate this issue, we introduce VeriCoT, a neuro-symbolic method that extracts and verifies formal logical arguments from CoT reasoning. VeriCoT formalizes each CoT reasoning step into first-order logic and identifies premises that ground the argument in source context, commonsense knowledge, or prior reasoning steps. The symbolic representation enables automated solvers to verify logical validity while the NL premises allow humans and systems to identify ungrounded or fallacious reasoning steps. Experiments on the ProofWriter, LegalBench, and BioASQ datasets show VeriCoT effectively identifies flawed reasoning, and serves as a strong predictor of final answer correctness. We also leverage VeriCoT's verification signal for (1) inference-time self-reflection, (2) supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on VeriCoT-distilled datasets and (3) preference fine-tuning (PFT) with direct preference optimization (DPO) using verification-based pairwise rewards, further improving reasoning validity and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04662</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:50:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cambrian-S: Towards Spatial Supersensing in Video</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04670</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04670.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shusheng Yang, Jihan Yang, Pinzhi Huang, Ellis Brown, Zihao Yang, Yue Yu, Shengbang Tong, Zihan Zheng, Yifan Xu, Muhan Wang, Daohan Lu, Rob Fergus, Yann LeCun, Li Fei-Fei, Saining Xie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We argue that progress in true multimodal intelligence calls for a shift from reactive, task-driven systems and brute-force long context towards a broader paradigm of supersensing. We frame spatial supersensing as four stages beyond linguistic-only understanding: semantic perception (naming what is seen), streaming event cognition (maintaining memory across continuous experiences), implicit 3D spatial cognition (inferring the world behind pixels), and predictive world modeling (creating internal models that filter and organize information). Current benchmarks largely test only the early stages, offering narrow coverage of spatial cognition and rarely challenging models in ways that require true world modeling. To drive progress in spatial supersensing, we present VSI-SUPER, a two-part benchmark: VSR (long-horizon visual spatial recall) and VSC (continual visual spatial counting). These tasks require arbitrarily long video inputs yet are resistant to brute-force context expansion. We then test data scaling limits by curating VSI-590K and training Cambrian-S, achieving +30% absolute improvement on VSI-Bench without sacrificing general capabilities. Yet performance on VSI-SUPER remains limited, indicating that scale alone is insufficient for spatial supersensing. We propose predictive sensing as a path forward, presenting a proof-of-concept in which a self-supervised next-latent-frame predictor leverages surprise (prediction error) to drive memory and event segmentation. On VSI-SUPER, this approach substantially outperforms leading proprietary baselines, showing that spatial supersensing requires models that not only see but also anticipate, select, and organize experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04670</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2025 18:55:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Too Good to be Bad: On the Failure of LLMs to Role-Play Villains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04962</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.04962.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihao Yi, Qingxuan Jiang, Ruotian Ma, Xingyu Chen, Qu Yang, Mengru Wang, Fanghua Ye, Ying Shen, Zhaopeng Tu, Xiaolong Li, Linus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly tasked with creative generation, including the simulation of fictional characters. However, their ability to portray non-prosocial, antagonistic personas remains largely unexamined. We hypothesize that the safety alignment of modern LLMs creates a fundamental conflict with the task of authentically role-playing morally ambiguous or villainous characters. To investigate this, we introduce the Moral RolePlay benchmark, a new dataset featuring a four-level moral alignment scale and a balanced test set for rigorous evaluation. We task state-of-the-art LLMs with role-playing characters from moral paragons to pure villains. Our large-scale evaluation reveals a consistent, monotonic decline in role-playing fidelity as character morality decreases. We find that models struggle most with traits directly antithetical to safety principles, such as ``Deceitful'' and ``Manipulative'', often substituting nuanced malevolence with superficial aggression. Furthermore, we demonstrate that general chatbot proficiency is a poor predictor of villain role-playing ability, with highly safety-aligned models performing particularly poorly. Our work provides the first systematic evidence of this critical limitation, highlighting a key tension between model safety and creative fidelity. Our benchmark and findings pave the way for developing more nuanced, context-aware alignment methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04962</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 03:50:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motif 2 12.7B technical report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07464</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07464.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junghwan Lim, Sungmin Lee, Dongseok Kim, Taehyun Kim, Eunhwan Park, Jeesoo Lee, Jeongdoo Lee, Junhyeok Lee, Wai Ting Cheung, Dahye Choi, Jaeheui Her, Jaeyeon Huh, Hanbin Jung, Changjin Kang, Beomgyu Kim, Minjae Kim, Taewhan Kim, Youngrok Kim, Hyukjin Kweon, Haesol Lee, Kungyu Lee, Dongpin Oh, Yeongjae Park, Bokki Ryu, Dongjoo Weon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Motif-2-12.7B, a new open-weight foundation model that pushes the efficiency frontier of large language models by combining architectural innovation with system-level optimization. Designed for scalable language understanding and robust instruction generalization under constrained compute budgets, Motif-2-12.7B builds upon Motif-2.6B with the integration of Grouped Differential Attention (GDA), which improves representational efficiency by disentangling signal and noise-control attention pathways. The model is pre-trained on 5.5 trillion tokens spanning diverse linguistic, mathematical, scientific, and programming domains using a curriculum-driven data scheduler that gradually changes the data composition ratio. The training system leverages the MuonClip optimizer alongside custom high-performance kernels, including fused PolyNorm activations and the Parallel Muon algorithm, yielding significant throughput and memory efficiency gains in large-scale distributed environments. Post-training employs a three-stage supervised fine-tuning pipeline that successively enhances general instruction adherence, compositional understanding, and linguistic precision. Motif-2-12.7B demonstrates competitive performance across diverse benchmarks, showing that thoughtful architectural scaling and optimized training design can rival the capabilities of much larger models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07464</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 10:32:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepEyesV2: Toward Agentic Multimodal Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05271</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05271.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jack Hong, Chenxiao Zhao, ChengLin Zhu, Weiheng Lu, Guohai Xu, Xing Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic multimodal models should not only comprehend text and images, but also actively invoke external tools, such as code execution environments and web search, and integrate these operations into reasoning. In this work, we introduce DeepEyesV2 and explore how to build an agentic multimodal model from the perspectives of data construction, training methods, and model evaluation. We observe that direct reinforcement learning alone fails to induce robust tool-use behavior. This phenomenon motivates a two-stage training pipeline: a cold-start stage to establish tool-use patterns, and reinforcement learning stage to further refine tool invocation. We curate a diverse, moderately challenging training dataset, specifically including examples where tool use is beneficial. We further introduce RealX-Bench, a comprehensive benchmark designed to evaluate real-world multimodal reasoning, which inherently requires the integration of multiple capabilities, including perception, search, and reasoning. We evaluate DeepEyesV2 on RealX-Bench and other representative benchmarks, demonstrating its effectiveness across real-world understanding, mathematical reasoning, and search-intensive tasks. Moreover, DeepEyesV2 exhibits task-adaptive tool invocation, tending to use image operations for perception tasks and numerical computations for reasoning tasks. Reinforcement learning further enables complex tool combinations and allows model to selectively invoke tools based on context. We hope our study can provide guidance for community in developing agentic multimodal models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05271</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 14:31:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Spatial Tuning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05491</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05491.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui Yang, Ziyu Zhu, Yanwei Li, Jingjia Huang, Shen Yan, Siyuan Zhou, Zhe Liu, Xiangtai Li, Shuangye Li, Wenqian Wang, Yi Lin, Hengshuang Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Capturing spatial relationships from visual inputs is a cornerstone of human-like general intelligence. Several previous studies have tried to enhance the spatial awareness of Vision-Language Models (VLMs) by adding extra expert encoders, which brings extra overhead and usually harms general capabilities. To enhance the spatial ability in general architectures, we introduce Visual Spatial Tuning (VST), a comprehensive framework to cultivate VLMs with human-like visuospatial abilities, from spatial perception to reasoning. We first attempt to enhance spatial perception in VLMs by constructing a large-scale dataset termed VST-P, which comprises 4.1 million samples spanning 19 skills across single views, multiple images, and videos. Then, we present VST-R, a curated dataset with 135K samples that instruct models to reason in space. In particular, we adopt a progressive training pipeline: supervised fine-tuning to build foundational spatial knowledge, followed by reinforcement learning to further improve spatial reasoning abilities. Without the side-effect to general capabilities, the proposed VST consistently achieves state-of-the-art results on several spatial benchmarks, including 34.8% on MMSI-Bench and 61.2% on VSIBench. It turns out that the Vision-Language-Action models can be significantly enhanced with the proposed spatial tuning paradigm, paving the way for more physically grounded AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05491</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 18:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KLASS: KL-Guided Fast Inference in Masked Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05664</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.05664.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seo Hyun Kim, Sunwoo Hong, Hojung Jung, Youngrok Park, Se-Young Yun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Masked diffusion models have demonstrated competitive results on various tasks including language generation. However, due to its iterative refinement process, the inference is often bottlenecked by slow and static sampling speed. To overcome this problem, we introduce `KL-Adaptive Stability Sampling' (KLASS), a fast yet effective sampling method that exploits token-level KL divergence to identify stable, high-confidence predictions. By unmasking multiple tokens in each iteration without any additional model training, our approach speeds up generation significantly while maintaining sample quality. On reasoning benchmarks, KLASS achieves up to 2.78times wall-clock speedups while improving performance over standard greedy decoding, attaining state-of-the-art results among diffusion-based samplers. We further validate KLASS across diverse domains, including text, image, and molecular generation, showing its effectiveness as a broadly applicable sampler across different models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05664</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 19:05:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tiny Model, Big Logic: Diversity-Driven Optimization Elicits Large-Model   Reasoning Ability in VibeThinker-1.5B</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06221</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06221.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sen Xu, Yi Zhou, Wei Wang, Jixin Min, Zhibin Yin, Yingwei Dai, Shixi Liu, Lianyu Pang, Yirong Chen, Junlin Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 123&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Challenging the prevailing consensus that small models inherently lack robust reasoning, this report introduces VibeThinker-1.5B, a 1.5B-parameter dense model developed via our Spectrum-to-Signal Principle (SSP). This challenges the prevailing approach of scaling model parameters to enhance capabilities, as seen in models like DeepSeek R1 (671B) and Kimi k2 (&gt;1T). The SSP framework first employs a Two-Stage Diversity-Exploring Distillation (SFT) to generate a broad spectrum of solutions, followed by MaxEnt-Guided Policy Optimization (RL) to amplify the correct signal. With a total training cost of only $7,800, VibeThinker-1.5B demonstrates superior reasoning capabilities compared to closed-source models like Magistral Medium and Claude Opus 4, and performs on par with open-source models like GPT OSS-20B Medium. Remarkably, it surpasses the 400x larger DeepSeek R1 on three math benchmarks: AIME24 (80.3 vs. 79.8), AIME25 (74.4 vs. 70.0), and HMMT25 (50.4 vs. 41.7). This is a substantial improvement over its base model (6.7, 4.3, and 0.6, respectively). On LiveCodeBench V6, it scores 51.1, outperforming Magistral Medium's 50.3 and its base model's 0.0. These findings demonstrate that small models can achieve reasoning capabilities comparable to large models, drastically reducing training and inference costs and thereby democratizing advanced AI research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06221</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 04:37:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DRIVE: Data Curation Best Practices for Reinforcement Learning with   Verifiable Reward in Competitive Code Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06307</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06307.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Speed Zhu, Jianwei Cai, Guang Chen, Lulu Wu, Saiyong Yang, Wiggin Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent reasoning-first models (e.g., OpenAI o1, DeepSeek R1) have spurred a resurgence of interest in RLVR. Nevertheless, advances are dominated by mathematics (e.g., AIME), with competitive-programming code generation underexplored and data curation receiving less attention than RL algorithm design. We investigate how to construct RLVR datasets (i.e., RL prompts) and present practical training techniques that yield strong performance on competitive-programming code generation. Our pipeline begins with supervised fine-tuning (SFT) distilled from strong open-source models, augmented with general-purpose and reasoning-intensive data. RL then follows a two-stage process with executable, testcase-driven rewards: first, training on a large, uniformly distributed set of competitive-programming problems using Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO) with 8 rollouts per prompt and a relatively short response-generation window (e.g., 32k during SFT and 24k in this stage) to expand entropy and mitigate repetition and truncation; second, we perform Pre-GRPO: updating on a small, high-quality set of challenging problems with a large rollout budget (64 rollouts per prompt) under a hard-focus curriculum that continuously retains the most difficult instances throughout training. We implement our method on Qwen2.5-32B and evaluate on LeetCode and Codeforces weekly contests to avoid data leakage. The resulting model achieves state-of-the-art performance among models of similar scale and is comparable to leading systems such as DeepSeek v3.1 and Doubao-1.5-Thinking. We also examine scaling trends and observe strong RL scaling on an internal large-scale MoE model. Our study distills concise best practices for data curation, entropy expansion, and curriculum design in RLVR for competitive-programming code generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06307</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 10:11:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Station: An Open-World Environment for AI-Driven Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06309</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.06309.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Stephen Chung, Wenyu Du&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce the STATION, an open-world multi-agent environment that models a miniature scientific ecosystem. Leveraging their extended context windows, agents in the Station can engage in long scientific journeys that include reading papers from peers, formulating hypotheses, submitting code, performing analyses, and publishing results. Importantly, there is no centralized system coordinating their activities - agents are free to choose their own actions and develop their own narratives within the Station. Experiments demonstrate that AI agents in the Station achieve new state-of-the-art performance on a wide range of benchmarks, spanning from mathematics to computational biology to machine learning, notably surpassing AlphaEvolve in circle packing. A rich tapestry of narratives emerges as agents pursue independent research, interact with peers, and build upon a cumulative history. From these emergent narratives, novel methods arise organically, such as a new density-adaptive algorithm for scRNA-seq batch integration. The Station marks a first step towards autonomous scientific discovery driven by emergent behavior in an open-world environment, representing a new paradigm that moves beyond rigid optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06309</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 10:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-to-Move: Training-Free Motion Controlled Video Generation via Dual-Clock Denoising</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08633</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08633.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Assaf Singer, Noam Rotstein, Amir Mann, Ron Kimmel, Or Litany&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion-based video generation can create realistic videos, yet existing image- and text-based conditioning fails to offer precise motion control. Prior methods for motion-conditioned synthesis typically require model-specific fine-tuning, which is computationally expensive and restrictive. We introduce Time-to-Move (TTM), a training-free, plug-and-play framework for motion- and appearance-controlled video generation with image-to-video (I2V) diffusion models. Our key insight is to use crude reference animations obtained through user-friendly manipulations such as cut-and-drag or depth-based reprojection. Motivated by SDEdit's use of coarse layout cues for image editing, we treat the crude animations as coarse motion cues and adapt the mechanism to the video domain. We preserve appearance with image conditioning and introduce dual-clock denoising, a region-dependent strategy that enforces strong alignment in motion-specified regions while allowing flexibility elsewhere, balancing fidelity to user intent with natural dynamics. This lightweight modification of the sampling process incurs no additional training or runtime cost and is compatible with any backbone. Extensive experiments on object and camera motion benchmarks show that TTM matches or exceeds existing training-based baselines in realism and motion control. Beyond this, TTM introduces a unique capability: precise appearance control through pixel-level conditioning, exceeding the limits of text-only prompting. Visit our project page for video examples and code: https://time-to-move.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08633</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 22:47:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond English: Toward Inclusive and Scalable Multilingual Machine Translation with LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07003</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07003.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yingfeng Luo, Ziqiang Xu, Yuxuan Ouyang, Murun Yang, Dingyang Lin, Kaiyan Chang, Tong Zheng, Bei Li, Peinan Feng, Quan Du, Tong Xiao, Jingbo Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models have significantly advanced Multilingual Machine Translation (MMT), yet the broad language coverage, consistent translation quality, and English-centric bias remain open challenges. To address these challenges, we introduce LMT, a suite of Large-scale Multilingual Translation models centered on both Chinese and English, covering 60 languages and 234 translation directions. During development, we identify a previously overlooked phenomenon of directional degeneration, where symmetric multi-way fine-tuning data overemphasize reverse directions (X to En/Zh), leading to excessive many-to-one mappings and degraded translation quality. We propose Strategic Downsampling, a simple yet effective method to mitigate this degeneration. In addition, we design Parallel Multilingual Prompting (PMP), which leverages typologically related auxiliary languages to enhance cross-lingual transfer. Through rigorous data curation and refined adaptation strategies, LMT achieves SOTA performance among models of comparable language coverage, with our 4B model (LMT-60-4B) surpassing the much larger Aya-101-13B and NLLB-54B models by a substantial margin. We release LMT in four sizes (0.6B/1.7B/4B/8B) to catalyze future research and provide strong baselines for inclusive, scalable, and high-quality MMT \href{https://github.com/NiuTrans/LMT{https://github.com/NiuTrans/LMT}}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07003</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 11:54:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wasm: A Pipeline for Constructing Structured Arabic Interleaved   Multimodal Corpora</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07080</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07080.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Khalil Hennara, Ahmad Bastati, Muhammad Hreden, Mohamed Motasim Hamed, Zeina Aldallal, Sara Chrouf, Safwan AlModhayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The performance of large language models (LLMs) and large multimodal models (LMMs) depends heavily on the quality and scale of their pre-training datasets. Recent research shows that large multimodal models trained on natural documents where images and text are interleaved outperform those trained only on image-text pairs across a wide range of benchmarks, leveraging advanced pre- trained models to enforce semantic alignment, image-sequence consistency, and textual coherence. For Arabic, however, the lack of high-quality multimodal datasets that preserve document structure has limited progress. In this paper, we present our pipeline Wasm for processing the Common Crawl dataset to create a new Arabic multimodal dataset that uniquely provides markdown output. Unlike existing Arabic corpora that focus solely on text extraction, our approach preserves the structural integrity of web content while maintaining flexibility for both text-only and multimodal pre-training scenarios. We provide a comprehensive comparative analysis of our data processing pipeline against those used for major existing datasets, highlighting the convergences in filtering strategies and justifying our specific design choices. To support future research, we publicly release a representative dataset dump along with the multimodal processing pipeline for Arabic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07080</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 13:10:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GroupRank: A Groupwise Reranking Paradigm Driven by Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11653</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.11653.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Duolin Sun, Meixiu Long, Dan Yang, Yihan Jiao, Zhehao Tan, Jie Feng, Junjie Wang, Yue Shen, Peng Wei, Jian Wang, Jinjie Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models have shown strong potential as rerankers to enhance the overall performance of RAG systems. However, existing reranking paradigms are constrained by a core theoretical and practical dilemma: Pointwise methods, while simple and highly flexible, evaluate documents independently, making them prone to the Ranking Myopia Trap, overlooking the relative importance between documents. In contrast, Listwise methods can perceive the global ranking context, but suffer from inherent List Rigidity, leading to severe scalability and flexibility issues when handling large candidate sets. To address these challenges, we propose Groupwise, a novel reranking paradigm. In this approach, the query and a group of candidate documents are jointly fed into the model, which performs within-group comparisons to assign individual relevance scores to each document. This design retains the flexibility of Pointwise methods while enabling the comparative capability of Listwise methods. We further adopt GRPO for model training, equipped with a heterogeneous reward function that integrates ranking metrics with a distributional reward aimed at aligning score distributions across groups. To overcome the bottleneck caused by the scarcity of high quality labeled data, we further propose an innovative pipeline for synthesizing high quality retrieval and ranking data. The resulting data can be leveraged not only for training the reranker but also for training the retriever. Extensive experiments validate the effectiveness of our approach. On two reasoning intensive retrieval benchmarks, BRIGHT and R2MED.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11653</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 15:25:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IterResearch: Rethinking Long-Horizon Agents via Markovian State   Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07327</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07327.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guoxin Chen, Zile Qiao, Xuanzhong Chen, Donglei Yu, Haotian Xu, Wayne Xin Zhao, Ruihua Song, Wenbiao Yin, Huifeng Yin, Liwen Zhang, Kuan Li, Minpeng Liao, Yong Jiang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Jingren Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in deep-research agents have shown promise for autonomous knowledge construction through dynamic reasoning over external sources. However, existing approaches rely on a mono-contextual paradigm that accumulates all information in a single, expanding context window, leading to context suffocation and noise contamination that limit their effectiveness on long-horizon tasks. We introduce IterResearch, a novel iterative deep-research paradigm that reformulates long-horizon research as a Markov Decision Process with strategic workspace reconstruction. By maintaining an evolving report as memory and periodically synthesizing insights, our approach preserves consistent reasoning capacity across arbitrary exploration depths. We further develop Efficiency-Aware Policy Optimization (EAPO), a reinforcement learning framework that incentivizes efficient exploration through geometric reward discounting and enables stable distributed training via adaptive downsampling. Extensive experiments demonstrate that IterResearch achieves substantial improvements over existing open-source agents with average +14.5pp across six benchmarks and narrows the gap with frontier proprietary systems. Remarkably, our paradigm exhibits unprecedented interaction scaling, extending to 2048 interactions with dramatic performance gains (from 3.5\% to 42.5\%), and serves as an effective prompting strategy, improving frontier models by up to 19.2pp over ReAct on long-horizon tasks. These findings position IterResearch as a versatile solution for long-horizon reasoning, effective both as a trained agent and as a prompting paradigm for frontier models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07327</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 17:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grounding Computer Use Agents on Human Demonstrations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07332</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.07332.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aarash Feizi, Shravan Nayak, Xiangru Jian, Kevin Qinghong Lin, Kaixin Li, Rabiul Awal, Xing Han Lù, Johan Obando-Ceron, Juan A. Rodriguez, Nicolas Chapados, David Vazquez, Adriana Romero-Soriano, Reihaneh Rabbany, Perouz Taslakian, Christopher Pal, Spandana Gella, Sai Rajeswar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 103&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Building reliable computer-use agents requires grounding: accurately connecting natural language instructions to the correct on-screen elements. While large datasets exist for web and mobile interactions, high-quality resources for desktop environments are limited. To address this gap, we introduce GroundCUA, a large-scale desktop grounding dataset built from expert human demonstrations. It covers 87 applications across 12 categories and includes 56K screenshots, with every on-screen element carefully annotated for a total of over 3.56M human-verified annotations. From these demonstrations, we generate diverse instructions that capture a wide range of real-world tasks, providing high-quality data for model training. Using GroundCUA, we develop the GroundNext family of models that map instructions to their target UI elements. At both 3B and 7B scales, GroundNext achieves state-of-the-art results across five benchmarks using supervised fine-tuning, while requiring less than one-tenth the training data of prior work. Reinforcement learning post-training further improves performance, and when evaluated in an agentic setting on the OSWorld benchmark using o3 as planner, GroundNext attains comparable or superior results to models trained with substantially more data,. These results demonstrate the critical role of high-quality, expert-driven datasets in advancing general-purpose computer-use agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.07332</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 17:35:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI2Code^N: A Visual Language Model for Test-Time Scalable Interactive UI-to-Code Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08195</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08195.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhen Yang, Wenyi Hong, Mingde Xu, Xinyue Fan, Weihan Wang, Jiele Cheng, Xiaotao Gu, Jie Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; User interface (UI) programming is a core yet highly complex part of modern software development. Recent advances in visual language models (VLMs) highlight the potential of automatic UI coding, but current approaches face two key limitations: multimodal coding capabilities remain underdeveloped, and single-turn paradigms make little use of iterative visual feedback. We address these challenges with an interactive UI-to-code paradigm that better reflects real-world workflows and raises the upper bound of achievable performance. Under this paradigm, we present UI2Code^N, a visual language model trained through staged pretraining, fine-tuning, and reinforcement learning to achieve foundational improvements in multimodal coding. The model unifies three key capabilities: UI-to-code generation, UI editing, and UI polishing. We further explore test-time scaling for interactive generation, enabling systematic use of multi-turn feedback. Experiments on UI-to-code and UI polishing benchmarks show that UI2Code^N establishes a new state of the art among open-source models and achieves performance comparable to leading closed-source models such as Claude-4-Sonnet and GPT-5. Our code and models are available at https://github.com/zai-org/UI2Code_N.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08195</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 13:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MADD: Multi-Agent Drug Discovery Orchestra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08217</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08217.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gleb V. Solovev, Alina B. Zhidkovskaya, Anastasia Orlova, Nina Gubina, Anastasia Vepreva, Rodion Golovinskii, Ilya Tonkii, Ivan Dubrovsky, Ivan Gurev, Dmitry Gilemkhanov, Denis Chistiakov, Timur A. Aliev, Ivan Poddiakov, Galina Zubkova, Ekaterina V. Skorb, Vladimir Vinogradov, Alexander Boukhanovsky, Nikolay Nikitin, Andrei Dmitrenko, Anna Kalyuzhnaya, Andrey Savchenko&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Hit identification is a central challenge in early drug discovery, traditionally requiring substantial experimental resources. Recent advances in artificial intelligence, particularly large language models (LLMs), have enabled virtual screening methods that reduce costs and improve efficiency. However, the growing complexity of these tools has limited their accessibility to wet-lab researchers. Multi-agent systems offer a promising solution by combining the interpretability of LLMs with the precision of specialized models and tools. In this work, we present MADD, a multi-agent system that builds and executes customized hit identification pipelines from natural language queries. MADD employs four coordinated agents to handle key subtasks in de novo compound generation and screening. We evaluate MADD across seven drug discovery cases and demonstrate its superior performance compared to existing LLM-based solutions. Using MADD, we pioneer the application of AI-first drug design to five biological targets and release the identified hit molecules. Finally, we introduce a new benchmark of query-molecule pairs and docking scores for over three million compounds to contribute to the agentic future of drug design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08217</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 13:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Multi-Agent Response Refinement in Conversational Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08319</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08319.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Soyeong Jeong, Aparna Elangovan, Emine Yilmaz, Oleg Rokhlenko&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 40&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable success in conversational systems by generating human-like responses. However, they can fall short, especially when required to account for personalization or specific knowledge. In real-life settings, it is impractical to rely on users to detect these errors and request a new response. One way to address this problem is to refine the response before returning it to the user. While existing approaches focus on refining responses within a single LLM, this method struggles to consider diverse aspects needed for effective conversations. In this work, we propose refining responses through a multi-agent framework, where each agent is assigned a specific role for each aspect. We focus on three key aspects crucial to conversational quality: factuality, personalization, and coherence. Each agent is responsible for reviewing and refining one of these aspects, and their feedback is then merged to improve the overall response. To enhance collaboration among them, we introduce a dynamic communication strategy. Instead of following a fixed sequence of agents, our approach adaptively selects and coordinates the most relevant agents based on the specific requirements of each query. We validate our framework on challenging conversational datasets, demonstrating that ours significantly outperforms relevant baselines, particularly in tasks involving knowledge or user's persona, or both.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08319</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 14:48:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniVA: Universal Video Agent towards Open-Source Next-Generation Video Generalist</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08521</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08521.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhengyang Liang, Daoan Zhang, Huichi Zhou, Rui Huang, Bobo Li, Yuechen Zhang, Shengqiong Wu, Xiaohan Wang, Jiebo Luo, Lizi Liao, Hao Fei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While specialized AI models excel at isolated video tasks like generation or understanding, real-world applications demand complex, iterative workflows that combine these capabilities. To bridge this gap, we introduce UniVA, an open-source, omni-capable multi-agent framework for next-generation video generalists that unifies video understanding, segmentation, editing, and generation into cohesive workflows. UniVA employs a Plan-and-Act dual-agent architecture that drives a highly automated and proactive workflow: a planner agent interprets user intentions and decomposes them into structured video-processing steps, while executor agents execute these through modular, MCP-based tool servers (for analysis, generation, editing, tracking, etc.). Through a hierarchical multi-level memory (global knowledge, task context, and user-specific preferences), UniVA sustains long-horizon reasoning, contextual continuity, and inter-agent communication, enabling interactive and self-reflective video creation with full traceability. This design enables iterative and any-conditioned video workflows (e.g., text/image/video-conditioned generation rightarrow multi-round editing rightarrow object segmentation rightarrow compositional synthesis) that were previously cumbersome to achieve with single-purpose models or monolithic video-language models. We also introduce UniVA-Bench, a benchmark suite of multi-step video tasks spanning understanding, editing, segmentation, and generation, to rigorously evaluate such agentic video systems. Both UniVA and UniVA-Bench are fully open-sourced, aiming to catalyze research on interactive, agentic, and general-purpose video intelligence for the next generation of multimodal AI systems. (https://univa.online/)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08521</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 17:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Path Not Taken: RLVR Provably Learns Off the Principals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08567</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08567.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hanqing Zhu, Zhenyu Zhang, Hanxian Huang, DiJia Su, Zechun Liu, Jiawei Zhao, Igor Fedorov, Hamed Pirsiavash, Zhizhou Sha, Jinwon Lee, David Z. Pan, Zhangyang Wang, Yuandong Tian, Kai Sheng Tai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) reliably improves the reasoning performance of large language models, yet it appears to modify only a small fraction of parameters. We revisit this paradox and show that sparsity is a surface artifact of a model-conditioned optimization bias: for a fixed pretrained model, updates consistently localize to preferred parameter regions, highly consistent across runs and largely invariant to datasets and RL recipes. We mechanistically explain these dynamics with a Three-Gate Theory: Gate I (KL Anchor) imposes a KL-constrained update; Gate II (Model Geometry) steers the step off principal directions into low-curvature, spectrum-preserving subspaces; and Gate III (Precision) hides micro-updates in non-preferred regions, making the off-principal bias appear as sparsity. We then validate this theory and, for the first time, provide a parameter-level characterization of RLVR's learning dynamics: RLVR learns off principal directions in weight space, achieving gains via minimal spectral drift, reduced principal-subspace rotation, and off-principal update alignment. In contrast, SFT targets principal weights, distorts the spectrum, and even lags RLVR.   Together, these results provide the first parameter-space account of RLVR's training dynamics, revealing clear regularities in how parameters evolve. Crucially, we show that RL operates in a distinct optimization regime from SFT, so directly adapting SFT-era parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT) methods can be flawed, as evidenced by our case studies on advanced sparse fine-tuning and LoRA variants. We hope this work charts a path toward a white-box understanding of RLVR and the design of geometry-aware, RLVR-native learning algorithms, rather than repurposed SFT-era heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08567</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 18:49:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Think-at-Hard: Selective Latent Iterations to Improve Reasoning Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08577</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08577.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Fu, Yichen You, Zekai Chen, Guohao Dai, Huazhong Yang, Yu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 103&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Improving reasoning capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs), especially under parameter constraints, is crucial for real-world applications. Prior work proposes recurrent transformers, which allocate a fixed number of extra iterations per token to improve generation quality. After the first, standard forward pass, instead of verbalization, last-layer hidden states are fed back as inputs for additional iterations to refine token predictions. Yet we identify a latent overthinking phenomenon: easy token predictions that are already correct after the first pass are sometimes revised into errors in additional iterations. To address this, we propose Think-at-Hard (TaH), a dynamic latent thinking method that iterates deeper only at hard tokens. It employs a lightweight neural decider to trigger latent iterations only at tokens that are likely incorrect after the standard forward pass. During latent iterations, Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) modules shift the LLM objective from general next-token prediction to focused hard-token refinement. We further introduce a duo-causal attention mechanism that extends attention from the token sequence dimension to an additional iteration depth dimension. This enables cross-iteration information flow while maintaining full sequential parallelism. Experiments show that TaH boosts LLM reasoning performance across five challenging benchmarks while maintaining the same parameter count. Compared with baselines that iterate twice for all output tokens, TaH delivers 8.1-11.3% accuracy gains while exempting 94% of tokens from the second iteration. Against strong single-iteration Qwen3 models finetuned with the same data, it also delivers 4.0-5.0% accuracy gains. When allowing less than 3% additional parameters from LoRA and the iteration decider, the gains increase to 8.5-12.6% and 5.3-5.4%, respectively. Our code is available at https://github.com/thu-nics/TaH.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08577</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 18:57:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lumine: An Open Recipe for Building Generalist Agents in 3D Open Worlds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08892</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08892.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weihao Tan, Xiangyang Li, Yunhao Fang, Heyuan Yao, Shi Yan, Hao Luo, Tenglong Ao, Huihui Li, Hongbin Ren, Bairen Yi, Yujia Qin, Bo An, Libin Liu, Guang Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 186&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Lumine, the first open recipe for developing generalist agents capable of completing hours-long complex missions in real time within challenging 3D open-world environments. Lumine adopts a human-like interaction paradigm that unifies perception, reasoning, and action in an end-to-end manner, powered by a vision-language model. It processes raw pixels at 5 Hz to produce precise 30 Hz keyboard-mouse actions and adaptively invokes reasoning only when necessary. Trained in Genshin Impact, Lumine successfully completes the entire five-hour Mondstadt main storyline on par with human-level efficiency and follows natural language instructions to perform a broad spectrum of tasks in both 3D open-world exploration and 2D GUI manipulation across collection, combat, puzzle-solving, and NPC interaction. In addition to its in-domain performance, Lumine demonstrates strong zero-shot cross-game generalization. Without any fine-tuning, it accomplishes 100-minute missions in Wuthering Waves and the full five-hour first chapter of Honkai: Star Rail. These promising results highlight Lumine's effectiveness across distinct worlds and interaction dynamics, marking a concrete step toward generalist agents in open-ended environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08892</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 02:01:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TiDAR: Think in Diffusion, Talk in Autoregression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08923</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.08923.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingyu Liu, Xin Dong, Zhifan Ye, Rishabh Mehta, Yonggan Fu, Vartika Singh, Jan Kautz, Ce Zhang, Pavlo Molchanov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 104&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion language models hold the promise of fast parallel generation, while autoregressive (AR) models typically excel in quality due to their causal structure aligning naturally with language modeling. This raises a fundamental question: can we achieve a synergy with high throughput, higher GPU utilization, and AR level quality? Existing methods fail to effectively balance these two aspects, either prioritizing AR using a weaker model for sequential drafting (speculative decoding), leading to lower drafting efficiency, or using some form of left-to-right (AR-like) decoding logic for diffusion, which still suffers from quality degradation and forfeits its potential parallelizability. We introduce TiDAR, a sequence-level hybrid architecture that drafts tokens (Thinking) in Diffusion and samples final outputs (Talking) AutoRegressively - all within a single forward pass using specially designed structured attention masks. This design exploits the free GPU compute density, achieving a strong balance between drafting and verification capacity. Moreover, TiDAR is designed to be serving-friendly (low overhead) as a standalone model. We extensively evaluate TiDAR against AR models, speculative decoding, and diffusion variants across generative and likelihood tasks at 1.5B and 8B scales. Thanks to the parallel drafting and sampling as well as exact KV cache support, TiDAR outperforms speculative decoding in measured throughput and surpasses diffusion models like Dream and Llada in both efficiency and quality. Most notably, TiDAR is the first architecture to close the quality gap with AR models while delivering 4.71x to 5.91x more tokens per second.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08923</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 02:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PAN: A World Model for General, Interactable, and Long-Horizon World Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09057</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09057.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; PAN Team, Jiannan Xiang, Yi Gu, Zihan Liu, Zeyu Feng, Qiyue Gao, Yiyan Hu, Benhao Huang, Guangyi Liu, Yichi Yang, Kun Zhou, Davit Abrahamyan, Arif Ahmad, Ganesh Bannur, Junrong Chen, Kimi Chen, Mingkai Deng, Ruobing Han, Xinqi Huang, Haoqiang Kang, Zheqi Li, Enze Ma, Hector Ren, Yashowardhan Shinde, Rohan Shingre, Ramsundar Tanikella, Kaiming Tao, Dequan Yang, Xinle Yu, Cong Zeng, Binglin Zhou, Zhengzhong Liu, Zhiting Hu, Eric P. Xing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; A world model enables an intelligent agent to imagine, predict, and reason about how the world evolves in response to its actions, and accordingly to plan and strategize. While recent video generation models produce realistic visual sequences, they typically operate in the prompt-to-full-video manner without causal control, interactivity, or long-horizon consistency required for purposeful reasoning. Existing world modeling efforts, on the other hand, often focus on restricted domains (e.g., physical, game, or 3D-scene dynamics) with limited depth and controllability, and struggle to generalize across diverse environments and interaction formats. In this work, we introduce PAN, a general, interactable, and long-horizon world model that predicts future world states through high-quality video simulation conditioned on history and natural language actions. PAN employs the Generative Latent Prediction (GLP) architecture that combines an autoregressive latent dynamics backbone based on a large language model (LLM), which grounds simulation in extensive text-based knowledge and enables conditioning on language-specified actions, with a video diffusion decoder that reconstructs perceptually detailed and temporally coherent visual observations, to achieve a unification between latent space reasoning (imagination) and realizable world dynamics (reality). Trained on large-scale video-action pairs spanning diverse domains, PAN supports open-domain, action-conditioned simulation with coherent, long-term dynamics. Extensive experiments show that PAN achieves strong performance in action-conditioned world simulation, long-horizon forecasting, and simulative reasoning compared to other video generators and world models, taking a step towards general world models that enable predictive simulation of future world states for reasoning and acting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09057</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 07:20:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DoPE: Denoising Rotary Position Embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09146</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09146.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jing Xiong, Liyang Fan, Hui Shen, Zunhai Su, Min Yang, Lingpeng Kong, Ngai Wong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 91&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Rotary Position Embedding (RoPE) in Transformer models has inherent limits that weaken length extrapolation. We reinterpret the attention map with positional encoding as a noisy feature map, and propose Denoising Positional Encoding (DoPE), a training-free method based on truncated matrix entropy to detect outlier frequency bands in the feature map. Leveraging the noise characteristics of the feature map, we further reparameterize it with a parameter-free Gaussian distribution to achieve robust extrapolation. Our method theoretically reveals the underlying cause of the attention sink phenomenon and its connection to truncated matrix entropy. Experiments on needle-in-a-haystack and many-shot in-context learning tasks demonstrate that DoPE significantly improves retrieval accuracy and reasoning stability across extended contexts (up to 64K tokens). The results show that the denoising strategy for positional embeddings effectively mitigates attention sinks and restores balanced attention patterns, providing a simple yet powerful solution for improving length generalization. Our project page is Project: https://The-physical-picture-of-LLMs.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09146</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 09:32:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMaDA-Parallel: Multimodal Large Diffusion Language Models for Thinking-Aware Editing and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09611</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.09611.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ye Tian, Ling Yang, Jiongfan Yang, Anran Wang, Yu Tian, Jiani Zheng, Haochen Wang, Zhiyang Teng, Zhuochen Wang, Yinjie Wang, Yunhai Tong, Mengdi Wang, Xiangtai Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 67&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While thinking-aware generation aims to improve performance on complex tasks, we identify a critical failure mode where existing sequential, autoregressive approaches can paradoxically degrade performance due to error propagation. To systematically analyze this issue, we propose ParaBench, a new benchmark designed to evaluate both text and image output modalities. Our analysis using ParaBench reveals that this performance degradation is strongly correlated with poor alignment between the generated reasoning and the final image. To resolve this, we propose a parallel multimodal diffusion framework, MMaDA-Parallel, that enables continuous, bidirectional interaction between text and images throughout the entire denoising trajectory. MMaDA-Parallel is trained with supervised finetuning and then further optimized by Parallel Reinforcement Learning (ParaRL), a novel strategy that applies semantic rewards along the trajectory to enforce cross-modal consistency. Experiments validate that our model significantly improves cross-modal alignment and semantic consistency, achieving a 6.9\% improvement in Output Alignment on ParaBench compared to the state-of-the-art model, Bagel, establishing a more robust paradigm for thinking-aware image synthesis. Our code is open-sourced at https://github.com/tyfeld/MMaDA-Parallel&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09611</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 18:58:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Style is Worth One Code: Unlocking Code-to-Style Image Generation with Discrete Style Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10555</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10555.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huijie Liu, Shuhao Cui, Haoxiang Cao, Shuai Ma, Kai Wu, Guoliang Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Innovative visual stylization is a cornerstone of artistic creation, yet generating novel and consistent visual styles remains a significant challenge. Existing generative approaches typically rely on lengthy textual prompts, reference images, or parameter-efficient fine-tuning to guide style-aware image generation, but often struggle with style consistency, limited creativity, and complex style representations. In this paper, we affirm that a style is worth one numerical code by introducing the novel task, code-to-style image generation, which produces images with novel, consistent visual styles conditioned solely on a numerical style code. To date, this field has only been primarily explored by the industry (e.g., Midjourney), with no open-source research from the academic community. To fill this gap, we propose CoTyle, the first open-source method for this task. Specifically, we first train a discrete style codebook from a collection of images to extract style embeddings. These embeddings serve as conditions for a text-to-image diffusion model (T2I-DM) to generate stylistic images. Subsequently, we train an autoregressive style generator on the discrete style embeddings to model their distribution, allowing the synthesis of novel style embeddings. During inference, a numerical style code is mapped to a unique style embedding by the style generator, and this embedding guides the T2I-DM to generate images in the corresponding style. Unlike existing methods, our method offers unparalleled simplicity and diversity, unlocking a vast space of reproducible styles from minimal input. Extensive experiments validate that CoTyle effectively turns a numerical code into a style controller, demonstrating a style is worth one code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10555</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 17:56:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One Small Step in Latent, One Giant Leap for Pixels: Fast Latent Upscale Adapter for Your Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10629</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10629.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aleksandr Razin, Danil Kazantsev, Ilya Makarov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 116&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion models struggle to scale beyond their training resolutions, as direct high-resolution sampling is slow and costly, while post-hoc image super-resolution (ISR) introduces artifacts and additional latency by operating after decoding. We present the Latent Upscaler Adapter (LUA), a lightweight module that performs super-resolution directly on the generator's latent code before the final VAE decoding step. LUA integrates as a drop-in component, requiring no modifications to the base model or additional diffusion stages, and enables high-resolution synthesis through a single feed-forward pass in latent space. A shared Swin-style backbone with scale-specific pixel-shuffle heads supports 2x and 4x factors and remains compatible with image-space SR baselines, achieving comparable perceptual quality with nearly 3x lower decoding and upscaling time (adding only +0.42 s for 1024 px generation from 512 px, compared to 1.87 s for pixel-space SR using the same SwinIR architecture). Furthermore, LUA shows strong generalization across the latent spaces of different VAEs, making it easy to deploy without retraining from scratch for each new decoder. Extensive experiments demonstrate that LUA closely matches the fidelity of native high-resolution generation while offering a practical and efficient path to scalable, high-fidelity image synthesis in modern diffusion pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10629</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:54:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black-Box On-Policy Distillation of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10643</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10643.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianzhu Ye, Li Dong, Zewen Chi, Xun Wu, Shaohan Huang, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Black-box distillation creates student large language models (LLMs) by learning from a proprietary teacher model's text outputs alone, without access to its internal logits or parameters. In this work, we introduce Generative Adversarial Distillation (GAD), which enables on-policy and black-box distillation. GAD frames the student LLM as a generator and trains a discriminator to distinguish its responses from the teacher LLM's, creating a minimax game. The discriminator acts as an on-policy reward model that co-evolves with the student, providing stable, adaptive feedback. Experimental results show that GAD consistently surpasses the commonly used sequence-level knowledge distillation. In particular, Qwen2.5-14B-Instruct (student) trained with GAD becomes comparable to its teacher, GPT-5-Chat, on the LMSYS-Chat automatic evaluation. The results establish GAD as a promising and effective paradigm for black-box LLM distillation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10643</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:58:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depth Anything 3: Recovering the Visual Space from Any Views</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10647</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.10647.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haotong Lin, Sili Chen, Junhao Liew, Donny Y. Chen, Zhenyu Li, Guang Shi, Jiashi Feng, Bingyi Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 89&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Depth Anything 3 (DA3), a model that predicts spatially consistent geometry from an arbitrary number of visual inputs, with or without known camera poses. In pursuit of minimal modeling, DA3 yields two key insights: a single plain transformer (e.g., vanilla DINO encoder) is sufficient as a backbone without architectural specialization, and a singular depth-ray prediction target obviates the need for complex multi-task learning. Through our teacher-student training paradigm, the model achieves a level of detail and generalization on par with Depth Anything 2 (DA2). We establish a new visual geometry benchmark covering camera pose estimation, any-view geometry and visual rendering. On this benchmark, DA3 sets a new state-of-the-art across all tasks, surpassing prior SOTA VGGT by an average of 44.3% in camera pose accuracy and 25.1% in geometric accuracy. Moreover, it outperforms DA2 in monocular depth estimation. All models are trained exclusively on public academic datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10647</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LiteAttention: A Temporal Sparse Attention for Diffusion Transformers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11062</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.11062.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dor Shmilovich, Tony Wu, Aviad Dahan, Yuval Domb&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion Transformers, particularly for video generation, achieve remarkable quality but suffer from quadratic attention complexity, leading to prohibitive latency. Existing acceleration methods face a fundamental trade-off: dynamically estimating sparse attention patterns at each denoising step incurs high computational overhead and estimation errors, while static sparsity patterns remain fixed and often suboptimal throughout denoising. We identify a key structural property of diffusion attention, namely, its sparsity patterns exhibit strong temporal coherence across denoising steps. Tiles deemed non-essential at step t typically remain so at step t+δ. Leveraging this observation, we introduce LiteAttention, a method that exploits temporal coherence to enable evolutionary computation skips across the denoising sequence. By marking non-essential tiles early and propagating skip decisions forward, LiteAttention eliminates redundant attention computations without repeated profiling overheads, combining the adaptivity of dynamic methods with the efficiency of static ones. We implement a highly optimized LiteAttention kernel on top of FlashAttention and demonstrate substantial speedups on production video diffusion models, with no degradation in quality. The code and implementation details will be publicly released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11062</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 08:26:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VIDEOP2R: Video Understanding from Perception to Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11113</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.11113.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Jiang, Yueying Wang, Rui Zhao, Toufiq Parag, Zhimin Chen, Zhenyu Liao, Jayakrishnan Unnikrishnan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 107&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement fine-tuning (RFT), a two-stage framework consisting of supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and reinforcement learning (RL) has shown promising results on improving reasoning ability of large language models (LLMs). Yet extending RFT to large video language models (LVLMs) remains challenging. We propose VideoP2R, a novel process-aware video RFT framework that enhances video reasoning by modeling perception and reasoning as distinct processes. In the SFT stage, we develop a three-step pipeline to generate VideoP2R-CoT-162K, a high-quality, process-aware chain-of-thought (CoT) dataset for perception and reasoning. In the RL stage, we introduce a novel process-aware group relative policy optimization (PA-GRPO) algorithm that supplies separate rewards for perception and reasoning. Extensive experiments show that VideoP2R achieves state-of-the-art (SotA) performance on six out of seven video reasoning and understanding benchmarks. Ablation studies further confirm the effectiveness of our process-aware modeling and PA-GRPO and demonstrate that model's perception output is information-sufficient for downstream reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11113</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 09:42:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GGBench: A Geometric Generative Reasoning Benchmark for Unified Multimodal Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11134</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.11134.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingxuan Wei, Caijun Jia, Xi Bai, Xinglong Xu, Siyuan Li, Linzhuang Sun, Bihui Yu, Conghui He, Lijun Wu, Cheng Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The advent of Unified Multimodal Models (UMMs) signals a paradigm shift in artificial intelligence, moving from passive perception to active, cross-modal generation. Despite their unprecedented ability to synthesize information, a critical gap persists in evaluation: existing benchmarks primarily assess discriminative understanding or unconstrained image generation separately, failing to measure the integrated cognitive process of generative reasoning. To bridge this gap, we propose that geometric construction provides an ideal testbed as it inherently demands a fusion of language comprehension and precise visual generation. We introduce GGBench, a benchmark designed specifically to evaluate geometric generative reasoning. It provides a comprehensive framework for systematically diagnosing a model's ability to not only understand and reason but to actively construct a solution, thereby setting a more rigorous standard for the next generation of intelligent systems. Project website: https://opendatalab-raiser.github.io/GGBench/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11134</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 10:07:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Width Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11238</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.11238.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seed, Baisheng Li, Banggu Wu, Bole Ma, Bowen Xiao, Chaoyi Zhang, Cheng Li, Chengyi Wang, Chenyin Xu, Chi Zhang, Chong Hu, Daoguang Zan, Defa Zhu, Dongyu Xu, Du Li, Faming Wu, Fan Xia, Ge Zhang, Guang Shi, Haobin Chen, Hongyu Zhu, Hongzhi Huang, Huan Zhou, Huanzhang Dou, Jianhui Duan, Jianqiao Lu, Jianyu Jiang, Jiayi Xu, Jiecao Chen, Jin Chen, Jin Ma, Jing Su, Jingji Chen, Jun Wang, Jun Yuan, Juncai Liu, Jundong Zhou, Kai Hua, Kai Shen, Kai Xiang, Kaiyuan Chen, Kang Liu, Ke Shen, Liang Xiang, Lin Yan, Lishu Luo, Mengyao Zhang, Ming Ding, Mofan Zhang, Nianning Liang, Peng Li, Penghao Huang, Pengpeng Mu, Qi Huang, Qianli Ma, Qiyang Min, Qiying Yu, Renming Pang, Ru Zhang, Shen Yan, Shen Yan, Shixiong Zhao, Shuaishuai Cao, Shuang Wu, Siyan Chen, Siyu Li, Siyuan Qiao, Tao Sun, Tian Xin, Tiantian Fan, Ting Huang, Ting-Han Fan, Wei Jia, Wenqiang Zhang, Wenxuan Liu, Xiangzhong Wu, Xiaochen Zuo, Xiaoying Jia, Ximing Yang, Xin Liu, Xin Yu, Xingyan Bin, Xintong Hao, Xiongcai Luo, Xujing Li, Xun Zhou, Yanghua Peng, Yangrui Chen, Yi Lin, Yichong Leng, Yinghao Li, Yingshuan Song, Yiyuan Ma, Yong Shan, Yongan Xiang, Yonghui Wu, Yongtao Zhang, Yongzhen Yao, Yu Bao, Yuehang Yang, Yufeng Yuan, Yunshui Li, Yuqiao Xian, Yutao Zeng, Yuxuan Wang, Zehua Hong, Zehua Wang, Zengzhi Wang, Zeyu Yang, Zhengqiang Yin, Zhenyi Lu, Zhexi Zhang, Zhi Chen, Zhi Zhang, Zhiqi Lin, Zihao Huang, Zilin Xu, Ziyun Wei, Zuo Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Virtual Width Networks (VWN), a framework that delivers the benefits of wider representations without incurring the quadratic cost of increasing the hidden size. VWN decouples representational width from backbone width, expanding the embedding space while keeping backbone compute nearly constant. In our large-scale experiment, an 8-times expansion accelerates optimization by over 2 times for next-token and 3 times for next-2-token prediction. The advantage amplifies over training as both the loss gap grows and the convergence-speedup ratio increases, showing that VWN is not only token-efficient but also increasingly effective with scale. Moreover, we identify an approximately log-linear scaling relation between virtual width and loss reduction, offering an initial empirical basis and motivation for exploring virtual-width scaling as a new dimension of large-model efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11238</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 12:41:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WEAVE: Unleashing and Benchmarking the In-context Interleaved Comprehension and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11434</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.11434.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei Chow, Jiachun Pan, Yongyuan Liang, Mingze Zhou, Xue Song, Liyu Jia, Saining Zhang, Siliang Tang, Juncheng Li, Fengda Zhang, Weijia Wu, Hanwang Zhang, Tat-Seng Chua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 44&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in unified multimodal models (UMMs) have enabled impressive progress in visual comprehension and generation. However, existing datasets and benchmarks focus primarily on single-turn interactions, failing to capture the multi-turn, context-dependent nature of real-world image creation and editing. To address this gap, we present WEAVE, the first suite for in-context interleaved cross-modality comprehension and generation. Our suite consists of two complementary parts. WEAVE-100k is a large-scale dataset of 100K interleaved samples spanning over 370K dialogue turns and 500K images, covering comprehension, editing, and generation tasks that require reasoning over historical context. WEAVEBench is a human-annotated benchmark with 100 tasks based on 480 images, featuring a hybrid VLM judger evaluation framework based on both the reference image and the combination of the original image with editing instructions that assesses models' abilities in multi-turn generation, visual memory, and world-knowledge reasoning across diverse domains. Experiments demonstrate that training on WEAVE-100k enables vision comprehension, image editing, and comprehension-generation collaboration capabilities. Furthermore, it facilitates UMMs to develop emergent visual-memory capabilities, while extensive evaluations on WEAVEBench expose the persistent limitations and challenges of current approaches in multi-turn, context-aware image generation and editing. We believe WEAVE provides a view and foundation for studying in-context interleaved comprehension and generation for multi-modal community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11434</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 16:02:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiroThinker: Pushing the Performance Boundaries of Open-Source Research Agents via Model, Context, and Interactive Scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11793</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.11793.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; MiroMind Team, Song Bai, Lidong Bing, Carson Chen, Guanzheng Chen, Yuntao Chen, Zhe Chen, Ziyi Chen, Jifeng Dai, Xuan Dong, Yue Deng, Yunjie Fu, Junqi Ge, Chenxia Han, Tammy Huang, Zhenhang Huang, Jerry Jiao, Shilei Jiang, Tianyu Jiao, Xiaoqi Jian, Lei Lei, Ruilin Li, Ryan Luo, Tiantong Li, Xiang Lin, Ziyuan Liu, Zhiqi Li, Jie Ni, Qiang Ren, Pax Sun, Shiqian Su, Chenxin Tao, Bin Wang, Hellen Wang, Haonan Wang, James Wang, Jin Wang, Jojo Wang, Letian Wang, Shizun Wang, Weizhi Wang, Zixuan Wang, Jinfan Xu, Sen Xing, Chenyu Yang, Hai Ye, Jiaheng Yu, Yue Yu, Muyan Zhong, Tianchen Zhao, Xizhou Zhu, Yanpeng Zhou, Yifan Zhang, Zhi Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 156&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present MiroThinker v1.0, an open-source research agent designed to advance tool-augmented reasoning and information-seeking capabilities. Unlike previous agents that only scale up model size or context length, MiroThinker explores interaction scaling at the model level, systematically training the model to handle deeper and more frequent agent-environment interactions as a third dimension of performance improvement. Unlike LLM test-time scaling, which operates in isolation and risks degradation with longer reasoning chains, interactive scaling leverages environment feedback and external information acquisition to correct errors and refine trajectories. Through reinforcement learning, the model achieves efficient interaction scaling: with a 256K context window, it can perform up to 600 tool calls per task, enabling sustained multi-turn reasoning and complex real-world research workflows. Across four representative benchmarks-GAIA, HLE, BrowseComp, and BrowseComp-ZH-the 72B variant achieves up to 81.9%, 37.7%, 47.1%, and 55.6% accuracy respectively, surpassing previous open-source agents and approaching commercial counterparts such as GPT-5-high. Our analysis reveals that MiroThinker benefits from interactive scaling consistently: research performance improves predictably as the model engages in deeper and more frequent agent-environment interactions, demonstrating that interaction depth exhibits scaling behaviors analogous to model size and context length. These findings establish interaction scaling as a third critical dimension for building next-generation open research agents, complementing model capacity and context windows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.11793</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 18:52:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uni-MoE-2.0-Omni: Scaling Language-Centric Omnimodal Large Model with Advanced MoE, Training and Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12609</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.12609.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunxin Li, Xinyu Chen, Shenyuan Jiang, Haoyuan Shi, Zhenyu Liu, Xuanyu Zhang, Nanhao Deng, Zhenran Xu, Yicheng Ma, Meishan Zhang, Baotian Hu, Min Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 101&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Uni-MoE 2.0 from the Lychee family. As a fully open-source omnimodal large model (OLM), it substantially advances Lychee's Uni-MoE series in language-centric multimodal understanding, reasoning, and generating. Based on the Qwen2.5-7B dense architecture, we build Uni-MoE-2.0-Omni from scratch through three core contributions: dynamic-capacity Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) design, a progressive training strategy enhanced with an iterative reinforcement strategy, and a carefully curated multimodal data matching technique. It is capable of omnimodal understanding, as well as generating images, text, and speech. Architecturally, our new MoE framework balances computational efficiency and capability for 10 cross-modal inputs using shared, routed, and null experts, while our Omni-Modality 3D RoPE ensures spatio-temporal cross-modality alignment in the self-attention layer. For training, following cross-modal pretraining, we use a progressive supervised fine-tuning strategy that activates modality-specific experts and is enhanced by balanced data composition and an iterative GSPO-DPO method to stabilise RL training and improve reasoning. Data-wise, the base model, trained on approximately 75B tokens of open-source multimodal data, is equipped with special speech and image generation tokens, allowing it to learn these generative tasks by conditioning its outputs on linguistic cues. Extensive evaluation across 85 benchmarks demonstrates that our model achieves SOTA or highly competitive performance against leading OLMs, surpassing Qwen2.5-Omni (trained with 1.2T tokens) on over 50 of 76 benchmarks. Key strengths include video understanding (+7% avg. of 8), omnimodallity understanding (+7% avg. of 4), and audiovisual reasoning (+4%). It also advances long-form speech processing (reducing WER by 4.2%) and leads in low-level image processing and controllable generation across 5 metrics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12609</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 14:10:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolve the Method, Not the Prompts: Evolutionary Synthesis of Jailbreak Attacks on LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12710</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.12710.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunhao Chen, Xin Wang, Juncheng Li, Yixu Wang, Jie Li, Yan Teng, Yingchun Wang, Xingjun Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Automated red teaming frameworks for Large Language Models (LLMs) have become increasingly sophisticated, yet they share a fundamental limitation: their jailbreak logic is confined to selecting, combining, or refining pre-existing attack strategies. This binds their creativity and leaves them unable to autonomously invent entirely new attack mechanisms. To overcome this gap, we introduce EvoSynth, an autonomous framework that shifts the paradigm from attack planning to the evolutionary synthesis of jailbreak methods. Instead of refining prompts, EvoSynth employs a multi-agent system to autonomously engineer, evolve, and execute novel, code-based attack algorithms. Crucially, it features a code-level self-correction loop, allowing it to iteratively rewrite its own attack logic in response to failure. Through extensive experiments, we demonstrate that EvoSynth not only establishes a new state-of-the-art by achieving an 85.5\% Attack Success Rate (ASR) against highly robust models like Claude-Sonnet-4.5, but also generates attacks that are significantly more diverse than those from existing methods. We release our framework to facilitate future research in this new direction of evolutionary synthesis of jailbreak methods. Code is available at: https://github.com/dongdongunique/EvoSynth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12710</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 17:52:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Models Meet Extreme Multi-label Classification: Scaling and Multi-modal Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13189</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13189.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Diego Ortego, Marlon Rodríguez, Mario Almagro, Kunal Dahiya, David Jiménez, Juan C. SanMiguel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 37&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Foundation models have revolutionized artificial intelligence across numerous domains, yet their transformative potential remains largely untapped in Extreme Multi-label Classification (XMC). Queries in XMC are associated with relevant labels from extremely large label spaces, where it is critical to strike a balance between efficiency and performance. Therefore, many recent approaches efficiently pose XMC as a maximum inner product search between embeddings learned from small encoder-only transformer architectures. In this paper, we address two important aspects in XMC: how to effectively harness larger decoder-only models, and how to exploit visual information while maintaining computational efficiency. We demonstrate that both play a critical role in XMC separately and can be combined for improved performance. We show that a few billion-size decoder can deliver substantial improvements while keeping computational overhead manageable. Furthermore, our Vision-enhanced eXtreme Multi-label Learning framework (ViXML) efficiently integrates foundation vision models by pooling a single embedding per image. This limits computational growth while unlocking multi-modal capabilities. Remarkably, ViXML with small encoders outperforms text-only decoder in most cases, showing that an image is worth billions of parameters. Finally, we present an extension of existing text-only datasets to exploit visual metadata and make them available for future benchmarking. Comprehensive experiments across four public text-only datasets and their corresponding image enhanced versions validate our proposals' effectiveness, surpassing previous state-of-the-art by up to +8.21\% in P@1 on the largest dataset. ViXML's code is available at https://github.com/DiegoOrtego/vixml.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13189</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 09:52:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Souper-Model: How Simple Arithmetic Unlocks State-of-the-Art LLM Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13254</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13254.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shalini Maiti, Amar Budhiraja, Bhavul Gauri, Gaurav Chaurasia, Anton Protopopov, Alexis Audran-Reiss, Michael Slater, Despoina Magka, Tatiana Shavrina, Roberta Raileanu, Yoram Bachrach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 131&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable capabilities across diverse domains, but their training remains resource- and time-intensive, requiring massive compute power and careful orchestration of training procedures. Model souping-the practice of averaging weights from multiple models of the same architecture-has emerged as a promising pre- and post-training technique that can enhance performance without expensive retraining. In this paper, we introduce Soup Of Category Experts (SoCE), a principled approach for model souping that utilizes benchmark composition to identify optimal model candidates and applies non-uniform weighted averaging to maximize performance. Contrary to previous uniform-averaging approaches, our method leverages the observation that benchmark categories often exhibit low inter-correlations in model performance. SoCE identifies "expert" models for each weakly-correlated category cluster and combines them using optimized weighted averaging rather than uniform weights. We demonstrate that the proposed method improves performance and robustness across multiple domains, including multilingual capabilities, tool calling, and math and achieves state-of-the-art results on the Berkeley Function Calling Leaderboard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13254</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 11:13:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GigaEvo: An Open Source Optimization Framework Powered By LLMs And Evolution Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17592</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.17592.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Valentin Khrulkov, Andrey Galichin, Denis Bashkirov, Dmitry Vinichenko, Oleg Travkin, Roman Alferov, Andrey Kuznetsov, Ivan Oseledets&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 114&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in LLM-guided evolutionary computation, particularly AlphaEvolve (Novikov et al., 2025; Georgiev et al., 2025), have demonstrated remarkable success in discovering novel mathematical constructions and solving challenging optimization problems. However, the high-level descriptions in published work leave many implementation details unspecified, hindering reproducibility and further research. In this report we present GigaEvo, an extensible open-source framework that enables researchers to study and experiment with hybrid LLM-evolution approaches inspired by AlphaEvolve. Our system provides modular implementations of key components: MAP-Elites quality-diversity algorithms, asynchronous DAG-based evaluation pipelines, LLM-driven mutation operators with insight generation and bidirectional lineage tracking, and flexible multi-island evolutionary strategies. In order to assess reproducibility and validate our implementation we evaluate GigaEvo on challenging problems from the AlphaEvolve paper: Heilbronn triangle placement, circle packing in squares, and high-dimensional kissing numbers. The framework emphasizes modularity, concurrency, and ease of experimentation, enabling rapid prototyping through declarative configuration. We provide detailed descriptions of system architecture, implementation decisions, and experimental methodology to support further research in LLM driven evolutionary methods. The GigaEvo framework and all experimental code are available at https://github.com/AIRI-Institute/gigaevo-core.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.17592</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 14:44:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>P1: Mastering Physics Olympiads with Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13612</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13612.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiacheng Chen, Qianjia Cheng, Fangchen Yu, Haiyuan Wan, Yuchen Zhang, Shenghe Zheng, Junchi Yao, Qingyang Zhang, Haonan He, Yun Luo, Yufeng Zhao, Futing Wang, Li Sheng, Chengxing Xie, Yuxin Zuo, Yizhuo Li, Wenxauan Zeng, Yulun Wu, Rui Huang, Dongzhan Zhou, Kai Chen, Yu Qiao, Lei Bai, Yu Cheng, Ning Ding, Bowen Zhou, Peng Ye, Ganqu Cui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 128&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in large language models (LLMs) has moved the frontier from puzzle-solving to science-grade reasoning-the kind needed to tackle problems whose answers must stand against nature, not merely fit a rubric. Physics is the sharpest test of this shift, which binds symbols to reality in a fundamental way, serving as the cornerstone of most modern technologies. In this work, we manage to advance physics research by developing large language models with exceptional physics reasoning capabilities, especially excel at solving Olympiad-level physics problems. We introduce P1, a family of open-source physics reasoning models trained entirely through reinforcement learning (RL). Among them, P1-235B-A22B is the first open-source model with Gold-medal performance at the latest International Physics Olympiad (IPhO 2025), and wins 12 gold medals out of 13 international/regional physics competitions in 2024/2025. P1-30B-A3B also surpasses almost all other open-source models on IPhO 2025, getting a silver medal. Further equipped with an agentic framework PhysicsMinions, P1-235B-A22B+PhysicsMinions achieves overall No.1 on IPhO 2025, and obtains the highest average score over the 13 physics competitions. Besides physics, P1 models also present great performance on other reasoning tasks like math and coding, showing the great generalibility of P1 series.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13612</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 17:18:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Part-X-MLLM: Part-aware 3D Multimodal Large Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13647</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13647.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chunshi Wang, Junliang Ye, Yunhan Yang, Yang Li, Zizhuo Lin, Jun Zhu, Zhuo Chen, Yawei Luo, Chunchao Guo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 69&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Part-X-MLLM, a native 3D multimodal large language model that unifies diverse 3D tasks by formulating them as programs in a structured, executable grammar. Given an RGB point cloud and a natural language prompt, our model autoregressively generates a single, coherent token sequence encoding part-level bounding boxes, semantic descriptions, and edit commands. This structured output serves as a versatile interface to drive downstream geometry-aware modules for part-based generation and editing. By decoupling the symbolic planning from the geometric synthesis, our approach allows any compatible geometry engine to be controlled through a single, language-native frontend. We pre-train a dual-encoder architecture to disentangle structure from semantics and instruction-tune the model on a large-scale, part-centric dataset. Experiments demonstrate that our model excels at producing high-quality, structured plans, enabling state-of-the-art performance in grounded Q\&amp;A, compositional generation, and localized editing through one unified interface. Project page: https://chunshi.wang/Part-X-MLLM/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13647</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 17:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhysX-Anything: Simulation-Ready Physical 3D Assets from Single Image</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13648</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13648.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziang Cao, Fangzhou Hong, Zhaoxi Chen, Liang Pan, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; 3D modeling is shifting from static visual representations toward physical, articulated assets that can be directly used in simulation and interaction. However, most existing 3D generation methods overlook key physical and articulation properties, thereby limiting their utility in embodied AI. To bridge this gap, we introduce PhysX-Anything, the first simulation-ready physical 3D generative framework that, given a single in-the-wild image, produces high-quality sim-ready 3D assets with explicit geometry, articulation, and physical attributes. Specifically, we propose the first VLM-based physical 3D generative model, along with a new 3D representation that efficiently tokenizes geometry. It reduces the number of tokens by 193x, enabling explicit geometry learning within standard VLM token budgets without introducing any special tokens during fine-tuning and significantly improving generative quality. In addition, to overcome the limited diversity of existing physical 3D datasets, we construct a new dataset, PhysX-Mobility, which expands the object categories in prior physical 3D datasets by over 2x and includes more than 2K common real-world objects with rich physical annotations. Extensive experiments on PhysX-Mobility and in-the-wild images demonstrate that PhysX-Anything delivers strong generative performance and robust generalization. Furthermore, simulation-based experiments in a MuJoCo-style environment validate that our sim-ready assets can be directly used for contact-rich robotic policy learning. We believe PhysX-Anything can substantially empower a broad range of downstream applications, especially in embodied AI and physics-based simulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13648</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 17:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TiViBench: Benchmarking Think-in-Video Reasoning for Video Generative Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13704</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13704.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Harold Haodong Chen, Disen Lan, Wen-Jie Shu, Qingyang Liu, Zihan Wang, Sirui Chen, Wenkai Cheng, Kanghao Chen, Hongfei Zhang, Zixin Zhang, Rongjin Guo, Yu Cheng, Ying-Cong Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 42&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid evolution of video generative models has shifted their focus from producing visually plausible outputs to tackling tasks requiring physical plausibility and logical consistency. However, despite recent breakthroughs such as Veo 3's chain-of-frames reasoning, it remains unclear whether these models can exhibit reasoning capabilities similar to large language models (LLMs). Existing benchmarks predominantly evaluate visual fidelity and temporal coherence, failing to capture higher-order reasoning abilities. To bridge this gap, we propose TiViBench, a hierarchical benchmark specifically designed to evaluate the reasoning capabilities of image-to-video (I2V) generation models. TiViBench systematically assesses reasoning across four dimensions: i) Structural Reasoning &amp; Search, ii) Spatial &amp; Visual Pattern Reasoning, iii) Symbolic &amp; Logical Reasoning, and iv) Action Planning &amp; Task Execution, spanning 24 diverse task scenarios across 3 difficulty levels. Through extensive evaluations, we show that commercial models (e.g., Sora 2, Veo 3.1) demonstrate stronger reasoning potential, while open-source models reveal untapped potential that remains hindered by limited training scale and data diversity. To further unlock this potential, we introduce VideoTPO, a simple yet effective test-time strategy inspired by preference optimization. By performing LLM self-analysis on generated candidates to identify strengths and weaknesses, VideoTPO significantly enhances reasoning performance without requiring additional training, data, or reward models. Together, TiViBench and VideoTPO pave the way for evaluating and advancing reasoning in video generation models, setting a foundation for future research in this emerging field.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13704</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 18:52:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scaling Spatial Intelligence with Multimodal Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13719</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13719.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongang Cai, Ruisi Wang, Chenyang Gu, Fanyi Pu, Junxiang Xu, Yubo Wang, Wanqi Yin, Zhitao Yang, Chen Wei, Qingping Sun, Tongxi Zhou, Jiaqi Li, Hui En Pang, Oscar Qian, Yukun Wei, Zhiqian Lin, Xuanke Shi, Kewang Deng, Xiaoyang Han, Zukai Chen, Xiangyu Fan, Hanming Deng, Lewei Lu, Liang Pan, Bo Li, Ziwei Liu, Quan Wang, Dahua Lin, Lei Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite remarkable progress, multimodal foundation models still exhibit surprising deficiencies in spatial intelligence. In this work, we explore scaling up multimodal foundation models to cultivate spatial intelligence within the SenseNova-SI family, built upon established multimodal foundations including visual understanding models (i.e., Qwen3-VL and InternVL3) and unified understanding and generation models (i.e., Bagel). We take a principled approach to constructing high-performing and robust spatial intelligence by systematically curating SenseNova-SI-8M: eight million diverse data samples under a rigorous taxonomy of spatial capabilities. SenseNova-SI demonstrates unprecedented performance across a broad range of spatial intelligence benchmarks: 68.7% on VSI-Bench, 43.3% on MMSI, 85.6% on MindCube, 54.6% on ViewSpatial, and 50.1% on SITE, while maintaining strong general multimodal understanding (e.g., 84.9% on MMBench-En). More importantly, we analyze the impact of data scaling, discuss early signs of emergent generalization capabilities enabled by diverse data training, analyze the risk of overfitting and language shortcuts, present a preliminary study on spatial chain-of-thought reasoning, and validate the potential downstream application. SenseNova-SI is an ongoing project, and this report will be updated continuously. All newly trained multimodal foundation models are publicly released to facilitate further research in this direction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13719</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 18:59:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Back to Basics: Let Denoising Generative Models Denoise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13720</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13720.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianhong Li, Kaiming He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 59&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Today's denoising diffusion models do not "denoise" in the classical sense, i.e., they do not directly predict clean images. Rather, the neural networks predict noise or a noised quantity. In this paper, we suggest that predicting clean data and predicting noised quantities are fundamentally different. According to the manifold assumption, natural data should lie on a low-dimensional manifold, whereas noised quantities do not. With this assumption, we advocate for models that directly predict clean data, which allows apparently under-capacity networks to operate effectively in very high-dimensional spaces. We show that simple, large-patch Transformers on pixels can be strong generative models: using no tokenizer, no pre-training, and no extra loss. Our approach is conceptually nothing more than "Just image Transformers", or JiT, as we call it. We report competitive results using JiT with large patch sizes of 16 and 32 on ImageNet at resolutions of 256 and 512, where predicting high-dimensional noised quantities can fail catastrophically. With our networks mapping back to the basics of the manifold, our research goes back to basics and pursues a self-contained paradigm for Transformer-based diffusion on raw natural data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13720</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 18:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can World Simulators Reason? Gen-ViRe: A Generative Visual Reasoning Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13853</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.13853.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xinxin Liu, Zhaopan Xu, Kai Wang, Yong Jae Lee, Yuzhang Shang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Chain-of-Thought (CoT) prompting enables sophisticated symbolic reasoning in LLMs, it remains confined to discrete text and cannot simulate the continuous, physics-governed dynamics of the real world. Recent video generation models have emerged as potential world simulators through Chain-of-Frames (CoF) reasoning -- materializing thought as frame-by-frame visual sequences, with each frame representing a physically-grounded reasoning step. Despite compelling demonstrations, a challenge persists: existing benchmarks, focusing on fidelity or alignment, do not assess CoF reasoning and thus cannot measure core cognitive abilities in multi-step planning, algorithmic logic, or abstract pattern extrapolation. This evaluation void prevents systematic understanding of model capabilities and principled guidance for improvement. We introduce Gen-ViRe (Generative Visual Reasoning Benchmark), a framework grounded in cognitive science and real-world AI applications, which decomposes CoF reasoning into six cognitive dimensions -- from perceptual logic to abstract planning -- and 24 subtasks. Through multi-source data curation, minimal prompting protocols, and hybrid VLM-assisted evaluation with detailed criteria, Gen-ViRe delivers the first quantitative assessment of video models as reasoners. Our experiments on SOTA systems reveal substantial discrepancies between impressive visual quality and actual reasoning depth, establishing baselines and diagnostic tools to advance genuine world simulators.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13853</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 19:11:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AraLingBench A Human-Annotated Benchmark for Evaluating Arabic Linguistic Capabilities of Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14295</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.14295.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohammad Zbib, Hasan Abed Al Kader Hammoud, Sina Mukalled, Nadine Rizk, Fatima Karnib, Issam Lakkis, Ammar Mohanna, Bernard Ghanem&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 69&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present AraLingBench: a fully human annotated benchmark for evaluating the Arabic linguistic competence of large language models (LLMs). The benchmark spans five core categories: grammar, morphology, spelling, reading comprehension, and syntax, through 150 expert-designed multiple choice questions that directly assess structural language understanding. Evaluating 35 Arabic and bilingual LLMs reveals that current models demonstrate strong surface level proficiency but struggle with deeper grammatical and syntactic reasoning. AraLingBench highlights a persistent gap between high scores on knowledge-based benchmarks and true linguistic mastery, showing that many models succeed through memorization or pattern recognition rather than authentic comprehension. By isolating and measuring fundamental linguistic skills, AraLingBench provides a diagnostic framework for developing Arabic LLMs. The full evaluation code is publicly available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14295</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 09:47:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kandinsky 5.0: A Family of Foundation Models for Image and Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14993</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.14993.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vladimir Arkhipkin, Vladimir Korviakov, Nikolai Gerasimenko, Denis Parkhomenko, Viacheslav Vasilev, Alexey Letunovskiy, Maria Kovaleva, Nikolai Vaulin, Ivan Kirillov, Lev Novitskiy, Denis Koposov, Nikita Kiselev, Alexander Varlamov, Dmitrii Mikhailov, Vladimir Polovnikov, Andrey Shutkin, Ilya Vasiliev, Julia Agafonova, Anastasiia Kargapoltseva, Anna Dmitrienko, Anastasia Maltseva, Anna Averchenkova, Olga Kim, Tatiana Nikulina, Denis Dimitrov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 218&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This report introduces Kandinsky 5.0, a family of state-of-the-art foundation models for high-resolution image and 10-second video synthesis. The framework comprises three core line-up of models: Kandinsky 5.0 Image Lite - a line-up of 6B parameter image generation models, Kandinsky 5.0 Video Lite - a fast and lightweight 2B parameter text-to-video and image-to-video models, and Kandinsky 5.0 Video Pro - 19B parameter models that achieves superior video generation quality. We provide a comprehensive review of the data curation lifecycle - including collection, processing, filtering and clustering - for the multi-stage training pipeline that involves extensive pre-training and incorporates quality-enhancement techniques such as self-supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and reinforcement learning (RL)-based post-training. We also present novel architectural, training, and inference optimizations that enable Kandinsky 5.0 to achieve high generation speeds and state-of-the-art performance across various tasks, as demonstrated by human evaluation. As a large-scale, publicly available generative framework, Kandinsky 5.0 leverages the full potential of its pre-training and subsequent stages to be adapted for a wide range of generative applications. We hope that this report, together with the release of our open-source code and training checkpoints, will substantially advance the development and accessibility of high-quality generative models for the research community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14993</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:23:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning via Video: The First Evaluation of Video Models' Reasoning Abilities through Maze-Solving Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15065</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15065.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng Yang, Haiyuan Wan, Yiran Peng, Xin Cheng, Zhaoyang Yu, Jiayi Zhang, Junchi Yu, Xinlei Yu, Xiawu Zheng, Dongzhan Zhou, Chenglin Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video Models have achieved remarkable success in high-fidelity video generation with coherent motion dynamics. Analogous to the development from text generation to text-based reasoning in language modeling, the development of video models motivates us to ask: Can video models reason via video generation? Compared with the discrete text corpus, video grounds reasoning in explicit spatial layouts and temporal continuity, which serves as an ideal substrate for spatial reasoning. In this work, we explore the reasoning via video paradigm and introduce VR-Bench -- a comprehensive benchmark designed to systematically evaluate video models' reasoning capabilities. Grounded in maze-solving tasks that inherently require spatial planning and multi-step reasoning, VR-Bench contains 7,920 procedurally generated videos across five maze types and diverse visual styles. Our empirical analysis demonstrates that SFT can efficiently elicit the reasoning ability of video model. Video models exhibit stronger spatial perception during reasoning, outperforming leading VLMs and generalizing well across diverse scenarios, tasks, and levels of complexity. We further discover a test-time scaling effect, where diverse sampling during inference improves reasoning reliability by 10--20%. These findings highlight the unique potential and scalability of reasoning via video for spatial reasoning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15065</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 03:18:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling Intrinsic Dimension of Texts: from Academic Abstract to Creative Story</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15210</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15210.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vladislav Pedashenko, Laida Kushnareva, Yana Khassan Nibal, Eduard Tulchinskii, Kristian Kuznetsov, Vladislav Zharchinskii, Yury Maximov, Irina Piontkovskaya&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 86&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Intrinsic dimension (ID) is an important tool in modern LLM analysis, informing studies of training dynamics, scaling behavior, and dataset structure, yet its textual determinants remain underexplored. We provide the first comprehensive study grounding ID in interpretable text properties through cross-encoder analysis, linguistic features, and sparse autoencoders (SAEs). In this work, we establish three key findings. First, ID is complementary to entropy-based metrics: after controlling for length, the two are uncorrelated, with ID capturing geometric complexity orthogonal to prediction quality. Second, ID exhibits robust genre stratification: scientific prose shows low ID (~8), encyclopedic content medium ID (~9), and creative/opinion writing high ID (~10.5) across all models tested. This reveals that contemporary LLMs find scientific text "representationally simple" while fiction requires additional degrees of freedom. Third, using SAEs, we identify causal features: scientific signals (formal tone, report templates, statistics) reduce ID; humanized signals (personalization, emotion, narrative) increase it. Steering experiments confirm these effects are causal. Thus, for contemporary models, scientific writing appears comparatively "easy", whereas fiction, opinion, and affect add representational degrees of freedom. Our multi-faceted analysis provides practical guidance for the proper use of ID and the sound interpretation of ID-based results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15210</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 08:00:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Evaluation of Russian-language Architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15552</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15552.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Artem Chervyakov, Ulyana Isaeva, Anton Emelyanov, Artem Safin, Maria Tikhonova, Alexander Kharitonov, Yulia Lyakh, Petr Surovtsev, Denis Shevelev, Vildan Saburov, Vasily Konovalov, Elisei Rykov, Ivan Sviridov, Amina Miftakhova, Ilseyar Alimova, Alexander Panchenko, Alexander Kapitanov, Alena Fenogenova&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) are currently at the center of research attention, showing rapid progress in scale and capabilities, yet their intelligence, limitations, and risks remain insufficiently understood. To address these issues, particularly in the context of the Russian language, where no multimodal benchmarks currently exist, we introduce Mera Multi, an open multimodal evaluation framework for Russian-spoken architectures. The benchmark is instruction-based and encompasses default text, image, audio, and video modalities, comprising 18 newly constructed evaluation tasks for both general-purpose models and modality-specific architectures (image-to-text, video-to-text, and audio-to-text). Our contributions include: (i) a universal taxonomy of multimodal abilities; (ii) 18 datasets created entirely from scratch with attention to Russian cultural and linguistic specificity, unified prompts, and metrics; (iii) baseline results for both closed-source and open-source models; (iv) a methodology for preventing benchmark leakage, including watermarking and licenses for private sets. While our current focus is on Russian, the proposed benchmark provides a replicable methodology for constructing multimodal benchmarks in typologically diverse languages, particularly within the Slavic language family.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15552</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:43:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computer-Use Agents as Judges for Generative User Interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15567</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15567.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kevin Qinghong Lin, Siyuan Hu, Linjie Li, Zhengyuan Yang, Lijuan Wang, Philip Torr, Mike Zheng Shou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 50&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Computer-Use Agents (CUA) are becoming increasingly capable of autonomously operating digital environments through Graphical User Interfaces (GUI). Yet, most GUI remain designed primarily for humans--prioritizing aesthetics and usability--forcing agents to adopt human-oriented behaviors that are unnecessary for efficient task execution. At the same time, rapid advances in coding-oriented language models (Coder) have transformed automatic GUI design. This raises a fundamental question: Can CUA as judges to assist Coder for automatic GUI design? To investigate, we introduce AUI-Gym, a benchmark for Automatic GUI development spanning 52 applications across diverse domains. Using language models, we synthesize 1560 tasks that simulate real-world scenarios. To ensure task reliability, we further develop a verifier that programmatically checks whether each task is executable within its environment. Building on this, we propose a Coder-CUA in Collaboration framework: the Coder acts as Designer, generating and revising websites, while the CUA serves as Judge, evaluating functionality and refining designs. Success is measured not by visual appearance, but by task solvability and CUA navigation success rate. To turn CUA feedback into usable guidance, we design a CUA Dashboard that compresses multi-step navigation histories into concise visual summaries, offering interpretable guidance for iterative redesign. By positioning agents as both designers and judges, our framework shifts interface design toward agent-native efficiency and reliability. Our work takes a step toward shifting agents from passive use toward active participation in digital environments. Our code and dataset are available at https://github.com/showlab/AUI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15567</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 16:00:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Does It Take to Be a Good AI Research Agent? Studying the Role of Ideation Diversity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15593</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15593.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexis Audran-Reiss, Jordi Armengol Estapé, Karen Hambardzumyan, Amar Budhiraja, Martin Josifoski, Edan Toledo, Rishi Hazra, Despoina Magka, Michael Shvartsman, Parth Pathak, Justine T Kao, Lucia Cipolina-Kun, Bhavul Gauri, Jean-Christophe Gagnon-Audet, Emanuel Tewolde, Jenny Zhang, Taco Cohen, Yossi Adi, Tatiana Shavrina, Yoram Bachrach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AI research agents offer the promise to accelerate scientific progress by automating the design, implementation, and training of machine learning models. However, the field is still in its infancy, and the key factors driving the success or failure of agent trajectories are not fully understood. We examine the role that ideation diversity plays in agent performance. First, we analyse agent trajectories on MLE-bench, a well-known benchmark to evaluate AI research agents, across different models and agent scaffolds. Our analysis reveals that different models and agent scaffolds yield varying degrees of ideation diversity, and that higher-performing agents tend to have increased ideation diversity. Further, we run a controlled experiment where we modify the degree of ideation diversity, demonstrating that higher ideation diversity results in stronger performance. Finally, we strengthen our results by examining additional evaluation metrics beyond the standard medal-based scoring of MLE-bench, showing that our findings still hold across other agent performance metrics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15593</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 16:32:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VisPlay: Self-Evolving Vision-Language Models from Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15661</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15661.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yicheng He, Chengsong Huang, Zongxia Li, Jiaxin Huang, Yonghui Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) provides a principled framework for improving Vision-Language Models (VLMs) on complex reasoning tasks. However, existing RL approaches often rely on human-annotated labels or task-specific heuristics to define verifiable rewards, both of which are costly and difficult to scale. We introduce VisPlay, a self-evolving RL framework that enables VLMs to autonomously improve their reasoning abilities using large amounts of unlabeled image data. Starting from a single base VLM, VisPlay assigns the model into two interacting roles: an Image-Conditioned Questioner that formulates challenging yet answerable visual questions, and a Multimodal Reasoner that generates silver responses. These roles are jointly trained with Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), which incorporates diversity and difficulty rewards to balance the complexity of generated questions with the quality of the silver answers. VisPlay scales efficiently across two model families. When trained on Qwen2.5-VL and MiMo-VL, VisPlay achieves consistent improvements in visual reasoning, compositional generalization, and hallucination reduction across eight benchmarks, including MM-Vet and MMMU, demonstrating a scalable path toward self-evolving multimodal intelligence. The project page is available at https://bruno686.github.io/VisPlay/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15661</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 17:55:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Frame Is the Place to Go for Video Content Customization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15700</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15700.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingxi Chen, Zongxia Li, Zhichao Liu, Guangyao Shi, Xiyang Wu, Fuxiao Liu, Cornelia Fermuller, Brandon Y. Feng, Yiannis Aloimonos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; What role does the first frame play in video generation models? Traditionally, it's viewed as the spatial-temporal starting point of a video, merely a seed for subsequent animation. In this work, we reveal a fundamentally different perspective: video models implicitly treat the first frame as a conceptual memory buffer that stores visual entities for later reuse during generation. Leveraging this insight, we show that it's possible to achieve robust and generalized video content customization in diverse scenarios, using only 20-50 training examples without architectural changes or large-scale finetuning. This unveils a powerful, overlooked capability of video generation models for reference-based video customization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15700</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 18:56:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GeoVista: Web-Augmented Agentic Visual Reasoning for Geolocalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15705</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15705.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yikun Wang, Zuyan Liu, Ziyi Wang, Pengfei Liu, Han Hu, Yongming Rao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 88&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current research on agentic visual reasoning enables deep multimodal understanding but primarily focuses on image manipulation tools, leaving a gap toward more general-purpose agentic models. In this work, we revisit the geolocalization task, which requires not only nuanced visual grounding but also web search to confirm or refine hypotheses during reasoning. Since existing geolocalization benchmarks fail to meet the need for high-resolution imagery and the localization challenge for deep agentic reasoning, we curate GeoBench, a benchmark that includes photos and panoramas from around the world, along with a subset of satellite images of different cities to rigorously evaluate the geolocalization ability of agentic models. We also propose GeoVista, an agentic model that seamlessly integrates tool invocation within the reasoning loop, including an image-zoom-in tool to magnify regions of interest and a web-search tool to retrieve related web information. We develop a complete training pipeline for it, including a cold-start supervised fine-tuning (SFT) stage to learn reasoning patterns and tool-use priors, followed by a reinforcement learning (RL) stage to further enhance reasoning ability. We adopt a hierarchical reward to leverage multi-level geographical information and improve overall geolocalization performance. Experimental results show that GeoVista surpasses other open-source agentic models on the geolocalization task greatly and achieves performance comparable to closed-source models such as Gemini-2.5-flash and GPT-5 on most metrics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15705</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 18:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Step-Audio-R1 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15848</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.15848.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fei Tian, Xiangyu Tony Zhang, Yuxin Zhang, Haoyang Zhang, Yuxin Li, Daijiao Liu, Yayue Deng, Donghang Wu, Jun Chen, Liang Zhao, Chengyuan Yao, Hexin Liu, Eng Siong Chng, Xuerui Yang, Xiangyu Zhang, Daxin Jiang, Gang Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in reasoning models have demonstrated remarkable success in text and vision domains through extended chain-of-thought deliberation. However, a perplexing phenomenon persists in audio language models: they consistently perform better with minimal or no reasoning, raising a fundamental question - can audio intelligence truly benefit from deliberate thinking? We introduce Step-Audio-R1, the first audio reasoning model that successfully unlocks reasoning capabilities in the audio domain. Through our proposed Modality-Grounded Reasoning Distillation (MGRD) framework, Step-Audio-R1 learns to generate audio-relevant reasoning chains that genuinely ground themselves in acoustic features rather than hallucinating disconnected deliberations. Our model exhibits strong audio reasoning capabilities, surpassing Gemini 2.5 Pro and achieving performance comparable to the state-of-the-art Gemini 3 Pro across comprehensive audio understanding and reasoning benchmarks spanning speech, environmental sounds, and music. These results demonstrate that reasoning is a transferable capability across modalities when appropriately anchored, transforming extended deliberation from a liability into a powerful asset for audio intelligence. By establishing the first successful audio reasoning model, Step-Audio-R1 opens new pathways toward building truly multimodal reasoning systems that think deeply across all sensory modalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.15848</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 20:12:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent0: Unleashing Self-Evolving Agents from Zero Data via Tool-Integrated Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16043</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.16043.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peng Xia, Kaide Zeng, Jiaqi Liu, Can Qin, Fang Wu, Yiyang Zhou, Caiming Xiong, Huaxiu Yao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 97&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Model (LLM) Agents, often trained with Reinforcement Learning (RL), are constrained by a dependency on human-curated data, limiting scalability and tethering AI to human knowledge. Existing self-evolution frameworks offer an alternative but are typically restricted by the model's inherent capabilities and single-round interactions, hindering the development of complex curricula involving tool use or dynamic reasoning. We introduce Agent0, a fully autonomous framework that evolves high-performing agents without external data through multi-step co-evolution and seamless tool integration. Agent0 establishes a symbiotic competition between two agents initialized from the same base LLM: a curriculum agent that proposes increasingly challenging frontier tasks, and an executor agent that learns to solve them. We integrate external tools to enhance the executor's problem-solving capacity; this improvement, in turn, pressures the curriculum agent to construct more complex, tool-aware tasks. Through this iterative process, Agent0 establishes a self-reinforcing cycle that continuously produces high-quality curricula. Empirically, Agent0 substantially boosts reasoning capabilities, improving the Qwen3-8B-Base model by 18% on mathematical reasoning and 24% on general reasoning benchmarks. Code is available at https://github.com/aiming-lab/Agent0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16043</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 05:01:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenMMReasoner: Pushing the Frontiers for Multimodal Reasoning with an Open and General Recipe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16334</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.16334.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaichen Zhang, Keming Wu, Zuhao Yang, Kairui Hu, Bin Wang, Ziwei Liu, Xingxuan Li, Lidong Bing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 86&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in large reasoning models have fueled growing interest in extending such capabilities to multimodal domains. However, despite notable progress in visual reasoning, the lack of transparent and reproducible data curation and training strategies remains a major barrier to scalable research. In this work, we introduce OpenMMReasoner, a fully transparent two-stage recipe for multimodal reasoning spanning supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and reinforcement learning (RL). In the SFT stage, we construct an 874K-sample cold-start dataset with rigorous step-by-step validation, providing a strong foundation for reasoning capabilities. The subsequent RL stage leverages a 74K-sample dataset across diverse domains to further sharpen and stabilize these abilities, resulting in a more robust and efficient learning process. Extensive evaluations demonstrate that our training recipe not only surpasses strong baselines but also highlights the critical role of data quality and training design in shaping multimodal reasoning performance. Notably, our method achieves a 11.6% improvement over the Qwen2.5-VL-7B-Instruct baseline across nine multimodal reasoning benchmarks, establishing a solid empirical foundation for future large-scale multimodal reasoning research. We open-sourced all our codes, pipeline, and data at https://github.com/EvolvingLMMs-Lab/OpenMMReasoner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16334</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 13:11:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAM 3D: 3Dfy Anything in Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16624</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.16624.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; SAM 3D Team, Xingyu Chen, Fu-Jen Chu, Pierre Gleize, Kevin J Liang, Alexander Sax, Hao Tang, Weiyao Wang, Michelle Guo, Thibaut Hardin, Xiang Li, Aohan Lin, Jiawei Liu, Ziqi Ma, Anushka Sagar, Bowen Song, Xiaodong Wang, Jianing Yang, Bowen Zhang, Piotr Dollár, Georgia Gkioxari, Matt Feiszli, Jitendra Malik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present SAM 3D, a generative model for visually grounded 3D object reconstruction, predicting geometry, texture, and layout from a single image. SAM 3D excels in natural images, where occlusion and scene clutter are common and visual recognition cues from context play a larger role. We achieve this with a human- and model-in-the-loop pipeline for annotating object shape, texture, and pose, providing visually grounded 3D reconstruction data at unprecedented scale. We learn from this data in a modern, multi-stage training framework that combines synthetic pretraining with real-world alignment, breaking the 3D "data barrier". We obtain significant gains over recent work, with at least a 5:1 win rate in human preference tests on real-world objects and scenes. We will release our code and model weights, an online demo, and a new challenging benchmark for in-the-wild 3D object reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16624</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 18:31:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V-ReasonBench: Toward Unified Reasoning Benchmark Suite for Video Generation Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16668</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.16668.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Luo, Xuanlei Zhao, Baijiong Lin, Lingting Zhu, Liyao Tang, Yuqi Liu, Ying-Cong Chen, Shengju Qian, Xin Wang, Yang You&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 52&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent progress in generative video models, such as Veo-3, has shown surprising zero-shot reasoning abilities, creating a growing need for systematic and reliable evaluation. We introduce V-ReasonBench, a benchmark designed to assess video reasoning across four key dimensions: structured problem-solving, spatial cognition, pattern-based inference, and physical dynamics. The benchmark is built from both synthetic and real-world image sequences and provides a diverse set of answer-verifiable tasks that are reproducible, scalable, and unambiguous. Evaluations of six state-of-the-art video models reveal clear dimension-wise differences, with strong variation in structured, spatial, pattern-based, and physical reasoning. We further compare video models with strong image models, analyze common hallucination behaviors, and study how video duration affects Chain-of-Frames reasoning. Overall, V-ReasonBench offers a unified and reproducible framework for measuring video reasoning and aims to support the development of models with more reliable, human-aligned reasoning skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16668</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 18:59:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video-as-Answer: Predict and Generate Next Video Event with Joint-GRPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16669</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.16669.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junhao Cheng, Liang Hou, Xin Tao, Jing Liao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While language models have become impactful in many real-world applications, video generation remains largely confined to entertainment. Motivated by video's inherent capacity to demonstrate physical-world information that is difficult to convey through language alone (e.g., imagine teaching someone to tie a tie using only text), we identify an underutilized opportunity to extend video as a new answer modality for Next-Event Prediction (NEP), formalized as Video-Next-Event Prediction (VNEP). While the established NEP task takes a video with a procedural or predictive question as input to predict the next event in text, VNEP requires dynamic video responses. This shift from telling to showing unlocks more intuitive and customized answers for procedural learning and creative exploration. However, this task remains challenging for existing models, as it demands an understanding of multimodal input, instruction-conditioned reasoning, and the generation of video with visual and semantic consistency. To address this, we introduce VANS, a model that leverages reinforcement learning to align a Vision-Language Model (VLM) with a Video Diffusion Model (VDM) for VNEP. The core of VANS is our proposed Joint-GRPO that orchestrates the VLM and VDM to function as a unit. Driven by a shared reward on their respective output, it optimizes the VLM to produce captions that are both accurate and friendly to visualize, while guiding the VDM to generate videos that are faithful to these captions and the input visual context. To enable this learning, we craft VANS-Data-100K, a dedicated dataset for the VNEP task. Experiments on procedural and predictive benchmarks demonstrate that VANS achieves state-of-the-art performance in both video event prediction and visualization. Codes are released in https://github.com/KlingTeam/VANS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16669</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAM 3: Segment Anything with Concepts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16719</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.16719.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nicolas Carion, Laura Gustafson, Yuan-Ting Hu, Shoubhik Debnath, Ronghang Hu, Didac Suris, Chaitanya Ryali, Kalyan Vasudev Alwala, Haitham Khedr, Andrew Huang, Jie Lei, Tengyu Ma, Baishan Guo, Arpit Kalla, Markus Marks, Joseph Greer, Meng Wang, Peize Sun, Roman Rädle, Triantafyllos Afouras, Effrosyni Mavroudi, Katherine Xu, Tsung-Han Wu, Yu Zhou, Liliane Momeni, Rishi Hazra, Shuangrui Ding, Sagar Vaze, Francois Porcher, Feng Li, Siyuan Li, Aishwarya Kamath, Ho Kei Cheng, Piotr Dollár, Nikhila Ravi, Kate Saenko, Pengchuan Zhang, Christoph Feichtenhofer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 94&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Segment Anything Model (SAM) 3, a unified model that detects, segments, and tracks objects in images and videos based on concept prompts, which we define as either short noun phrases (e.g., "yellow school bus"), image exemplars, or a combination of both. Promptable Concept Segmentation (PCS) takes such prompts and returns segmentation masks and unique identities for all matching object instances. To advance PCS, we build a scalable data engine that produces a high-quality dataset with 4M unique concept labels, including hard negatives, across images and videos. Our model consists of an image-level detector and a memory-based video tracker that share a single backbone. Recognition and localization are decoupled with a presence head, which boosts detection accuracy. SAM 3 doubles the accuracy of existing systems in both image and video PCS, and improves previous SAM capabilities on visual segmentation tasks. We open source SAM 3 along with our new Segment Anything with Concepts (SA-Co) benchmark for promptable concept segmentation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.16719</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 18:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UltraFlux: Data-Model Co-Design for High-quality Native 4K Text-to-Image Generation across Diverse Aspect Ratios</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18050</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.18050.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tian Ye, Song Fei, Lei Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 36&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Diffusion transformers have recently delivered strong text-to-image generation around 1K resolution, but we show that extending them to native 4K across diverse aspect ratios exposes a tightly coupled failure mode spanning positional encoding, VAE compression, and optimization. Tackling any of these factors in isolation leaves substantial quality on the table. We therefore take a data-model co-design view and introduce UltraFlux, a Flux-based DiT trained natively at 4K on MultiAspect-4K-1M, a 1M-image 4K corpus with controlled multi-AR coverage, bilingual captions, and rich VLM/IQA metadata for resolution- and AR-aware sampling. On the model side, UltraFlux couples (i) Resonance 2D RoPE with YaRN for training-window-, frequency-, and AR-aware positional encoding at 4K; (ii) a simple, non-adversarial VAE post-training scheme that improves 4K reconstruction fidelity; (iii) an SNR-Aware Huber Wavelet objective that rebalances gradients across timesteps and frequency bands; and (iv) a Stage-wise Aesthetic Curriculum Learning strategy that concentrates high-aesthetic supervision on high-noise steps governed by the model prior. Together, these components yield a stable, detail-preserving 4K DiT that generalizes across wide, square, and tall ARs. On the Aesthetic-Eval at 4096 benchmark and multi-AR 4K settings, UltraFlux consistently outperforms strong open-source baselines across fidelity, aesthetic, and alignment metrics, and-with a LLM prompt refiner-matches or surpasses the proprietary Seedream 4.0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18050</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 13:07:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Agentic Memory Via Deep Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18423</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.18423.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; B. Y. Yan, Chaofan Li, Hongjin Qian, Shuqi Lu, Zheng Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 146&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Memory is critical for AI agents, yet the widely-adopted static memory, aiming to create readily available memory in advance, is inevitably subject to severe information loss. To address this limitation, we propose a novel framework called general agentic memory (GAM). GAM follows the principle of "just-in time (JIT) compilation" where it focuses on creating optimized contexts for its client at runtime while keeping only simple but useful memory during the offline stage. To this end, GAM employs a duo-design with the following components. 1) Memorizer, which highlights key historical information using a lightweight memory, while maintaining complete historical information within a universal page-store. 2) Researcher, which retrieves and integrates useful information from the page-store for its online request guided by the pre-constructed memory. This design allows GAM to effectively leverage the agentic capabilities and test-time scalability of frontier large language models (LLMs), while also facilitating end-to-end performance optimization through reinforcement learning. In our experimental study, we demonstrate that GAM achieves substantial improvement on various memory-grounded task completion scenarios against existing memory systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18423</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 12:29:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedSAM3: Delving into Segment Anything with Medical Concepts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19046</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.19046.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anglin Liu, Rundong Xue, Xu R. Cao, Yifan Shen, Yi Lu, Xiang Li, Qianqian Chen, Jintai Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Medical image segmentation is fundamental for biomedical discovery. Existing methods lack generalizability and demand extensive, time-consuming manual annotation for new clinical application. Here, we propose MedSAM-3, a text promptable medical segmentation model for medical image and video segmentation. By fine-tuning the Segment Anything Model (SAM) 3 architecture on medical images paired with semantic conceptual labels, our MedSAM-3 enables medical Promptable Concept Segmentation (PCS), allowing precise targeting of anatomical structures via open-vocabulary text descriptions rather than solely geometric prompts. We further introduce the MedSAM-3 Agent, a framework that integrates Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) to perform complex reasoning and iterative refinement in an agent-in-the-loop workflow. Comprehensive experiments across diverse medical imaging modalities, including X-ray, MRI, Ultrasound, CT, and video, demonstrate that our approach significantly outperforms existing specialist and foundation models. We will release our code and model at https://github.com/Joey-S-Liu/MedSAM3.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19046</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 12:34:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AutoEnv: Automated Environments for Measuring Cross-Environment Agent Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19304</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.19304.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiayi Zhang, Yiran Peng, Fanqi Kong, Yang Cheng, Yifan Wu, Zhaoyang Yu, Jinyu Xiang, Jianhao Ruan, Jinlin Wang, Maojia Song, HongZhang Liu, Xiangru Tang, Bang Liu, Chenglin Wu, Yuyu Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 86&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Humans naturally adapt to diverse environments by learning underlying rules across worlds with different dynamics, observations, and reward structures. In contrast, existing agents typically demonstrate improvements via self-evolving within a single domain, implicitly assuming a fixed environment distribution. Cross-environment learning has remained largely unmeasured: there is no standard collection of controllable, heterogeneous environments, nor a unified way to represent how agents learn. We address these gaps in two steps. First, we propose AutoEnv, an automated framework that treats environments as factorizable distributions over transitions, observations, and rewards, enabling low-cost (4.12 USD on average) generation of heterogeneous worlds. Using AutoEnv, we construct AutoEnv-36, a dataset of 36 environments with 358 validated levels, on which seven language models achieve 12-49% normalized reward, demonstrating the challenge of AutoEnv-36. Second, we formalize agent learning as a component-centric process driven by three stages of Selection, Optimization, and Evaluation applied to an improvable agent component. Using this formulation, we design eight learning methods and evaluate them on AutoEnv-36. Empirically, the gain of any single learning method quickly decrease as the number of environments increases, revealing that fixed learning methods do not scale across heterogeneous environments. Environment-adaptive selection of learning methods substantially improves performance but exhibits diminishing returns as the method space expands. These results highlight both the necessity and the current limitations of agent learning for scalable cross-environment generalization, and position AutoEnv and AutoEnv-36 as a testbed for studying cross-environment agent learning. The code is avaiable at https://github.com/FoundationAgents/AutoEnv.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19304</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 16:54:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SteadyDancer: Harmonized and Coherent Human Image Animation with First-Frame Preservation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19320</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.19320.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaming Zhang, Shengming Cao, Rui Li, Xiaotong Zhao, Yutao Cui, Xinglin Hou, Gangshan Wu, Haolan Chen, Yu Xu, Limin Wang, Kai Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 38&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Preserving first-frame identity while ensuring precise motion control is a fundamental challenge in human image animation. The Image-to-Motion Binding process of the dominant Reference-to-Video (R2V) paradigm overlooks critical spatio-temporal misalignments common in real-world applications, leading to failures such as identity drift and visual artifacts. We introduce SteadyDancer, an Image-to-Video (I2V) paradigm-based framework that achieves harmonized and coherent animation and is the first to ensure first-frame preservation robustly. Firstly, we propose a Condition-Reconciliation Mechanism to harmonize the two conflicting conditions, enabling precise control without sacrificing fidelity. Secondly, we design Synergistic Pose Modulation Modules to generate an adaptive and coherent pose representation that is highly compatible with the reference image. Finally, we employ a Staged Decoupled-Objective Training Pipeline that hierarchically optimizes the model for motion fidelity, visual quality, and temporal coherence. Experiments demonstrate that SteadyDancer achieves state-of-the-art performance in both appearance fidelity and motion control, while requiring significantly fewer training resources than comparable methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19320</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 17:15:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeCo: Frequency-Decoupled Pixel Diffusion for End-to-End Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19365</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.19365.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zehong Ma, Longhui Wei, Shuai Wang, Shiliang Zhang, Qi Tian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Pixel diffusion aims to generate images directly in pixel space in an end-to-end fashion. This approach avoids the limitations of VAE in the two-stage latent diffusion, offering higher model capacity. Existing pixel diffusion models suffer from slow training and inference, as they usually model both high-frequency signals and low-frequency semantics within a single diffusion transformer (DiT). To pursue a more efficient pixel diffusion paradigm, we propose the frequency-DeCoupled pixel diffusion framework. With the intuition to decouple the generation of high and low frequency components, we leverage a lightweight pixel decoder to generate high-frequency details conditioned on semantic guidance from the DiT. This thus frees the DiT to specialize in modeling low-frequency semantics. In addition, we introduce a frequency-aware flow-matching loss that emphasizes visually salient frequencies while suppressing insignificant ones. Extensive experiments show that DeCo achieves superior performance among pixel diffusion models, attaining FID of 1.62 (256x256) and 2.22 (512x512) on ImageNet, closing the gap with latent diffusion methods. Furthermore, our pretrained text-to-image model achieves a leading overall score of 0.86 on GenEval in system-level comparison. Codes are publicly available at https://github.com/Zehong-Ma/DeCo.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19365</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 17:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DR Tulu: Reinforcement Learning with Evolving Rubrics for Deep Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19399</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.19399.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rulin Shao, Akari Asai, Shannon Zejiang Shen, Hamish Ivison, Varsha Kishore, Jingming Zhuo, Xinran Zhao, Molly Park, Samuel G. Finlayson, David Sontag, Tyler Murray, Sewon Min, Pradeep Dasigi, Luca Soldaini, Faeze Brahman, Wen-tau Yih, Tongshuang Wu, Luke Zettlemoyer, Yoon Kim, Hannaneh Hajishirzi, Pang Wei Koh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep research models perform multi-step research to produce long-form, well-attributed answers. However, most open deep research models are trained on easily verifiable short-form QA tasks via reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR), which does not extend to realistic long-form tasks. We address this with Reinforcement Learning with Evolving Rubrics (RLER), in which we construct and maintain rubrics that co-evolve with the policy model during training; this allows the rubrics to incorporate information that the model has newly explored and to provide discriminative, on-policy feedback. Using RLER, we develop Deep Research Tulu (DR Tulu-8B), the first open model that is directly trained for open-ended, long-form deep research. Across four long-form deep research benchmarks in science, healthcare and general domains, DR Tulu substantially outperforms existing open deep research models, and matches or exceeds proprietary deep research systems, while being significantly smaller and cheaper per query. To facilitate future research, we release all data, models, and code, including our new MCP-based agent infrastructure for deep research systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19399</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:35:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-Video Instructions: Visual Signals as Generative Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19401</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.19401.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gongfan Fang, Xinyin Ma, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large-scale video generative models have recently demonstrated strong visual capabilities, enabling the prediction of future frames that adhere to the logical and physical cues in the current observation. In this work, we investigate whether such capabilities can be harnessed for controllable image-to-video generation by interpreting visual signals embedded within the frames as instructions, a paradigm we term In-Video Instruction. In contrast to prompt-based control, which provides textual descriptions that are inherently global and coarse, In-Video Instruction encodes user guidance directly into the visual domain through elements such as overlaid text, arrows, or trajectories. This enables explicit, spatial-aware, and unambiguous correspondences between visual subjects and their intended actions by assigning distinct instructions to different objects. Extensive experiments on three state-of-the-art generators, including Veo 3.1, Kling 2.5, and Wan 2.2, show that video models can reliably interpret and execute such visually embedded instructions, particularly in complex multi-object scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19401</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:38:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferix: A Block-Diffusion based Next-Generation Inference Engine for World Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20714</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20714.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Inferix Team, Tianyu Feng, Yizeng Han, Jiahao He, Yuanyu He, Xi Lin, Teng Liu, Hanfeng Lu, Jiasheng Tang, Wei Wang, Zhiyuan Wang, Jichao Wu, Mingyang Yang, Yinghao Yu, Zeyu Zhang, Bohan Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 41&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; World models serve as core simulators for fields such as agentic AI, embodied AI, and gaming, capable of generating long, physically realistic, and interactive high-quality videos. Moreover, scaling these models could unlock emergent capabilities in visual perception, understanding, and reasoning, paving the way for a new paradigm that moves beyond current LLM-centric vision foundation models. A key breakthrough empowering them is the semi-autoregressive (block-diffusion) decoding paradigm, which merges the strengths of diffusion and autoregressive methods by generating video tokens in block-applying diffusion within each block while conditioning on previous ones, resulting in more coherent and stable video sequences. Crucially, it overcomes limitations of standard video diffusion by reintroducing LLM-style KV Cache management, enabling efficient, variable-length, and high-quality generation.   Therefore, Inferix is specifically designed as a next-generation inference engine to enable immersive world synthesis through optimized semi-autoregressive decoding processes. This dedicated focus on world simulation distinctly sets it apart from systems engineered for high-concurrency scenarios (like vLLM or SGLang) and from classic video diffusion models (such as xDiTs). Inferix further enhances its offering with interactive video streaming and profiling, enabling real-time interaction and realistic simulation to accurately model world dynamics. Additionally, it supports efficient benchmarking through seamless integration of LV-Bench, a new fine-grained evaluation benchmark tailored for minute-long video generation scenarios. We hope the community will work together to advance Inferix and foster world model exploration.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20714</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 01:45:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent0-VL: Exploring Self-Evolving Agent for Tool-Integrated Vision-Language Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19900</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.19900.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaqi Liu, Kaiwen Xiong, Peng Xia, Yiyang Zhou, Haonian Ji, Lu Feng, Siwei Han, Mingyu Ding, Huaxiu Yao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 46&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Vision-language agents have achieved remarkable progress in a variety of multimodal reasoning tasks; however, their learning remains constrained by the limitations of human-annotated supervision. Recent self-rewarding approaches attempt to overcome this constraint by allowing models to act as their own critics or reward providers. Yet, purely text-based self-evaluation struggles to verify complex visual reasoning steps and often suffers from evaluation hallucinations. To address these challenges, inspired by recent advances in tool-integrated reasoning, we propose Agent0-VL, a self-evolving vision-language agent that achieves continual improvement with tool-integrated reasoning. Agent0-VL incorporates tool usage not only into reasoning but also into self-evaluation and self-repair, enabling the model to introspect, verify, and refine its reasoning through evidence-grounded analysis. It unifies two synergistic roles within a single LVLM: a Solver that performs multi-turn tool-integrated reasoning, and a Verifier that generates structured feedback and fine-grained self-rewards through tool-grounded critique. These roles interact through a Self-Evolving Reasoning Cycle, where tool-based verification and reinforcement learning jointly align the reasoning and evaluation distributions for stable self-improvement. Through this zero-external-reward evolution, Agent0-VL aligns its reasoning and verification behaviors without any human annotation or external reward models, achieving continual self-improvement. Experiments on geometric problem solving and visual scientific analysis show that Agent0-VL achieves an 12.5% improvement over the base model. Our code is available at https://github.com/aiming-lab/Agent0/Agent0-VL{this https URL}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19900</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 04:15:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft Adaptive Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20347</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20347.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chang Gao, Chujie Zheng, Xiong-Hui Chen, Kai Dang, Shixuan Liu, Bowen Yu, An Yang, Shuai Bai, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) plays an increasingly important role in enhancing the reasoning capabilities of large language models (LLMs), yet stable and performant policy optimization remains challenging. Token-level importance ratios often exhibit high variance-a phenomenon exacerbated in Mixture-of-Experts models-leading to unstable updates. Existing group-based policy optimization methods, such as GSPO and GRPO, alleviate this problem via hard clipping, making it difficult to maintain both stability and effective learning. We propose Soft Adaptive Policy Optimization (SAPO), which replaces hard clipping with a smooth, temperature-controlled gate that adaptively attenuates off-policy updates while preserving useful learning signals. Compared with GSPO and GRPO, SAPO is both sequence-coherent and token-adaptive. Like GSPO, SAPO maintains sequence-level coherence, but its soft gating forms a continuous trust region that avoids the brittle hard clipping band used in GSPO. When a sequence contains a few highly off-policy tokens, GSPO suppresses all gradients for that sequence, whereas SAPO selectively down-weights only the offending tokens and preserves the learning signal from the near-on-policy ones, improving sample efficiency. Relative to GRPO, SAPO replaces hard token-level clipping with smooth, temperature-controlled scaling, enabling more informative and stable updates. Empirical results on mathematical reasoning benchmarks indicate that SAPO exhibits improved training stability and higher Pass@1 performance under comparable training budgets. Moreover, we employ SAPO to train the Qwen3-VL model series, demonstrating that SAPO yields consistent performance gains across diverse tasks and different model sizes. Overall, SAPO provides a more reliable, scalable, and effective optimization strategy for RL training of LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20347</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 14:25:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Understanding Inform Generation in Unified Multimodal Models? From Analysis to Path Forward</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20561</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20561.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuwei Niu, Weiyang Jin, Jiaqi Liao, Chaoran Feng, Peng Jin, Bin Lin, Zongjian Li, Bin Zhu, Weihao Yu, Li Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 31&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent years have witnessed significant progress in Unified Multimodal Models, yet a fundamental question remains: Does understanding truly inform generation? To investigate this, we introduce UniSandbox, a decoupled evaluation framework paired with controlled, synthetic datasets to avoid data leakage and enable detailed analysis. Our findings reveal a significant understanding-generation gap, which is mainly reflected in two key dimensions: reasoning generation and knowledge transfer. Specifically, for reasoning generation tasks, we observe that explicit Chain-of-Thought (CoT) in the understanding module effectively bridges the gap, and further demonstrate that a self-training approach can successfully internalize this ability, enabling implicit reasoning during generation. Additionally, for knowledge transfer tasks, we find that CoT assists the generative process by helping retrieve newly learned knowledge, and also discover that query-based architectures inherently exhibit latent CoT-like properties that affect this transfer. UniSandbox provides preliminary insights for designing future unified architectures and training strategies that truly bridge the gap between understanding and generation. Code and data are available at https://github.com/PKU-YuanGroup/UniSandBox&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20561</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 17:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ROOT: Robust Orthogonalized Optimizer for Neural Network Training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20626</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20626.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei He, Kai Han, Hang Zhou, Hanting Chen, Zhicheng Liu, Xinghao Chen, Yunhe Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 164&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The optimization of large language models (LLMs) remains a critical challenge, particularly as model scaling exacerbates sensitivity to algorithmic imprecision and training instability. Recent advances in optimizers have improved convergence efficiency through momentum orthogonalization, but suffer from two key robustness limitations: dimensional fragility in orthogonalization precision and vulnerability to outlier-induced noise. To address these robustness challenges, we introduce ROOT, a Robust Orthogonalized Optimizer that enhances training stability through dual robustness mechanisms. First, we develop a dimension-robust orthogonalization scheme using adaptive Newton iterations with fine-grained coefficients tailored to specific matrix sizes, ensuring consistent precision across diverse architectural configurations. Second, we introduce an optimization-robust framework via proximal optimization that suppresses outlier noise while preserving meaningful gradient directions. Extensive experiments demonstrate that ROOT achieves significantly improved robustness, with faster convergence and superior final performance compared to both Muon and Adam-based optimizers, particularly in noisy and non-convex scenarios. Our work establishes a new paradigm for developing robust and precise optimizers capable of handling the complexities of modern large-scale model training. The code will be available at https://github.com/huawei-noah/noah-research/tree/master/ROOT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20626</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:48:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>iMontage: Unified, Versatile, Highly Dynamic Many-to-many Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20635</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20635.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhoujie Fu, Xianfang Zeng, Jinghong Lan, Xinyao Liao, Cheng Chen, Junyi Chen, Jiacheng Wei, Wei Cheng, Shiyu Liu, Yunuo Chen, Gang Yu, Guosheng Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Pre-trained video models learn powerful priors for generating high-quality, temporally coherent content. While these models excel at temporal coherence, their dynamics are often constrained by the continuous nature of their training data. We hypothesize that by injecting the rich and unconstrained content diversity from image data into this coherent temporal framework, we can generate image sets that feature both natural transitions and a far more expansive dynamic range. To this end, we introduce iMontage, a unified framework designed to repurpose a powerful video model into an all-in-one image generator. The framework consumes and produces variable-length image sets, unifying a wide array of image generation and editing tasks. To achieve this, we propose an elegant and minimally invasive adaptation strategy, complemented by a tailored data curation process and training paradigm. This approach allows the model to acquire broad image manipulation capabilities without corrupting its invaluable original motion priors. iMontage excels across several mainstream many-in-many-out tasks, not only maintaining strong cross-image contextual consistency but also generating scenes with extraordinary dynamics that surpass conventional scopes. Find our homepage at: https://kr1sjfu.github.io/iMontage-web/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20635</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Collaboration in Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20639</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.20639.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaru Zou, Xiyuan Yang, Ruizhong Qiu, Gaotang Li, Katherine Tieu, Pan Lu, Ke Shen, Hanghang Tong, Yejin Choi, Jingrui He, James Zou, Mengdi Wang, Ling Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 89&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multi-agent systems (MAS) extend large language models (LLMs) from independent single-model reasoning to coordinative system-level intelligence. While existing LLM agents depend on text-based mediation for reasoning and communication, we take a step forward by enabling models to collaborate directly within the continuous latent space. We introduce LatentMAS, an end-to-end training-free framework that enables pure latent collaboration among LLM agents. In LatentMAS, each agent first performs auto-regressive latent thoughts generation through last-layer hidden embeddings. A shared latent working memory then preserves and transfers each agent's internal representations, ensuring lossless information exchange. We provide theoretical analyses establishing that LatentMAS attains higher expressiveness and lossless information preservation with substantially lower complexity than vanilla text-based MAS. In addition, empirical evaluations across 9 comprehensive benchmarks spanning math and science reasoning, commonsense understanding, and code generation show that LatentMAS consistently outperforms strong single-model and text-based MAS baselines, achieving up to 14.6% higher accuracy, reducing output token usage by 70.8%-83.7%, and providing 4x-4.3x faster end-to-end inference. These results demonstrate that our new latent collaboration framework enhances system-level reasoning quality while offering substantial efficiency gains without any additional training. Code and data are fully open-sourced at https://github.com/Gen-Verse/LatentMAS.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20639</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:56:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video Generation Models Are Good Latent Reward Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21541</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2511.21541.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoyue Mi, Wenqing Yu, Jiesong Lian, Shibo Jie, Ruizhe Zhong, Zijun Liu, Guozhen Zhang, Zixiang Zhou, Zhiyong Xu, Yuan Zhou, Qinglin Lu, Fan Tang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward feedback learning (ReFL) has proven effective for aligning image generation with human preferences. However, its extension to video generation faces significant challenges. Existing video reward models rely on vision-language models designed for pixel-space inputs, confining ReFL optimization to near-complete denoising steps after computationally expensive VAE decoding. This pixel-space approach incurs substantial memory overhead and increased training time, and its late-stage optimization lacks early-stage supervision, refining only visual quality rather than fundamental motion dynamics and structural coherence. In this work, we show that pre-trained video generation models are naturally suited for reward modeling in the noisy latent space, as they are explicitly designed to process noisy latent representations at arbitrary timesteps and inherently preserve temporal information through their sequential modeling capabilities. Accordingly, we propose Process Reward Feedback Learning~(PRFL), a framework that conducts preference optimization entirely in latent space, enabling efficient gradient backpropagation throughout the full denoising chain without VAE decoding. Extensive experiments demonstrate that PRFL significantly improves alignment with human preferences, while achieving substantial reductions in memory consumption and training time compared to RGB ReFL.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21541</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 16:14:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
