<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:02:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>SoK: Evaluating Jailbreak Guardrails for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10597</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.10597.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xunguang Wang, Zhenlan Ji, Wenxuan Wang, Zongjie Li, Daoyuan Wu, Shuai Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have achieved remarkable progress, but their deployment has exposed critical vulnerabilities, particularly to jailbreak attacks that circumvent safety mechanisms. Guardrails--external defense mechanisms that monitor and control LLM interaction--have emerged as a promising solution. However, the current landscape of LLM guardrails is fragmented, lacking a unified taxonomy and comprehensive evaluation framework. In this Systematization of Knowledge (SoK) paper, we present the first holistic analysis of jailbreak guardrails for LLMs. We propose a novel, multi-dimensional taxonomy that categorizes guardrails along six key dimensions, and introduce a Security-Efficiency-Utility evaluation framework to assess their practical effectiveness. Through extensive analysis and experiments, we identify the strengths and limitations of existing guardrail approaches, explore their universality across attack types, and provide insights into optimizing defense combinations. Our work offers a structured foundation for future research and development, aiming to guide the principled advancement and deployment of robust LLM guardrails. The code is available at https://github.com/xunguangwang/SoK4JailbreakGuardrails.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10597</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 11:42:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spec2RTL-Agent: Automated Hardware Code Generation from Complex   Specifications Using LLM Agent Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13905</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13905.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhongzhi Yu, Mingjie Liu, Michael Zimmer, Yingyan Celine Lin, Yong Liu, Haoxing Ren&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite recent progress in generating hardware RTL code with LLMs, existing solutions still suffer from a substantial gap between practical application scenarios and the requirements of real-world RTL code development. Prior approaches either focus on overly simplified hardware descriptions or depend on extensive human guidance to process complex specifications, limiting their scalability and automation potential. In this paper, we address this gap by proposing an LLM agent system, termed Spec2RTL-Agent, designed to directly process complex specification documentation and generate corresponding RTL code implementations, advancing LLM-based RTL code generation toward more realistic application settings. To achieve this goal, Spec2RTL-Agent introduces a novel multi-agent collaboration framework that integrates three key enablers: (1) a reasoning and understanding module that translates specifications into structured, step-by-step implementation plans; (2) a progressive coding and prompt optimization module that iteratively refines the code across multiple representations to enhance correctness and synthesisability for RTL conversion; and (3) an adaptive reflection module that identifies and traces the source of errors during generation, ensuring a more robust code generation flow. Instead of directly generating RTL from natural language, our system strategically generates synthesizable C++ code, which is then optimized for HLS. This agent-driven refinement ensures greater correctness and compatibility compared to naive direct RTL generation approaches. We evaluate Spec2RTL-Agent on three specification documents, showing it generates accurate RTL code with up to 75% fewer human interventions than existing methods. This highlights its role as the first fully automated multi-agent system for RTL generation from unstructured specs, reducing reliance on human effort in hardware design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13905</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 18:33:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OAgents: An Empirical Study of Building Effective Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15741</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.15741.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; He Zhu, Tianrui Qin, King Zhu, Heyuan Huang, Yeyi Guan, Jinxiang Xia, Yi Yao, Hanhao Li, Ningning Wang, Pai Liu, Tianhao Peng, Xin Gui, Xiaowan Li, Yuhui Liu, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Jun Wang, Changwang Zhang, Xiangru Tang, Ge Zhang, Jian Yang, Minghao Liu, Xitong Gao, Jiaheng Liu, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, Agentic AI has become an increasingly popular research field. However, we argue that current agent research practices lack standardization and scientific rigor, making it hard to conduct fair comparisons among methods. As a result, it is still unclear how different design choices in agent frameworks affect effectiveness, and measuring their progress remains challenging. In this work, we conduct a systematic empirical study on GAIA benchmark and BrowseComp to examine the impact of popular design choices in key agent components in a fair and rigorous manner. We find that the lack of a standard evaluation protocol makes previous works, even open-sourced ones, non-reproducible, with significant variance between random runs. Therefore, we introduce a more robust evaluation protocol to stabilize comparisons. Our study reveals which components and designs are crucial for effective agents, while others are redundant, despite seeming logical. Based on our findings, we build and open-source OAgents, a new foundation agent framework that achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-source projects. OAgents offers a modular design for various agent components, promoting future research in Agentic AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15741</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jun 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying the Visual Quality Paradox in Multimodal Large Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15645</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.15645.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shuo Xing, Lanqing Guo, Hongyuan Hua, Seoyoung Lee, Peiran Li, Yufei Wang, Zhangyang Wang, Zhengzhong Tu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) excel on benchmark vision-language tasks, yet little is known about how input visual quality shapes their responses. Does higher perceptual quality of images already translate to better MLLM understanding? We conduct the first systematic study spanning leading MLLMs and a suite of vision-language benchmarks, applying controlled degradations and stylistic shifts to each image. Surprisingly, we uncover a visual-quality paradox: model, task, and even individual-instance performance can improve when images deviate from human-perceived fidelity. Off-the-shelf restoration pipelines fail to reconcile these idiosyncratic preferences. To close the gap, we introduce Visual-Quality Test-Time Tuning (VQ-TTT)-a lightweight adaptation module that: (1) inserts a learnable, low-rank kernel before the frozen vision encoder to modulate frequency content; and (2) fine-tunes only shallow vision-encoder layers via LoRA. VQ-TTT dynamically adjusts each input image in a single forward pass, aligning it with task-specific model preferences. Across the evaluated MLLMs and all datasets, VQ-TTT lifts significant average accuracy, with no external models, cached features, or extra training data. These findings redefine ``better'' visual inputs for MLLMs and highlight the need for adaptive, rather than universally ``clean'', imagery, in the new era of AI being the main data customer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15645</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 17:14:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I Know Which LLM Wrote Your Code Last Summer: LLM generated Code   Stylometry for Authorship Attribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17323</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17323.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tamas Bisztray, Bilel Cherif, Richard A. Dubniczky, Nils Gruschka, Bertalan Borsos, Mohamed Amine Ferrag, Attila Kovacs, Vasileios Mavroeidis, Norbert Tihanyi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Detecting AI-generated code, deepfakes, and other synthetic content is an emerging research challenge. As code generated by Large Language Models (LLMs) becomes more common, identifying the specific model behind each sample is increasingly important. This paper presents the first systematic study of LLM authorship attribution for C programs. We released CodeT5-Authorship, a novel model that uses only the encoder layers from the original CodeT5 encoder-decoder architecture, discarding the decoder to focus on classification. Our model's encoder output (first token) is passed through a two-layer classification head with GELU activation and dropout, producing a probability distribution over possible authors. To evaluate our approach, we introduce LLM-AuthorBench, a benchmark of 32,000 compilable C programs generated by eight state-of-the-art LLMs across diverse tasks. We compare our model to seven traditional ML classifiers and eight fine-tuned transformer models, including BERT, RoBERTa, CodeBERT, ModernBERT, DistilBERT, DeBERTa-V3, Longformer, and LoRA-fine-tuned Qwen2-1.5B. In binary classification, our model achieves 97.56% accuracy in distinguishing C programs generated by closely related models such as GPT-4.1 and GPT-4o, and 95.40% accuracy for multi-class attribution among five leading LLMs (Gemini 2.5 Flash, Claude 3.5 Haiku, GPT-4.1, Llama 3.3, and DeepSeek-V3). To support open science, we release the CodeT5-Authorship architecture, the LLM-AuthorBench benchmark, and all relevant Google Colab scripts on GitHub: https://github.com/LLMauthorbench/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17323</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 19:49:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4Real-Video-V2: Fused View-Time Attention and Feedforward Reconstruction   for 4D Scene Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18839</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18839.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chaoyang Wang, Ashkan Mirzaei, Vidit Goel, Willi Menapace, Aliaksandr Siarohin, Avalon Vinella, Michael Vasilkovsky, Ivan Skorokhodov, Vladislav Shakhrai, Sergey Korolev, Sergey Tulyakov, Peter Wonka&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose the first framework capable of computing a 4D spatio-temporal grid of video frames and 3D Gaussian particles for each time step using a feed-forward architecture. Our architecture has two main components, a 4D video model and a 4D reconstruction model. In the first part, we analyze current 4D video diffusion architectures that perform spatial and temporal attention either sequentially or in parallel within a two-stream design. We highlight the limitations of existing approaches and introduce a novel fused architecture that performs spatial and temporal attention within a single layer. The key to our method is a sparse attention pattern, where tokens attend to others in the same frame, at the same timestamp, or from the same viewpoint. In the second part, we extend existing 3D reconstruction algorithms by introducing a Gaussian head, a camera token replacement algorithm, and additional dynamic layers and training. Overall, we establish a new state of the art for 4D generation, improving both visual quality and reconstruction capability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18839</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 23:44:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FinCoT: Grounding Chain-of-Thought in Expert Financial Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16123</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16123.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Natapong Nitarach, Warit Sirichotedumrong, Panop Pitchayarthorn, Pittawat Taveekitworachai, Potsawee Manakul, Kunat Pipatanakul&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents FinCoT, a structured chain-of-thought (CoT) prompting approach that incorporates insights from domain-specific expert financial reasoning to guide the reasoning traces of large language models. We investigate that there are three main prompting styles in FinNLP: (1) standard prompting--zero-shot prompting; (2) unstructured CoT--CoT prompting without an explicit reasoning structure, such as the use of tags; and (3) structured CoT prompting--CoT prompting with explicit instructions or examples that define structured reasoning steps. Previously, FinNLP has primarily focused on prompt engineering with either standard or unstructured CoT prompting. However, structured CoT prompting has received limited attention in prior work. Furthermore, the design of reasoning structures in structured CoT prompting is often based on heuristics from non-domain experts. In this study, we investigate each prompting approach in FinNLP. We evaluate the three main prompting styles and FinCoT on CFA-style questions spanning ten financial domains. We observe that FinCoT improves performance from 63.2% to 80.5% and Qwen-2.5-7B-Instruct from 69.7% to 74.2%, while reducing generated tokens eight-fold compared to structured CoT prompting. Our findings show that domain-aligned structured prompts not only improve performance and reduce inference costs but also yield more interpretable and expert-aligned reasoning traces.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16123</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 08:18:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Reward Modeling via Causal Rubrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16507</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16507.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pragya Srivastava, Harman Singh, Rahul Madhavan, Gandharv Patil, Sravanti Addepalli, Arun Suggala, Rengarajan Aravamudhan, Soumya Sharma, Anirban Laha, Aravindan Raghuveer, Karthikeyan Shanmugam, Doina Precup&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reward models (RMs) are fundamental to aligning Large Language Models (LLMs) via human feedback, yet they often suffer from reward hacking. They tend to latch on to superficial or spurious attributes, such as response length or formatting, mistaking these cues learned from correlations in training data for the true causal drivers of quality (e.g., factuality, relevance). This occurs because standard training objectives struggle to disentangle these factors, leading to brittle RMs and misaligned policies. We introduce Crome (Causally Robust Reward Modeling), a novel framework grounded in an explicit causal model designed to mitigate reward hacking. Crome employs the following synthetic targeted augmentations during training: (1) Causal Augmentations, which are pairs that differ along specific causal attributes, to enforce sensitivity along each causal attribute individually, and (2) Neutral Augmentations, which are tie-label pairs varying primarily in spurious attributes, to enforce invariance along spurious attributes. Notably, our augmentations are produced without any knowledge of spurious factors, via answer interventions only along causal rubrics, that are identified by querying an oracle LLM. Empirically, Crome significantly outperforms standard baselines on RewardBench, improving average accuracy by up to 5.4% and achieving gains of up to 13.2% and 7.2% in specific categories. The robustness of Crome is further testified by the consistent gains obtained in a Best-of-N inference setting across increasing N, across various benchmarks, including the popular RewardBench (covering chat, chat-hard, safety, and reasoning tasks), the safety-focused WildGuardTest, and the reasoning-specific GSM8k.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16507</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 17:59:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A deep learning and machine learning approach to predict neonatal death   in the context of São Paulo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16929</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16929.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohon Raihan, Plabon Kumar Saha, Rajan Das Gupta, A Z M Tahmidul Kabir, Afia Anjum Tamanna, Md. Harun-Ur-Rashid, Adnan Bin Abdus Salam, Md Tanvir Anjum, A Z M Ahteshamul Kabir&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Neonatal death is still a concerning reality for underdeveloped and even some developed countries. Worldwide data indicate that 26.693 babies out of 1,000 births die, according to Macro Trades. To reduce this number, early prediction of endangered babies is crucial. Such prediction enables the opportunity to take ample care of the child and mother so that early child death can be avoided. In this context, machine learning was used to determine whether a newborn baby is at risk. To train the predictive model, historical data of 1.4 million newborns was used. Machine learning and deep learning techniques such as logical regression, K-nearest neighbor, random forest classifier, extreme gradient boosting (XGBoost), convolutional neural network, and long short-term memory (LSTM) were implemented using the dataset to identify the most accurate model for predicting neonatal mortality. Among the machine learning algorithms, XGBoost and random forest classifier achieved the best accuracy with 94%, while among the deep learning models, LSTM delivered the highest accuracy with 99%. Therefore, using LSTM appears to be the most suitable approach to predict whether precautionary measures for a child are necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16929</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 11:44:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Step-by-Step and Verifiable Medical Reasoning in MLLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16962</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16962.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoran Sun, Yankai Jiang, Wenjie Lou, Yujie Zhang, Wenjie Li, Lilong Wang, Mianxin Liu, Lei Liu, Xiaosong Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have begun to demonstrate robust reasoning capabilities on general tasks, yet their application in the medical domain remains in its early stages. Constructing chain-of-thought (CoT) training data is essential for bolstering the reasoning abilities of medical MLLMs. However, existing approaches exhibit a deficiency in offering a comprehensive framework for searching and evaluating effective reasoning paths towards critical diagnosis. To address this challenge, we propose Mentor-Intern Collaborative Search (MICS), a novel reasoning-path searching scheme to generate rigorous and effective medical CoT data. MICS first leverages mentor models to initialize the reasoning, one step at a time, then prompts each intern model to continue the thinking along those initiated paths, and finally selects the optimal reasoning path according to the overall reasoning performance of multiple intern models. The reasoning performance is determined by an MICS-Score, which assesses the quality of generated reasoning paths. Eventually, we construct MMRP, a multi-task medical reasoning dataset with ranked difficulty, and Chiron-o1, a new medical MLLM devised via a curriculum learning strategy, with robust visual question-answering and generalizable reasoning capabilities. Extensive experiments demonstrate that Chiron-o1, trained on our CoT dataset constructed using MICS, achieves state-of-the-art performance across a list of medical visual question answering and reasoning benchmarks. Codes are available at GitHub - manglu097/Chiron-o1: Enhancing Step-by-Step and Verifiable Medical Reasoning in MLLMs&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16962</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 12:51:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ConsumerBench: Benchmarking Generative AI Applications on End-User   Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17538</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17538.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yile Gu, Rohan Kadekodi, Hoang Nguyen, Keisuke Kamahori, Yiyu Liu, Baris Kasikci&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The recent shift in Generative AI (GenAI) applications from cloud-only environments to end-user devices introduces new challenges in resource management, system efficiency, and user experience. This paper presents ConsumerBench, a comprehensive benchmarking framework designed to evaluate the system efficiency and response time of GenAI models running on end-user devices. Unlike existing benchmarks that assume exclusive model access on dedicated GPUs, ConsumerBench simulates realistic multi-application scenarios executing concurrently on constrained hardware. Furthermore, ConsumerBench supports customizable workflows that simulate complex tasks requiring coordination among multiple applications. ConsumerBench captures both application-level metrics, including latency and Service Level Objective (SLO) attainment, and system-level metrics like CPU/GPU utilization and memory bandwidth. Through extensive experiments, ConsumerBench reveals inefficiencies in resource sharing, unfair scheduling under greedy allocation, and performance pitfalls of static model server configurations. The paper also provides practical insights for model developers and system designers, highlighting the benefits of custom kernels tailored to consumer-grade GPU architectures and the value of implementing SLO-aware scheduling strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17538</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 01:32:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TPTT: Transforming Pretrained Transformer into Titans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17671</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17671.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fabien Furfaro&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have led to remarkable progress in natural language processing, but their computational and memory demands remain a significant challenge, particularly for long-context inference. We introduce TPTT (Transforming Pretrained Transformer into Titans), a novel framework for enhancing pretrained Transformer models with efficient linearized attention mechanisms and advanced memory management. TPTT employs techniques such as Memory as Gate (MaG) and mixed linearized attention (LiZA). It is fully compatible with the Hugging Face Transformers library, enabling seamless adaptation of any causal LLM through parameter-efficient fine-tuning (LoRA) without full retraining. We show the effectiveness of TPTT on the MMLU benchmark with models of approximately 1 billion parameters, observing substantial improvements in both efficiency and accuracy. For instance, Titans-Llama-3.2-1B achieves a 20% increase in Exact Match (EM) over its baseline. Statistical analyses and comparisons with recent state-of-the-art methods confirm the practical scalability and robustness of TPTT. Code is available at https://github.com/fabienfrfr/tptt . Python package at https://pypi.org/project/tptt/ .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17671</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 10:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FaithfulSAE: Towards Capturing Faithful Features with Sparse   Autoencoders without External Dataset Dependencies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17673</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17673.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seonglae Cho, Harryn Oh, Donghyun Lee, Luis Eduardo Rodrigues Vieira, Andrew Bermingham, Ziad El Sayed&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Sparse Autoencoders (SAEs) have emerged as a promising solution for decomposing large language model representations into interpretable features. However, Paulo and Belrose (2025) have highlighted instability across different initialization seeds, and Heap et al. (2025) have pointed out that SAEs may not capture model-internal features. These problems likely stem from training SAEs on external datasets - either collected from the Web or generated by another model - which may contain out-of-distribution (OOD) data beyond the model's generalisation capabilities. This can result in hallucinated SAE features, which we term "Fake Features", that misrepresent the model's internal activations. To address these issues, we propose FaithfulSAE, a method that trains SAEs on the model's own synthetic dataset. Using FaithfulSAEs, we demonstrate that training SAEs on less-OOD instruction datasets results in SAEs being more stable across seeds. Notably, FaithfulSAEs outperform SAEs trained on web-based datasets in the SAE probing task and exhibit a lower Fake Feature Ratio in 5 out of 7 models. Overall, our approach eliminates the dependency on external datasets, advancing interpretability by better capturing model-internal features while highlighting the often neglected importance of SAE training datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17673</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 10:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CultureMERT: Continual Pre-Training for Cross-Cultural Music   Representation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17818</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17818.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Angelos-Nikolaos Kanatas, Charilaos Papaioannou, Alexandros Potamianos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in music foundation models have improved audio representation learning, yet their effectiveness across diverse musical traditions remains limited. We introduce CultureMERT-95M, a multi-culturally adapted foundation model developed to enhance cross-cultural music representation learning and understanding. To achieve this, we propose a two-stage continual pre-training strategy that integrates learning rate re-warming and re-decaying, enabling stable adaptation even with limited computational resources. Training on a 650-hour multi-cultural data mix, comprising Greek, Turkish, and Indian music traditions, results in an average improvement of 4.9% in ROC-AUC and AP across diverse non-Western music auto-tagging tasks, surpassing prior state-of-the-art, with minimal forgetting on Western-centric benchmarks. We further investigate task arithmetic, an alternative approach to multi-cultural adaptation that merges single-culture adapted models in the weight space. Task arithmetic performs on par with our multi-culturally trained model on non-Western auto-tagging tasks and shows no regression on Western datasets. Cross-cultural evaluation reveals that single-culture models transfer with varying effectiveness across musical traditions, whereas the multi-culturally adapted model achieves the best overall performance. To support research on world music representation learning, we publicly release CultureMERT-95M and CultureMERT-TA-95M, fostering the development of more culturally aware music foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17818</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 21:16:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Alignment Shrinks the Generative Horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17871</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17871.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenghao Yang, Ari Holtzman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite their impressive capabilities, aligned large language models (LLMs) often generate outputs that lack diversity. What drives this stability in the generation? We investigate this phenomenon through the lens of probability concentration in the model's output distribution. To quantify this concentration, we introduce the Branching Factor (BF) -- a token-invariant measure of the effective number of plausible next steps during generation. Our empirical analysis reveals two key findings: (1) BF often decreases as generation progresses, suggesting that LLMs become more predictable as they generate. (2) alignment tuning substantially sharpens the model's output distribution from the outset, reducing BF by nearly an order of magnitude (e.g., from 12 to 1.2) relative to base models. This stark reduction helps explain why aligned models often appear less sensitive to decoding strategies. Building on this insight, we find this stability has surprising implications for complex reasoning. Aligned Chain-of-Thought (CoT) models (e.g., DeepSeek-distilled models), for instance, leverage this effect; by generating longer reasoning chains, they push generation into later, more deterministic (lower BF) stages, resulting in more stable outputs. We hypothesize that alignment tuning does not fundamentally change a model's behavior, but instead steers it toward stylistic tokens (e.g., "Sure") that unlock low-entropy trajectories already present in the base model. This view is supported by nudging experiments, which show that prompting base models with such tokens can similarly reduce BF. Together, our findings establish BF as a powerful diagnostic for understanding and controlling LLM outputs - clarifying how alignment reduces variability, how CoT promotes stable generations, and how base models can be steered away from diversity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17871</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 02:00:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GEMeX-ThinkVG: Towards Thinking with Visual Grounding in Medical VQA via   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17939</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17939.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bo Liu, Xiangyu Zhao, Along He, Yidi Chen, Huazhu Fu, Xiao-Ming Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Medical visual question answering aims to support clinical decision-making by enabling models to answer natural language questions based on medical images. While recent advances in multi-modal learning have significantly improved performance, current methods still suffer from limited answer reliability and poor interpretability, impairing the ability of clinicians and patients to understand and trust model-generated answers. To address this, this work first proposes a Thinking with Visual Grounding (ThinkVG) dataset wherein the answer generation is decomposed into intermediate reasoning steps that explicitly ground relevant visual regions of the medical image, thereby providing fine-grained explainability. Furthermore, we introduce a novel verifiable reward mechanism for reinforcement learning to guide post-training, improving the alignment between the model's reasoning process and its final answer. Remarkably, our method achieves comparable performance using only one-eighth of the training data, demonstrating the efficiency and effectiveness of the proposal. The dataset is available at https://huggingface.co/datasets/BoKelvin/GEMeX-ThinkVG.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17939</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 08:09:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RLPR: Extrapolating RLVR to General Domains without Verifiers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18254</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18254.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Yu, Bo Ji, Shouli Wang, Shu Yao, Zefan Wang, Ganqu Cui, Lifan Yuan, Ning Ding, Yuan Yao, Zhiyuan Liu, Maosong Sun, Tat-Seng Chua&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR) demonstrates promising potential in advancing the reasoning capabilities of LLMs. However, its success remains largely confined to mathematical and code domains. This primary limitation stems from the heavy reliance on domain-specific verifiers, which results in prohibitive complexity and limited scalability. To address the challenge, our key observation is that LLM's intrinsic probability of generating a correct free-form answer directly indicates its own evaluation of the reasoning reward (i.e., how well the reasoning process leads to the correct answer). Building on this insight, we propose RLPR, a simple verifier-free framework that extrapolates RLVR to broader general domains. RLPR uses the LLM's own token probability scores for reference answers as the reward signal and maximizes the expected reward during training. We find that addressing the high variance of this noisy probability reward is crucial to make it work, and propose prob-to-reward and stabilizing methods to ensure a precise and stable reward from LLM intrinsic probabilities. Comprehensive experiments in four general-domain benchmarks and three mathematical benchmarks show that RLPR consistently improves reasoning capabilities in both areas for Gemma, Llama, and Qwen based models. Notably, RLPR outperforms concurrent VeriFree by 7.6 points on TheoremQA and 7.5 points on Minerva, and even surpasses strong verifier-model-dependent approaches General-Reasoner by 1.6 average points across seven benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18254</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 02:56:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LettinGo: Explore User Profile Generation for Recommendation System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18309</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18309.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lu Wang, Di Zhang, Fangkai Yang, Pu Zhao, Jianfeng Liu, Yuefeng Zhan, Hao Sun, Qingwei Lin, Weiwei Deng, Dongmei Zhang, Feng Sun, Qi Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; User profiling is pivotal for recommendation systems, as it transforms raw user interaction data into concise and structured representations that drive personalized recommendations. While traditional embedding-based profiles lack interpretability and adaptability, recent advances with large language models (LLMs) enable text-based profiles that are semantically richer and more transparent. However, existing methods often adhere to fixed formats that limit their ability to capture the full diversity of user behaviors. In this paper, we introduce LettinGo, a novel framework for generating diverse and adaptive user profiles. By leveraging the expressive power of LLMs and incorporating direct feedback from downstream recommendation tasks, our approach avoids the rigid constraints imposed by supervised fine-tuning (SFT). Instead, we employ Direct Preference Optimization (DPO) to align the profile generator with task-specific performance, ensuring that the profiles remain adaptive and effective. LettinGo operates in three stages: (1) exploring diverse user profiles via multiple LLMs, (2) evaluating profile quality based on their impact in recommendation systems, and (3) aligning the profile generation through pairwise preference data derived from task performance. Experimental results demonstrate that our framework significantly enhances recommendation accuracy, flexibility, and contextual awareness. This work enhances profile generation as a key innovation for next-generation recommendation systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18309</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 05:51:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SlimMoE: Structured Compression of Large MoE Models via Expert Slimming   and Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18349</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18349.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zichong Li, Chen Liang, Zixuan Zhang, Ilgee Hong, Young Jin Kim, Weizhu Chen, Tuo Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The Mixture of Experts (MoE) architecture has emerged as a powerful paradigm for scaling large language models (LLMs) while maintaining inference efficiency. However, their enormous memory requirements make them prohibitively expensive to fine-tune or deploy in resource-constrained environments. To address this challenge, we introduce SlimMoE, a multi-stage compression framework for transforming large MoE models into much smaller, efficient variants without incurring the prohibitive costs of training from scratch. Our method systematically reduces parameter counts by slimming experts and transferring knowledge through intermediate stages, effectively mitigating the performance degradation common in one-shot pruning approaches. Using this framework, we compress Phi 3.5-MoE (41.9B total/6.6B activated parameters) to create Phi-mini-MoE (7.6B total/2.4B activated parameters) and Phi-tiny-MoE (3.8B total/1.1B activated parameters) using only 400B tokens--less than 10% of the original model's training data. These compressed models can be fine-tuned on a single GPU (A100 for Phi-mini-MoE, A6000 for Phi-tiny-MoE), making them highly suitable for academic and resource-limited settings. Our experiments demonstrate that these compressed models outperform others of similar size and remain competitive with larger models. For instance, Phi-mini-MoE achieves similar or better performance to Phi-3-mini using only 2/3 of the activated parameters and yields comparable MMLU scores to Llama 3.1 8B despite having significantly lower latency. Our findings demonstrate that structured pruning combined with staged distillation offers an effective path to creating high-quality, compact MoE models, paving the way for broader adoption of MoE architectures. We make our models publicly available at https://huggingface.co/microsoft/Phi-mini-MoE-instruct and https://huggingface.co/microsoft/Phi-tiny-MoE-instruct .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18349</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 07:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RePIC: Reinforced Post-Training for Personalizing Multi-Modal Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18369</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18369.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yeongtak Oh, Jisoo Mok, Dohyun Chung, Juhyeon Shin, Sangha Park, Johan Barthelemy, Sungroh Yoon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent multi-modal large language models (MLLMs) often struggle to generate personalized image captions, even when trained on high-quality captions. In this work, we observe that such limitations persist in existing post-training-based MLLM personalization methods. Specifically, despite being post-tuned with large-scale caption data through supervised fine-tuning (SFT), these models frequently fail to produce faithful descriptions in real-world scenarios, such as multi-concept image captioning. However, acquiring large-scale, high-quality captions for such complex settings is both costly and difficult. To address the data-centric nature of SFT, we propose a reinforcement learning (RL)-based post-training framework. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first RL-based approach to post-train MLLMs for personalized image captioning. Our method significantly enhances both visual recognition and personalized generation capabilities of MLLMs, and consistently outperforms existing SFT-based baselines, especially in the challenging multi-concept image captioning task.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18369</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 07:55:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DIP: Unsupervised Dense In-Context Post-training of Visual   Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18463</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18463.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sophia Sirko-Galouchenko, Spyros Gidaris, Antonin Vobecky, Andrei Bursuc, Nicolas Thome&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce DIP, a novel unsupervised post-training method designed to enhance dense image representations in large-scale pretrained vision encoders for in-context scene understanding. Unlike prior approaches that rely on complex self-distillation architectures, our method trains the vision encoder using pseudo-tasks that explicitly simulate downstream in-context scenarios, inspired by meta-learning principles. To enable post-training on unlabeled data, we propose an automatic mechanism for generating in-context tasks that combines a pretrained diffusion model and the vision encoder itself. DIP is simple, unsupervised, and computationally efficient, requiring less than 9 hours on a single A100 GPU. By learning dense representations through pseudo in-context tasks, it achieves strong performance across a wide variety of downstream real-world in-context scene understanding tasks. It outperforms both the initial vision encoder and prior methods, offering a practical and effective solution for improving dense representations. Code available here: https://github.com/sirkosophia/DIP&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18463</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 10:01:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Auto-Regressively Generating Multi-View Consistent Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18527</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18527.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; JiaKui Hu, Yuxiao Yang, Jialun Liu, Jinbo Wu, Chen Zhao, Yanye Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generating multi-view images from human instructions is crucial for 3D content creation. The primary challenges involve maintaining consistency across multiple views and effectively synthesizing shapes and textures under diverse conditions. In this paper, we propose the Multi-View Auto-Regressive (MV-AR) method, which leverages an auto-regressive model to progressively generate consistent multi-view images from arbitrary prompts. Firstly, the next-token-prediction capability of the AR model significantly enhances its effectiveness in facilitating progressive multi-view synthesis. When generating widely-separated views, MV-AR can utilize all its preceding views to extract effective reference information. Subsequently, we propose a unified model that accommodates various prompts via architecture designing and training strategies. To address multiple conditions, we introduce condition injection modules for text, camera pose, image, and shape. To manage multi-modal conditions simultaneously, a progressive training strategy is employed. This strategy initially adopts the text-to-multi-view (t2mv) model as a baseline to enhance the development of a comprehensive X-to-multi-view (X2mv) model through the randomly dropping and combining conditions. Finally, to alleviate the overfitting problem caused by limited high-quality data, we propose the "Shuffle View" data augmentation technique, thus significantly expanding the training data by several magnitudes. Experiments demonstrate the performance and versatility of our MV-AR, which consistently generates consistent multi-view images across a range of conditions and performs on par with leading diffusion-based multi-view image generation models. Code and models will be released at https://github.com/MILab-PKU/MVAR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18527</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 11:28:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReDit: Reward Dithering for Improved LLM Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18631</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18631.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenxing Wei, Jiarui Yu, Ying Tiffany He, Hande Dong, Yao Shu, Fei Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; DeepSeek-R1 has successfully enhanced Large Language Model (LLM) reasoning capabilities through its rule-based reward system. While it's a ''perfect'' reward system that effectively mitigates reward hacking, such reward functions are often discrete. Our experimental observations suggest that discrete rewards can lead to gradient anomaly, unstable optimization, and slow convergence. To address this issue, we propose ReDit (Reward Dithering), a method that dithers the discrete reward signal by adding simple random noise. With this perturbed reward, exploratory gradients are continuously provided throughout the learning process, enabling smoother gradient updates and accelerating convergence. The injected noise also introduces stochasticity into flat reward regions, encouraging the model to explore novel policies and escape local optima. Experiments across diverse tasks demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of ReDit. On average, ReDit achieves performance comparable to vanilla GRPO with only approximately 10% the training steps, and furthermore, still exhibits a 4% performance improvement over vanilla GRPO when trained for a similar duration. Visualizations confirm significant mitigation of gradient issues with ReDit. Moreover, theoretical analyses are provided to further validate these advantages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18631</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 13:36:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Arena: An Open Platform for Generative 3D Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18787</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18787.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dylan Ebert&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Evaluating Generative 3D models remains challenging due to misalignment between automated metrics and human perception of quality. Current benchmarks rely on image-based metrics that ignore 3D structure or geometric measures that fail to capture perceptual appeal and real-world utility. To address this gap, we present 3D Arena, an open platform for evaluating image-to-3D generation models through large-scale human preference collection using pairwise comparisons.   Since launching in June 2024, the platform has collected 123,243 votes from 8,096 users across 19 state-of-the-art models, establishing the largest human preference evaluation for Generative 3D. We contribute the iso3d dataset of 100 evaluation prompts and demonstrate quality control achieving 99.75% user authenticity through statistical fraud detection. Our ELO-based ranking system provides reliable model assessment, with the platform becoming an established evaluation resource.   Through analysis of this preference data, we present insights into human preference patterns. Our findings reveal preferences for visual presentation features, with Gaussian splat outputs achieving a 16.6 ELO advantage over meshes and textured models receiving a 144.1 ELO advantage over untextured models. We provide recommendations for improving evaluation methods, including multi-criteria assessment, task-oriented evaluation, and format-aware comparison. The platform's community engagement establishes 3D Arena as a benchmark for the field while advancing understanding of human-centered evaluation in Generative 3D.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18787</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 15:57:10 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ViDAR: Video Diffusion-Aware 4D Reconstruction From Monocular Inputs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18792</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18792.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Michal Nazarczuk, Sibi Catley-Chandar, Thomas Tanay, Zhensong Zhang, Gregory Slabaugh, Eduardo Pérez-Pellitero&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Dynamic Novel View Synthesis aims to generate photorealistic views of moving subjects from arbitrary viewpoints. This task is particularly challenging when relying on monocular video, where disentangling structure from motion is ill-posed and supervision is scarce. We introduce Video Diffusion-Aware Reconstruction (ViDAR), a novel 4D reconstruction framework that leverages personalised diffusion models to synthesise a pseudo multi-view supervision signal for training a Gaussian splatting representation. By conditioning on scene-specific features, ViDAR recovers fine-grained appearance details while mitigating artefacts introduced by monocular ambiguity. To address the spatio-temporal inconsistency of diffusion-based supervision, we propose a diffusion-aware loss function and a camera pose optimisation strategy that aligns synthetic views with the underlying scene geometry. Experiments on DyCheck, a challenging benchmark with extreme viewpoint variation, show that ViDAR outperforms all state-of-the-art baselines in visual quality and geometric consistency. We further highlight ViDAR's strong improvement over baselines on dynamic regions and provide a new benchmark to compare performance in reconstructing motion-rich parts of the scene. Project page: https://vidar-4d.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18792</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 16:01:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LongWriter-Zero: Mastering Ultra-Long Text Generation via Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18841</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18841.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhao Wu, Yushi Bai, Zhiqiang Hu, Roy Ka-Wei Lee, Juanzi Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 39&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Ultra-long generation by large language models (LLMs) is a widely demanded scenario, yet it remains a significant challenge due to their maximum generation length limit and overall quality degradation as sequence length increases. Previous approaches, exemplified by LongWriter, typically rely on ''teaching'', which involves supervised fine-tuning (SFT) on synthetic long-form outputs. However, this strategy heavily depends on synthetic SFT data, which is difficult and costly to construct, often lacks coherence and consistency, and tends to be overly artificial and structurally monotonous. In this work, we propose an incentivization-based approach that, starting entirely from scratch and without relying on any annotated or synthetic data, leverages reinforcement learning (RL) to foster the emergence of ultra-long, high-quality text generation capabilities in LLMs. We perform RL training starting from a base model, similar to R1-Zero, guiding it to engage in reasoning that facilitates planning and refinement during the writing process. To support this, we employ specialized reward models that steer the LLM towards improved length control, writing quality, and structural formatting. Experimental evaluations show that our LongWriter-Zero model, trained from Qwen2.5-32B, consistently outperforms traditional SFT methods on long-form writing tasks, achieving state-of-the-art results across all metrics on WritingBench and Arena-Write, and even surpassing 100B+ models such as DeepSeek R1 and Qwen3-235B. We open-source our data and model checkpoints under https://huggingface.co/THU-KEG/LongWriter-Zero-32B&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18841</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 16:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phantom-Data : Towards a General Subject-Consistent Video Generation   Dataset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18851</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18851.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuowei Chen, Bingchuan Li, Tianxiang Ma, Lijie Liu, Mingcong Liu, Yi Zhang, Gen Li, Xinghui Li, Siyu Zhou, Qian He, Xinglong Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Subject-to-video generation has witnessed substantial progress in recent years. However, existing models still face significant challenges in faithfully following textual instructions. This limitation, commonly known as the copy-paste problem, arises from the widely used in-pair training paradigm. This approach inherently entangles subject identity with background and contextual attributes by sampling reference images from the same scene as the target video. To address this issue, we introduce Phantom-Data, the first general-purpose cross-pair subject-to-video consistency dataset, containing approximately one million identity-consistent pairs across diverse categories. Our dataset is constructed via a three-stage pipeline: (1) a general and input-aligned subject detection module, (2) large-scale cross-context subject retrieval from more than 53 million videos and 3 billion images, and (3) prior-guided identity verification to ensure visual consistency under contextual variation. Comprehensive experiments show that training with Phantom-Data significantly improves prompt alignment and visual quality while preserving identity consistency on par with in-pair baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18851</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:11:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniGen2: Exploration to Advanced Multimodal Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18871</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18871.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenyuan Wu, Pengfei Zheng, Ruiran Yan, Shitao Xiao, Xin Luo, Yueze Wang, Wanli Li, Xiyan Jiang, Yexin Liu, Junjie Zhou, Ze Liu, Ziyi Xia, Chaofan Li, Haoge Deng, Jiahao Wang, Kun Luo, Bo Zhang, Defu Lian, Xinlong Wang, Zhongyuan Wang, Tiejun Huang, Zheng Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we introduce OmniGen2, a versatile and open-source generative model designed to provide a unified solution for diverse generation tasks, including text-to-image, image editing, and in-context generation. Unlike OmniGen v1, OmniGen2 features two distinct decoding pathways for text and image modalities, utilizing unshared parameters and a decoupled image tokenizer. This design enables OmniGen2 to build upon existing multimodal understanding models without the need to re-adapt VAE inputs, thereby preserving the original text generation capabilities. To facilitate the training of OmniGen2, we developed comprehensive data construction pipelines, encompassing image editing and in-context generation data. Additionally, we introduce a reflection mechanism tailored for image generation tasks and curate a dedicated reflection dataset based on OmniGen2. Despite its relatively modest parameter size, OmniGen2 achieves competitive results on multiple task benchmarks, including text-to-image and image editing. To further evaluate in-context generation, also referred to as subject-driven tasks, we introduce a new benchmark named OmniContext. OmniGen2 achieves state-of-the-art performance among open-source models in terms of consistency. We will release our models, training code, datasets, and data construction pipeline to support future research in this field. Project Page: https://vectorspacelab.github.io/OmniGen2; GitHub Link: https://github.com/VectorSpaceLab/OmniGen2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18871</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:38:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CommVQ: Commutative Vector Quantization for KV Cache Compression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18879</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18879.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyan Li, Yang Zhang, Muhammad Yusuf Hassan, Talha Chafekar, Tianle Cai, Zhile Ren, Pengsheng Guo, Foroozan Karimzadeh, Colorado Reed, Chong Wang, Chuang Gan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly used in applications requiring long context lengths, but the key-value (KV) cache often becomes a memory bottleneck on GPUs as context grows. To address this, we propose Commutative Vector Quantization (CommVQ) to significantly reduce memory usage for long-context LLM inference. We first introduce additive quantization with a lightweight encoder and codebook to compress the KV cache, which can be decoded via simple matrix multiplication. To further reduce computational costs during decoding, we design the codebook to be commutative with Rotary Position Embedding (RoPE) and train it using an Expectation-Maximization (EM) algorithm. This enables efficient integration of decoding into the self-attention mechanism. Our approach achieves high accuracy with additive quantization and low overhead via the RoPE-commutative codebook. Experiments on long-context benchmarks and GSM8K show that our method reduces FP16 KV cache size by 87.5% with 2-bit quantization, while outperforming state-of-the-art KV cache quantization methods. Notably, it enables 1-bit KV cache quantization with minimal accuracy loss, allowing a LLaMA-3.1 8B model to run with a 128K context length on a single RTX 4090 GPU. The source code is available at: https://github.com/UMass-Embodied-AGI/CommVQ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18879</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:50:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light of Normals: Unified Feature Representation for Universal   Photometric Stereo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18882</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18882.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hong Li, Houyuan Chen, Chongjie Ye, Zhaoxi Chen, Bohan Li, Shaocong Xu, Xianda Guo, Xuhui Liu, Yikai Wang, Baochang Zhang, Satoshi Ikehata, Boxin Shi, Anyi Rao, Hao Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 68&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal photometric stereo (PS) aims to recover high-quality surface normals from objects under arbitrary lighting conditions without relying on specific illumination models. Despite recent advances such as SDM-UniPS and Uni MS-PS, two fundamental challenges persist: 1) the deep coupling between varying illumination and surface normal features, where ambiguity in observed intensity makes it difficult to determine whether brightness variations stem from lighting changes or surface orientation; and 2) the preservation of high-frequency geometric details in complex surfaces, where intricate geometries create self-shadowing, inter-reflections, and subtle normal variations that conventional feature processing operations struggle to capture accurately.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18882</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steering Conceptual Bias via Transformer Latent-Subspace Activation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18887</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18887.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vansh Sharma, Venkat Raman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This work examines whether activating latent subspaces in language models (LLMs) can steer scientific code generation toward a specific programming language. Five causal LLMs were first evaluated on scientific coding prompts to quantify their baseline bias among four programming languages. A static neuron-attribution method, perturbing the highest activated MLP weight for a C++ or CPP token, proved brittle and exhibited limited generalization across prompt styles and model scales. To address these limitations, a gradient-refined adaptive activation steering framework (G-ACT) was developed: per-prompt activation differences are clustered into a small set of steering directions, and lightweight per-layer probes are trained and refined online to select the appropriate steering vector. In LLaMA-3.2 3B, this approach reliably biases generation towards the CPP language by increasing the average probe classification accuracy by 15% and the early layers (0-6) improving the probe classification accuracy by 61.5% compared to the standard ACT framework. For LLaMA-3.3 70B, where attention-head signals become more diffuse, targeted injections at key layers still improve language selection. Although per-layer probing introduces a modest inference overhead, it remains practical by steering only a subset of layers and enables reproducible model behavior. These results demonstrate a scalable, interpretable and efficient mechanism for concept-level control for practical agentic systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18887</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:56:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4D-LRM: Large Space-Time Reconstruction Model From and To Any View at   Any Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18890</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18890.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziqiao Ma, Xuweiyi Chen, Shoubin Yu, Sai Bi, Kai Zhang, Chen Ziwen, Sihan Xu, Jianing Yang, Zexiang Xu, Kalyan Sunkavalli, Mohit Bansal, Joyce Chai, Hao Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Can we scale 4D pretraining to learn general space-time representations that reconstruct an object from a few views at some times to any view at any time? We provide an affirmative answer with 4D-LRM, the first large-scale 4D reconstruction model that takes input from unconstrained views and timestamps and renders arbitrary novel view-time combinations. Unlike prior 4D approaches, e.g., optimization-based, geometry-based, or generative, that struggle with efficiency, generalization, or faithfulness, 4D-LRM learns a unified space-time representation and directly predicts per-pixel 4D Gaussian primitives from posed image tokens across time, enabling fast, high-quality rendering at, in principle, infinite frame rate. Our results demonstrate that scaling spatiotemporal pretraining enables accurate and efficient 4D reconstruction. We show that 4D-LRM generalizes to novel objects, interpolates across time, and handles diverse camera setups. It reconstructs 24-frame sequences in one forward pass with less than 1.5 seconds on a single A100 GPU.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18890</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:57:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ReasonFlux-PRM: Trajectory-Aware PRMs for Long Chain-of-Thought   Reasoning in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18896</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18896.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaru Zou, Ling Yang, Jingwen Gu, Jiahao Qiu, Ke Shen, Jingrui He, Mengdi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Process Reward Models (PRMs) have recently emerged as a powerful framework for supervising intermediate reasoning steps in large language models (LLMs). Previous PRMs are primarily trained on model final output responses and struggle to evaluate intermediate thinking trajectories robustly, especially in the emerging setting of trajectory-response outputs generated by frontier reasoning models like Deepseek-R1. In this work, we introduce ReasonFlux-PRM, a novel trajectory-aware PRM explicitly designed to evaluate the trajectory-response type of reasoning traces. ReasonFlux-PRM incorporates both step-level and trajectory-level supervision, enabling fine-grained reward assignment aligned with structured chain-of-thought data. We adapt ReasonFlux-PRM to support reward supervision under both offline and online settings, including (i) selecting high-quality model distillation data for downstream supervised fine-tuning of smaller models, (ii) providing dense process-level rewards for policy optimization during reinforcement learning, and (iii) enabling reward-guided Best-of-N test-time scaling. Empirical results on challenging downstream benchmarks such as AIME, MATH500, and GPQA-Diamond demonstrate that ReasonFlux-PRM-7B selects higher quality data than strong PRMs (e.g., Qwen2.5-Math-PRM-72B) and human-curated baselines. Furthermore, our derived ReasonFlux-PRM-7B yields consistent performance improvements, achieving average gains of 12.1% in supervised fine-tuning, 4.5% in reinforcement learning, and 6.3% in test-time scaling. We also release our efficient ReasonFlux-PRM-1.5B for resource-constrained applications and edge deployment. Projects: https://github.com/Gen-Verse/ReasonFlux&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18896</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vision as a Dialect: Unifying Visual Understanding and Generation via   Text-Aligned Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18898</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18898.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaming Han, Hao Chen, Yang Zhao, Hanyu Wang, Qi Zhao, Ziyan Yang, Hao He, Xiangyu Yue, Lu Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper presents a multimodal framework that attempts to unify visual understanding and generation within a shared discrete semantic representation. At its core is the Text-Aligned Tokenizer (TA-Tok), which converts images into discrete tokens using a text-aligned codebook projected from a large language model's (LLM) vocabulary. By integrating vision and text into a unified space with an expanded vocabulary, our multimodal LLM, Tar, enables cross-modal input and output through a shared interface, without the need for modality-specific designs. Additionally, we propose scale-adaptive encoding and decoding to balance efficiency and visual detail, along with a generative de-tokenizer to produce high-fidelity visual outputs. To address diverse decoding needs, we utilize two complementary de-tokenizers: a fast autoregressive model and a diffusion-based model. To enhance modality fusion, we investigate advanced pre-training tasks, demonstrating improvements in both visual understanding and generation. Experiments across benchmarks show that Tar matches or surpasses existing multimodal LLM methods, achieving faster convergence and greater training efficiency. Code, models, and data are available at https://tar.csuhan.com&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18898</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Audit &amp; Repair: An Agentic Framework for Consistent Story Visualization   in Text-to-Image Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18900</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18900.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kiymet Akdemir, Tahira Kazimi, Pinar Yanardag&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Story visualization has become a popular task where visual scenes are generated to depict a narrative across multiple panels. A central challenge in this setting is maintaining visual consistency, particularly in how characters and objects persist and evolve throughout the story. Despite recent advances in diffusion models, current approaches often fail to preserve key character attributes, leading to incoherent narratives. In this work, we propose a collaborative multi-agent framework that autonomously identifies, corrects, and refines inconsistencies across multi-panel story visualizations. The agents operate in an iterative loop, enabling fine-grained, panel-level updates without re-generating entire sequences. Our framework is model-agnostic and flexibly integrates with a variety of diffusion models, including rectified flow transformers such as Flux and latent diffusion models such as Stable Diffusion. Quantitative and qualitative experiments show that our method outperforms prior approaches in terms of multi-panel consistency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18900</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Virtual Games to Real-World Play</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18901</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18901.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenqiang Sun, Fangyun Wei, Jinjing Zhao, Xi Chen, Zilong Chen, Hongyang Zhang, Jun Zhang, Yan Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce RealPlay, a neural network-based real-world game engine that enables interactive video generation from user control signals. Unlike prior works focused on game-style visuals, RealPlay aims to produce photorealistic, temporally consistent video sequences that resemble real-world footage. It operates in an interactive loop: users observe a generated scene, issue a control command, and receive a short video chunk in response. To enable such realistic and responsive generation, we address key challenges including iterative chunk-wise prediction for low-latency feedback, temporal consistency across iterations, and accurate control response. RealPlay is trained on a combination of labeled game data and unlabeled real-world videos, without requiring real-world action annotations. Notably, we observe two forms of generalization: (1) control transfer-RealPlay effectively maps control signals from virtual to real-world scenarios; and (2) entity transfer-although training labels originate solely from a car racing game, RealPlay generalizes to control diverse real-world entities, including bicycles and pedestrians, beyond vehicles. Project page can be found: https://wenqsun.github.io/RealPlay/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18901</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VMem: Consistent Interactive Video Scene Generation with Surfel-Indexed   View Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18903</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18903.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runjia Li, Philip Torr, Andrea Vedaldi, Tomas Jakab&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel memory mechanism to build video generators that can explore environments interactively. Similar results have previously been achieved by out-painting 2D views of the scene while incrementally reconstructing its 3D geometry, which quickly accumulates errors, or by video generators with a short context window, which struggle to maintain scene coherence over the long term. To address these limitations, we introduce Surfel-Indexed View Memory (VMem), a mechanism that remembers past views by indexing them geometrically based on the 3D surface elements (surfels) they have observed. VMem enables the efficient retrieval of the most relevant past views when generating new ones. By focusing only on these relevant views, our method produces consistent explorations of imagined environments at a fraction of the computational cost of using all past views as context. We evaluate our approach on challenging long-term scene synthesis benchmarks and demonstrate superior performance compared to existing methods in maintaining scene coherence and camera control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18903</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TC-Light: Temporally Consistent Relighting for Dynamic Long Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18904</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.18904.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Liu, Chuanchen Luo, Zimo Tang, Yingyan Li, Yuran Yang, Yuanyong Ning, Lue Fan, Junran Peng, Zhaoxiang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Editing illumination in long videos with complex dynamics has significant value in various downstream tasks, including visual content creation and manipulation, as well as data scaling up for embodied AI through sim2real and real2real transfer. Nevertheless, existing video relighting techniques are predominantly limited to portrait videos or fall into the bottleneck of temporal consistency and computation efficiency. In this paper, we propose TC-Light, a novel paradigm characterized by the proposed two-stage post optimization mechanism. Starting from the video preliminarily relighted by an inflated video relighting model, it optimizes appearance embedding in the first stage to align global illumination. Then it optimizes the proposed canonical video representation, i.e., Unique Video Tensor (UVT), to align fine-grained texture and lighting in the second stage. To comprehensively evaluate performance, we also establish a long and highly dynamic video benchmark. Extensive experiments show that our method enables physically plausible relighting results with superior temporal coherence and low computation cost. The code and video demos are available at https://dekuliutesla.github.io/tclight/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18904</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 17:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
