<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:02:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>AI Agent Behavioral Science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06366</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.06366.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lin Chen, Yunke Zhang, Jie Feng, Haoye Chai, Honglin Zhang, Bingbing Fan, Yibo Ma, Shiyuan Zhang, Nian Li, Tianhui Liu, Nicholas Sukiennik, Keyu Zhao, Yu Li, Ziyi Liu, Fengli Xu, Yong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have enabled the development of AI agents that exhibit increasingly human-like behaviors, including planning, adaptation, and social dynamics across diverse, interactive, and open-ended scenarios. These behaviors are not solely the product of the internal architectures of the underlying models, but emerge from their integration into agentic systems operating within specific contexts, where environmental factors, social cues, and interaction feedbacks shape behavior over time. This evolution necessitates a new scientific perspective: AI Agent Behavioral Science. Rather than focusing only on internal mechanisms, this perspective emphasizes the systematic observation of behavior, design of interventions to test hypotheses, and theory-guided interpretation of how AI agents act, adapt, and interact over time. We systematize a growing body of research across individual agent, multi-agent, and human-agent interaction settings, and further demonstrate how this perspective informs responsible AI by treating fairness, safety, interpretability, accountability, and privacy as behavioral properties. By unifying recent findings and laying out future directions, we position AI Agent Behavioral Science as a necessary complement to traditional model-centric approaches, providing essential tools for understanding, evaluating, and governing the real-world behavior of increasingly autonomous AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06366</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 08:12:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Real to Synthetic: Synthesizing Millions of Diversified and   Complicated User Instructions with Attributed Grounding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03968</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.03968.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chiwei Zhu, Benfeng Xu, Xiaorui Wang, Zhendong Mao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The pursuit of diverse, complex, and large-scale instruction data is crucial for automatically aligning large language models (LLMs). While there are methods capable of generating synthetic instructions at scale, they either suffer from limited grounding sources, leading to a narrow distribution, or rely on trivial extensions that fail to produce meaningful trajectories in terms of complexity. In contrast, instructions that benefit efficient alignment are typically crafted with cognitive insights and grounded in real-world use cases. In this paper, we synthesize such instructions using attributed grounding, which involves 1) a top-down attribution process that grounds a selective set of real instructions to situated users, and 2) a bottom-up synthesis process that leverages web documents to first generate a situation, then a meaningful instruction. This framework allows us to harvest diverse and complex instructions at scale, utilizing the vast range of web documents. Specifically, we construct a dataset of 1 million instructions, called SynthQuestions, and demonstrate that models trained on it achieve leading performance on several common benchmarks, with improvements that continually scale with more web corpora. Data, models and codes will be available at https://github.com/Ignoramus0817/SynthQuestions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03968</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 14:00:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LETS Forecast: Learning Embedology for Time Series Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06454</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.06454.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abrar Majeedi, Viswanatha Reddy Gajjala, Satya Sai Srinath Namburi GNVV, Nada Magdi Elkordi, Yin Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Real-world time series are often governed by complex nonlinear dynamics. Understanding these underlying dynamics is crucial for precise future prediction. While deep learning has achieved major success in time series forecasting, many existing approaches do not explicitly model the dynamics. To bridge this gap, we introduce DeepEDM, a framework that integrates nonlinear dynamical systems modeling with deep neural networks. Inspired by empirical dynamic modeling (EDM) and rooted in Takens' theorem, DeepEDM presents a novel deep model that learns a latent space from time-delayed embeddings, and employs kernel regression to approximate the underlying dynamics, while leveraging efficient implementation of softmax attention and allowing for accurate prediction of future time steps. To evaluate our method, we conduct comprehensive experiments on synthetic data of nonlinear dynamical systems as well as real-world time series across domains. Our results show that DeepEDM is robust to input noise, and outperforms state-of-the-art methods in forecasting accuracy. Our code is available at: https://abrarmajeedi.github.io/deep_edm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06454</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 18:24:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AR-RAG: Autoregressive Retrieval Augmentation for Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06962</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.06962.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingyuan Qi, Zhiyang Xu, Qifan Wang, Lifu Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Autoregressive Retrieval Augmentation (AR-RAG), a novel paradigm that enhances image generation by autoregressively incorporating knearest neighbor retrievals at the patch level. Unlike prior methods that perform a single, static retrieval before generation and condition the entire generation on fixed reference images, AR-RAG performs context-aware retrievals at each generation step, using prior-generated patches as queries to retrieve and incorporate the most relevant patch-level visual references, enabling the model to respond to evolving generation needs while avoiding limitations (e.g., over-copying, stylistic bias, etc.) prevalent in existing methods. To realize AR-RAG, we propose two parallel frameworks: (1) Distribution-Augmentation in Decoding (DAiD), a training-free plug-and-use decoding strategy that directly merges the distribution of model-predicted patches with the distribution of retrieved patches, and (2) Feature-Augmentation in Decoding (FAiD), a parameter-efficient fine-tuning method that progressively smooths the features of retrieved patches via multi-scale convolution operations and leverages them to augment the image generation process. We validate the effectiveness of AR-RAG on widely adopted benchmarks, including Midjourney-30K, GenEval and DPG-Bench, demonstrating significant performance gains over state-of-the-art image generation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06962</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 01:33:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incorporating Domain Knowledge into Materials Tokenization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11115</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.11115.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yerim Oh, Jun-Hyung Park, Junho Kim, SungHo Kim, SangKeun Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While language models are increasingly utilized in materials science, typical models rely on frequency-centric tokenization methods originally developed for natural language processing. However, these methods frequently produce excessive fragmentation and semantic loss, failing to maintain the structural and semantic integrity of material concepts. To address this issue, we propose MATTER, a novel tokenization approach that integrates material knowledge into tokenization. Based on MatDetector trained on our materials knowledge base and a re-ranking method prioritizing material concepts in token merging, MATTER maintains the structural integrity of identified material concepts and prevents fragmentation during tokenization, ensuring their semantic meaning remains intact. The experimental results demonstrate that MATTER outperforms existing tokenization methods, achieving an average performance gain of 4% and 2% in the generation and classification tasks, respectively. These results underscore the importance of domain knowledge for tokenization strategies in scientific text processing. Our code is available at https://github.com/yerimoh/MATTER&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11115</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 04:59:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BridgeVLA: Input-Output Alignment for Efficient 3D Manipulation Learning   with Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07961</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.07961.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peiyan Li, Yixiang Chen, Hongtao Wu, Xiao Ma, Xiangnan Wu, Yan Huang, Liang Wang, Tao Kong, Tieniu Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, leveraging pre-trained vision-language models (VLMs) for building vision-language-action (VLA) models has emerged as a promising approach to effective robot manipulation learning. However, only few methods incorporate 3D signals into VLMs for action prediction, and they do not fully leverage the spatial structure inherent in 3D data, leading to low sample efficiency. In this paper, we introduce BridgeVLA, a novel 3D VLA model that (1) projects 3D inputs to multiple 2D images, ensuring input alignment with the VLM backbone, and (2) utilizes 2D heatmaps for action prediction, unifying the input and output spaces within a consistent 2D image space. In addition, we propose a scalable pre-training method that equips the VLM backbone with the capability to predict 2D heatmaps before downstream policy learning. Extensive experiments show the proposed method is able to learn 3D manipulation efficiently and effectively. BridgeVLA outperforms state-of-the-art baseline methods across three simulation benchmarks. In RLBench, it improves the average success rate from 81.4% to 88.2%. In COLOSSEUM, it demonstrates significantly better performance in challenging generalization settings, boosting the average success rate from 56.7% to 64.0%. In GemBench, it surpasses all the comparing baseline methods in terms of average success rate. In real-robot experiments, BridgeVLA outperforms a state-of-the-art baseline method by 32% on average. It generalizes robustly in multiple out-of-distribution settings, including visual disturbances and unseen instructions. Remarkably, it is able to achieve a success rate of 96.8% on 10+ tasks with only 3 trajectories per task, highlighting its extraordinary sample efficiency. Project Website:https://bridgevla.github.io/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07961</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 17:36:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wait, We Don't Need to "Wait"! Removing Thinking Tokens Improves   Reasoning Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08343</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.08343.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chenlong Wang, Yuanning Feng, Dongping Chen, Zhaoyang Chu, Ranjay Krishna, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 30&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large reasoning models have enabled complex, step-by-step reasoning but often introduce significant overthinking, resulting in verbose and redundant outputs that hinder efficiency. In this study, we examine whether explicit self-reflection, signaled by tokens such as "Wait" and "Hmm", is necessary for advanced reasoning. We propose NoWait, a simple yet effective approach that disables explicit self-reflection by suppressing these tokens during inference. Extensive experiments on ten benchmarks across textual, visual, and video reasoning tasks show that NoWait reduces chain-of-thought trajectory length by up to 27%-51% in five R1-style model series, without compromising model utility. NoWait thus offers a plug-and-play solution for efficient and utility-preserving multimodal reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08343</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 01:54:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ALE-Bench: A Benchmark for Long-Horizon Objective-Driven Algorithm   Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09050</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.09050.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuki Imajuku, Kohki Horie, Yoichi Iwata, Kensho Aoki, Naohiro Takahashi, Takuya Akiba&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; How well do AI systems perform in algorithm engineering for hard optimization problems in domains such as package-delivery routing, crew scheduling, factory production planning, and power-grid balancing? We introduce ALE-Bench, a new benchmark for evaluating AI systems on score-based algorithmic programming contests. Drawing on real tasks from the AtCoder Heuristic Contests, ALE-Bench presents optimization problems that are computationally hard and admit no known exact solution. Unlike short-duration, pass/fail coding benchmarks, ALE-Bench encourages iterative solution refinement over long time horizons. Our software framework supports interactive agent architectures that leverage test-run feedback and visualizations. Our evaluation of frontier LLMs revealed that while they demonstrate high performance on specific problems, a notable gap remains compared to humans in terms of consistency across problems and long-horizon problem-solving capabilities. This highlights the need for this benchmark to foster future AI advancements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09050</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 17:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marrying Autoregressive Transformer and Diffusion with Multi-Reference   Autoregression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09482</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.09482.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dingcheng Zhen, Qian Qiao, Tan Yu, Kangxi Wu, Ziwei Zhang, Siyuan Liu, Shunshun Yin, Ming Tao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 23&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce TransDiff, the first image generation model that marries Autoregressive (AR) Transformer with diffusion models. In this joint modeling framework, TransDiff encodes labels and images into high-level semantic features and employs a diffusion model to estimate the distribution of image samples. On the ImageNet 256x256 benchmark, TransDiff significantly outperforms other image generation models based on standalone AR Transformer or diffusion models. Specifically, TransDiff achieves a Fr\'echet Inception Distance (FID) of 1.61 and an Inception Score (IS) of 293.4, and further provides x2 faster inference latency compared to state-of-the-art methods based on AR Transformer and x112 faster inference compared to diffusion-only models. Furthermore, building on the TransDiff model, we introduce a novel image generation paradigm called Multi-Reference Autoregression (MRAR), which performs autoregressive generation by predicting the next image. MRAR enables the model to reference multiple previously generated images, thereby facilitating the learning of more diverse representations and improving the quality of generated images in subsequent iterations. By applying MRAR, the performance of TransDiff is improved, with the FID reduced from 1.61 to 1.42. We expect TransDiff to open up a new frontier in the field of image generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09482</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 07:50:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SRLAgent: Enhancing Self-Regulated Learning Skills through Gamification   and LLM Assistance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09968</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.09968.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wentao Ge, Yuqing Sun, Ziyan Wang, Haoyue Zheng, Weiyang He, Piaohong Wang, Qianyu Zhu, Benyou Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Self-regulated learning (SRL) is crucial for college students navigating increased academic demands and independence. Insufficient SRL skills can lead to disorganized study habits, low motivation, and poor time management, undermining learners ability to thrive in challenging environments. Through a formative study involving 59 college students, we identified key challenges students face in developing SRL skills, including difficulties with goal-setting, time management, and reflective learning. To address these challenges, we introduce SRLAgent, an LLM-assisted system that fosters SRL skills through gamification and adaptive support from large language models (LLMs). Grounded in Zimmermans three-phase SRL framework, SRLAgent enables students to engage in goal-setting, strategy execution, and self-reflection within an interactive game-based environment. The system offers real-time feedback and scaffolding powered by LLMs to support students independent study efforts. We evaluated SRLAgent using a between-subjects design, comparing it to a baseline system (SRL without Agent features) and a traditional multimedia learning condition. Results showed significant improvements in SRL skills within the SRLAgent group (p &lt; .001, Cohens d = 0.234) and higher engagement compared to the baselines. This work highlights the value of embedding SRL scaffolding and real-time AI support within gamified environments, offering design implications for educational technologies that aim to promote deeper learning and metacognitive skill development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09968</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 17:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TaskCraft: Automated Generation of Agentic Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10055</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.10055.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dingfeng Shi, Jingyi Cao, Qianben Chen, Weichen Sun, Weizhen Li, Hongxuan Lu, Fangchen Dong, Tianrui Qin, King Zhu, Minghao Yang, Jian Yang, Ge Zhang, Jiaheng Liu, Changwang Zhang, Jun Wang, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agentic tasks, which require multi-step problem solving with autonomy, tool use, and adaptive reasoning, are becoming increasingly central to the advancement of NLP and AI. However, existing instruction data lacks tool interaction, and current agentic benchmarks rely on costly human annotation, limiting their scalability. We introduce TaskCraft, an automated workflow for generating difficulty-scalable, multi-tool, and verifiable agentic tasks with execution trajectories. TaskCraft expands atomic tasks using depth-based and width-based extensions to create structurally and hierarchically complex challenges. Empirical results show that these tasks improve prompt optimization in the generation workflow and enhance supervised fine-tuning of agentic foundation models. We present a large-scale synthetic dataset of approximately 36,000 tasks with varying difficulty to support future research on agent tuning and evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10055</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 17:58:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provably Learning from Language Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10341</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.10341.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wanqiao Xu, Allen Nie, Ruijie Zheng, Aditya Modi, Adith Swaminathan, Ching-An Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Interactively learning from observation and language feedback is an increasingly studied area driven by the emergence of large language model (LLM) agents. While impressive empirical demonstrations have been shown, so far a principled framing of these decision problems remains lacking. In this paper, we formalize the Learning from Language Feedback (LLF) problem, assert sufficient assumptions to enable learning despite latent rewards, and introduce transfer eluder dimension as a complexity measure to characterize the hardness of LLF problems. We show that transfer eluder dimension captures the intuition that information in the feedback changes the learning complexity of the LLF problem. We demonstrate cases where learning from rich language feedback can be exponentially faster than learning from reward. We develop a no-regret algorithm, called HELiX, that provably solves LLF problems through sequential interactions, with performance guarantees that scale with the transfer eluder dimension of the problem. Across several empirical domains, we show that HELiX performs well even when repeatedly prompting LLMs does not work reliably. Our contributions mark a first step towards designing principled interactive learning algorithms from generic language feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10341</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 04:35:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scientists' First Exam: Probing Cognitive Abilities of MLLM via   Perception, Understanding, and Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10521</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.10521.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuhao Zhou, Yiheng Wang, Xuming He, Ruoyao Xiao, Zhiwei Li, Qiantai Feng, Zijie Guo, Yuejin Yang, Hao Wu, Wenxuan Huang, Jiaqi Wei, Dan Si, Xiuqi Yao, Jia Bu, Haiwen Huang, Tianfan Fu, Shixiang Tang, Ben Fei, Dongzhan Zhou, Fenghua Ling, Yan Lu, Siqi Sun, Chenhui Li, Guanjie Zheng, Jiancheng Lv, Wenlong Zhang, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scientific discoveries increasingly rely on complex multimodal reasoning based on information-intensive scientific data and domain-specific expertise. Empowered by expert-level scientific benchmarks, scientific Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) hold the potential to significantly enhance this discovery process in realistic workflows. However, current scientific benchmarks mostly focus on evaluating the knowledge understanding capabilities of MLLMs, leading to an inadequate assessment of their perception and reasoning abilities. To address this gap, we present the Scientists' First Exam (SFE) benchmark, designed to evaluate the scientific cognitive capacities of MLLMs through three interconnected levels: scientific signal perception, scientific attribute understanding, scientific comparative reasoning. Specifically, SFE comprises 830 expert-verified VQA pairs across three question types, spanning 66 multimodal tasks across five high-value disciplines. Extensive experiments reveal that current state-of-the-art GPT-o3 and InternVL-3 achieve only 34.08% and 26.52% on SFE, highlighting significant room for MLLMs to improve in scientific realms. We hope the insights obtained in SFE will facilitate further developments in AI-enhanced scientific discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10521</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 09:29:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepResearch Bench: A Comprehensive Benchmark for Deep Research Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11763</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.11763.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingxuan Du, Benfeng Xu, Chiwei Zhu, Xiaorui Wang, Zhendong Mao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 43&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Deep Research Agents are a prominent category of LLM-based agents. By autonomously orchestrating multistep web exploration, targeted retrieval, and higher-order synthesis, they transform vast amounts of online information into analyst-grade, citation-rich reports--compressing hours of manual desk research into minutes. However, a comprehensive benchmark for systematically evaluating the capabilities of these agents remains absent. To bridge this gap, we present DeepResearch Bench, a benchmark consisting of 100 PhD-level research tasks, each meticulously crafted by domain experts across 22 distinct fields. Evaluating DRAs is inherently complex and labor-intensive. We therefore propose two novel methodologies that achieve strong alignment with human judgment. The first is a reference-based method with adaptive criteria to assess the quality of generated research reports. The other framework is introduced to evaluate DRA's information retrieval and collection capabilities by assessing its effective citation count and overall citation accuracy. We have open-sourced DeepResearch Bench and key components of these frameworks at https://github.com/Ayanami0730/deep_research_bench to accelerate the development of practical LLM-based agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11763</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 13:17:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VGR: Visual Grounded Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11991</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.11991.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiacong Wang, Zijiang Kang, Haochen Wang, Haiyong Jiang, Jiawen Li, Bohong Wu, Ya Wang, Jiao Ran, Xiao Liang, Chao Feng, Jun Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In the field of multimodal chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning, existing approaches predominantly rely on reasoning on pure language space, which inherently suffers from language bias and is largely confined to math or science domains. This narrow focus limits their ability to handle complex visual reasoning tasks that demand comprehensive understanding of image details. To address these limitations, this paper introduces VGR, a novel reasoning multimodal large language model (MLLM) with enhanced fine-grained visual perception capabilities. Unlike traditional MLLMs that answer the question or reasoning solely on the language space, our VGR first detects relevant regions that may help to solve problems, and then provides precise answers based on replayed image regions. To achieve this, we conduct a large-scale SFT dataset called VGR -SFT that contains reasoning data with mixed vision grounding and language deduction. The inference pipeline of VGR allows the model to choose bounding boxes for visual reference and a replay stage is introduced to integrates the corresponding regions into the reasoning process, enhancing multimodel comprehension. Experiments on the LLaVA-NeXT-7B baseline show that VGR achieves superior performance on multi-modal benchmarks requiring comprehensive image detail understanding. Compared to the baseline, VGR uses only 30\% of the image token count while delivering scores of +4.1 on MMStar, +7.1 on AI2D, and a +12.9 improvement on ChartQA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11991</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 17:47:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hatevolution: What Static Benchmarks Don't Tell Us</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12148</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12148.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chiara Di Bonaventura, Barbara McGillivray, Yulan He, Albert Meroño-Peñuela&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Language changes over time, including in the hate speech domain, which evolves quickly following social dynamics and cultural shifts. While NLP research has investigated the impact of language evolution on model training and has proposed several solutions for it, its impact on model benchmarking remains under-explored. Yet, hate speech benchmarks play a crucial role to ensure model safety. In this paper, we empirically evaluate the robustness of 20 language models across two evolving hate speech experiments, and we show the temporal misalignment between static and time-sensitive evaluations. Our findings call for time-sensitive linguistic benchmarks in order to correctly and reliably evaluate language models in the hate speech domain.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12148</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 18:08:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supernova Event Dataset: Interpreting Large Language Model's Personality   through Critical Event Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12189</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12189.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pranav Agarwal, Ioana Ciucă&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) are increasingly integrated into everyday applications. As their influence grows, understanding their decision making and underlying personality becomes essential. In this work, we interpret model personality using our proposed Supernova Event Dataset, a novel dataset with diverse articles spanning biographies, historical events, news, and scientific discoveries. We use this dataset to benchmark LLMs on extracting and ranking key events from text, a subjective and complex challenge that requires reasoning over long-range context and modeling causal chains. We evaluate small models like Phi-4, Orca 2, and Qwen 2.5, and large, stronger models such as Claude 3.7, Gemini 2.5, and OpenAI o3, and propose a framework where another LLM acts as a judge to infer each model's personality based on its selection and classification of events. Our analysis shows distinct personality traits: for instance, Orca 2 demonstrates emotional reasoning focusing on interpersonal dynamics, while Qwen 2.5 displays a more strategic, analytical style. When analyzing scientific discovery events, Claude Sonnet 3.7 emphasizes conceptual framing, Gemini 2.5 Pro prioritizes empirical validation, and o3 favors step-by-step causal reasoning. This analysis improves model interpretability, making them user-friendly for a wide range of diverse applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12189</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 19:31:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EgoPrivacy: What Your First-Person Camera Says About You?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12258</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12258.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yijiang Li, Genpei Zhang, Jiacheng Cheng, Yi Li, Xiaojun Shan, Dashan Gao, Jiancheng Lyu, Yuan Li, Ning Bi, Nuno Vasconcelos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While the rapid proliferation of wearable cameras has raised significant concerns about egocentric video privacy, prior work has largely overlooked the unique privacy threats posed to the camera wearer. This work investigates the core question: How much privacy information about the camera wearer can be inferred from their first-person view videos? We introduce EgoPrivacy, the first large-scale benchmark for the comprehensive evaluation of privacy risks in egocentric vision. EgoPrivacy covers three types of privacy (demographic, individual, and situational), defining seven tasks that aim to recover private information ranging from fine-grained (e.g., wearer's identity) to coarse-grained (e.g., age group). To further emphasize the privacy threats inherent to egocentric vision, we propose Retrieval-Augmented Attack, a novel attack strategy that leverages ego-to-exo retrieval from an external pool of exocentric videos to boost the effectiveness of demographic privacy attacks. An extensive comparison of the different attacks possible under all threat models is presented, showing that private information of the wearer is highly susceptible to leakage. For instance, our findings indicate that foundation models can effectively compromise wearer privacy even in zero-shot settings by recovering attributes such as identity, scene, gender, and race with 70-80% accuracy. Our code and data are available at https://github.com/williamium3000/ego-privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12258</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 22:19:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QGuard:Question-based Zero-shot Guard for Multi-modal LLM Safety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12299</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12299.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Taegyeong Lee, Jeonghwa Yoo, Hyoungseo Cho, Soo Yong Kim, Yunho Maeng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The recent advancements in Large Language Models(LLMs) have had a significant impact on a wide range of fields, from general domains to specialized areas. However, these advancements have also significantly increased the potential for malicious users to exploit harmful and jailbreak prompts for malicious attacks. Although there have been many efforts to prevent harmful prompts and jailbreak prompts, protecting LLMs from such malicious attacks remains an important and challenging task. In this paper, we propose QGuard, a simple yet effective safety guard method, that utilizes question prompting to block harmful prompts in a zero-shot manner. Our method can defend LLMs not only from text-based harmful prompts but also from multi-modal harmful prompt attacks. Moreover, by diversifying and modifying guard questions, our approach remains robust against the latest harmful prompts without fine-tuning. Experimental results show that our model performs competitively on both text-only and multi-modal harmful datasets. Additionally, by providing an analysis of question prompting, we enable a white-box analysis of user inputs. We believe our method provides valuable insights for real-world LLM services in mitigating security risks associated with harmful prompts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12299</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 01:23:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Language Surgery in Multilingual Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12450</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12450.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Joanito Agili Lopo, Muhammad Ravi Shulthan Habibi, Tack Hwa Wong, Muhammad Ilham Ghozali, Fajri Koto, Genta Indra Winata, Peerat Limkonchotiwat, Alham Fikri Aji, Samuel Cahyawijaya&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated remarkable generalization capabilities across tasks and languages, revolutionizing natural language processing. This paper investigates the naturally emerging representation alignment in LLMs, particularly in the middle layers, and its implications for disentangling language-specific and language-agnostic information. We empirically confirm the existence of this alignment, analyze its behavior in comparison to explicitly designed alignment models, and demonstrate its potential for language-specific manipulation without semantic degradation. Building on these findings, we propose Inference-Time Language Control (ITLC), a novel method that leverages latent injection to enable precise cross-lingual language control and mitigate language confusion in LLMs. Our experiments highlight ITLC's strong cross-lingual control capabilities while preserving semantic integrity in target languages. Furthermore, we demonstrate its effectiveness in alleviating the cross-lingual language confusion problem, which persists even in current large-scale LLMs, leading to inconsistent language generation. This work advances our understanding of representation alignment in LLMs and introduces a practical solution for enhancing their cross-lingual performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12450</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 11:09:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Profiling News Media for Factuality and Bias Using LLMs and the   Fact-Checking Methodology of Human Experts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12552</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12552.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zain Muhammad Mujahid, Dilshod Azizov, Maha Tufail Agro, Preslav Nakov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In an age characterized by the proliferation of mis- and disinformation online, it is critical to empower readers to understand the content they are reading. Important efforts in this direction rely on manual or automatic fact-checking, which can be challenging for emerging claims with limited information. Such scenarios can be handled by assessing the reliability and the political bias of the source of the claim, i.e., characterizing entire news outlets rather than individual claims or articles. This is an important but understudied research direction. While prior work has looked into linguistic and social contexts, we do not analyze individual articles or information in social media. Instead, we propose a novel methodology that emulates the criteria that professional fact-checkers use to assess the factuality and political bias of an entire outlet. Specifically, we design a variety of prompts based on these criteria and elicit responses from large language models (LLMs), which we aggregate to make predictions. In addition to demonstrating sizable improvements over strong baselines via extensive experiments with multiple LLMs, we provide an in-depth error analysis of the effect of media popularity and region on model performance. Further, we conduct an ablation study to highlight the key components of our dataset that contribute to these improvements. To facilitate future research, we released our dataset and code at https://github.com/mbzuai-nlp/llm-media-profiling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12552</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 15:49:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DoTA-RAG: Dynamic of Thought Aggregation RAG</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12571</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12571.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Saksorn Ruangtanusak, Natthapath Rungseesiripak, Peerawat Rojratchadakorn, Monthol Charattrakool, Natapong Nitarach&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce DoTA-RAG (Dynamic-of-Thought Aggregation RAG), a retrieval-augmented generation system optimized for high-throughput, large-scale web knowledge indexes. Traditional RAG pipelines often suffer from high latency and limited accuracy over massive, diverse datasets. DoTA-RAG addresses these challenges with a three-stage pipeline: query rewriting, dynamic routing to specialized sub-indexes, and multi-stage retrieval and ranking. We further enhance retrieval by evaluating and selecting a superior embedding model, re-embedding the large FineWeb-10BT corpus. Moreover, we create a diverse Q&amp;A dataset of 500 questions generated via the DataMorgana setup across a broad range of WebOrganizer topics and formats. DoTA-RAG improves the answer correctness score from 0.752 (baseline, using LiveRAG pre-built vector store) to 1.478 while maintaining low latency, and it achieves a 0.929 correctness score on the Live Challenge Day. These results highlight DoTA-RAG's potential for practical deployment in domains requiring fast, reliable access to large and evolving knowledge sources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12571</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 16:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MS4UI: A Dataset for Multi-modal Summarization of User Interface   Instructional Videos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12623</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12623.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuan Zang, Hao Tan, Seunghyun Yoon, Franck Dernoncourt, Jiuxiang Gu, Kushal Kafle, Chen Sun, Trung Bui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We study multi-modal summarization for instructional videos, whose goal is to provide users an efficient way to learn skills in the form of text instructions and key video frames. We observe that existing benchmarks focus on generic semantic-level video summarization, and are not suitable for providing step-by-step executable instructions and illustrations, both of which are crucial for instructional videos. We propose a novel benchmark for user interface (UI) instructional video summarization to fill the gap. We collect a dataset of 2,413 UI instructional videos, which spans over 167 hours. These videos are manually annotated for video segmentation, text summarization, and video summarization, which enable the comprehensive evaluations for concise and executable video summarization. We conduct extensive experiments on our collected MS4UI dataset, which suggest that state-of-the-art multi-modal summarization methods struggle on UI video summarization, and highlight the importance of new methods for UI instructional video summarization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12623</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 20:39:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PersonaFeedback: A Large-scale Human-annotated Benchmark For   Personalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12915</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12915.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Meiling Tao, Chenghao Zhu, Dongyi Ding, Tiannan Wang, Yuchen Eleanor Jiang, Wangchunshu Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; With the rapid improvement in the general capabilities of LLMs, LLM personalization, i.e., how to build LLM systems that can generate personalized responses or services that are tailored to distinct user personas, has become an increasingly important research and engineering problem. However, unlike many new challenging benchmarks being released for evaluating the general/reasoning capabilities, the lack of high-quality benchmarks for evaluating LLM personalization greatly hinders progress in this field. To address this, we introduce PersonaFeedback, a new benchmark that directly evaluates LLMs' ability to provide personalized responses given pre-defined user personas and queries. Unlike existing benchmarks that require models to infer implicit user personas from historical interactions, PersonaFeedback decouples persona inference from personalization, focusing on evaluating the model's ability to generate responses tailored to explicit personas. PersonaFeedback consists of 8298 human-annotated test cases, which are categorized into easy, medium, and hard tiers based on the contextual complexity of the user personas and the difficulty in distinguishing subtle differences between two personalized responses. We conduct comprehensive evaluations across a wide range of models. The empirical results reveal that even state-of-the-art LLMs that can solve complex real-world reasoning tasks could fall short on the hard tier of PersonaFeedback where even human evaluators may find the distinctions challenging. Furthermore, we conduct an in-depth analysis of failure modes across various types of systems, demonstrating that the current retrieval-augmented framework should not be seen as a de facto solution for personalization tasks. All benchmark data, annotation protocols, and the evaluation pipeline will be publicly available to facilitate future research on LLM personalization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12915</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 17:19:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting Time Series with LLMs via Patch-Based Prompting and   Decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12953</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.12953.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mayank Bumb, Anshul Vemulapalli, Sri Harsha Vardhan Prasad Jella, Anish Gupta, An La, Ryan A. Rossi, Hongjie Chen, Franck Dernoncourt, Nesreen K. Ahmed, Yu Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated new possibilities for accurate and efficient time series analysis, but prior work often required heavy fine-tuning and/or ignored inter-series correlations. In this work, we explore simple and flexible prompt-based strategies that enable LLMs to perform time series forecasting without extensive retraining or the use of a complex external architecture. Through the exploration of specialized prompting methods that leverage time series decomposition, patch-based tokenization, and similarity-based neighbor augmentation, we find that it is possible to enhance LLM forecasting quality while maintaining simplicity and requiring minimal preprocessing of data. To this end, we propose our own method, PatchInstruct, which enables LLMs to make precise and effective predictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12953</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 19:42:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ai-Facilitated Analysis of Abstracts and Conclusions: Flagging   Unsubstantiated Claims and Ambiguous Pronouns</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13172</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13172.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Evgeny Markhasin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present and evaluate a suite of proof-of-concept (PoC), structured workflow prompts designed to elicit human-like hierarchical reasoning while guiding Large Language Models (LLMs) in high-level semantic and linguistic analysis of scholarly manuscripts. The prompts target two non-trivial analytical tasks: identifying unsubstantiated claims in summaries (informational integrity) and flagging ambiguous pronoun references (linguistic clarity). We conducted a systematic, multi-run evaluation on two frontier models (Gemini Pro 2.5 Pro and ChatGPT Plus o3) under varied context conditions. Our results for the informational integrity task reveal a significant divergence in model performance: while both models successfully identified an unsubstantiated head of a noun phrase (95% success), ChatGPT consistently failed (0% success) to identify an unsubstantiated adjectival modifier that Gemini correctly flagged (95% success), raising a question regarding potential influence of the target's syntactic role. For the linguistic analysis task, both models performed well (80-90% success) with full manuscript context. In a summary-only setting, however, ChatGPT achieved a perfect (100%) success rate, while Gemini's performance was substantially degraded. Our findings suggest that structured prompting is a viable methodology for complex textual analysis but show that prompt performance may be highly dependent on the interplay between the model, task type, and context, highlighting the need for rigorous, model-specific testing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13172</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 07:34:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SeqPE: Transformer with Sequential Position Encoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13277</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13277.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huyang Li, Yahui Liu, Hongyu Sun, Deng Cai, Leyang Cui, Wei Bi, Peilin Zhao, Taro Watanabe&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Since self-attention layers in Transformers are permutation invariant by design, positional encodings must be explicitly incorporated to enable spatial understanding. However, fixed-size lookup tables used in traditional learnable position embeddings (PEs) limit extrapolation capabilities beyond pre-trained sequence lengths. Expert-designed methods such as ALiBi and RoPE, mitigate this limitation but demand extensive modifications for adapting to new modalities, underscoring fundamental challenges in adaptability and scalability. In this work, we present SeqPE, a unified and fully learnable position encoding framework that represents each n-dimensional position index as a symbolic sequence and employs a lightweight sequential position encoder to learn their embeddings in an end-to-end manner. To regularize SeqPE's embedding space, we introduce two complementary objectives: a contrastive objective that aligns embedding distances with a predefined position-distance function, and a knowledge distillation loss that anchors out-of-distribution position embeddings to in-distribution teacher representations, further enhancing extrapolation performance. Experiments across language modeling, long-context question answering, and 2D image classification demonstrate that SeqPE not only surpasses strong baselines in perplexity, exact match (EM), and accuracy--particularly under context length extrapolation--but also enables seamless generalization to multi-dimensional inputs without requiring manual architectural redesign. We release our code, data, and checkpoints at https://github.com/ghrua/seqpe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13277</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 09:16:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AceReason-Nemotron 1.1: Advancing Math and Code Reasoning through SFT   and RL Synergy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13284</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13284.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zihan Liu, Zhuolin Yang, Yang Chen, Chankyu Lee, Mohammad Shoeybi, Bryan Catanzaro, Wei Ping&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we investigate the synergy between supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and reinforcement learning (RL) in developing strong reasoning models. We begin by curating the SFT training data through two scaling strategies: increasing the number of collected prompts and the number of generated responses per prompt. Both approaches yield notable improvements in reasoning performance, with scaling the number of prompts resulting in more substantial gains. We then explore the following questions regarding the synergy between SFT and RL: (i) Does a stronger SFT model consistently lead to better final performance after large-scale RL training? (ii) How can we determine an appropriate sampling temperature during RL training to effectively balance exploration and exploitation for a given SFT initialization? Our findings suggest that (i) holds true, provided effective RL training is conducted, particularly when the sampling temperature is carefully chosen to maintain the temperature-adjusted entropy around 0.3, a setting that strikes a good balance between exploration and exploitation. Notably, the performance gap between initial SFT models narrows significantly throughout the RL process. Leveraging a strong SFT foundation and insights into the synergistic interplay between SFT and RL, our AceReason-Nemotron-1.1 7B model significantly outperforms AceReason-Nemotron-1.0 and achieves new state-of-the-art performance among Qwen2.5-7B-based reasoning models on challenging math and code benchmarks, thereby demonstrating the effectiveness of our post-training recipe. We release the model and data at: https://huggingface.co/nvidia/AceReason-Nemotron-1.1-7B&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13284</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 09:27:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Technical Study into Small Reasoning Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13404</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13404.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xialie Zhuang, Peixian Ma, Zhikai Jia, Zheng Cao, Shiwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The ongoing evolution of language models has led to the development of large-scale architectures that demonstrate exceptional performance across a wide range of tasks. However, these models come with significant computational and energy demands, as well as potential privacy implications. In this context, Small Reasoning Language Models (SRLMs) with approximately 0.5 billion parameters present a compelling alternative due to their remarkable computational efficiency and cost effectiveness, particularly in resource-constrained environments. Despite these advantages, the limited capacity of 0.5 billion parameter models poses challenges in handling complex tasks such as mathematical reasoning and code generation. This research investigates various training strategies, including supervised fine-tuning (SFT), knowledge distillation (KD), and reinforcement learning (RL), as well as their hybrid implementations, to enhance the performance of 0.5B SRLMs. We analyze effective methodologies to bridge the performance gap between SRLMS and larger models and present insights into optimal training pipelines tailored for these smaller architectures. Through extensive experimental validation and analysis, our work aims to provide actionable recommendations for maximizing the reasoning capabilities of 0.5B models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13404</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 12:18:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty-Aware Remaining Lifespan Prediction from Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13430</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13430.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tristan Kenneweg, Philip Kenneweg, Barbara Hammer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Predicting mortality-related outcomes from images offers the prospect of accessible, noninvasive, and scalable health screening. We present a method that leverages pretrained vision transformer foundation models to estimate remaining lifespan from facial and whole-body images, alongside robust uncertainty quantification. We show that predictive uncertainty varies systematically with the true remaining lifespan, and that this uncertainty can be effectively modeled by learning a Gaussian distribution for each sample. Our approach achieves state-of-the-art mean absolute error (MAE) of 7.48 years on an established Dataset, and further improves to 4.79 and 5.07 years MAE on two new, higher-quality datasets curated and published in this work. Importantly, our models provide well-calibrated uncertainty estimates, as demonstrated by a bucketed expected calibration error of 0.62 years. While not intended for clinical deployment, these results highlight the potential of extracting medically relevant signals from images. We make all code and datasets available to facilitate further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13430</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 12:47:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BOW: Bottlenecked Next Word Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13502</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13502.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Shen, Zhikun Xu, Xiao Ye, Jacob Dineen, Ben Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are typically trained via next-word prediction (NWP), which provides strong surface-level fluency but often lacks support for robust reasoning. We propose BOttlenecked next Word exploration (BOW), a novel RL framework that rethinks NWP by introducing a reasoning bottleneck where a policy model first generates a reasoning path rather than predicting the next token directly, after which a frozen judge model predicts the next token distribution based solely on this reasoning path. We train the policy model using GRPO with rewards that quantify how effectively the reasoning path facilitates next-word recovery. Compared with other continual pretraining baselines, we show that BOW improves both the general and next-word reasoning capabilities of the base model, evaluated on various benchmarks. Our findings show that BOW can serve as an effective and scalable alternative to vanilla NWP.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13502</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:58:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiniMax-M1: Scaling Test-Time Compute Efficiently with Lightning   Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13585</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13585.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; MiniMax, Aili Chen, Aonian Li, Bangwei Gong, Binyang Jiang, Bo Fei, Bo Yang, Boji Shan, Changqing Yu, Chao Wang, Cheng Zhu, Chengjun Xiao, Chengyu Du, Chi Zhang, Chu Qiao, Chunhao Zhang, Chunhui Du, Congchao Guo, Da Chen, Deming Ding, Dianjun Sun, Dong Li, Enwei Jiao, Haigang Zhou, Haimo Zhang, Han Ding, Haohai Sun, Haoyu Feng, Huaiguang Cai, Haichao Zhu, Jian Sun, Jiaqi Zhuang, Jiaren Cai, Jiayuan Song, Jin Zhu, Jingyang Li, Jinhao Tian, Jinli Liu, Junhao Xu, Junjie Yan, Junteng Liu, Junxian He, Kaiyi Feng, Ke Yang, Kecheng Xiao, Le Han, Leyang Wang, Lianfei Yu, Liheng Feng, Lin Li, Lin Zheng, Linge Du, Lingyu Yang, Lunbin Zeng, Minghui Yu, Mingliang Tao, Mingyuan Chi, Mozhi Zhang, Mujie Lin, Nan Hu, Nongyu Di, Peng Gao, Pengfei Li, Pengyu Zhao, Qibing Ren, Qidi Xu, Qile Li, Qin Wang, Rong Tian, Ruitao Leng, Shaoxiang Chen, Shaoyu Chen, Shengmin Shi, Shitong Weng, Shuchang Guan, Shuqi Yu, Sichen Li, Songquan Zhu, Tengfei Li, Tianchi Cai, Tianrun Liang, Weiyu Cheng, Weize Kong, Wenkai Li, Xiancai Chen, Xiangjun Song, Xiao Luo, Xiao Su, Xiaobo Li, Xiaodong Han, Xinzhu Hou, Xuan Lu, Xun Zou, Xuyang Shen, Yan Gong, Yan Ma, Yang Wang, Yiqi Shi, Yiran Zhong, Yonghong Duan, Yongxiang Fu, Yongyi Hu, Yu Gao, Yuanxiang Fan, Yufeng Yang, Yuhao Li, Yulin Hu, Yunan Huang, Yunji Li, Yunzhi Xu, Yuxin Mao, Yuxuan Shi, Yuze Wenren, Zehan Li, Zelin Li, Zhanxu Tian, Zhengmao Zhu, Zhenhua Fan, Zhenzhen Wu, Zhichao Xu, Zhihang Yu, Zhiheng Lyu, Zhuo Jiang, Zibo Gao, Zijia Wu, Zijian Song, Zijun Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 184&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce MiniMax-M1, the world's first open-weight, large-scale hybrid-attention reasoning model. MiniMax-M1 is powered by a hybrid Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) architecture combined with a lightning attention mechanism. The model is developed based on our previous MiniMax-Text-01 model, which contains a total of 456 billion parameters with 45.9 billion parameters activated per token. The M1 model natively supports a context length of 1 million tokens, 8x the context size of DeepSeek R1. Furthermore, the lightning attention mechanism in MiniMax-M1 enables efficient scaling of test-time compute. These properties make M1 particularly suitable for complex tasks that require processing long inputs and thinking extensively. MiniMax-M1 is trained using large-scale reinforcement learning (RL) on diverse problems including sandbox-based, real-world software engineering environments. In addition to M1's inherent efficiency advantage for RL training, we propose CISPO, a novel RL algorithm to further enhance RL efficiency. CISPO clips importance sampling weights rather than token updates, outperforming other competitive RL variants. Combining hybrid-attention and CISPO enables MiniMax-M1's full RL training on 512 H800 GPUs to complete in only three weeks, with a rental cost of just $534,700. We release two versions of MiniMax-M1 models with 40K and 80K thinking budgets respectively, where the 40K model represents an intermediate phase of the 80K training. Experiments on standard benchmarks show that our models are comparable or superior to strong open-weight models such as the original DeepSeek-R1 and Qwen3-235B, with particular strengths in complex software engineering, tool utilization, and long-context tasks. We publicly release MiniMax-M1 at https://github.com/MiniMax-AI/MiniMax-M1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13585</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 15:08:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ego-R1: Chain-of-Tool-Thought for Ultra-Long Egocentric Video Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13654</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13654.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shulin Tian, Ruiqi Wang, Hongming Guo, Penghao Wu, Yuhao Dong, Xiuying Wang, Jingkang Yang, Hao Zhang, Hongyuan Zhu, Ziwei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Ego-R1, a novel framework for reasoning over ultra-long (i.e., in days and weeks) egocentric videos, which leverages a structured Chain-of-Tool-Thought (CoTT) process, orchestrated by an Ego-R1 Agent trained via reinforcement learning (RL). Inspired by human problem-solving strategies, CoTT decomposes complex reasoning into modular steps, with the RL agent invoking specific tools, one per step, to iteratively and collaboratively answer sub-questions tackling such tasks as temporal retrieval and multi-modal understanding. We design a two-stage training paradigm involving supervised finetuning (SFT) of a pretrained language model using CoTT data and RL to enable our agent to dynamically propose step-by-step tools for long-range reasoning. To facilitate training, we construct a dataset called Ego-R1 Data, which consists of Ego-CoTT-25K for SFT and Ego-QA-4.4K for RL. Furthermore, our Ego-R1 agent is evaluated on a newly curated week-long video QA benchmark, Ego-R1 Bench, which contains human-verified QA pairs from hybrid sources. Extensive results demonstrate that the dynamic, tool-augmented chain-of-thought reasoning by our Ego-R1 Agent can effectively tackle the unique challenges of understanding ultra-long egocentric videos, significantly extending the time coverage from few hours to a week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13654</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 16:17:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Test3R: Learning to Reconstruct 3D at Test Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13750</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13750.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuheng Yuan, Qiuhong Shen, Shizun Wang, Xingyi Yang, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Dense matching methods like DUSt3R regress pairwise pointmaps for 3D reconstruction. However, the reliance on pairwise prediction and the limited generalization capability inherently restrict the global geometric consistency. In this work, we introduce Test3R, a surprisingly simple test-time learning technique that significantly boosts geometric accuracy. Using image triplets (I_1,I_2,I_3), Test3R generates reconstructions from pairs (I_1,I_2) and (I_1,I_3). The core idea is to optimize the network at test time via a self-supervised objective: maximizing the geometric consistency between these two reconstructions relative to the common image I_1. This ensures the model produces cross-pair consistent outputs, regardless of the inputs. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our technique significantly outperforms previous state-of-the-art methods on the 3D reconstruction and multi-view depth estimation tasks. Moreover, it is universally applicable and nearly cost-free, making it easily applied to other models and implemented with minimal test-time training overhead and parameter footprint. Code is available at https://github.com/nopQAQ/Test3R.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13750</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 17:56:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steering LLM Thinking with Budget Guidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13752</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13752.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyan Li, Wenshuo Zhao, Yang Zhang, Chuang Gan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent deep-thinking large language models often reason extensively to improve performance, but such lengthy reasoning is not always desirable, as it incurs excessive inference costs with disproportionate performance gains. Controlling reasoning length without sacrificing performance is therefore important, but remains challenging, especially under tight thinking budgets. We propose budget guidance, a simple yet effective method for steering the reasoning process of LLMs toward a target budget without requiring any LLM fine-tuning. Our approach introduces a lightweight predictor that models a Gamma distribution over the remaining thinking length during next-token generation. This signal is then used to guide generation in a soft, token-level manner, ensuring that the overall reasoning trace adheres to the specified thinking budget. Budget guidance enables natural control of the thinking length, along with significant token efficiency improvements over baseline methods on challenging math benchmarks. For instance, it achieves up to a 26% accuracy gain on the MATH-500 benchmark under tight budgets compared to baseline methods, while maintaining competitive accuracy with only 63% of the thinking tokens used by the full-thinking model. Budget guidance also generalizes to broader task domains and exhibits emergent capabilities, such as estimating question difficulty. The source code is available at: https://github.com/UMass-Embodied-AGI/BudgetGuidance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13752</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 17:57:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Diffusion in Large Language and Multimodal Models: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13759</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.13759.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runpeng Yu, Qi Li, Xinchao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this work, we provide a systematic survey of Discrete Diffusion Language Models (dLLMs) and Discrete Diffusion Multimodal Language Models (dMLLMs). Unlike autoregressive (AR) models, dLLMs and dMLLMs adopt a multi-token, parallel decoding paradigm using full attention and a denoising-based generation strategy. This paradigm naturally enables parallel generation, fine-grained output controllability, and dynamic, response-aware perception. These capabilities are previously difficult to achieve with AR models. Recently, a growing number of industrial-scale proprietary d(M)LLMs, as well as a large number of open-source academic d(M)LLMs, have demonstrated performance comparable to their autoregressive counterparts, while achieving up to 10x acceleration in inference speed.   The advancement of discrete diffusion LLMs and MLLMs has been largely driven by progress in two domains. The first is the development of autoregressive LLMs and MLLMs, which has accumulated vast amounts of data, benchmarks, and foundational infrastructure for training and inference. The second contributing domain is the evolution of the mathematical models underlying discrete diffusion. Together, these advancements have catalyzed a surge in dLLMs and dMLLMs research in early 2025.   In this work, we present a comprehensive overview of the research in the dLLM and dMLLM domains. We trace the historical development of dLLMs and dMLLMs, formalize the underlying mathematical frameworks, and categorize representative models. We further analyze key techniques for training and inference, and summarize emerging applications across language, vision-language, and biological domains. We conclude by discussing future directions for research and deployment.   Paper collection: https://github.com/LiQiiiii/DLLM-Survey&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13759</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 17:59:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
