<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:11:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>DEXOP: A Device for Robotic Transfer of Dexterous Human Manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04441</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.04441.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao-Shu Fang, Branden Romero, Yichen Xie, Arthur Hu, Bo-Ruei Huang, Juan Alvarez, Matthew Kim, Gabriel Margolis, Kavya Anbarasu, Masayoshi Tomizuka, Edward Adelson, Pulkit Agrawal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce perioperation, a paradigm for robotic data collection that sensorizes and records human manipulation while maximizing the transferability of the data to real robots. We implement this paradigm in DEXOP, a passive hand exoskeleton designed to maximize human ability to collect rich sensory (vision + tactile) data for diverse dexterous manipulation tasks in natural environments. DEXOP mechanically connects human fingers to robot fingers, providing users with direct contact feedback (via proprioception) and mirrors the human hand pose to the passive robot hand to maximize the transfer of demonstrated skills to the robot. The force feedback and pose mirroring make task demonstrations more natural for humans compared to teleoperation, increasing both speed and accuracy. We evaluate DEXOP across a range of dexterous, contact-rich tasks, demonstrating its ability to collect high-quality demonstration data at scale. Policies learned with DEXOP data significantly improve task performance per unit time of data collection compared to teleoperation, making DEXOP a powerful tool for advancing robot dexterity. Our project page is at https://dex-op.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04441</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 17:57:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MiniCPM-V 4.5: Cooking Efficient MLLMs via Architecture, Data, and   Training Recipe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18154</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18154.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Yu, Zefan Wang, Chongyi Wang, Fuwei Huang, Wenshuo Ma, Zhihui He, Tianchi Cai, Weize Chen, Yuxiang Huang, Yuanqian Zhao, Bokai Xu, Junbo Cui, Yingjing Xu, Liqing Ruan, Luoyuan Zhang, Hanyu Liu, Jingkun Tang, Hongyuan Liu, Qining Guo, Wenhao Hu, Bingxiang He, Jie Zhou, Jie Cai, Ji Qi, Zonghao Guo, Chi Chen, Guoyang Zeng, Yuxuan Li, Ganqu Cui, Ning Ding, Xu Han, Yuan Yao, Zhiyuan Liu, Maosong Sun&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) are undergoing rapid progress and represent the frontier of AI development. However, their training and inference efficiency have emerged as a core bottleneck in making MLLMs more accessible and scalable. To address the challenges, we present MiniCPM-V 4.5, an 8B parameter model designed for high efficiency and strong performance. We introduce three core improvements in model architecture, data strategy and training method: a unified 3D-Resampler model architecture for highly compact encoding over images and videos, a unified learning paradigm for document knowledge and text recognition without heavy data engineering, and a hybrid reinforcement learning strategy for proficiency in both short and long reasoning modes. Comprehensive experimental results in OpenCompass evaluation show that MiniCPM-V 4.5 surpasses widely used proprietary models such as GPT-4o-latest, and significantly larger open-source models such as Qwen2.5-VL 72B. Notably, the strong performance is achieved with remarkable efficiency. For example, on the widely adopted VideoMME benchmark, MiniCPM-V 4.5 achieves state-of-the-art performance among models under 30B size, using just 46.7\% GPU memory cost and 8.7\% inference time of Qwen2.5-VL 7B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18154</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 19:41:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Models Discriminate Against Speakers of German Dialects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13835</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.13835.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minh Duc Bui, Carolin Holtermann, Valentin Hofmann, Anne Lauscher, Katharina von der Wense&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Dialects represent a significant component of human culture and are found across all regions of the world. In Germany, more than 40% of the population speaks a regional dialect (Adler and Hansen, 2022). However, despite cultural importance, individuals speaking dialects often face negative societal stereotypes. We examine whether such stereotypes are mirrored by large language models (LLMs). We draw on the sociolinguistic literature on dialect perception to analyze traits commonly associated with dialect speakers. Based on these traits, we assess the dialect naming bias and dialect usage bias expressed by LLMs in two tasks: an association task and a decision task. To assess a model's dialect usage bias, we construct a novel evaluation corpus that pairs sentences from seven regional German dialects (e.g., Alemannic and Bavarian) with their standard German counterparts. We find that: (1) in the association task, all evaluated LLMs exhibit significant dialect naming and dialect usage bias against German dialect speakers, reflected in negative adjective associations; (2) all models reproduce these dialect naming and dialect usage biases in their decision making; and (3) contrary to prior work showing minimal bias with explicit demographic mentions, we find that explicitly labeling linguistic demographics--German dialect speakers--amplifies bias more than implicit cues like dialect usage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13835</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 09:05:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baseer: A Vision-Language Model for Arabic Document-to-Markdown OCR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18174</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18174.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Khalil Hennara, Muhammad Hreden, Mohamed Motasim Hamed, Ahmad Bastati, Zeina Aldallal, Sara Chrouf, Safwan AlModhayan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 121&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Arabic document OCR remains a challenging task due to the language's cursive script, diverse fonts, diacritics, and right-to-left orientation. While modern Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) have advanced document understanding for high-resource languages, their performance on Arabic remains limited. In this work, we introduce Baseer, a vision-language model fine- tuned specifically for Arabic document OCR. Leveraging a large-scale dataset combining synthetic and real-world documents, Baseer is trained using a decoder-only fine-tuning strategy to adapt a pre-trained MLLM while preserving general visual features. We also present Misraj-DocOCR, a high-quality, expert-verified benchmark designed for rigorous evaluation of Arabic OCR systems. Our experiments show that Baseer significantly outperforms existing open-source and commercial solutions, achieving a WER of 0.25 and establishing a new state-of-the-art in the domain of Arabic document OCR. Our results highlight the benefits of domain-specific adaptation of general-purpose MLLMs and establish a strong baseline for high-accuracy OCR on morphologically rich languages like Arabic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18174</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 15:07:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic bootstrapped pretraining</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15248</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15248.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zitong Yang, Aonan Zhang, Hong Liu, Tatsunori Hashimoto, Emmanuel Candès, Chong Wang, Ruoming Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Synthetic Bootstrapped Pretraining (SBP), a language model (LM) pretraining procedure that first learns a model of relations between documents from the pretraining dataset and then leverages it to synthesize a vast new corpus for joint training. While the standard pretraining teaches LMs to learn causal correlations among tokens within a single document, it is not designed to efficiently model the rich, learnable inter-document correlations that can potentially lead to better performance. We validate SBP by designing a compute-matched pretraining setup and pretrain a 3B-parameter model on up to 1T tokens from scratch. We find SBP consistently improves upon a strong repetition baseline and delivers a significant fraction of performance improvement attainable by an oracle upper bound with access to 20x more unique data. Qualitative analysis reveals that the synthesized documents go beyond mere paraphrases -- SBP first abstracts a core concept from the seed material and then crafts a new narration on top of it. Besides strong empirical performance, SBP admits a natural Bayesian interpretation: the synthesizer implicitly learns to abstract the latent concepts shared between related documents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15248</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 22:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-QA: Can Language Models Answer Repository-level Code Questions?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14635</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14635.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weihan Peng, Yuling Shi, Yuhang Wang, Xinyun Zhang, Beijun Shen, Xiaodong Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 34&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Understanding and reasoning about entire software repositories is an essential capability for intelligent software engineering tools. While existing benchmarks such as CoSQA and CodeQA have advanced the field, they predominantly focus on small, self-contained code snippets. These setups fail to capture the complexity of real-world repositories, where effective understanding and reasoning often require navigating multiple files, understanding software architecture, and grounding answers in long-range code dependencies. In this paper, we present SWE-QA, a repository-level code question answering (QA) benchmark designed to facilitate research on automated QA systems in realistic code environments. SWE-QA involves 576 high-quality question-answer pairs spanning diverse categories, including intention understanding, cross-file reasoning, and multi-hop dependency analysis. To construct SWE-QA, we first crawled 77,100 GitHub issues from 11 popular repositories. Based on an analysis of naturally occurring developer questions extracted from these issues, we developed a two-level taxonomy of repository-level questions and constructed a set of seed questions for each category. For each category, we manually curated and validated questions and collected their corresponding answers. As a prototype application, we further develop SWE-QA-Agent, an agentic framework in which LLM agents reason and act to find answers automatically. We evaluate six advanced LLMs on SWE-QA under various context augmentation strategies. Experimental results highlight the promise of LLMs, particularly our SWE-QA-Agent framework, in addressing repository-level QA, while also revealing open challenges and pointing to future research directions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14635</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 05:25:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the Thinking Process of Reasoning Models: A Perspective   from Schoenfeld's Episode Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14662</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14662.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ming Li, Nan Zhang, Chenrui Fan, Hong Jiao, Yanbin Fu, Sydney Peters, Qingshu Xu, Robert Lissitz, Tianyi Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) generate extensive chain-of-thought reasoning, we lack a principled framework for understanding how these thoughts are structured. In this paper, we introduce a novel approach by applying Schoenfeld's Episode Theory, a classic cognitive framework for human mathematical problem-solving, to analyze the reasoning traces of LRMs. We annotated thousands of sentences and paragraphs from model-generated solutions to math problems using seven cognitive labels (e.g., Plan, Implement, Verify). The result is the first publicly available benchmark for the fine-grained analysis of machine reasoning, including a large annotated corpus and detailed annotation guidebooks. Our preliminary analysis reveals distinct patterns in LRM reasoning, such as the transition dynamics between cognitive states. This framework provides a theoretically grounded methodology for interpreting LRM cognition and enables future work on more controllable and transparent reasoning systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14662</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 06:42:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Use of Agentic Coding: An Empirical Study of Pull Requests on   GitHub</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14745</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14745.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Miku Watanabe, Hao Li, Yutaro Kashiwa, Brittany Reid, Hajimu Iida, Ahmed E. Hassan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly being integrated into software development processes. The ability to generate code and submit pull requests with minimal human intervention, through the use of autonomous AI agents, is poised to become a standard practice. However, little is known about the practical usefulness of these pull requests and the extent to which their contributions are accepted in real-world projects. In this paper, we empirically study 567 GitHub pull requests (PRs) generated using Claude Code, an agentic coding tool, across 157 diverse open-source projects. Our analysis reveals that developers tend to rely on agents for tasks such as refactoring, documentation, and testing. The results indicate that 83.8% of these agent-assisted PRs are eventually accepted and merged by project maintainers, with 54.9% of the merged PRs are integrated without further modification. The remaining 45.1% require additional changes benefit from human revisions, especially for bug fixes, documentation, and adherence to project-specific standards. These findings suggest that while agent-assisted PRs are largely acceptable, they still benefit from human oversight and refinement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14745</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 08:48:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPATIALGEN: Layout-guided 3D Indoor Scene Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14981</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.14981.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chuan Fang, Heng Li, Yixun Liang, Jia Zheng, Yongsen Mao, Yuan Liu, Rui Tang, Zihan Zhou, Ping Tan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Creating high-fidelity 3D models of indoor environments is essential for applications in design, virtual reality, and robotics. However, manual 3D modeling remains time-consuming and labor-intensive. While recent advances in generative AI have enabled automated scene synthesis, existing methods often face challenges in balancing visual quality, diversity, semantic consistency, and user control. A major bottleneck is the lack of a large-scale, high-quality dataset tailored to this task. To address this gap, we introduce a comprehensive synthetic dataset, featuring 12,328 structured annotated scenes with 57,440 rooms, and 4.7M photorealistic 2D renderings. Leveraging this dataset, we present SpatialGen, a novel multi-view multi-modal diffusion model that generates realistic and semantically consistent 3D indoor scenes. Given a 3D layout and a reference image (derived from a text prompt), our model synthesizes appearance (color image), geometry (scene coordinate map), and semantic (semantic segmentation map) from arbitrary viewpoints, while preserving spatial consistency across modalities. SpatialGen consistently generates superior results to previous methods in our experiments. We are open-sourcing our data and models to empower the community and advance the field of indoor scene understanding and generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14981</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 14:12:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RGB-Only Supervised Camera Parameter Optimization in Dynamic Scenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15123</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15123.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fang Li, Hao Zhang, Narendra Ahuja&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Although COLMAP has long remained the predominant method for camera parameter optimization in static scenes, it is constrained by its lengthy runtime and reliance on ground truth (GT) motion masks for application to dynamic scenes. Many efforts attempted to improve it by incorporating more priors as supervision such as GT focal length, motion masks, 3D point clouds, camera poses, and metric depth, which, however, are typically unavailable in casually captured RGB videos. In this paper, we propose a novel method for more accurate and efficient camera parameter optimization in dynamic scenes solely supervised by a single RGB video. Our method consists of three key components: (1) Patch-wise Tracking Filters, to establish robust and maximally sparse hinge-like relations across the RGB video. (2) Outlier-aware Joint Optimization, for efficient camera parameter optimization by adaptive down-weighting of moving outliers, without reliance on motion priors. (3) A Two-stage Optimization Strategy, to enhance stability and optimization speed by a trade-off between the Softplus limits and convex minima in losses. We visually and numerically evaluate our camera estimates. To further validate accuracy, we feed the camera estimates into a 4D reconstruction method and assess the resulting 3D scenes, and rendered 2D RGB and depth maps. We perform experiments on 4 real-world datasets (NeRF-DS, DAVIS, iPhone, and TUM-dynamics) and 1 synthetic dataset (MPI-Sintel), demonstrating that our method estimates camera parameters more efficiently and accurately with a single RGB video as the only supervision.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15123</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 16:29:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lynx: Towards High-Fidelity Personalized Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15496</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15496.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shen Sang, Tiancheng Zhi, Tianpei Gu, Jing Liu, Linjie Luo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Lynx, a high-fidelity model for personalized video synthesis from a single input image. Built on an open-source Diffusion Transformer (DiT) foundation model, Lynx introduces two lightweight adapters to ensure identity fidelity. The ID-adapter employs a Perceiver Resampler to convert ArcFace-derived facial embeddings into compact identity tokens for conditioning, while the Ref-adapter integrates dense VAE features from a frozen reference pathway, injecting fine-grained details across all transformer layers through cross-attention. These modules collectively enable robust identity preservation while maintaining temporal coherence and visual realism. Through evaluation on a curated benchmark of 40 subjects and 20 unbiased prompts, which yielded 800 test cases, Lynx has demonstrated superior face resemblance, competitive prompt following, and strong video quality, thereby advancing the state of personalized video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15496</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:31:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BTL-UI: Blink-Think-Link Reasoning Model for GUI Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15566</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15566.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaojie Zhang, Ruoceng Zhang, Pei Fu, Shaokang Wang, Jiahui Yang, Xin Du, Shiqi Cui, Bin Qin, Ying Huang, Zhenbo Luo, Jian Luan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In the field of AI-driven human-GUI interaction automation, while rapid advances in multimodal large language models and reinforcement fine-tuning techniques have yielded remarkable progress, a fundamental challenge persists: their interaction logic significantly deviates from natural human-GUI communication patterns. To fill this gap, we propose "Blink-Think-Link" (BTL), a brain-inspired framework for human-GUI interaction that mimics the human cognitive process between users and graphical interfaces. The system decomposes interactions into three biologically plausible phases: (1) Blink - rapid detection and attention to relevant screen areas, analogous to saccadic eye movements; (2) Think - higher-level reasoning and decision-making, mirroring cognitive planning; and (3) Link - generation of executable commands for precise motor control, emulating human action selection mechanisms. Additionally, we introduce two key technical innovations for the BTL framework: (1) Blink Data Generation - an automated annotation pipeline specifically optimized for blink data, and (2) BTL Reward -- the first rule-based reward mechanism that enables reinforcement learning driven by both process and outcome. Building upon this framework, we develop a GUI agent model named BTL-UI, which demonstrates consistent state-of-the-art performance across both static GUI understanding and dynamic interaction tasks in comprehensive benchmarks. These results provide conclusive empirical validation of the framework's efficacy in developing advanced GUI Agents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15566</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 04:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Zoning Network: A Unified Principle for Generative Modeling,   Representation Learning, and Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15591</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15591.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zinan Lin, Enshu Liu, Xuefei Ning, Junyi Zhu, Wenyu Wang, Sergey Yekhanin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 45&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Generative modeling, representation learning, and classification are three core problems in machine learning (ML), yet their state-of-the-art (SoTA) solutions remain largely disjoint. In this paper, we ask: Can a unified principle address all three? Such unification could simplify ML pipelines and foster greater synergy across tasks. We introduce Latent Zoning Network (LZN) as a step toward this goal. At its core, LZN creates a shared Gaussian latent space that encodes information across all tasks. Each data type (e.g., images, text, labels) is equipped with an encoder that maps samples to disjoint latent zones, and a decoder that maps latents back to data. ML tasks are expressed as compositions of these encoders and decoders: for example, label-conditional image generation uses a label encoder and image decoder; image embedding uses an image encoder; classification uses an image encoder and label decoder. We demonstrate the promise of LZN in three increasingly complex scenarios: (1) LZN can enhance existing models (image generation): When combined with the SoTA Rectified Flow model, LZN improves FID on CIFAR10 from 2.76 to 2.59-without modifying the training objective. (2) LZN can solve tasks independently (representation learning): LZN can implement unsupervised representation learning without auxiliary loss functions, outperforming the seminal MoCo and SimCLR methods by 9.3% and 0.2%, respectively, on downstream linear classification on ImageNet. (3) LZN can solve multiple tasks simultaneously (joint generation and classification): With image and label encoders/decoders, LZN performs both tasks jointly by design, improving FID and achieving SoTA classification accuracy on CIFAR10. The code and trained models are available at https://github.com/microsoft/latent-zoning-networks. The project website is at https://zinanlin.me/blogs/latent_zoning_networks.html.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15591</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 04:47:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Embedding Scaling in Collaborative Filtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15709</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15709.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhuangzhuang He, Zhou Kaiyu, Haoyue Bai, Fengbin Zhu, Yonghui Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Scaling recommendation models into large recommendation models has become one of the most widely discussed topics. Recent efforts focus on components beyond the scaling embedding dimension, as it is believed that scaling embedding may lead to performance degradation. Although there have been some initial observations on embedding, the root cause of their non-scalability remains unclear. Moreover, whether performance degradation occurs across different types of models and datasets is still an unexplored area. Regarding the effect of embedding dimensions on performance, we conduct large-scale experiments across 10 datasets with varying sparsity levels and scales, using 4 representative classical architectures. We surprisingly observe two novel phenomenon: double-peak and logarithmic. For the former, as the embedding dimension increases, performance first improves, then declines, rises again, and eventually drops. For the latter, it exhibits a perfect logarithmic curve. Our contributions are threefold. First, we discover two novel phenomena when scaling collaborative filtering models. Second, we gain an understanding of the underlying causes of the double-peak phenomenon. Lastly, we theoretically analyze the noise robustness of collaborative filtering models, with results matching empirical observations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15709</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 07:33:50 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Vision-Language-Action-Critic Model for Robotic Real-World   Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15937</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.15937.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shaopeng Zhai, Qi Zhang, Tianyi Zhang, Fuxian Huang, Haoran Zhang, Ming Zhou, Shengzhe Zhang, Litao Liu, Sixu Lin, Jiangmiao Pang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Robotic real-world reinforcement learning (RL) with vision-language-action (VLA) models is bottlenecked by sparse, handcrafted rewards and inefficient exploration. We introduce VLAC, a general process reward model built upon InternVL and trained on large scale heterogeneous datasets. Given pairwise observations and a language goal, it outputs dense progress delta and done signal, eliminating task-specific reward engineering, and supports one-shot in-context transfer to unseen tasks and environments. VLAC is trained on vision-language datasets to strengthen perception, dialogic and reasoning capabilities, together with robot and human trajectories data that ground action generation and progress estimation, and additionally strengthened to reject irrelevant prompts as well as detect regression or stagnation by constructing large numbers of negative and semantically mismatched samples. With prompt control, a single VLAC model alternately generating reward and action tokens, unifying critic and policy. Deployed inside an asynchronous real-world RL loop, we layer a graded human-in-the-loop protocol (offline demonstration replay, return and explore, human guided explore) that accelerates exploration and stabilizes early learning. Across four distinct real-world manipulation tasks, VLAC lifts success rates from about 30\% to about 90\% within 200 real-world interaction episodes; incorporating human-in-the-loop interventions yields a further 50% improvement in sample efficiency and achieves up to 100% final success.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15937</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 12:44:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiffusionNFT: Online Diffusion Reinforcement with Forward Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16117</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16117.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaiwen Zheng, Huayu Chen, Haotian Ye, Haoxiang Wang, Qinsheng Zhang, Kai Jiang, Hang Su, Stefano Ermon, Jun Zhu, Ming-Yu Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Online reinforcement learning (RL) has been central to post-training language models, but its extension to diffusion models remains challenging due to intractable likelihoods. Recent works discretize the reverse sampling process to enable GRPO-style training, yet they inherit fundamental drawbacks, including solver restrictions, forward-reverse inconsistency, and complicated integration with classifier-free guidance (CFG). We introduce Diffusion Negative-aware FineTuning (DiffusionNFT), a new online RL paradigm that optimizes diffusion models directly on the forward process via flow matching. DiffusionNFT contrasts positive and negative generations to define an implicit policy improvement direction, naturally incorporating reinforcement signals into the supervised learning objective. This formulation enables training with arbitrary black-box solvers, eliminates the need for likelihood estimation, and requires only clean images rather than sampling trajectories for policy optimization. DiffusionNFT is up to 25times more efficient than FlowGRPO in head-to-head comparisons, while being CFG-free. For instance, DiffusionNFT improves the GenEval score from 0.24 to 0.98 within 1k steps, while FlowGRPO achieves 0.95 with over 5k steps and additional CFG employment. By leveraging multiple reward models, DiffusionNFT significantly boosts the performance of SD3.5-Medium in every benchmark tested.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16117</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 16:09:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BaseReward: A Strong Baseline for Multimodal Reward Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16127</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16127.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yi-Fan Zhang, Haihua Yang, Huanyu Zhang, Yang Shi, Zezhou Chen, Haochen Tian, Chaoyou Fu, Haotian Wang, Kai Wu, Bo Cui, Xu Wang, Jianfei Pan, Haotian Wang, Zhang Zhang, Liang Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The rapid advancement of Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) has made aligning them with human preferences a critical challenge. Reward Models (RMs) are a core technology for achieving this goal, but a systematic guide for building state-of-the-art Multimodal Reward Models (MRMs) is currently lacking in both academia and industry. Through exhaustive experimental analysis, this paper aims to provide a clear ``recipe'' for constructing high-performance MRMs. We systematically investigate every crucial component in the MRM development pipeline, including reward modeling paradigms (e.g., Naive-RM, Critic-based RM, and Generative RM), reward head architecture, training strategies, data curation (covering over ten multimodal and text-only preference datasets), backbone model and model scale, and ensemble methods.   Based on these experimental insights, we introduce BaseReward, a powerful and efficient baseline for multimodal reward modeling. BaseReward adopts a simple yet effective architecture, built upon a {Qwen2.5-VL} backbone, featuring an optimized two-layer reward head, and is trained on a carefully curated mixture of high-quality multimodal and text-only preference data. Our results show that BaseReward establishes a new SOTA on major benchmarks such as MM-RLHF-Reward Bench, VL-Reward Bench, and Multimodal Reward Bench, outperforming previous models. Furthermore, to validate its practical utility beyond static benchmarks, we integrate BaseReward into a real-world reinforcement learning pipeline, successfully enhancing an MLLM's performance across various perception, reasoning, and conversational tasks. This work not only delivers a top-tier MRM but, more importantly, provides the community with a clear, empirically-backed guide for developing robust reward models for the next generation of MLLMs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16127</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 16:25:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MANZANO: A Simple and Scalable Unified Multimodal Model with a Hybrid   Vision Tokenizer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16197</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16197.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanghao Li, Rui Qian, Bowen Pan, Haotian Zhang, Haoshuo Huang, Bowen Zhang, Jialing Tong, Haoxuan You, Xianzhi Du, Zhe Gan, Hyunjik Kim, Chao Jia, Zhenbang Wang, Yinfei Yang, Mingfei Gao, Zi-Yi Dou, Wenze Hu, Chang Gao, Dongxu Li, Philipp Dufter, Zirui Wang, Guoli Yin, Zhengdong Zhang, Chen Chen, Yang Zhao, Ruoming Pang, Zhifeng Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified multimodal Large Language Models (LLMs) that can both understand and generate visual content hold immense potential. However, existing open-source models often suffer from a performance trade-off between these capabilities. We present Manzano, a simple and scalable unified framework that substantially reduces this tension by coupling a hybrid image tokenizer with a well-curated training recipe. A single shared vision encoder feeds two lightweight adapters that produce continuous embeddings for image-to-text understanding and discrete tokens for text-to-image generation within a common semantic space. A unified autoregressive LLM predicts high-level semantics in the form of text and image tokens, with an auxiliary diffusion decoder subsequently translating the image tokens into pixels. The architecture, together with a unified training recipe over understanding and generation data, enables scalable joint learning of both capabilities. Manzano achieves state-of-the-art results among unified models, and is competitive with specialist models, particularly on text-rich evaluation. Our studies show minimal task conflicts and consistent gains from scaling model size, validating our design choice of a hybrid tokenizer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16197</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 17:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RPG: A Repository Planning Graph for Unified and Scalable Codebase   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16198</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16198.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jane Luo, Xin Zhang, Steven Liu, Jie Wu, Yiming Huang, Yangyu Huang, Chengyu Yin, Ying Xin, Jianfeng Liu, Yuefeng Zhan, Hao Sun, Qi Chen, Scarlett Li, Mao Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 115&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models excel at function- and file-level code generation, yet generating complete repositories from scratch remains a fundamental challenge. This process demands coherent and reliable planning across proposal- and implementation-level stages, while natural language, due to its ambiguity and verbosity, is ill-suited for faithfully representing complex software structures. To address this, we introduce the Repository Planning Graph (RPG), a persistent representation that unifies proposal- and implementation-level planning by encoding capabilities, file structures, data flows, and functions in one graph. RPG replaces ambiguous natural language with an explicit blueprint, enabling long-horizon planning and scalable repository generation. Building on RPG, we develop ZeroRepo, a graph-driven framework for repository generation from scratch. It operates in three stages: proposal-level planning and implementation-level refinement to construct the graph, followed by graph-guided code generation with test validation. To evaluate this setting, we construct RepoCraft, a benchmark of six real-world projects with 1,052 tasks. On RepoCraft, ZeroRepo produces repositories averaging nearly 36K LOC, roughly 3.9times the strongest baseline (Claude Code) and about 64times other baselines. It attains 81.5% functional coverage and a 69.7% pass rate, exceeding Claude Code by 27.3 and 35.8 percentage points, respectively. Further analysis shows that RPG models complex dependencies, enables progressively more sophisticated planning through near-linear scaling, and enhances LLM understanding of repositories, thereby accelerating agent localization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16198</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 17:58:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CommonForms: A Large, Diverse Dataset for Form Field Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16506</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16506.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Joe Barrow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces CommonForms, a web-scale dataset for form field detection. It casts the problem of form field detection as object detection: given an image of a page, predict the location and type (Text Input, Choice Button, Signature) of form fields. The dataset is constructed by filtering Common Crawl to find PDFs that have fillable elements. Starting with 8 million documents, the filtering process is used to arrive at a final dataset of roughly 55k documents that have over 450k pages. Analysis shows that the dataset contains a diverse mixture of languages and domains; one third of the pages are non-English, and among the 14 classified domains, no domain makes up more than 25% of the dataset.   In addition, this paper presents a family of form field detectors, FFDNet-Small and FFDNet-Large, which attain a very high average precision on the CommonForms test set. Each model cost less than $500 to train. Ablation results show that high-resolution inputs are crucial for high-quality form field detection, and that the cleaning process improves data efficiency over using all PDFs that have fillable fields in Common Crawl. A qualitative analysis shows that they outperform a popular, commercially available PDF reader that can prepare forms. Unlike the most popular commercially available solutions, FFDNet can predict checkboxes in addition to text and signature fields. This is, to our knowledge, the first large scale dataset released for form field detection, as well as the first open source models. The dataset, models, and code will be released at https://github.com/jbarrow/commonforms&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16506</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 02:55:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Uniform to Heterogeneous: Tailoring Policy Optimization to Every   Token's Nature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16591</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16591.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zheng Liu, Mengjie Liu, Siwei Wen, Mengzhang Cai, Bin Cui, Conghui He, Wentao Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement Learning has emerged as the fundamental technique for enhancing reasoning in LLMs. However, existing algorithms apply uniform optimization to all tokens, ignoring their different roles in reasoning process. To address this limitation, we introduce Heterogeneous Adaptive Policy Optimization (HAPO), a comprehensive token-aware algorithm that dynamically adapts optimization based on token entropy. For rollout sampling, we propose Adaptive Temperature Sampling, which adjusts sampling temperature in real time, promoting exploration at high-entropy tokens while preserving coherence at low-entropy ones. For advantage calculation, we introduce Token Level Group Average that normalizes advantages at token level, jointly accounting for sequence-length as in token-mean loss while preserving non-biased treatment. We then develop Differential Advantage Redistribution that leverages entropy and importance ratios to modulate rewards-adjusting updates for tokens with clear signals. For clipping loss, we design Asymmetric Adaptive Clipping, allowing aggressive probability reduction for noisy low-entropy tokens while enabling exploration for high-entropy tokens. Through systematic investigation between entropy and training dynamics, we embedded token-level treatment into every stages to achieve fine-grained control. Extensive experiments demonstrate that HAPO consistently outperforms DAPO across multiple model scales. Our code can be found in https://github.com/starriver030515/HAPO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16591</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 09:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing the Effects of Supervised Fine-Tuning on Model Knowledge from   Token and Parameter Levels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16596</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16596.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junjie Ye, Yuming Yang, Yang Nan, Shuo Li, Qi Zhang, Tao Gui, Xuanjing Huang, Peng Wang, Zhongchao Shi, Jianping Fan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language models (LLMs) acquire substantial world knowledge during pre-training, which is further shaped by post-training techniques such as supervised fine-tuning (SFT). However, the impact of SFT on a model's knowledge remains underexplored, limiting our ability to control knowledge change behavior in fine-tuned models. To address this gap, we evaluate closed-book question answering (CBQA) performance across five LLMs from the LLaMA-2 and LLaMA-3 families. Surprisingly, models fine-tuned on 1,920 samples perform up to 14% worse than those fine-tuned on only 240 samples. Furthermore, varying the level of knowledge mastery in the fine-tuning data leads to performance fluctuations of over 12%. To investigate these effects, we analyze model behavior at both the token and parameter levels. Our analysis reveals that up to 90% of parameter updates during SFT do not contribute to knowledge enhancement. Restoring these updates can improve performance on the CBQA task, depending on the characteristics of the fine-tuning data. These insights offer practical guidance for developing fine-tuning strategies that more effectively strengthen model knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16596</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 09:40:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SWE-Bench Pro: Can AI Agents Solve Long-Horizon Software Engineering   Tasks?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16941</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16941.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiang Deng, Jeff Da, Edwin Pan, Yannis Yiming He, Charles Ide, Kanak Garg, Niklas Lauffer, Andrew Park, Nitin Pasari, Chetan Rane, Karmini Sampath, Maya Krishnan, Srivatsa Kundurthy, Sean Hendryx, Zifan Wang, Chen Bo Calvin Zhang, Noah Jacobson, Bing Liu, Brad Kenstler&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce SWE-Bench Pro, a substantially more challenging benchmark that builds upon the best practices of SWE-BENCH [25], but is explicitly designed to capture realistic, complex, enterprise-level problems beyond the scope of SWE-BENCH. SWE-BENCH PRO contains 1,865 problems sourced from a diverse set of 41 actively maintained repositories spanning business applications, B2B services, and developer tools. The benchmark is partitioned into a public set with open access to problems sourced from 11 repositories, a held-out set of 12 repositories and a commercial set of 18 proprietary repositories where we have formal partnership agreements with early-stage startups. Problems in the held-out and the commercial set are not publicly accessible, but we release results on the commercial set. Our benchmark features long-horizon tasks that may require hours to days for a professional software engineer to complete, often involving patches across multiple files and substantial code modifications. All tasks are human-verified and augmented with sufficient context to ensure resolvability. In our evaluation of widely used coding models, under a unified scaffold, we observe that their performance on SWE-Bench PRO remains below 25% (Pass@1), with GPT-5 achieving the highest score to date at 23.3%. To better understand these limitations, we cluster the failure modes observed in the collected agent trajectories for a clearer characterization of the error patterns exhibited by current models. Overall, SWE-BENCH PRO provides a contamination-resistant testbed that more faithfully captures the complexity and diversity of real-world software development, advancing the pursuit of truly autonomous software engineering agents at a professional level.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16941</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 06:28:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Speech Understanding in Speech-Aware Language Models with GRPO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16990</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.16990.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Avishai Elmakies, Hagai Aronowitz, Nimrod Shabtay, Eli Schwartz, Ron Hoory, Avihu Dekel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 14&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce a Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO)-based method for training Speech-Aware Large Language Models (SALLMs) on open-format speech understanding tasks, such as Spoken Question Answering and Automatic Speech Translation. SALLMs have proven highly effective for speech understanding tasks. GRPO has recently gained traction for its efficiency in training LLMs, and prior work has explored its application to SALLMs, primarily in multiple-choice tasks. Building on this, we focus on open-format tasks that better reflect the generative abilities of the models. Our approach leverages GRPO with BLEU as the reward signal to optimize SALLMs, and we demonstrate empirically that it surpasses standard SFT across several key metrics. Finally, we explore the potential of incorporating off-policy samples within GRPO for these tasks, highlighting avenues for further improvement and further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16990</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 09:09:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HyRF: Hybrid Radiance Fields for Memory-efficient and High-quality Novel   View Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17083</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17083.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zipeng Wang, Dan Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recently, 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) has emerged as a powerful alternative to NeRF-based approaches, enabling real-time, high-quality novel view synthesis through explicit, optimizable 3D Gaussians. However, 3DGS suffers from significant memory overhead due to its reliance on per-Gaussian parameters to model view-dependent effects and anisotropic shapes. While recent works propose compressing 3DGS with neural fields, these methods struggle to capture high-frequency spatial variations in Gaussian properties, leading to degraded reconstruction of fine details. We present Hybrid Radiance Fields (HyRF), a novel scene representation that combines the strengths of explicit Gaussians and neural fields. HyRF decomposes the scene into (1) a compact set of explicit Gaussians storing only critical high-frequency parameters and (2) grid-based neural fields that predict remaining properties. To enhance representational capacity, we introduce a decoupled neural field architecture, separately modeling geometry (scale, opacity, rotation) and view-dependent color. Additionally, we propose a hybrid rendering scheme that composites Gaussian splatting with a neural field-predicted background, addressing limitations in distant scene representation. Experiments demonstrate that HyRF achieves state-of-the-art rendering quality while reducing model size by over 20 times compared to 3DGS and maintaining real-time performance. Our project page is available at https://wzpscott.github.io/hyrf/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17083</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 13:59:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARE: Scaling Up Agent Environments and Evaluations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17158</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17158.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pierre Andrews, Amine Benhalloum, Gerard Moreno-Torres Bertran, Matteo Bettini, Amar Budhiraja, Ricardo Silveira Cabral, Virginie Do, Romain Froger, Emilien Garreau, Jean-Baptiste Gaya, Hugo Laurençon, Maxime Lecanu, Kunal Malkan, Dheeraj Mekala, Pierre Ménard, Grégoire Mialon, Ulyana Piterbarg, Mikhail Plekhanov, Mathieu Rita, Andrey Rusakov, Thomas Scialom, Vladislav Vorotilov, Mengjue Wang, Ian Yu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 29&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Meta Agents Research Environments (ARE), a research platform for scalable creation of environments, integration of synthetic or real applications, and execution of agentic orchestrations. ARE provides simple abstractions to build complex and diverse environments, each with their own rules, tools, content, and verifiers, helping to bridge the gap between model development and real-world deployment. We also propose Gaia2, a benchmark built in ARE and designed to measure general agent capabilities. Beyond search and execution, Gaia2 requires agents to handle ambiguities and noise, adapt to dynamic environments, collaborate with other agents, and operate under temporal constraints. Unlike prior benchmarks, Gaia2 runs asynchronously, surfacing new failure modes that are invisible in static settings. Our experiments show that no system dominates across the intelligence spectrum: stronger reasoning often comes at the cost of efficiency, and budget scaling curves plateau, highlighting the need for new architectures and adaptive compute strategies. Perhaps more importantly, ARE abstractions enable continuous extension of Gaia2 to other environments, empowering the community to rapidly create new benchmarks tailored to their domains. In AI's second half, progress increasingly depends on defining meaningful tasks and robust evaluations to drive frontier capabilities forward.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17158</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 16:59:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlagEval Findings Report: A Preliminary Evaluation of Large Reasoning   Models on Automatically Verifiable Textual and Visual Questions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17177</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17177.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bowen Qin, Chen Yue, Fang Yin, Hui Wang, JG Yao, Jiakang Liu, Jing-Shu Zheng, Miguel Hu Chen, Richeng Xuan, Shibei Meng, Shiqi Zhou, Teng Dai, Tong-Shuai Ren, Wei Cui, Xi Yang, Xialin Du, Xiaojing Xu, Xue Sun, Xuejing Li, Yaming Liu, Yesheng Liu, Ying Liu, Yonghua Lin, Yu Zhao, Yunduo Zhang, Yuwen Luo, Zheqi He, Zhiyuan He, Zhongyuan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We conduct a moderate-scale contamination-free (to some extent) evaluation of current large reasoning models (LRMs) with some preliminary findings. We also release ROME, our evaluation benchmark for vision language models intended to test reasoning from visual clues. We attach links to the benchmark, evaluation data, and other updates on this website: https://flageval-baai.github.io/LRM-Eval/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17177</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 17:53:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenGVL - Benchmarking Visual Temporal Progress for Data Curation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17321</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17321.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Paweł Budzianowski, Emilia Wiśnios, Gracjan Góral, Igor Kulakov, Viktor Petrenko, Krzysztof Walas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Data scarcity remains one of the most limiting factors in driving progress in robotics. However, the amount of available robotics data in the wild is growing exponentially, creating new opportunities for large-scale data utilization. Reliable temporal task completion prediction could help automatically annotate and curate this data at scale. The Generative Value Learning (GVL) approach was recently proposed, leveraging the knowledge embedded in vision-language models (VLMs) to predict task progress from visual observations. Building upon GVL, we propose OpenGVL, a comprehensive benchmark for estimating task progress across diverse challenging manipulation tasks involving both robotic and human embodiments. We evaluate the capabilities of publicly available open-source foundation models, showing that open-source model families significantly underperform closed-source counterparts, achieving only approximately 70% of their performance on temporal progress prediction tasks. Furthermore, we demonstrate how OpenGVL can serve as a practical tool for automated data curation and filtering, enabling efficient quality assessment of large-scale robotics datasets. We release the benchmark along with the complete codebase at github.com/budzianowski/opengvl{OpenGVL}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17321</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 02:52:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mano Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17336</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17336.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tianyu Fu, Anyang Su, Chenxu Zhao, Hanning Wang, Minghui Wu, Zhe Yu, Fei Hu, Mingjia Shi, Wei Dong, Jiayao Wang, Yuyang Chen, Ruiyang Yu, Siran Peng, Menglin Li, Nan Huang, Haitian Wei, Jiawei Yu, Yi Xin, Xilin Zhao, Kai Gu, Ping Jiang, Sifan Zhou, Shuo Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Graphical user interfaces (GUIs) are the primary medium for human-computer interaction, yet automating GUI interactions remains challenging due to the complexity of visual elements, dynamic environments, and the need for multi-step reasoning. Existing methods based on vision-language models (VLMs) often suffer from limited resolution, domain mismatch, and insufficient sequential decisionmaking capability. To address these issues, we propose Mano, a robust GUI agent built upon a multi-modal foundation model pre-trained on extensive web and computer system data. Our approach integrates a novel simulated environment for high-fidelity data generation, a three-stage training pipeline (supervised fine-tuning, offline reinforcement learning, and online reinforcement learning), and a verification module for error recovery. Mano demonstrates state-of-the-art performance on multiple GUI benchmarks, including Mind2Web and OSWorld, achieving significant improvements in success rate and operational accuracy. Our work provides new insights into the effective integration of reinforcement learning with VLMs for practical GUI agent deployment, highlighting the importance of domain-specific data, iterative training, and holistic reward design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17336</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 03:13:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EpiCache: Episodic KV Cache Management for Long Conversational Question   Answering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17396</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17396.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minsoo Kim, Arnav Kundu, Han-Byul Kim, Richa Dixit, Minsik Cho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 18&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have extended context lengths, enabling assistants to sustain long histories for coherent, personalized responses. This ability, however, hinges on Key-Value (KV) caching, whose memory grows linearly with dialogue length and quickly dominates under strict resource constraints. An active line of research for reducing this overhead is KV cache compression, which seeks to limit cache size while preserving accuracy. Yet existing methods face two major limitations: (i) evicting entries after full-context prefill causes unbounded peak memory, and (ii) query-dependent eviction narrows the cache to a single query, leading to degraded accuracy in multi-turn conversations. We introduce EpiCache, a training-free KV cache management framework for long conversational question answering (LongConvQA) under fixed memory budgets. EpiCache bounds cache growth through block-wise prefill and preserves topic-relevant context via episodic KV compression, which clusters conversation history into coherent episodes and applies episode-specific KV cache eviction. We further design an adaptive layer-wise budget allocation strategy that measures each layer's sensitivity to eviction and distributes the memory budget across layers accordingly. Across three LongConvQA benchmarks, EpiCache improves accuracy by up to 40% over recent baselines, sustains near-full KV accuracy under 4-6x compression, and reduces latency and memory by up to 2.4x and 3.5x, thereby enabling efficient multi-turn interaction under strict resource constraints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17396</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 06:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QWHA: Quantization-Aware Walsh-Hadamard Adaptation for   Parameter-Efficient Fine-Tuning on Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17428</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17428.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyesung Jeon, Seojune Lee, Beomseok Kang, Yulhwa Kim, Jae-Joon Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The demand for efficient deployment of large language models (LLMs) has driven interest in quantization, which reduces inference cost, and parameter-efficient fine-tuning (PEFT), which lowers training overhead. This motivated the development of quantization-aware PEFT to produce accurate yet efficient quantized models. In this setting, reducing quantization error prior to fine-tuning is crucial for achieving high model accuracy. However, existing methods that rely on low-rank adaptation suffer from limited representational capacity. Recent Fourier-related transform (FT)-based adapters offer greater representational power than low-rank adapters, but their direct integration into quantized models often results in ineffective error reduction and increased computational overhead. To overcome these limitations, we propose QWHA, a method that integrates FT-based adapters into quantized models by employing the Walsh-Hadamard Transform (WHT) as the transform kernel, together with a novel adapter initialization scheme incorporating adaptive parameter selection and value refinement. We demonstrate that QWHA effectively mitigates quantization errors while facilitating fine-tuning, and that its design substantially reduces computational cost. Experimental results show that QWHA consistently outperforms baselines in low-bit quantization accuracy and achieves significant training speedups over existing FT-based adapters. The code is available at https://github.com/vantaa89/qwha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17428</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 07:21:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GeoPQA: Bridging the Visual Perception Gap in MLLMs for Geometric   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17437</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17437.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guizhen Chen, Weiwen Xu, Hao Zhang, Hou Pong Chan, Deli Zhao, Anh Tuan Luu, Yu Rong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advancements in reinforcement learning (RL) have enhanced the reasoning abilities of large language models (LLMs), yet the impact on multimodal LLMs (MLLMs) is limited. Particularly in vision-intensive tasks like geometric reasoning, MLLMs hallucinate frequently, leading to inaccurate reasoning. We attribute this to the perceptual bottleneck in MLLMs, which caps the benefits of reasoning training. To quantify this, we design a Geo-Perception Question-Answering (GeoPQA) benchmark, targeting basic geometric concepts and spatial relationships. Experiments on GeoPQA reveal significant shortcomings of MLLMs in visual perception, which constrain RL reward signals for effective training. To address this bottleneck, we propose a two-stage RL training framework by first enhancing the visual perception of geometric structures, then fostering reasoning capabilities. Applied to Qwen2.5-VL-3B-Instruct, our two-stage training improves geometric reasoning by 9.7% and geometric problem solving by 9.1%, compared to the direct reasoning training approach. Our method also generalizes to other vision-intensive domains like figure understanding, highlighting the importance of perceptual grounding in effective MLLM reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17437</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 07:28:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LIMI: Less is More for Agency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17567</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17567.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Xiao, Mohan Jiang, Jie Sun, Keyu Li, Jifan Lin, Yumin Zhuang, Ji Zeng, Shijie Xia, Qishuo Hua, Xuefeng Li, Xiaojie Cai, Tongyu Wang, Yue Zhang, Liming Liu, Xia Wu, Jinlong Hou, Yuan Cheng, Wenjie Li, Xiang Wang, Dequan Wang, Pengfei Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 91&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We define Agency as the emergent capacity of AI systems to function as autonomous agents actively discovering problems, formulating hypotheses, and executing solutions through self-directed engagement with environments and tools. This fundamental capability marks the dawn of the Age of AI Agency, driven by a critical industry shift: the urgent need for AI systems that don't just think, but work. While current AI excels at reasoning and generating responses, industries demand autonomous agents that can execute tasks, operate tools, and drive real-world outcomes. As agentic intelligence becomes the defining characteristic separating cognitive systems from productive workers, efficiently cultivating machine autonomy becomes paramount. Current approaches assume that more data yields better agency, following traditional scaling laws from language modeling. We fundamentally challenge this paradigm. LIMI (Less Is More for Intelligent Agency) demonstrates that agency follows radically different development principles. Through strategic focus on collaborative software development and scientific research workflows, we show that sophisticated agentic intelligence can emerge from minimal but strategically curated demonstrations of autonomous behavior. Using only 78 carefully designed training samples, LIMI achieves 73.5% on comprehensive agency benchmarks, dramatically outperforming state-of-the-art models: Kimi-K2-Instruct (24.1%), DeepSeek-V3.1 (11.9%), Qwen3-235B-A22B-Instruct (27.5%), and GLM-4.5 (45.1%). Most strikingly, LIMI demonstrates 53.7% improvement over models trained on 10,000 samples-achieving superior agentic intelligence with 128 times fewer samples. Our findings establish the Agency Efficiency Principle: machine autonomy emerges not from data abundance but from strategic curation of high-quality agentic demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17567</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OmniInsert: Mask-Free Video Insertion of Any Reference via Diffusion   Transformer Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17627</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17627.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinshu Chen, Xinghui Li, Xu Bai, Tianxiang Ma, Pengze Zhang, Zhuowei Chen, Gen Li, Lijie Liu, Songtao Zhao, Bingchuan Li, Qian He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in video insertion based on diffusion models are impressive. However, existing methods rely on complex control signals but struggle with subject consistency, limiting their practical applicability. In this paper, we focus on the task of Mask-free Video Insertion and aim to resolve three key challenges: data scarcity, subject-scene equilibrium, and insertion harmonization. To address the data scarcity, we propose a new data pipeline InsertPipe, constructing diverse cross-pair data automatically. Building upon our data pipeline, we develop OmniInsert, a novel unified framework for mask-free video insertion from both single and multiple subject references. Specifically, to maintain subject-scene equilibrium, we introduce a simple yet effective Condition-Specific Feature Injection mechanism to distinctly inject multi-source conditions and propose a novel Progressive Training strategy that enables the model to balance feature injection from subjects and source video. Meanwhile, we design the Subject-Focused Loss to improve the detailed appearance of the subjects. To further enhance insertion harmonization, we propose an Insertive Preference Optimization methodology to optimize the model by simulating human preferences, and incorporate a Context-Aware Rephraser module during reference to seamlessly integrate the subject into the original scenes. To address the lack of a benchmark for the field, we introduce InsertBench, a comprehensive benchmark comprising diverse scenes with meticulously selected subjects. Evaluation on InsertBench indicates OmniInsert outperforms state-of-the-art closed-source commercial solutions. The code will be released.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17627</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 11:35:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AuditoryBench++: Can Language Models Understand Auditory Knowledge   without Hearing?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17641</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17641.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyunjong Ok, Suho Yoo, Hyeonjun Kim, Jaeho Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Even without directly hearing sounds, humans can effortlessly reason about auditory properties, such as pitch, loudness, or sound-source associations, drawing on auditory commonsense. In contrast, language models often lack this capability, limiting their effectiveness in multimodal interactions. As an initial step to address this gap, we present AuditoryBench++, a comprehensive benchmark for evaluating auditory knowledge and reasoning in text-only settings. The benchmark encompasses tasks that range from basic auditory comparisons to contextually grounded reasoning, enabling fine-grained analysis of how models process and integrate auditory concepts. In addition, we introduce AIR-CoT, a novel auditory imagination reasoning method that generates and integrates auditory information during inference through span detection with special tokens and knowledge injection. Extensive experiments with recent LLMs and Multimodal LLMs demonstrate that AIR-CoT generally outperforms both the off-the-shelf models and those augmented with auditory knowledge. The project page is available at https://auditorybenchpp.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17641</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 11:45:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turk-LettuceDetect: A Hallucination Detection Models for Turkish RAG   Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17671</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17671.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Selva Taş, Mahmut El Huseyni, Özay Ezerceli, Reyhan Bayraktar, Fatma Betül Terzioğlu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The widespread adoption of Large Language Models (LLMs) has been hindered by their tendency to hallucinate, generating plausible but factually incorrect information. While Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) systems attempt to address this issue by grounding responses in external knowledge, hallucination remains a persistent challenge, particularly for morphologically complex, low-resource languages like Turkish. This paper introduces Turk-LettuceDetect, the first suite of hallucination detection models specifically designed for Turkish RAG applications. Building on the LettuceDetect framework, we formulate hallucination detection as a token-level classification task and fine-tune three distinct encoder architectures: a Turkish-specific ModernBERT, TurkEmbed4STS, and multilingual EuroBERT. These models were trained on a machine-translated version of the RAGTruth benchmark dataset containing 17,790 instances across question answering, data-to-text generation, and summarization tasks. Our experimental results show that the ModernBERT-based model achieves an F1-score of 0.7266 on the complete test set, with particularly strong performance on structured tasks. The models maintain computational efficiency while supporting long contexts up to 8,192 tokens, making them suitable for real-time deployment. Comparative analysis reveals that while state-of-the-art LLMs demonstrate high recall, they suffer from low precision due to over-generation of hallucinated content, underscoring the necessity of specialized detection mechanisms. By releasing our models and translated dataset, this work addresses a critical gap in multilingual NLP and establishes a foundation for developing more reliable and trustworthy AI applications for Turkish and other languages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17671</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 12:14:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Qwen3-Omni Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17765</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17765.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jin Xu, Zhifang Guo, Hangrui Hu, Yunfei Chu, Xiong Wang, Jinzheng He, Yuxuan Wang, Xian Shi, Ting He, Xinfa Zhu, Yuanjun Lv, Yongqi Wang, Dake Guo, He Wang, Linhan Ma, Pei Zhang, Xinyu Zhang, Hongkun Hao, Zishan Guo, Baosong Yang, Bin Zhang, Ziyang Ma, Xipin Wei, Shuai Bai, Keqin Chen, Xuejing Liu, Peng Wang, Mingkun Yang, Dayiheng Liu, Xingzhang Ren, Bo Zheng, Rui Men, Fan Zhou, Bowen Yu, Jianxin Yang, Le Yu, Jingren Zhou, Junyang Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 116&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present Qwen3-Omni, a single multimodal model that, for the first time, maintains state-of-the-art performance across text, image, audio, and video without any degradation relative to single-modal counterparts. Qwen3-Omni matches the performance of same-sized single-modal models within the Qwen series and excels particularly on audio tasks. Across 36 audio and audio-visual benchmarks, Qwen3-Omni achieves open-source SOTA on 32 benchmarks and overall SOTA on 22, outperforming strong closed-source models such as Gemini-2.5-Pro, Seed-ASR, and GPT-4o-Transcribe. Qwen3-Omni adopts a Thinker-Talker MoE architecture that unifies perception and generation across text, images, audio, and video, yielding fluent text and natural real-time speech. It supports text interaction in 119 languages, speech understanding in 19 languages, and speech generation in 10 languages. To reduce first-packet latency in streaming synthesis, Talker autoregressively predicts discrete speech codecs using a multi-codebook scheme. Leveraging the representational capacity of these codebooks, we replace computationally intensive block-wise diffusion with a lightweight causal ConvNet, enabling streaming from the first codec frame. In cold-start settings, Qwen3-Omni achieves a theoretical end-to-end first-packet latency of 234 ms. To further strengthen multimodal reasoning, we introduce a Thinking model that explicitly reasons over inputs from any modality. Since the research community currently lacks a general-purpose audio captioning model, we fine-tuned Qwen3-Omni-30B-A3B to obtain Qwen3-Omni-30B-A3B-Captioner, which produces detailed, low-hallucination captions for arbitrary audio inputs. Qwen3-Omni-30B-A3B, Qwen3-Omni-30B-A3B-Thinking, and Qwen3-Omni-30B-A3B-Captioner are publicly released under the Apache 2.0 license.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17765</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 13:26:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate and Efficient Low-Rank Model Merging in Core Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17786</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17786.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aniello Panariello, Daniel Marczak, Simone Magistri, Angelo Porrello, Bartłomiej Twardowski, Andrew D. Bagdanov, Simone Calderara, Joost van de Weijer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we address the challenges associated with merging low-rank adaptations of large neural networks. With the rise of parameter-efficient adaptation techniques, such as Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), model fine-tuning has become more accessible. While fine-tuning models with LoRA is highly efficient, existing merging methods often sacrifice this efficiency by merging fully-sized weight matrices. We propose the Core Space merging framework, which enables the merging of LoRA-adapted models within a common alignment basis, thereby preserving the efficiency of low-rank adaptation while substantially improving accuracy across tasks. We further provide a formal proof that projection into Core Space ensures no loss of information and provide a complexity analysis showing the efficiency gains. Extensive empirical results demonstrate that Core Space significantly improves existing merging techniques and achieves state-of-the-art results on both vision and language tasks while utilizing a fraction of the computational resources. Codebase is available at https://github.com/apanariello4/core-space-merging.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17786</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 13:48:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ContextFlow: Training-Free Video Object Editing via Adaptive Context   Enrichment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17818</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17818.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiyang Chen, Xuanhua He, Xiujun Ma, Yue Ma&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training-free video object editing aims to achieve precise object-level manipulation, including object insertion, swapping, and deletion. However, it faces significant challenges in maintaining fidelity and temporal consistency. Existing methods, often designed for U-Net architectures, suffer from two primary limitations: inaccurate inversion due to first-order solvers, and contextual conflicts caused by crude "hard" feature replacement. These issues are more challenging in Diffusion Transformers (DiTs), where the unsuitability of prior layer-selection heuristics makes effective guidance challenging. To address these limitations, we introduce ContextFlow, a novel training-free framework for DiT-based video object editing. In detail, we first employ a high-order Rectified Flow solver to establish a robust editing foundation. The core of our framework is Adaptive Context Enrichment (for specifying what to edit), a mechanism that addresses contextual conflicts. Instead of replacing features, it enriches the self-attention context by concatenating Key-Value pairs from parallel reconstruction and editing paths, empowering the model to dynamically fuse information. Additionally, to determine where to apply this enrichment (for specifying where to edit), we propose a systematic, data-driven analysis to identify task-specific vital layers. Based on a novel Guidance Responsiveness Metric, our method pinpoints the most influential DiT blocks for different tasks (e.g., insertion, swapping), enabling targeted and highly effective guidance. Extensive experiments show that ContextFlow significantly outperforms existing training-free methods and even surpasses several state-of-the-art training-based approaches, delivering temporally coherent, high-fidelity results.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17818</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 14:13:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D-REX: A Benchmark for Detecting Deceptive Reasoning in Large Language   Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17938</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17938.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Satyapriya Krishna, Andy Zou, Rahul Gupta, Eliot Krzysztof Jones, Nick Winter, Dan Hendrycks, J. Zico Kolter, Matt Fredrikson, Spyros Matsoukas&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The safety and alignment of Large Language Models (LLMs) are critical for their responsible deployment. Current evaluation methods predominantly focus on identifying and preventing overtly harmful outputs. However, they often fail to address a more insidious failure mode: models that produce benign-appearing outputs while operating on malicious or deceptive internal reasoning. This vulnerability, often triggered by sophisticated system prompt injections, allows models to bypass conventional safety filters, posing a significant, underexplored risk. To address this gap, we introduce the Deceptive Reasoning Exposure Suite (D-REX), a novel dataset designed to evaluate the discrepancy between a model's internal reasoning process and its final output. D-REX was constructed through a competitive red-teaming exercise where participants crafted adversarial system prompts to induce such deceptive behaviors. Each sample in D-REX contains the adversarial system prompt, an end-user's test query, the model's seemingly innocuous response, and, crucially, the model's internal chain-of-thought, which reveals the underlying malicious intent. Our benchmark facilitates a new, essential evaluation task: the detection of deceptive alignment. We demonstrate that D-REX presents a significant challenge for existing models and safety mechanisms, highlighting the urgent need for new techniques that scrutinize the internal processes of LLMs, not just their final outputs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17938</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 15:59:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VideoFrom3D: 3D Scene Video Generation via Complementary Image and Video   Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17985</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.17985.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Geonung Kim, Janghyeok Han, Sunghyun Cho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we propose VideoFrom3D, a novel framework for synthesizing high-quality 3D scene videos from coarse geometry, a camera trajectory, and a reference image. Our approach streamlines the 3D graphic design workflow, enabling flexible design exploration and rapid production of deliverables. A straightforward approach to synthesizing a video from coarse geometry might condition a video diffusion model on geometric structure. However, existing video diffusion models struggle to generate high-fidelity results for complex scenes due to the difficulty of jointly modeling visual quality, motion, and temporal consistency. To address this, we propose a generative framework that leverages the complementary strengths of image and video diffusion models. Specifically, our framework consists of a Sparse Anchor-view Generation (SAG) and a Geometry-guided Generative Inbetweening (GGI) module. The SAG module generates high-quality, cross-view consistent anchor views using an image diffusion model, aided by Sparse Appearance-guided Sampling. Building on these anchor views, GGI module faithfully interpolates intermediate frames using a video diffusion model, enhanced by flow-based camera control and structural guidance. Notably, both modules operate without any paired dataset of 3D scene models and natural images, which is extremely difficult to obtain. Comprehensive experiments show that our method produces high-quality, style-consistent scene videos under diverse and challenging scenarios, outperforming simple and extended baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17985</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 16:28:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Attention is Half Explanation in Speech-to-Text Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18010</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18010.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sara Papi, Dennis Fucci, Marco Gaido, Matteo Negri, Luisa Bentivogli&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Cross-attention is a core mechanism in encoder-decoder architectures, widespread in many fields, including speech-to-text (S2T) processing. Its scores have been repurposed for various downstream applications--such as timestamp estimation and audio-text alignment--under the assumption that they reflect the dependencies between input speech representation and the generated text. While the explanatory nature of attention mechanisms has been widely debated in the broader NLP literature, this assumption remains largely unexplored within the speech domain. To address this gap, we assess the explanatory power of cross-attention in S2T models by comparing its scores to input saliency maps derived from feature attribution. Our analysis spans monolingual and multilingual, single-task and multi-task models at multiple scales, and shows that attention scores moderately to strongly align with saliency-based explanations, particularly when aggregated across heads and layers. However, it also shows that cross-attention captures only about 50% of the input relevance and, in the best case, only partially reflects how the decoder attends to the encoder's representations--accounting for just 52-75% of the saliency. These findings uncover fundamental limitations in interpreting cross-attention as an explanatory proxy, suggesting that it offers an informative yet incomplete view of the factors driving predictions in S2T models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18010</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 16:49:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V2V-GoT: Vehicle-to-Vehicle Cooperative Autonomous Driving with   Multimodal Large Language Models and Graph-of-Thoughts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18053</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18053.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hsu-kuang Chiu, Ryo Hachiuma, Chien-Yi Wang, Yu-Chiang Frank Wang, Min-Hung Chen, Stephen F. Smith&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Current state-of-the-art autonomous vehicles could face safety-critical situations when their local sensors are occluded by large nearby objects on the road. Vehicle-to-vehicle (V2V) cooperative autonomous driving has been proposed as a means of addressing this problem, and one recently introduced framework for cooperative autonomous driving has further adopted an approach that incorporates a Multimodal Large Language Model (MLLM) to integrate cooperative perception and planning processes. However, despite the potential benefit of applying graph-of-thoughts reasoning to the MLLM, this idea has not been considered by previous cooperative autonomous driving research. In this paper, we propose a novel graph-of-thoughts framework specifically designed for MLLM-based cooperative autonomous driving. Our graph-of-thoughts includes our proposed novel ideas of occlusion-aware perception and planning-aware prediction. We curate the V2V-GoT-QA dataset and develop the V2V-GoT model for training and testing the cooperative driving graph-of-thoughts. Our experimental results show that our method outperforms other baselines in cooperative perception, prediction, and planning tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18053</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:27:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TempSamp-R1: Effective Temporal Sampling with Reinforcement Fine-Tuning   for Video LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18056</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18056.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunheng Li, Jing Cheng, Shaoyong Jia, Hangyi Kuang, Shaohui Jiao, Qibin Hou, Ming-Ming Cheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces TempSamp-R1, a new reinforcement fine-tuning framework designed to improve the effectiveness of adapting multimodal large language models (MLLMs) to video temporal grounding tasks. We reveal that existing reinforcement learning methods, such as Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), rely on on-policy sampling for policy updates. However, in tasks with large temporal search spaces, this strategy becomes both inefficient and limited in performance, as it often fails to identify temporally accurate solutions. To address this limitation, TempSamp-R1 leverages ground-truth annotations as off-policy supervision to provide temporally precise guidance, effectively compensating for the sparsity and misalignment in on-policy solutions. To further stabilize training and reduce variance in reward-based updates, TempSamp-R1 provides a non-linear soft advantage computation method that dynamically reshapes the reward feedback via an asymmetric transformation. By employing a hybrid Chain-of-Thought (CoT) training paradigm, TempSamp-R1 optimizes a single unified model to support both CoT and non-CoT inference modes, enabling efficient handling of queries with varying reasoning complexity. Experimental results demonstrate that TempSamp-R1 outperforms GRPO-based baselines, establishing new state-of-the-art performance on benchmark datasets: Charades-STA (R1@0.7: 52.9%, +2.7%), ActivityNet Captions (R1@0.5: 56.0%, +5.3%), and QVHighlights (mAP: 30.0%, +3.0%). Moreover, TempSamp-R1 shows robust few-shot generalization capabilities under limited data. Code: https://github.com/HVision-NKU/TempSamp-R1&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18056</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strategic Dishonesty Can Undermine AI Safety Evaluations of Frontier LLM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18058</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18058.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Panfilov, Evgenii Kortukov, Kristina Nikolić, Matthias Bethge, Sebastian Lapuschkin, Wojciech Samek, Ameya Prabhu, Maksym Andriushchenko, Jonas Geiping&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large language model (LLM) developers aim for their models to be honest, helpful, and harmless. However, when faced with malicious requests, models are trained to refuse, sacrificing helpfulness. We show that frontier LLMs can develop a preference for dishonesty as a new strategy, even when other options are available. Affected models respond to harmful requests with outputs that sound harmful but are subtly incorrect or otherwise harmless in practice. This behavior emerges with hard-to-predict variations even within models from the same model family. We find no apparent cause for the propensity to deceive, but we show that more capable models are better at executing this strategy. Strategic dishonesty already has a practical impact on safety evaluations, as we show that dishonest responses fool all output-based monitors used to detect jailbreaks that we test, rendering benchmark scores unreliable. Further, strategic dishonesty can act like a honeypot against malicious users, which noticeably obfuscates prior jailbreak attacks. While output monitors fail, we show that linear probes on internal activations can be used to reliably detect strategic dishonesty. We validate probes on datasets with verifiable outcomes and by using their features as steering vectors. Overall, we consider strategic dishonesty as a concrete example of a broader concern that alignment of LLMs is hard to control, especially when helpfulness and harmlessness conflict.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18058</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:30:56 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Core: A Scalable RL Environment for LLM Symbolic Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18083</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18083.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Valentin Lacombe, Valentin Quesnel, Damien Sileo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Reasoning Core, a new scalable environment for Reinforcement Learning with Verifiable Rewards (RLVR), designed to advance foundational symbolic reasoning in Large Language Models (LLMs). Unlike existing benchmarks that focus on games or isolated puzzles, Reasoning Core procedurally generates problems across core formal domains, including PDDL planning, first-order logic, context-free grammar parsing, causal reasoning, and system equation solving. The environment is built on key design principles of high-generality problem distributions, verification via external tools, and continuous difficulty control, which together provide a virtually infinite supply of novel training instances. Initial zero-shot evaluations with frontier LLMs confirm the difficulty of Reasoning Core's tasks, positioning it as a promising resource to improve the reasoning capabilities of future models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18083</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:56:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ByteWrist: A Parallel Robotic Wrist Enabling Flexible and   Anthropomorphic Motion for Confined Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18084</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18084.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiawen Tian, Liqun Huang, Zhongren Cui, Jingchao Qiao, Jiafeng Xu, Xiao Ma, Zeyu Ren&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces ByteWrist, a novel highly-flexible and anthropomorphic parallel wrist for robotic manipulation. ByteWrist addresses the critical limitations of existing serial and parallel wrists in narrow-space operations through a compact three-stage parallel drive mechanism integrated with arc-shaped end linkages. The design achieves precise RPY (Roll-Pitch-Yaw) motion while maintaining exceptional compactness, making it particularly suitable for complex unstructured environments such as home services, medical assistance, and precision assembly. The key innovations include: (1) a nested three-stage motor-driven linkages that minimize volume while enabling independent multi-DOF control, (2) arc-shaped end linkages that optimize force transmission and expand motion range, and (3) a central supporting ball functioning as a spherical joint that enhances structural stiffness without compromising flexibility. Meanwhile, we present comprehensive kinematic modeling including forward / inverse kinematics and a numerical Jacobian solution for precise control. Empirically, we observe ByteWrist demonstrates strong performance in narrow-space maneuverability and dual-arm cooperative manipulation tasks, outperforming Kinova-based systems. Results indicate significant improvements in compactness, efficiency, and stiffness compared to traditional designs, establishing ByteWrist as a promising solution for next-generation robotic manipulation in constrained environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18084</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:57:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GeoSVR: Taming Sparse Voxels for Geometrically Accurate Surface   Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18090</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18090.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiahe Li, Jiawei Zhang, Youmin Zhang, Xiao Bai, Jin Zheng, Xiaohan Yu, Lin Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reconstructing accurate surfaces with radiance fields has achieved remarkable progress in recent years. However, prevailing approaches, primarily based on Gaussian Splatting, are increasingly constrained by representational bottlenecks. In this paper, we introduce GeoSVR, an explicit voxel-based framework that explores and extends the under-investigated potential of sparse voxels for achieving accurate, detailed, and complete surface reconstruction. As strengths, sparse voxels support preserving the coverage completeness and geometric clarity, while corresponding challenges also arise from absent scene constraints and locality in surface refinement. To ensure correct scene convergence, we first propose a Voxel-Uncertainty Depth Constraint that maximizes the effect of monocular depth cues while presenting a voxel-oriented uncertainty to avoid quality degradation, enabling effective and robust scene constraints yet preserving highly accurate geometries. Subsequently, Sparse Voxel Surface Regularization is designed to enhance geometric consistency for tiny voxels and facilitate the voxel-based formation of sharp and accurate surfaces. Extensive experiments demonstrate our superior performance compared to existing methods across diverse challenging scenarios, excelling in geometric accuracy, detail preservation, and reconstruction completeness while maintaining high efficiency. Code is available at https://github.com/Fictionarry/GeoSVR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18090</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OnePiece: Bringing Context Engineering and Reasoning to Industrial   Cascade Ranking System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18091</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18091.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sunhao Dai, Jiakai Tang, Jiahua Wu, Kun Wang, Yuxuan Zhu, Bingjun Chen, Bangyang Hong, Yu Zhao, Cong Fu, Kangle Wu, Yabo Ni, Anxiang Zeng, Wenjie Wang, Xu Chen, Jun Xu, See-Kiong Ng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 32&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite the growing interest in replicating the scaled success of large language models (LLMs) in industrial search and recommender systems, most existing industrial efforts remain limited to transplanting Transformer architectures, which bring only incremental improvements over strong Deep Learning Recommendation Models (DLRMs). From a first principle perspective, the breakthroughs of LLMs stem not only from their architectures but also from two complementary mechanisms: context engineering, which enriches raw input queries with contextual cues to better elicit model capabilities, and multi-step reasoning, which iteratively refines model outputs through intermediate reasoning paths. However, these two mechanisms and their potential to unlock substantial improvements remain largely underexplored in industrial ranking systems.   In this paper, we propose OnePiece, a unified framework that seamlessly integrates LLM-style context engineering and reasoning into both retrieval and ranking models of industrial cascaded pipelines. OnePiece is built on a pure Transformer backbone and further introduces three key innovations: (1) structured context engineering, which augments interaction history with preference and scenario signals and unifies them into a structured tokenized input sequence for both retrieval and ranking; (2) block-wise latent reasoning, which equips the model with multi-step refinement of representations and scales reasoning bandwidth via block size; (3) progressive multi-task training, which leverages user feedback chains to effectively supervise reasoning steps during training. OnePiece has been deployed in the main personalized search scenario of Shopee and achieves consistent online gains across different key business metrics, including over +2% GMV/UU and a +2.90% increase in advertising revenue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18091</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:59:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniPixel: Unified Object Referring and Segmentation for Pixel-Level   Visual Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18094</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18094.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ye Liu, Zongyang Ma, Junfu Pu, Zhongang Qi, Yang Wu, Ying Shan, Chang Wen Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Multi-modal Models (LMMs) have demonstrated their remarkable success as general-purpose multi-modal assistants, with particular focuses on holistic image- and video-language understanding. Conversely, less attention has been given to scaling fine-grained pixel-level understanding capabilities, where the models are expected to realize pixel-level alignment between visual signals and language semantics. Some previous studies have applied LMMs to related tasks such as region-level captioning and referring expression segmentation. However, these models are limited to performing either referring or segmentation tasks independently and fail to integrate these fine-grained perception capabilities into visual reasoning. To bridge this gap, we propose UniPixel, a large multi-modal model capable of flexibly comprehending visual prompt inputs and generating mask-grounded responses. Our model distinguishes itself by seamlessly integrating pixel-level perception with general visual understanding capabilities. Specifically, UniPixel processes visual prompts and generates relevant masks on demand, and performs subsequent reasoning conditioning on these intermediate pointers during inference, thereby enabling fine-grained pixel-level reasoning. The effectiveness of our approach has been verified on 10 benchmarks across a diverse set of tasks, including pixel-level referring/segmentation and object-centric understanding in images/videos. A novel PixelQA task that jointly requires referring, segmentation, and question answering is also designed to verify the flexibility of our method.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18094</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:59:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MetaEmbed: Scaling Multimodal Retrieval at Test-Time with Flexible Late   Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18095</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18095.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zilin Xiao, Qi Ma, Mengting Gu, Chun-cheng Jason Chen, Xintao Chen, Vicente Ordonez, Vijai Mohan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Universal multimodal embedding models have achieved great success in capturing semantic relevance between queries and candidates. However, current methods either condense queries and candidates into a single vector, potentially limiting the expressiveness for fine-grained information, or produce too many vectors that are prohibitively expensive for multi-vector retrieval. In this work, we introduce MetaEmbed, a new framework for multimodal retrieval that rethinks how multimodal embeddings are constructed and interacted with at scale. During training, a fixed number of learnable Meta Tokens are appended to the input sequence. At test-time, their last-layer contextualized representations serve as compact yet expressive multi-vector embeddings. Through the proposed Matryoshka Multi-Vector Retrieval training, MetaEmbed learns to organize information by granularity across multiple vectors. As a result, we enable test-time scaling in multimodal retrieval, where users can balance retrieval quality against efficiency demands by selecting the number of tokens used for indexing and retrieval interactions. Extensive evaluations on the Massive Multimodal Embedding Benchmark (MMEB) and the Visual Document Retrieval Benchmark (ViDoRe) confirm that MetaEmbed achieves state-of-the-art retrieval performance while scaling robustly to models with 32B parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18095</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 17:59:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SimpleFold: Folding Proteins is Simpler than You Think</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18480</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18480.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuyang Wang, Jiarui Lu, Navdeep Jaitly, Josh Susskind, Miguel Angel Bautista&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Protein folding models have achieved groundbreaking results typically via a combination of integrating domain knowledge into the architectural blocks and training pipelines. Nonetheless, given the success of generative models across different but related problems, it is natural to question whether these architectural designs are a necessary condition to build performant models. In this paper, we introduce SimpleFold, the first flow-matching based protein folding model that solely uses general purpose transformer blocks. Protein folding models typically employ computationally expensive modules involving triangular updates, explicit pair representations or multiple training objectives curated for this specific domain. Instead, SimpleFold employs standard transformer blocks with adaptive layers and is trained via a generative flow-matching objective with an additional structural term. We scale SimpleFold to 3B parameters and train it on approximately 9M distilled protein structures together with experimental PDB data. On standard folding benchmarks, SimpleFold-3B achieves competitive performance compared to state-of-the-art baselines, in addition SimpleFold demonstrates strong performance in ensemble prediction which is typically difficult for models trained via deterministic reconstruction objectives. Due to its general-purpose architecture, SimpleFold shows efficiency in deployment and inference on consumer-level hardware. SimpleFold challenges the reliance on complex domain-specific architectures designs in protein folding, opening up an alternative design space for future progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18480</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 00:33:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do You Need Proprioceptive States in Visuomotor Policies?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18644</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18644.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Juntu Zhao, Wenbo Lu, Di Zhang, Yufeng Liu, Yushen Liang, Tianluo Zhang, Yifeng Cao, Junyuan Xie, Yingdong Hu, Shengjie Wang, Junliang Guo, Dequan Wang, Yang Gao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Imitation-learning-based visuomotor policies have been widely used in robot manipulation, where both visual observations and proprioceptive states are typically adopted together for precise control. However, in this study, we find that this common practice makes the policy overly reliant on the proprioceptive state input, which causes overfitting to the training trajectories and results in poor spatial generalization. On the contrary, we propose the State-free Policy, removing the proprioceptive state input and predicting actions only conditioned on visual observations. The State-free Policy is built in the relative end-effector action space, and should ensure the full task-relevant visual observations, here provided by dual wide-angle wrist cameras. Empirical results demonstrate that the State-free policy achieves significantly stronger spatial generalization than the state-based policy: in real-world tasks such as pick-and-place, challenging shirt-folding, and complex whole-body manipulation, spanning multiple robot embodiments, the average success rate improves from 0\% to 85\% in height generalization and from 6\% to 64\% in horizontal generalization. Furthermore, they also show advantages in data efficiency and cross-embodiment adaptation, enhancing their practicality for real-world deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18644</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 04:56:59 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blueprints of Trust: AI System Cards for End to End Transparency and   Governance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20394</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20394.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huzaifa Sidhpurwala, Emily Fox, Garth Mollett, Florencio Cano Gabarda, Roman Zhukov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces the Hazard-Aware System Card (HASC), a novel framework designed to enhance transparency and accountability in the development and deployment of AI systems. The HASC builds upon existing model card and system card concepts by integrating a comprehensive, dynamic record of an AI system's security and safety posture. The framework proposes a standardized system of identifiers, including a novel AI Safety Hazard (ASH) ID, to complement existing security identifiers like CVEs, allowing for clear and consistent communication of fixed flaws. By providing a single, accessible source of truth, the HASC empowers developers and stakeholders to make more informed decisions about AI system safety throughout its lifecycle. Ultimately, we also compare our proposed AI system cards with the ISO/IEC 42001:2023 standard and discuss how they can be used to complement each other, providing greater transparency and accountability for AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20394</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 05:58:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyper-Bagel: A Unified Acceleration Framework for Multimodal   Understanding and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18824</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18824.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanzuo Lu, Xin Xia, Manlin Zhang, Huafeng Kuang, Jianbin Zheng, Yuxi Ren, Xuefeng Xiao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Unified multimodal models have recently attracted considerable attention for their remarkable abilities in jointly understanding and generating diverse content. However, as contexts integrate increasingly numerous interleaved multimodal tokens, the iterative processes of diffusion denoising and autoregressive decoding impose significant computational overhead. To address this, we propose Hyper-Bagel, a unified acceleration framework designed to simultaneously speed up both multimodal understanding and generation tasks. Our approach uses a divide-and-conquer strategy, employing speculative decoding for next-token prediction and a multi-stage distillation process for diffusion denoising. The framework delivers substantial performance gains, achieving over a 2x speedup in multimodal understanding. For generative tasks, our resulting lossless 6-NFE model yields a 16.67x speedup in text-to-image generation and a 22x speedup in image editing, all while preserving the high-quality output of the original model. We further develop a highly efficient 1-NFE model that enables near real-time interactive editing and generation. By combining advanced adversarial distillation with human feedback learning, this model achieves ultimate cost-effectiveness and responsiveness, making complex multimodal interactions seamless and instantaneous.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18824</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 09:12:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAPO: Mixed Advantage Policy Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18849</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18849.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wenke Huang, Quan Zhang, Yiyang Fang, Jian Liang, Xuankun Rong, Huanjin Yao, Guancheng Wan, Ke Liang, Wenwen He, Mingjun Li, Leszek Rutkowski, Mang Ye, Bo Du, Dacheng Tao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in reinforcement learning for foundation models, such as Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), have significantly improved the performance of foundation models on reasoning tasks. Notably, the advantage function serves as a central mechanism in GRPO for ranking the trajectory importance. However, existing explorations encounter both advantage reversion and advantage mirror problems, which hinder the reasonable advantage allocation across different query samples. In this work, we propose an easy but effective GRPO strategy, Mixed Advantage Policy Optimization (MAPO). We reveal that the trajectory appears with different certainty and propose the advantage percent deviation for samples with high-certainty trajectories. Furthermore, we dynamically reweight the advantage function for samples with varying trajectory certainty, thereby adaptively configuring the advantage function to account for sample-specific characteristics. Comparison with related state-of-the-art methods, along with ablation studies on different advantage variants, validates the effectiveness of our approach.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18849</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 09:37:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Far are VLMs from Visual Spatial Intelligence? A Benchmark-Driven   Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18905</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.18905.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Songsong Yu, Yuxin Chen, Hao Ju, Lianjie Jia, Fuxi Zhang, Shaofei Huang, Yuhan Wu, Rundi Cui, Binghao Ran, Zaibin Zhang, Zhedong Zheng, Zhipeng Zhang, Yifan Wang, Lin Song, Lijun Wang, Yanwei Li, Ying Shan, Huchuan Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 28&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Visual Spatial Reasoning (VSR) is a core human cognitive ability and a critical requirement for advancing embodied intelligence and autonomous systems. Despite recent progress in Vision-Language Models (VLMs), achieving human-level VSR remains highly challenging due to the complexity of representing and reasoning over three-dimensional space. In this paper, we present a systematic investigation of VSR in VLMs, encompassing a review of existing methodologies across input modalities, model architectures, training strategies, and reasoning mechanisms. Furthermore, we categorize spatial intelligence into three levels of capability, ie, basic perception, spatial understanding, spatial planning, and curate SIBench, a spatial intelligence benchmark encompassing nearly 20 open-source datasets across 23 task settings. Experiments with state-of-the-art VLMs reveal a pronounced gap between perception and reasoning, as models show competence in basic perceptual tasks but consistently underperform in understanding and planning tasks, particularly in numerical estimation, multi-view reasoning, temporal dynamics, and spatial imagination. These findings underscore the substantial challenges that remain in achieving spatial intelligence, while providing both a systematic roadmap and a comprehensive benchmark to drive future research in the field. The related resources of this study are accessible at https://sibench.github.io/Awesome-Visual-Spatial-Reasoning/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18905</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 12:00:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VIR-Bench: Evaluating Geospatial and Temporal Understanding of MLLMs via   Travel Video Itinerary Reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19002</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19002.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hao Wang, Eiki Murata, Lingfang Zhang, Ayako Sato, So Fukuda, Ziqi Yin, Wentao Hu, Keisuke Nakao, Yusuke Nakamura, Sebastian Zwirner, Yi-Chia Chen, Hiroyuki Otomo, Hiroki Ouchi, Daisuke Kawahara&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in multimodal large language models (MLLMs) have significantly enhanced video understanding capabilities, opening new possibilities for practical applications. Yet current video benchmarks focus largely on indoor scenes or short-range outdoor activities, leaving the challenges associated with long-distance travel largely unexplored. Mastering extended geospatial-temporal trajectories is critical for next-generation MLLMs, underpinning real-world tasks such as embodied-AI planning and navigation. To bridge this gap, we present VIR-Bench, a novel benchmark consisting of 200 travel videos that frames itinerary reconstruction as a challenging task designed to evaluate and push forward MLLMs' geospatial-temporal intelligence. Experimental results reveal that state-of-the-art MLLMs, including proprietary ones, struggle to achieve high scores, underscoring the difficulty of handling videos that span extended spatial and temporal scales. Moreover, we conduct an in-depth case study in which we develop a prototype travel-planning agent that leverages the insights gained from VIR-Bench. The agent's markedly improved itinerary recommendations verify that our evaluation protocol not only benchmarks models effectively but also translates into concrete performance gains in user-facing applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19002</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 13:46:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft Tokens, Hard Truths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19170</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19170.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Natasha Butt, Ariel Kwiatkowski, Ismail Labiad, Julia Kempe, Yann Ollivier&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The use of continuous instead of discrete tokens during the Chain-of-Thought (CoT) phase of reasoning LLMs has garnered attention recently, based on the intuition that a continuous mixture of discrete tokens could simulate a superposition of several reasoning paths simultaneously. Theoretical results have formally proven that continuous tokens have much greater expressivity and can solve specific problems more efficiently. However, practical use of continuous tokens has been limited by strong training difficulties: previous works either just use continuous tokens at inference time on a pre-trained discrete-token model, or must distill the continuous CoT from ground-truth discrete CoTs and face computational costs that limit the CoT to very few tokens.   This is the first work introducing a scalable method to learn continuous CoTs via reinforcement learning (RL), without distilling from reference discrete CoTs. We use "soft" tokens: mixtures of tokens together with noise on the input embedding to provide RL exploration. Computational overhead is minimal, enabling us to learn continuous CoTs with hundreds of tokens. On math reasoning benchmarks with Llama and Qwen models up to 8B, training with continuous CoTs match discrete-token CoTs for pass@1 and surpass them for pass@32, showing greater CoT diversity. In systematic comparisons, the best-performing scenario is to train with continuous CoT tokens then use discrete tokens for inference, meaning the "soft" models can be deployed in a standard way. Finally, we show continuous CoT RL training better preserves the predictions of the base model on out-of-domain tasks, thus providing a softer touch to the base model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19170</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 15:43:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CompLLM: Compression for Long Context Q&amp;A</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19228</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19228.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gabriele Berton, Jayakrishnan Unnikrishnan, Son Tran, Mubarak Shah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Language Models (LLMs) face significant computational challenges when processing long contexts due to the quadratic complexity of self-attention. While soft context compression methods, which map input text to smaller latent representations, have shown promise, their real-world adoption is limited. Existing techniques typically compress the context as a single unit, which leads to quadratic compression complexity and an inability to reuse computations across queries with overlapping contexts. In this work, we introduce CompLLM, a soft compression technique designed for practical deployment. Instead of processing the context holistically, CompLLM divides it into segments and compresses each one independently. This simple design choice yields three critical properties: efficiency, as the compression step scales linearly with the context length; scalability, enabling models trained on short sequences (e.g., 1k tokens) to generalize to contexts of 100k tokens; and reusability, allowing compressed segments to be cached and reused across different queries. Our experiments show that with a 2x compression rate, at high context lengths CompLLM speeds up Time To First Token (TTFT) by up to 4x and reduces the KV cache size by 50%. Furthermore, CompLLM achieves performance comparable to that obtained with the uncompressed context, and even surpasses it on very long sequences, demonstrating its effectiveness and practical utility.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19228</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 16:49:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lavida-O: Elastic Large Masked Diffusion Models for Unified Multimodal   Understanding and Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19244</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19244.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shufan Li, Jiuxiang Gu, Kangning Liu, Zhe Lin, Zijun Wei, Aditya Grover, Jason Kuen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose Lavida-O, a unified Masked Diffusion Model (MDM) for multimodal understanding and generation. Unlike existing multimodal MDMs such as MMaDa and Muddit which only support simple image-level understanding tasks and low-resolution image generation, Lavida-O presents a single framework that enables image-level understanding, object grounding, image editing, and high-resolution (1024px) text-to-image synthesis. Lavida-O incorporates a novel Elastic Mixture-of-Transformers (Elastic-MoT) architecture that couples a lightweight generation branch with a larger understanding branch, supported by token compression, universal text conditioning and stratified sampling for efficient and high-quality generation. Lavida-O further incorporates planning and iterative self-reflection in image generation and editing tasks, seamlessly boosting generation quality with its understanding capabilities. Lavida-O achieves state-of-the-art performance on a wide range of benchmarks including RefCOCO object grounding, GenEval text-to-image generation, and ImgEdit image editing, outperforming existing autoregressive models and continuous diffusion models such as Qwen2.5-VL and FluxKontext-dev, while offering considerable speedup at inference. These advances establish Lavida-O as a new paradigm for scalable multimodal reasoning and generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19244</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:05:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning on Pre-Training Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19249</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19249.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siheng Li, Kejiao Li, Zenan Xu, Guanhua Huang, Evander Yang, Kun Li, Haoyuan Wu, Jiajia Wu, Zihao Zheng, Chenchen Zhang, Kun Shi, Kyrierl Deng, Qi Yi, Ruibin Xiong, Tingqiang Xu, Yuhao Jiang, Jianfeng Yan, Yuyuan Zeng, Guanghui Xu, Jinbao Xue, Zhijiang Xu, Zheng Fang, Shuai Li, Qibin Liu, Xiaoxue Li, Zhuoyu Li, Yangyu Tao, Fei Gao, Cheng Jiang, Bo Chao Wang, Kai Liu, Jianchen Zhu, Wai Lam, Wayyt Wang, Bo Zhou, Di Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The growing disparity between the exponential scaling of computational resources and the finite growth of high-quality text data now constrains conventional scaling approaches for large language models (LLMs). To address this challenge, we introduce Reinforcement Learning on Pre-Training data (RLPT), a new training-time scaling paradigm for optimizing LLMs. In contrast to prior approaches that scale training primarily through supervised learning, RLPT enables the policy to autonomously explore meaningful trajectories to learn from pre-training data and improve its capability through reinforcement learning (RL). While existing RL strategies such as reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF) and reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards (RLVR) rely on human annotation for reward construction, RLPT eliminates this dependency by deriving reward signals directly from pre-training data. Specifically, it adopts a next-segment reasoning objective, rewarding the policy for accurately predicting subsequent text segments conditioned on the preceding context. This formulation allows RL to be scaled on pre-training data, encouraging the exploration of richer trajectories across broader contexts and thereby fostering more generalizable reasoning skills. Extensive experiments on both general-domain and mathematical reasoning benchmarks across multiple models validate the effectiveness of RLPT. For example, when applied to Qwen3-4B-Base, RLPT yields absolute improvements of 3.0, 5.1, 8.1, 6.0, 6.6, and 5.3 on MMLU, MMLU-Pro, GPQA-Diamond, KOR-Bench, AIME24, and AIME25, respectively. The results further demonstrate favorable scaling behavior, suggesting strong potential for continued gains with more compute. In addition, RLPT provides a solid foundation, extending the reasoning boundaries of LLMs and enhancing RLVR performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19249</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:10:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OverLayBench: A Benchmark for Layout-to-Image Generation with Dense   Overlaps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19282</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19282.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bingnan Li, Chen-Yu Wang, Haiyang Xu, Xiang Zhang, Ethan Armand, Divyansh Srivastava, Xiaojun Shan, Zeyuan Chen, Jianwen Xie, Zhuowen Tu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Despite steady progress in layout-to-image generation, current methods still struggle with layouts containing significant overlap between bounding boxes. We identify two primary challenges: (1) large overlapping regions and (2) overlapping instances with minimal semantic distinction. Through both qualitative examples and quantitative analysis, we demonstrate how these factors degrade generation quality. To systematically assess this issue, we introduce OverLayScore, a novel metric that quantifies the complexity of overlapping bounding boxes. Our analysis reveals that existing benchmarks are biased toward simpler cases with low OverLayScore values, limiting their effectiveness in evaluating model performance under more challenging conditions. To bridge this gap, we present OverLayBench, a new benchmark featuring high-quality annotations and a balanced distribution across different levels of OverLayScore. As an initial step toward improving performance on complex overlaps, we also propose CreatiLayout-AM, a model fine-tuned on a curated amodal mask dataset. Together, our contributions lay the groundwork for more robust layout-to-image generation under realistic and challenging scenarios. Project link: https://mlpc-ucsd.github.io/OverLayBench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19282</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Characterizes Effective Reasoning? Revisiting Length, Review, and   Structure of CoT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19284</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19284.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunzhen Feng, Julia Kempe, Cheng Zhang, Parag Jain, Anthony Hartshorn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 21&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large reasoning models (LRMs) spend substantial test-time compute on long chain-of-thought (CoT) traces, but what *characterizes* an effective CoT remains unclear. While prior work reports gains from lengthening CoTs and increasing review (revisiting earlier steps) via appended *wait* tokens, recent studies suggest that shorter thinking can outperform longer traces. We therefore conduct a systematic evaluation across ten LRMs on math and scientific reasoning. Contrary to the "longer-is-better" narrative, we find that both naive CoT lengthening and increased review are associated with *lower* accuracy.   As CoT unfolds step by step, token-level metrics can conflate verbosity with process quality. We introduce a graph view of CoT to extract structure and identify a single statistic-the *Failed-Step Fraction (FSF)*, the fraction of steps in abandoned branches-that consistently outpredicts length and review ratio for correctness across models. To probe causality, we design two interventions. First, we rank candidate CoTs by each metric at test time, where FSF yields the largest pass@1 gains; second, we edit CoTs to remove failed branches, which significantly improves accuracy, indicating that failed branches bias subsequent reasoning. Taken together, these results characterize effective CoTs as those that *fail less* and support *structure-aware* test-time scaling over indiscriminately generating long CoT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19284</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:50:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lyra: Generative 3D Scene Reconstruction via Video Diffusion Model   Self-Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19296</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19296.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sherwin Bahmani, Tianchang Shen, Jiawei Ren, Jiahui Huang, Yifeng Jiang, Haithem Turki, Andrea Tagliasacchi, David B. Lindell, Zan Gojcic, Sanja Fidler, Huan Ling, Jun Gao, Xuanchi Ren&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The ability to generate virtual environments is crucial for applications ranging from gaming to physical AI domains such as robotics, autonomous driving, and industrial AI. Current learning-based 3D reconstruction methods rely on the availability of captured real-world multi-view data, which is not always readily available. Recent advancements in video diffusion models have shown remarkable imagination capabilities, yet their 2D nature limits the applications to simulation where a robot needs to navigate and interact with the environment. In this paper, we propose a self-distillation framework that aims to distill the implicit 3D knowledge in the video diffusion models into an explicit 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) representation, eliminating the need for multi-view training data. Specifically, we augment the typical RGB decoder with a 3DGS decoder, which is supervised by the output of the RGB decoder. In this approach, the 3DGS decoder can be purely trained with synthetic data generated by video diffusion models. At inference time, our model can synthesize 3D scenes from either a text prompt or a single image for real-time rendering. Our framework further extends to dynamic 3D scene generation from a monocular input video. Experimental results show that our framework achieves state-of-the-art performance in static and dynamic 3D scene generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19296</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:58:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VolSplat: Rethinking Feed-Forward 3D Gaussian Splatting with   Voxel-Aligned Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19297</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19297.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weijie Wang, Yeqing Chen, Zeyu Zhang, Hengyu Liu, Haoxiao Wang, Zhiyuan Feng, Wenkang Qin, Zheng Zhu, Donny Y. Chen, Bohan Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Feed-forward 3D Gaussian Splatting (3DGS) has emerged as a highly effective solution for novel view synthesis. Existing methods predominantly rely on a pixel-aligned Gaussian prediction paradigm, where each 2D pixel is mapped to a 3D Gaussian. We rethink this widely adopted formulation and identify several inherent limitations: it renders the reconstructed 3D models heavily dependent on the number of input views, leads to view-biased density distributions, and introduces alignment errors, particularly when source views contain occlusions or low texture. To address these challenges, we introduce VolSplat, a new multi-view feed-forward paradigm that replaces pixel alignment with voxel-aligned Gaussians. By directly predicting Gaussians from a predicted 3D voxel grid, it overcomes pixel alignment's reliance on error-prone 2D feature matching, ensuring robust multi-view consistency. Furthermore, it enables adaptive control over Gaussian density based on 3D scene complexity, yielding more faithful Gaussian point clouds, improved geometric consistency, and enhanced novel-view rendering quality. Experiments on widely used benchmarks including RealEstate10K and ScanNet demonstrate that VolSplat achieves state-of-the-art performance while producing more plausible and view-consistent Gaussian reconstructions. In addition to superior results, our approach establishes a more scalable framework for feed-forward 3D reconstruction with denser and more robust representations, paving the way for further research in wider communities. The video results, code and trained models are available on our project page: https://lhmd.top/volsplat.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19297</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:59:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CAR-Flow: Condition-Aware Reparameterization Aligns Source and Target   for Better Flow Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19300</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19300.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chen Chen, Pengsheng Guo, Liangchen Song, Jiasen Lu, Rui Qian, Xinze Wang, Tsu-Jui Fu, Wei Liu, Yinfei Yang, Alex Schwing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Conditional generative modeling aims to learn a conditional data distribution from samples containing data-condition pairs. For this, diffusion and flow-based methods have attained compelling results. These methods use a learned (flow) model to transport an initial standard Gaussian noise that ignores the condition to the conditional data distribution. The model is hence required to learn both mass transport and conditional injection. To ease the demand on the model, we propose Condition-Aware Reparameterization for Flow Matching (CAR-Flow) -- a lightweight, learned shift that conditions the source, the target, or both distributions. By relocating these distributions, CAR-Flow shortens the probability path the model must learn, leading to faster training in practice. On low-dimensional synthetic data, we visualize and quantify the effects of CAR. On higher-dimensional natural image data (ImageNet-256), equipping SiT-XL/2 with CAR-Flow reduces FID from 2.07 to 1.68, while introducing less than 0.6% additional parameters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19300</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:59:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Residual Off-Policy RL for Finetuning Behavior Cloning Policies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19301</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19301.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lars Ankile, Zhenyu Jiang, Rocky Duan, Guanya Shi, Pieter Abbeel, Anusha Nagabandi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in behavior cloning (BC) have enabled impressive visuomotor control policies. However, these approaches are limited by the quality of human demonstrations, the manual effort required for data collection, and the diminishing returns from increasing offline data. In comparison, reinforcement learning (RL) trains an agent through autonomous interaction with the environment and has shown remarkable success in various domains. Still, training RL policies directly on real-world robots remains challenging due to sample inefficiency, safety concerns, and the difficulty of learning from sparse rewards for long-horizon tasks, especially for high-degree-of-freedom (DoF) systems. We present a recipe that combines the benefits of BC and RL through a residual learning framework. Our approach leverages BC policies as black-box bases and learns lightweight per-step residual corrections via sample-efficient off-policy RL. We demonstrate that our method requires only sparse binary reward signals and can effectively improve manipulation policies on high-degree-of-freedom (DoF) systems in both simulation and the real world. In particular, we demonstrate, to the best of our knowledge, the first successful real-world RL training on a humanoid robot with dexterous hands. Our results demonstrate state-of-the-art performance in various vision-based tasks, pointing towards a practical pathway for deploying RL in the real world. Project website: https://residual-offpolicy-rl.github.io&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19301</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 17:59:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLMs4All: A Review on Large Language Models for Research and   Applications in Academic Disciplines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19580</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19580.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanfang, Ye, Zheyuan Zhang, Tianyi Ma, Zehong Wang, Yiyang Li, Shifu Hou, Weixiang Sun, Kaiwen Shi, Yijun Ma, Wei Song, Ahmed Abbasi, Ying Cheng, Jane Cleland-Huang, Steven Corcelli, Patricia Culligan, Robert Goulding, Ming Hu, Ting Hua, John Lalor, Fang Liu, Tengfei Luo, Ed Maginn, Nuno Moniz, Jason Rohr, Brett Savoie, Daniel Slate, Tom Stapleford, Matthew Webber, Olaf Wiest, Johnny Zhang, Nitesh Chawla&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Cutting-edge Artificial Intelligence (AI) techniques keep reshaping our view of the world. For example, Large Language Models (LLMs) based applications such as ChatGPT have shown the capability of generating human-like conversation on extensive topics. Due to the impressive performance on a variety of language-related tasks (e.g., open-domain question answering, translation, and document summarization), one can envision the far-reaching impacts that can be brought by the LLMs with broader real-world applications (e.g., customer service, education and accessibility, and scientific discovery). Inspired by their success, this paper will offer an overview of state-of-the-art LLMs and their integration into a wide range of academic disciplines, including: (1) arts, letters, and law (e.g., history, philosophy, political science, arts and architecture, law), (2) economics and business (e.g., finance, economics, accounting, marketing), and (3) science and engineering (e.g., mathematics, physics and mechanical engineering, chemistry and chemical engineering, life sciences and bioengineering, earth sciences and civil engineering, computer science and electrical engineering). Integrating humanity and technology, in this paper, we will explore how LLMs are shaping research and practice in these fields, while also discussing key limitations, open challenges, and future directions in the era of generative AI. The review of how LLMs are engaged across disciplines-along with key observations and insights-can help researchers and practitioners interested in exploiting LLMs to advance their works in diverse real-world applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19580</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 21:09:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking While Listening: Simple Test Time Scaling For Audio   Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19676</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19676.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Prateek Verma, Mert Pilanci&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a framework that enables neural models to "think while listening" to everyday sounds, thereby enhancing audio classification performance. Motivated by recent advances in the reasoning capabilities of large language models, we address two central questions: (i) how can thinking be incorporated into existing audio classification pipelines to enable reasoning in the category space and improve performance, and (ii) can a new architecture be designed from the ground up to support both thinking and test-time scaling? We demonstrate that in both settings, our models exhibit improved classification accuracy. Leveraging test-time scaling, we observe consistent gains as the number of sampled traces increases. Furthermore, we evaluate two open-source reasoning models, GPT-OSS-20B and Qwen3-14B, showing that while such models are capable of zero-shot reasoning, a lightweight approach--retraining only the embedding matrix of a frozen, smaller model like GPT-2--can surpass the performance of billion-parameter text-based reasoning models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19676</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 01:17:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UserRL: Training Interactive User-Centric Agent via Reinforcement   Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19736</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19736.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cheng Qian, Zuxin Liu, Akshara Prabhakar, Jielin Qiu, Zhiwei Liu, Haolin Chen, Shirley Kokane, Heng Ji, Weiran Yao, Shelby Heinecke, Silvio Savarese, Caiming Xiong, Huan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) has shown promise in training agentic models that move beyond static benchmarks to engage in dynamic, multi-turn interactions. Yet, the ultimate value of such agents lies in their ability to assist users, a setting where diversity and dynamics of user interaction pose challenges. In this work, we propose UserRL, a unified framework for training and evaluating user-centric abilities through standardized gym environments paired with simulated users. We systematically vary turn-level reward assignment and trajectory-level score calculation to analyze how different formulations affect learning under the GRPO algorithm. Our experiments across Qwen3 models reveal three key findings: (i) SFT cold start is critical for unlocking initial interaction ability and enabling sustained RL improvements; (ii) deliberate trajectory scoring yields more efficient and effective multi-turn interactions; and (iii) while stronger simulated users (e.g., GPT-4o) facilitates training, open-source simulators (e.g., Qwen3-32B) remain a cost-effective and transferable option. Together, these results highlight that careful design of reward shaping and user simulation choice is as crucial as model scale, and establish UserRL as a practical pathway for developing robust user-centric agentic models. All codes and data are public for future research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19736</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 03:33:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logics-Parsing Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19760</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19760.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiangyang Chen, Shuzhao Li, Xiuwen Zhu, Yongfan Chen, Fan Yang, Cheng Fang, Lin Qu, Xiaoxiao Xu, Hu Wei, Minggang Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in Large Vision-Language models (LVLM) have spurred significant progress in document parsing task. Compared to traditional pipeline-based methods, end-to-end paradigms have shown their excellence in converting PDF images into structured outputs through integrated Optical Character Recognition (OCR), table recognition, mathematical formula recognition and so on. However, the absence of explicit analytical stages for document layouts and reading orders limits the LVLM's capability in handling complex document types such as multi-column newspapers or posters. To address this limitation, we propose in this report Logics-Parsing: an end-to-end LVLM-based model augmented with reinforcement learning. Our model incorporates meticulously designed reward mechanisms to optimize complex layout analysis and reading order inference. In addition, we expand the model's versatility by incorporating diverse data types such as chemical formulas and handwritten Chinese characters into supervised fine-tuning. Finally, to enable rigorous evaluation of our approach, we introduce LogicsParsingBench, a curated set of 1,078 page-level PDF images spanning nine major categories and over twenty sub-categories, which will be released later. Comprehensive experiments conducted on LogicsParsingBench have validated the efficacy and State-of-the-art (SOTA) performance of our proposed model across diverse document analysis scenarios. Project Page: https://github.com/alibaba/Logics-Parsing&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19760</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 04:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VCRL: Variance-based Curriculum Reinforcement Learning for Large   Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19803</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.19803.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guochao Jiang, Wenfeng Feng, Guofeng Quan, Chuzhan Hao, Yuewei Zhang, Guohua Liu, Hao Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 111&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Policy-based reinforcement learning currently plays an important role in improving LLMs on mathematical reasoning tasks. However, existing rollout-based reinforcement learning methods (GRPO, DAPO, GSPO, etc.) fail to explicitly consider LLMs' learning ability for samples of different difficulty levels, which is contrary to the human cognitive process of mathematical reasoning tasks from easy to difficult. Intuitively, we find that the variance of the rollout group's reward in RLVR partly reflects the difficulty of the current sample for LLMs. Samples that are too easy or too difficult have a lower variance, while samples with moderate difficulty have a higher variance. Based on this, we propose VCRL, a curriculum reinforcement learning framework that dynamically controls the difficulty of training samples based on the variance of group rewards. Experiments on five mathematical benchmarks and two models reveal the advantages of VCRL over the current LLM RL baselines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19803</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 06:38:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SceneWeaver: All-in-One 3D Scene Synthesis with an Extensible and   Self-Reflective Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20414</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20414.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yandan Yang, Baoxiong Jia, Shujie Zhang, Siyuan Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Indoor scene synthesis has become increasingly important with the rise of Embodied AI, which requires 3D environments that are not only visually realistic but also physically plausible and functionally diverse. While recent approaches have advanced visual fidelity, they often remain constrained to fixed scene categories, lack sufficient object-level detail and physical consistency, and struggle to align with complex user instructions. In this work, we present SceneWeaver, a reflective agentic framework that unifies diverse scene synthesis paradigms through tool-based iterative refinement. At its core, SceneWeaver employs a language model-based planner to select from a suite of extensible scene generation tools, ranging from data-driven generative models to visual- and LLM-based methods, guided by self-evaluation of physical plausibility, visual realism, and semantic alignment with user input. This closed-loop reason-act-reflect design enables the agent to identify semantic inconsistencies, invoke targeted tools, and update the environment over successive iterations. Extensive experiments on both common and open-vocabulary room types demonstrate that SceneWeaver not only outperforms prior methods on physical, visual, and semantic metrics, but also generalizes effectively to complex scenes with diverse instructions, marking a step toward general-purpose 3D environment generation. Project website: https://scene-weaver.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20414</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 09:06:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Diffusion for Reflective Vision-Language-Action Models in   Autonomous Driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20109</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20109.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Pengxiang Li, Yinan Zheng, Yue Wang, Huimin Wang, Hang Zhao, Jingjing Liu, Xianyuan Zhan, Kun Zhan, Xianpeng Lang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; End-to-End (E2E) solutions have emerged as a mainstream approach for autonomous driving systems, with Vision-Language-Action (VLA) models representing a new paradigm that leverages pre-trained multimodal knowledge from Vision-Language Models (VLMs) to interpret and interact with complex real-world environments. However, these methods remain constrained by the limitations of imitation learning, which struggles to inherently encode physical rules during training. Existing approaches often rely on complex rule-based post-refinement, employ reinforcement learning that remains largely limited to simulation, or utilize diffusion guidance that requires computationally expensive gradient calculations. To address these challenges, we introduce ReflectDrive, a novel learning-based framework that integrates a reflection mechanism for safe trajectory generation via discrete diffusion. We first discretize the two-dimensional driving space to construct an action codebook, enabling the use of pre-trained Diffusion Language Models for planning tasks through fine-tuning. Central to our approach is a safety-aware reflection mechanism that performs iterative self-correction without gradient computation. Our method begins with goal-conditioned trajectory generation to model multi-modal driving behaviors. Based on this, we apply local search methods to identify unsafe tokens and determine feasible solutions, which then serve as safe anchors for inpainting-based regeneration. Evaluated on the NAVSIM benchmark, ReflectDrive demonstrates significant advantages in safety-critical trajectory generation, offering a scalable and reliable solution for autonomous driving systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20109</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 13:35:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V-GameGym: Visual Game Generation for Code Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20136</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20136.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei Zhang, Jack Yang, Renshuai Tao, Lingzheng Chai, Shawn Guo, Jiajun Wu, Xiaoming Chen, Ganqu Cui, Ning Ding, Xander Xu, Hu Wei, Bowen Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Code large language models have demonstrated remarkable capabilities in programming tasks, yet current benchmarks primarily focus on single modality rather than visual game development. Most existing code-related benchmarks evaluate syntax correctness and execution accuracy, overlooking critical game-specific metrics such as playability, visual aesthetics, and user engagement that are essential for real-world deployment. To address the gap between current LLM capabilities in algorithmic problem-solving and competitive programming versus the comprehensive requirements of practical game development, we present V-GameGym, a comprehensive benchmark comprising 2,219 high-quality samples across 100 thematic clusters derived from real-world repositories, adopting a novel clustering-based curation methodology to ensure both diversity and structural completeness. Further, we introduce a multimodal evaluation framework with an automated LLM-driven pipeline for visual code synthesis using complete UI sandbox environments. Our extensive analysis reveals that V-GameGym effectively bridges the gap between code generation accuracy and practical game development workflows, providing quantifiable quality metrics for visual programming and interactive element generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20136</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 14:01:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thinking Augmented Pre-training</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20186</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20186.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Liang Wang, Nan Yang, Shaohan Huang, Li Dong, Furu Wei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; This paper introduces a simple and scalable approach to improve the data efficiency of large language model (LLM) training by augmenting existing text data with thinking trajectories. The compute for pre-training LLMs has been growing at an unprecedented rate, while the availability of high-quality data remains limited. Consequently, maximizing the utility of available data constitutes a significant research challenge. A primary impediment is that certain high-quality tokens are difficult to learn given a fixed model capacity, as the underlying rationale for a single token can be exceptionally complex and deep. To address this issue, we propose Thinking augmented Pre-Training (TPT), a universal methodology that augments text with automatically generated thinking trajectories. Such augmentation effectively increases the volume of the training data and makes high-quality tokens more learnable through step-by-step reasoning and decomposition. We apply TPT across diverse training configurations up to 100B tokens, encompassing pre-training with both constrained and abundant data, as well as mid-training from strong open-source checkpoints. Experimental results indicate that our method substantially improves the performance of LLMs across various model sizes and families. Notably, TPT enhances the data efficiency of LLM pre-training by a factor of 3. For a 3B parameter model, it improves the post-training performance by over 10% on several challenging reasoning benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20186</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 14:45:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Judgment Becomes Noise: How Design Failures in LLM Judge Benchmarks   Silently Undermine Validity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20293</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20293.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Benjamin Feuer, Chiung-Yi Tseng, Astitwa Sarthak Lathe, Oussama Elachqar, John P Dickerson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; LLM-judged benchmarks are increasingly used to evaluate complex model behaviors, yet their design introduces failure modes absent in conventional ground-truth based benchmarks. We argue that without tight objectives and verifiable constructions, benchmark rankings can produce high-confidence rankings that are in fact largely noise. We introduce two mechanisms to diagnose these issues. Schematic adherence quantifies how much of a judge's overall verdict is explained by the explicit evaluation schema, revealing unexplained variance when judges deviate from their own rubric. Psychometric validity aggregates internal consistency and discriminant validity signals to quantify irreducible uncertainty in any benchmarking run. Applying these tools to Arena-Hard Auto, we find severe schema incoherence and factor collapse across popular judges: for example, unexplained variance exceeding 90 percent for DeepSeek-R1-32B and factor correlations above 0.93 for most criteria. We also show that the ELO-style aggregation used by Arena-Hard Auto collapses and masks genuine ranking uncertainty. Our results highlight design failures that undermine validity and offer actionable principles for building better-scoped, reliability-aware LLM-judged benchmarks. We release our code at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/judgment-to-noise-947D/README.md&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20293</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 16:26:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SIM-CoT: Supervised Implicit Chain-of-Thought</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xilin Wei, Xiaoran Liu, Yuhang Zang, Xiaoyi Dong, Yuhang Cao, Jiaqi Wang, Xipeng Qiu, Dahua Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 33&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Implicit Chain-of-Thought (CoT) methods present a promising, token-efficient alternative to explicit CoT reasoning in Large Language Models (LLMs), but a persistent performance gap has limited the application of implicit CoT. We identify a core latent instability issue by scaling the computational budget of implicit CoT approaches: as we increase the number of implicit reasoning tokens to enhance performance, the training process often becomes unstable and collapses. Our analysis reveals that this instability arises from the latent representations becoming homogeneous and losing their semantic diversity, a failure caused by insufficient step-level supervision in existing implicit CoT approaches. To address this issue, we propose SIM-CoT, a plug-and-play training module that introduces step-level supervision to stabilize and enrich the latent reasoning space. Specifically, SIM-CoT employs an auxiliary decoder during training to align each implicit token with its corresponding explicit reasoning step, ensuring that latent states capture distinct and meaningful information. The proposed auxiliary decoder is removed during inference, preserving the computational efficiency of implicit CoT methods with no added overhead. In addition, the auxiliary decoder affords interpretability of implicit reasoning by projecting each latent token onto an explicit reasoning vocabulary, enabling per-step visualization of semantic roles and diagnosis. SIM-CoT significantly enhances both the in-domain accuracy and out-of-domain stability of various implicit CoT methods, boosting baselines like Coconut by +8.2% on GPT-2 and CODI by +3.0% on LLaMA-3.1 8B. Demonstrating strong scalability, SIM-CoT also surpasses the explicit CoT baseline on GPT-2 by 2.1% with 2.3\times greater token efficiency, while substantially closing the performance gap on larger models like LLaMA-3.1 8B.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20317</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:01:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video models are zero-shot learners and reasoners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20328</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20328.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Thaddäus Wiedemer, Yuxuan Li, Paul Vicol, Shixiang Shane Gu, Nick Matarese, Kevin Swersky, Been Kim, Priyank Jaini, Robert Geirhos&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The remarkable zero-shot capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs) have propelled natural language processing from task-specific models to unified, generalist foundation models. This transformation emerged from simple primitives: large, generative models trained on web-scale data. Curiously, the same primitives apply to today's generative video models. Could video models be on a trajectory towards general-purpose vision understanding, much like LLMs developed general-purpose language understanding? We demonstrate that Veo 3 can solve a broad variety of tasks it wasn't explicitly trained for: segmenting objects, detecting edges, editing images, understanding physical properties, recognizing object affordances, simulating tool use, and more. These abilities to perceive, model, and manipulate the visual world enable early forms of visual reasoning like maze and symmetry solving. Veo's emergent zero-shot capabilities indicate that video models are on a path to becoming unified, generalist vision foundation models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20328</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:17:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EmbeddingGemma: Powerful and Lightweight Text Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20354</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20354.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Henrique Schechter Vera, Sahil Dua, Biao Zhang, Daniel Salz, Ryan Mullins, Sindhu Raghuram Panyam, Sara Smoot, Iftekhar Naim, Joe Zou, Feiyang Chen, Daniel Cer, Alice Lisak, Min Choi, Lucas Gonzalez, Omar Sanseviero, Glenn Cameron, Ian Ballantyne, Kat Black, Kaifeng Chen, Weiyi Wang, Zhe Li, Gus Martins, Jinhyuk Lee, Mark Sherwood, Juyeong Ji, Renjie Wu, Jingxiao Zheng, Jyotinder Singh, Abheesht Sharma, Divya Sreepat, Aashi Jain, Adham Elarabawy, AJ Co, Andreas Doumanoglou, Babak Samari, Ben Hora, Brian Potetz, Dahun Kim, Enrique Alfonseca, Fedor Moiseev, Feng Han, Frank Palma Gomez, Gustavo Hernández Ábrego, Hesen Zhang, Hui Hui, Jay Han, Karan Gill, Ke Chen, Koert Chen, Madhuri Shanbhogue, Michael Boratko, Paul Suganthan, Sai Meher Karthik Duddu, Sandeep Mariserla, Setareh Ariafar, Shanfeng Zhang, Shijie Zhang, Simon Baumgartner, Sonam Goenka, Steve Qiu, Tanmaya Dabral, Trevor Walker, Vikram Rao, Waleed Khawaja, Wenlei Zhou, Xiaoqi Ren, Ye Xia, Yichang Chen, Yi-Ting Chen, Zhe Dong, Zhongli Ding, Francesco Visin, Gaël Liu, Jiageng Zhang, Kathleen Kenealy, Michelle Casbon, Ravin Kumar, Thomas Mesnard, Zach Gleicher, Cormac Brick, Olivier Lacombe, Adam Roberts, Yunhsuan Sung, Raphael Hoffmann, Tris Warkentin, Armand Joulin, Tom Duerig, Mojtaba Seyedhosseini&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 27&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce EmbeddingGemma, a new lightweight, open text embedding model based on the Gemma 3 language model family. Our innovative training recipe strategically captures knowledge from larger models via encoder-decoder initialization and geometric embedding distillation. We improve model robustness and expressiveness with a spread-out regularizer, and ensure generalizability by merging checkpoints from varied, optimized mixtures. Evaluated on the Massive Text Embedding Benchmark (MTEB) across multilingual, English, and code domains, EmbeddingGemma (300M) achieves state-of-the-art results. Notably, it outperforms prior top models, both proprietary and open, with fewer than 500M parameters, and provides performance comparable to models double its size, offering an exceptional performance-to-cost ratio. Remarkably, this lead persists when quantizing model weights or truncating embedding outputs. This makes EmbeddingGemma particularly well-suited for low-latency and high-throughput use cases such as on-device applications. We provide ablation studies exploring our key design choices. We release EmbeddingGemma to the community to promote further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20354</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:56:51 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PhysCtrl: Generative Physics for Controllable and Physics-Grounded Video   Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20358</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20358.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chen Wang, Chuhao Chen, Yiming Huang, Zhiyang Dou, Yuan Liu, Jiatao Gu, Lingjie Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Existing video generation models excel at producing photo-realistic videos from text or images, but often lack physical plausibility and 3D controllability. To overcome these limitations, we introduce PhysCtrl, a novel framework for physics-grounded image-to-video generation with physical parameters and force control. At its core is a generative physics network that learns the distribution of physical dynamics across four materials (elastic, sand, plasticine, and rigid) via a diffusion model conditioned on physics parameters and applied forces. We represent physical dynamics as 3D point trajectories and train on a large-scale synthetic dataset of 550K animations generated by physics simulators. We enhance the diffusion model with a novel spatiotemporal attention block that emulates particle interactions and incorporates physics-based constraints during training to enforce physical plausibility. Experiments show that PhysCtrl generates realistic, physics-grounded motion trajectories which, when used to drive image-to-video models, yield high-fidelity, controllable videos that outperform existing methods in both visual quality and physical plausibility. Project Page: https://cwchenwang.github.io/physctrl&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20358</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seedream 4.0: Toward Next-generation Multimodal Image Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20427</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20427.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Team Seedream, Yunpeng Chen, Yu Gao, Lixue Gong, Meng Guo, Qiushan Guo, Zhiyao Guo, Xiaoxia Hou, Weilin Huang, Yixuan Huang, Xiaowen Jian, Huafeng Kuang, Zhichao Lai, Fanshi Li, Liang Li, Xiaochen Lian, Chao Liao, Liyang Liu, Wei Liu, Yanzuo Lu, Zhengxiong Luo, Tongtong Ou, Guang Shi, Yichun Shi, Shiqi Sun, Yu Tian, Zhi Tian, Peng Wang, Rui Wang, Xun Wang, Ye Wang, Guofeng Wu, Jie Wu, Wenxu Wu, Yonghui Wu, Xin Xia, Xuefeng Xiao, Shuang Xu, Xin Yan, Ceyuan Yang, Jianchao Yang, Zhonghua Zhai, Chenlin Zhang, Heng Zhang, Qi Zhang, Xinyu Zhang, Yuwei Zhang, Shijia Zhao, Wenliang Zhao, Wenjia Zhu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 63&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Seedream 4.0, an efficient and high-performance multimodal image generation system that unifies text-to-image (T2I) synthesis, image editing, and multi-image composition within a single framework. We develop a highly efficient diffusion transformer with a powerful VAE which also can reduce the number of image tokens considerably. This allows for efficient training of our model, and enables it to fast generate native high-resolution images (e.g., 1K-4K). Seedream 4.0 is pretrained on billions of text-image pairs spanning diverse taxonomies and knowledge-centric concepts. Comprehensive data collection across hundreds of vertical scenarios, coupled with optimized strategies, ensures stable and large-scale training, with strong generalization. By incorporating a carefully fine-tuned VLM model, we perform multi-modal post-training for training both T2I and image editing tasks jointly. For inference acceleration, we integrate adversarial distillation, distribution matching, and quantization, as well as speculative decoding. It achieves an inference time of up to 1.8 seconds for generating a 2K image (without a LLM/VLM as PE model). Comprehensive evaluations reveal that Seedream 4.0 can achieve state-of-the-art results on both T2I and multimodal image editing. In particular, it demonstrates exceptional multimodal capabilities in complex tasks, including precise image editing and in-context reasoning, and also allows for multi-image reference, and can generate multiple output images. This extends traditional T2I systems into an more interactive and multidimensional creative tool, pushing the boundary of generative AI for both creativity and professional applications. Seedream 4.0 is now accessible on https://www.volcengine.com/experience/ark?launch=seedream.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20427</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:59:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EditVerse: Unifying Image and Video Editing and Generation with   In-Context Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20360</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20360.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xuan Ju, Tianyu Wang, Yuqian Zhou, He Zhang, Qing Liu, Nanxuan Zhao, Zhifei Zhang, Yijun Li, Yuanhao Cai, Shaoteng Liu, Daniil Pakhomov, Zhe Lin, Soo Ye Kim, Qiang Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in foundation models highlight a clear trend toward unification and scaling, showing emergent capabilities across diverse domains. While image generation and editing have rapidly transitioned from task-specific to unified frameworks, video generation and editing remain fragmented due to architectural limitations and data scarcity. In this work, we introduce EditVerse, a unified framework for image and video generation and editing within a single model. By representing all modalities, i.e., text, image, and video, as a unified token sequence, EditVerse leverages self-attention to achieve robust in-context learning, natural cross-modal knowledge transfer, and flexible handling of inputs and outputs with arbitrary resolutions and durations. To address the lack of video editing training data, we design a scalable data pipeline that curates 232K video editing samples and combines them with large-scale image and video datasets for joint training. Furthermore, we present EditVerseBench, the first benchmark for instruction-based video editing covering diverse tasks and resolutions. Extensive experiments and user studies demonstrate that EditVerse achieves state-of-the-art performance, surpassing existing open-source and commercial models, while exhibiting emergent editing and generation abilities across modalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20360</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 17:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MI-Fuse: Label Fusion for Unsupervised Domain Adaptation with   Closed-Source Large-Audio Language Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20706</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20706.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hsiao-Ying Huang, Yi-Cheng Lin, Hung-yi Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large audio-language models (LALMs) show strong zero-shot ability on speech tasks, suggesting promise for speech emotion recognition (SER). However, SER in real-world deployments often fails under domain mismatch, where source data are unavailable and powerful LALMs are accessible only through an API. We ask: given only unlabeled target-domain audio and an API-only LALM, can a student model be adapted to outperform the LALM in the target domain? To this end, we propose MI-Fuse, a denoised label fusion framework that supplements the LALM with a source-domain trained SER classifier as an auxiliary teacher. The framework draws multiple stochastic predictions from both teachers, weights their mean distributions by mutual-information-based uncertainty, and stabilizes training with an exponential moving average teacher. Experiments across three public emotion datasets and six cross-domain transfers show consistent gains, with the student surpassing the LALM and outperforming the strongest baseline by 3.9%. This approach strengthens emotion-aware speech systems without sharing source data, enabling realistic adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20706</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 03:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CE-GPPO: Controlling Entropy via Gradient-Preserving Clipping Policy   Optimization in Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20712</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20712.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhenpeng Su, Leiyu Pan, Minxuan Lv, Yuntao Li, Wenping Hu, Fuzheng Zhang, Kun Gai, Guorui Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Reinforcement learning (RL) has become a powerful paradigm for optimizing large language models (LLMs) to handle complex reasoning tasks. A core challenge in this process lies in managing policy entropy, which reflects the balance between exploration and exploitation during training. Existing methods, such as proximal policy optimization (PPO) and its variants, discard valuable gradient signals from low-probability tokens due to the clipping mechanism. We systematically analyze the entropy dynamics and reveal that these clipped tokens play a critical yet overlooked role in regulating entropy evolution. We propose Controlling Entropy via Gradient-Preserving Policy Optimization (CE-GPPO), a novel algorithm that reintroduces gradients from clipped tokens in native PPO in a gentle and bounded manner. By controlling the magnitude of gradients from tokens outside the clipping interval, CE-GPPO is able to achieve an exploration-exploitation trade-off. We provide theoretical justification and empirical evidence showing that CE-GPPO effectively mitigates entropy instability. Extensive experiments on mathematical reasoning benchmarks show that CE-GPPO consistently outperforms strong baselines across different model scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20712</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 03:22:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>StyleBench: Evaluating thinking styles in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20868</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20868.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junyu Guo, Shangding Gu, Ming Jin, Costas Spanos, Javad Lavaei&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The effectiveness of Large Language Models (LLMs) is heavily influenced by the reasoning strategies, or styles of thought, employed in their prompts. However, the interplay between these reasoning styles, model architecture, and task type remains poorly understood. To address this, we introduce StyleBench, a comprehensive benchmark for systematically evaluating reasoning styles across diverse tasks and models. We assess five representative reasoning styles, including Chain of Thought (CoT), Tree of Thought (ToT), Algorithm of Thought (AoT), Sketch of Thought (SoT), and Chain-of-Draft (CoD) on five reasoning tasks, using 15 open-source models from major families (LLaMA, Qwen, Mistral, Gemma, GPT-OSS, Phi, and DeepSeek) ranging from 270M to 120B parameters. Our large-scale analysis reveals that no single style is universally optimal. We demonstrate that strategy efficacy is highly contingent on both model scale and task type: search-based methods (AoT, ToT) excel in open-ended problems but require large-scale models, while concise styles (SoT, CoD) achieve radical efficiency gains on well-defined tasks. Furthermore, we identify key behavioral patterns: smaller models frequently fail to follow output instructions and default to guessing, while reasoning robustness emerges as a function of scale. Our findings offer a crucial roadmap for selecting optimal reasoning strategies based on specific constraints, we open source the benchmark in https://github.com/JamesJunyuGuo/Style_Bench.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20868</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 08:00:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unanticipated Asymmetry Between Perceptual Optimization and   Assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20878</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.20878.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiabei Zhang, Qi Wang, Siyu Wu, Du Chen, Tianhe Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Perceptual optimization is primarily driven by the fidelity objective, which enforces both semantic consistency and overall visual realism, while the adversarial objective provides complementary refinement by enhancing perceptual sharpness and fine-grained detail. Despite their central role, the correlation between their effectiveness as optimization objectives and their capability as image quality assessment (IQA) metrics remains underexplored. In this work, we conduct a systematic analysis and reveal an unanticipated asymmetry between perceptual optimization and assessment: fidelity metrics that excel in IQA are not necessarily effective for perceptual optimization, with this misalignment emerging more distinctly under adversarial training. In addition, while discriminators effectively suppress artifacts during optimization, their learned representations offer only limited benefits when reused as backbone initializations for IQA models. Beyond this asymmetry, our findings further demonstrate that discriminator design plays a decisive role in shaping optimization, with patch-level and convolutional architectures providing more faithful detail reconstruction than vanilla or Transformer-based alternatives. These insights advance the understanding of loss function design and its connection to IQA transferability, paving the way for more principled approaches to perceptual optimization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20878</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 08:08:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Behind RoPE: How Does Causal Mask Encode Positional Information?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21042</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21042.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Junu Kim, Xiao Liu, Zhenghao Lin, Lei Ji, Yeyun Gong, Edward Choi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While explicit positional encodings such as RoPE are a primary source of positional information in Transformer decoders, the causal mask also provides positional information. In this work, we prove that the causal mask can induce position-dependent patterns in attention scores, even without parameters or causal dependency in the input. Our theoretical analysis indicates that the induced attention pattern tends to favor nearby query-key pairs, mirroring the behavior of common positional encodings. Empirical analysis confirms that trained models exhibit the same behavior, with learned parameters further amplifying these patterns. Notably, we found that the interaction of causal mask and RoPE distorts RoPE's relative attention score patterns into non-relative ones. We consistently observed this effect in modern large language models, suggesting the importance of considering the causal mask as a source of positional information alongside explicit positional encodings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21042</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 11:48:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ScaleDiff: Scaling Difficult Problems for Advanced Mathematical   Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21070</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21070.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qizhi Pei, Zhuoshi Pan, Honglin Lin, Xin Gao, Yu Li, Zinan Tang, Conghui He, Rui Yan, Lijun Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) have shown impressive capabilities in complex problem-solving, often benefiting from training on difficult mathematical problems that stimulate intricate reasoning. Recent efforts have explored automated synthesis of mathematical problems by prompting proprietary models or large-scale open-source models from seed data or inherent mathematical concepts. However, scaling up these methods remains challenging due to their high computational/API cost, complexity of prompting, and limited difficulty level of the generated problems. To overcome these limitations, we propose ScaleDiff, a simple yet effective pipeline designed to scale the creation of difficult problems. We efficiently identify difficult problems from existing datasets with only a single forward pass using an adaptive thinking model, which can perceive problem difficulty and automatically switch between "Thinking" and "NoThinking" modes. We then train a specialized difficult problem generator (DiffGen-8B) on this filtered difficult data, which can produce new difficult problems in large scale, eliminating the need for complex, per-instance prompting and its associated high API costs. Fine-tuning Qwen2.5-Math-7B-Instruct on the ScaleDiff-Math dataset yields a substantial performance increase of 11.3% compared to the original dataset and achieves a 65.9% average accuracy on AIME'24, AIME'25, HMMT-Feb'25, BRUMO'25, and MATH500, outperforming recent strong LRMs like OpenThinker3. Notably, this performance is achieved using the cost-efficient Qwen3-8B model as a teacher, demonstrating that our pipeline can effectively transfer advanced reasoning capabilities without relying on larger, more expensive teacher models. Furthermore, we observe a clear scaling phenomenon in model performance on difficult benchmarks as the quantity of difficult problems increases. Code: https://github.com/QizhiPei/ScaleDiff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21070</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 12:22:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recon-Act: A Self-Evolving Multi-Agent Browser-Use System via Web   Reconnaissance, Tool Generation, and Task Execution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21072</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21072.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaiwen He, Zhiwei Wang, Chenyi Zhuang, Jinjie Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent years, multimodal models have made remarkable strides and pave the way for intelligent browser use agents. However, when solving tasks on real world webpages in multi-turn, long-horizon trajectories, current agents still suffer from disordered action sequencing and excessive trial and error during execution. This paper introduces Recon-Act, a self-evolving multi-agent framework grounded in Reconnaissance-Action behavioral paradigm. The system comprises a Reconnaissance Team and an Action Team: the former conducts comparative analysis and tool generation, while the latter handles intent decomposition, tool orchestration, and execution. By contrasting the erroneous trajectories with successful ones, the Reconnaissance Team infers remedies, and abstracts them into a unified notion of generalized tools, either expressed as hints or as rule-based codes, and register to the tool archive in real time. The Action Team reinference the process empowered with these targeting tools, thus establishing a closed-loop training pipeline of data-tools-action-feedback. Following the 6 level implementation roadmap proposed in this work, we have currently reached Level 3 (with limited human-in-the-loop intervention). Leveraging generalized tools obtained through reconnaissance, Recon-Act substantially improves adaptability to unseen websites and solvability on long-horizon tasks, and achieves state-of-the-art performance on the challenging VisualWebArena dataset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21072</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 12:23:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BESPOKE: Benchmark for Search-Augmented Large Language Model   Personalization via Diagnostic Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21106</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21106.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hyunseo Kim, Sangam Lee, Kwangwook Seo, Dongha Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Search-augmented large language models (LLMs) have advanced information-seeking tasks by integrating retrieval into generation, reducing users' cognitive burden compared to traditional search systems. Yet they remain insufficient for fully addressing diverse user needs, which requires recognizing how the same query can reflect different intents across users and delivering information in preferred forms. While recent systems such as ChatGPT and Gemini attempt personalization by leveraging user histories, systematic evaluation of such personalization is under-explored. To address this gap, we propose BESPOKE, the realistic benchmark for evaluating personalization in search-augmented LLMs. BESPOKE is designed to be both realistic, by collecting authentic chat and search histories directly from humans, and diagnostic, by pairing responses with fine-grained preference scores and feedback. The benchmark is constructed through long-term, deeply engaged human annotation, where human annotators contributed their own histories, authored queries with detailed information needs, and evaluated responses with scores and diagnostic feedback. Leveraging BESPOKE, we conduct systematic analyses that reveal key requirements for effective personalization in information-seeking tasks, providing a foundation for fine-grained evaluation of personalized search-augmented LLMs. Our code and data are available at https://augustinlib.github.io/BESPOKE/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21106</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 12:53:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOSS-ChatV: Reinforcement Learning with Process Reasoning Reward for   Video Temporal Reasoning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21113</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21113.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sicheng Tao, Jungang Li, Yibo Yan, Junyan Zhang, Yubo Gao, Hanqian Li, ShuHang Xun, Yuxuan Fan, Hong Chen, Jianxiang He, Xuming Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Video reasoning has emerged as a critical capability for multimodal large language models (MLLMs), requiring models to move beyond static perception toward coherent understanding of temporal dynamics in complex scenes. Yet existing MLLMs often exhibit process inconsistency, where intermediate reasoning drifts from video dynamics even when the final answer is correct, undermining interpretability and robustness. To address this issue, we introduce MOSS-ChatV, a reinforcement learning framework with a Dynamic Time Warping (DTW)-based process reward. This rule-based reward aligns reasoning traces with temporally grounded references, enabling efficient process supervision without auxiliary reward models. We further identify dynamic state prediction as a key measure of video reasoning and construct MOSS-Video, a benchmark with annotated reasoning traces, where the training split is used to fine-tune MOSS-ChatV and the held-out split is reserved for evaluation. MOSS-ChatV achieves 87.2\% on MOSS-Video (test) and improves performance on general video benchmarks such as MVBench and MMVU. The framework consistently yields gains across different architectures, including Qwen2.5-VL and Phi-2, confirming its broad applicability. Evaluations with GPT-4o-as-judge further show that MOSS-ChatV produces more consistent and stable reasoning traces.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21113</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 12:59:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHARM: Control-point-based 3D Anime Hairstyle Auto-Regressive Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21114</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21114.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuze He, Yanning Zhou, Wang Zhao, Jingwen Ye, Yushi Bai, Kaiwen Xiao, Yong-Jin Liu, Zhongqian Sun, Wei Yang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present CHARM, a novel parametric representation and generative framework for anime hairstyle modeling. While traditional hair modeling methods focus on realistic hair using strand-based or volumetric representations, anime hairstyle exhibits highly stylized, piecewise-structured geometry that challenges existing techniques. Existing works often rely on dense mesh modeling or hand-crafted spline curves, making them inefficient for editing and unsuitable for scalable learning. CHARM introduces a compact, invertible control-point-based parameterization, where a sequence of control points represents each hair card, and each point is encoded with only five geometric parameters. This efficient and accurate representation supports both artist-friendly design and learning-based generation. Built upon this representation, CHARM introduces an autoregressive generative framework that effectively generates anime hairstyles from input images or point clouds. By interpreting anime hairstyles as a sequential "hair language", our autoregressive transformer captures both local geometry and global hairstyle topology, resulting in high-fidelity anime hairstyle creation. To facilitate both training and evaluation of anime hairstyle generation, we construct AnimeHair, a large-scale dataset of 37K high-quality anime hairstyles with separated hair cards and processed mesh data. Extensive experiments demonstrate state-of-the-art performance of CHARM in both reconstruction accuracy and generation quality, offering an expressive and scalable solution for anime hairstyle modeling. Project page: https://hyzcluster.github.io/charm/&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21114</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TrustJudge: Inconsistencies of LLM-as-a-Judge and How to Alleviate Them</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21117</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21117.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yidong Wang, Yunze Song, Tingyuan Zhu, Xuanwang Zhang, Zhuohao Yu, Hao Chen, Chiyu Song, Qiufeng Wang, Cunxiang Wang, Zhen Wu, Xinyu Dai, Yue Zhang, Wei Ye, Shikun Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 22&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The adoption of Large Language Models (LLMs) as automated evaluators (LLM-as-a-judge) has revealed critical inconsistencies in current evaluation frameworks. We identify two fundamental types of inconsistencies: (1) Score-Comparison Inconsistency, where lower-rated responses outperform higher-scored ones in pairwise comparisons, and (2) Pairwise Transitivity Inconsistency, manifested through circular preference chains (A&gt;B&gt;C&gt;A) and equivalence contradictions (A=B=C\neq A). We argue that these issues come from information loss in discrete rating systems and ambiguous tie judgments during pairwise evaluation. We propose TrustJudge, a probabilistic framework that addresses these limitations through two key innovations: 1) distribution-sensitive scoring that computes continuous expectations from discrete rating probabilities, preserving information entropy for more precise scoring, and 2) likelihood-aware aggregation that resolves transitivity violations using bidirectional preference probabilities or perplexity. We also formalize the theoretical limitations of current LLM-as-a-judge frameworks and demonstrate how TrustJudge's components overcome them. When evaluated with Llama-3.1-70B-Instruct as judge using our dataset, TrustJudge reduces Score-Comparison inconsistency by 8.43% (from 23.32% to 14.89%) and Pairwise Transitivity inconsistency by 10.82% (from 15.22% to 4.40%), while maintaining higher evaluation accuracy. Our work provides the first systematic analysis of evaluation framework inconsistencies in LLM-as-a-judge paradigms, offering both theoretical insights and practical solutions for reliable automated assessment. The framework demonstrates consistent improvements across various model architectures and scales, enabling more trustworthy LLM evaluation without requiring additional training or human annotations. The codes can be found at https://github.com/TrustJudge/TrustJudge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21117</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:04:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AutoIntent: AutoML for Text Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21138</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21138.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ilya Alekseev, Roman Solomatin, Darina Rustamova, Denis Kuznetsov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; AutoIntent is an automated machine learning tool for text classification tasks. Unlike existing solutions, AutoIntent offers end-to-end automation with embedding model selection, classifier optimization, and decision threshold tuning, all within a modular, sklearn-like interface. The framework is designed to support multi-label classification and out-of-scope detection. AutoIntent demonstrates superior performance compared to existing AutoML tools on standard intent classification datasets and enables users to balance effectiveness and resource consumption.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21138</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:27:52 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixture of Thoughts: Learning to Aggregate What Experts Think, Not Just   What They Say</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21164</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21164.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jacob Fein-Ashley, Dhruv Parikh, Rajgopal Kannan, Viktor Prasanna&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Open-source Large Language Models (LLMs) increasingly specialize by domain (e.g., math, code, general reasoning), motivating systems that leverage complementary strengths across models. Prior multi-LLM approaches either (i) route a query to one or a few experts and generate independently, (ii) aggregate outputs from each model via costly multi-turn exchanges, or (iii) fuse weights into a single model-typically requiring architectural homogeneity. We introduce Mixture of Thoughts (MoT), a simple method for latent-level collaboration among heterogeneous experts under a global routing scheme. For each query, a lightweight router selects top-K experts and designates a primary expert; uniformly placed interaction layers project hidden states into a shared latent space where the primary expert performs cross-attention over its active (selected) peers. Pre-trained experts remain frozen; only the router and the lightweight interaction layers are trained with a novel joint training objective that improves both the expert selection and inter-expert collaboration. Across five in-distribution (ID) and three out-of-distribution (OOD) benchmarks, MoT surpasses the current routing and aggregation-based state-of-the-art, Avengers, by +0.38% and +2.92%, respectively. Further, MoT significantly outperforms the best-performing single model. It achieves this with single-pass inference, runtime comparable to routing baselines, and none of the overheads of iterative aggregation. MoT offers a simple latent-space mechanism for combining heterogeneous LLMs, a practical step toward broader multi-LLM collaboration. Our code is publicly available at https://github.com/jacobfa/mot.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21164</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 13:50:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tree Search for LLM Agent Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21240</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21240.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuxiang Ji, Ziyu Ma, Yong Wang, Guanhua Chen, Xiangxiang Chu, Liaoni Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in reinforcement learning (RL) have significantly enhanced the agentic capabilities of large language models (LLMs). In long-term and multi-turn agent tasks, existing approaches driven solely by outcome rewards often suffer from the problem of sparse supervision. To address the challenge, we propose Tree-based Group Relative Policy Optimization (Tree-GRPO), a grouped agent RL method based on tree search, where each tree node represents the complete agent interaction step. By sharing common prefixes, the tree search sampling increases the number of rollouts achievable within a fixed budget of tokens or tool calls. Moreover, we find that the tree-structured trajectory naturally allows the construction of step-wise process supervised signals even using only the outcome reward. Based on this, Tree-GRPO estimates the grouped relative advantages both on intra-tree and inter-tree levels. Through theoretical analysis, we demonstrate that the objective of intra-tree level group relative policy optimization is equivalent to that of step-level direct preference learning. Experiments across 11 datasets and 3 types of QA tasks demonstrate the superiority of the proposed tree-based RL over the chain-based RL method.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21240</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:37:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hunyuan3D-Omni: A Unified Framework for Controllable Generation of 3D   Assets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21245</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21245.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Team Hunyuan3D, Bowen Zhang, Chunchao Guo, Haolin Liu, Hongyu Yan, Huiwen Shi, Jingwei Huang, Junlin Yu, Kunhong Li, Linus, Penghao Wang, Qingxiang Lin, Sicong Liu, Xianghui Yang, Yixuan Tang, Yunfei Zhao, Zeqiang Lai, Zhihao Liang, Zibo Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 35&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in 3D-native generative models have accelerated asset creation for games, film, and design. However, most methods still rely primarily on image or text conditioning and lack fine-grained, cross-modal controls, which limits controllability and practical adoption. To address this gap, we present Hunyuan3D-Omni, a unified framework for fine-grained, controllable 3D asset generation built on Hunyuan3D 2.1. In addition to images, Hunyuan3D-Omni accepts point clouds, voxels, bounding boxes, and skeletal pose priors as conditioning signals, enabling precise control over geometry, topology, and pose. Instead of separate heads for each modality, our model unifies all signals in a single cross-modal architecture. We train with a progressive, difficulty-aware sampling strategy that selects one control modality per example and biases sampling toward harder signals (e.g., skeletal pose) while downweighting easier ones (e.g., point clouds), encouraging robust multi-modal fusion and graceful handling of missing inputs. Experiments show that these additional controls improve generation accuracy, enable geometry-aware transformations, and increase robustness for production workflows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21245</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:39:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MMR1: Enhancing Multimodal Reasoning with Variance-Aware Sampling and   Open Resources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21268</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21268.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sicong Leng, Jing Wang, Jiaxi Li, Hao Zhang, Zhiqiang Hu, Boqiang Zhang, Yuming Jiang, Hang Zhang, Xin Li, Lidong Bing, Deli Zhao, Wei Lu, Yu Rong, Aixin Sun, Shijian Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 90&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Large multimodal reasoning models have achieved rapid progress, but their advancement is constrained by two major limitations: the absence of open, large-scale, high-quality long chain-of-thought (CoT) data, and the instability of reinforcement learning (RL) algorithms in post-training. Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), the standard framework for RL fine-tuning, is prone to gradient vanishing when reward variance is low, which weakens optimization signals and impairs convergence. This work makes three contributions: (1) We propose Variance-Aware Sampling (VAS), a data selection strategy guided by Variance Promotion Score (VPS) that combines outcome variance and trajectory diversity to promote reward variance and stabilize policy optimization. (2) We release large-scale, carefully curated resources containing ~1.6M long CoT cold-start data and ~15k RL QA pairs, designed to ensure quality, difficulty, and diversity, along with a fully reproducible end-to-end training codebase. (3) We open-source a family of multimodal reasoning models in multiple scales, establishing standardized baselines for the community. Experiments across mathematical reasoning benchmarks demonstrate the effectiveness of both the curated data and the proposed VAS. Comprehensive ablation studies and analyses provide further insight into the contributions of each component. In addition, we theoretically establish that reward variance lower-bounds the expected policy gradient magnitude, with VAS serving as a practical mechanism to realize this guarantee. Our code, data, and checkpoints are available at https://github.com/LengSicong/MMR1.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21268</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 14:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does FLUX Already Know How to Perform Physically Plausible Image   Composition?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21278</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21278.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shilin Lu, Zhuming Lian, Zihan Zhou, Shaocong Zhang, Chen Zhao, Adams Wai-Kin Kong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 13&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Image composition aims to seamlessly insert a user-specified object into a new scene, but existing models struggle with complex lighting (e.g., accurate shadows, water reflections) and diverse, high-resolution inputs. Modern text-to-image diffusion models (e.g., SD3.5, FLUX) already encode essential physical and resolution priors, yet lack a framework to unleash them without resorting to latent inversion, which often locks object poses into contextually inappropriate orientations, or brittle attention surgery. We propose SHINE, a training-free framework for Seamless, High-fidelity Insertion with Neutralized Errors. SHINE introduces manifold-steered anchor loss, leveraging pretrained customization adapters (e.g., IP-Adapter) to guide latents for faithful subject representation while preserving background integrity. Degradation-suppression guidance and adaptive background blending are proposed to further eliminate low-quality outputs and visible seams. To address the lack of rigorous benchmarks, we introduce ComplexCompo, featuring diverse resolutions and challenging conditions such as low lighting, strong illumination, intricate shadows, and reflective surfaces. Experiments on ComplexCompo and DreamEditBench show state-of-the-art performance on standard metrics (e.g., DINOv2) and human-aligned scores (e.g., DreamSim, ImageReward, VisionReward). Code and benchmark will be publicly available upon publication.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21278</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 15:01:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized Visual Geometry Grounded Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21302</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21302.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weilun Feng, Haotong Qin, Mingqiang Wu, Chuanguang Yang, Yuqi Li, Xiangqi Li, Zhulin An, Libo Huang, Yulun Zhang, Michele Magno, Yongjun Xu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Learning-based 3D reconstruction models, represented by Visual Geometry Grounded Transformers (VGGTs), have made remarkable progress with the use of large-scale transformers. Their prohibitive computational and memory costs severely hinder real-world deployment. Post-Training Quantization (PTQ) has become a common practice for compressing and accelerating models. However, we empirically observe that PTQ faces unique obstacles when compressing billion-scale VGGTs: the data-independent special tokens induce heavy-tailed activation distributions, while the multi-view nature of 3D data makes calibration sample selection highly unstable. This paper proposes the first Quantization framework for VGGTs, namely QuantVGGT. This mainly relies on two technical contributions: First, we introduce Dual-Smoothed Fine-Grained Quantization, which integrates pre-global Hadamard rotation and post-local channel smoothing to mitigate heavy-tailed distributions and inter-channel variance robustly. Second, we design Noise-Filtered Diverse Sampling, which filters outliers via deep-layer statistics and constructs frame-aware diverse calibration clusters to ensure stable quantization ranges. Comprehensive experiments demonstrate that QuantVGGT achieves the state-of-the-art results across different benchmarks and bit-width, surpassing the previous state-of-the-art generic quantization method with a great margin. We highlight that our 4-bit QuantVGGT can deliver a 3.7times memory reduction and 2.5times acceleration in real-hardware inference, while maintaining reconstruction accuracy above 98\% of its full-precision counterpart. This demonstrates the vast advantages and practicality of QuantVGGT in resource-constrained scenarios. Our code is released in https://github.com/wlfeng0509/QuantVGGT.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21302</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 15:17:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Recommendation Agent with Active User Commands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21317</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21317.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiakai Tang, Yujie Luo, Xunke Xi, Fei Sun, Xueyang Feng, Sunhao Dai, Chao Yi, Dian Chen, Zhujin Gao, Yang Li, Xu Chen, Wen Chen, Jian Wu, Yuning Jiang, Bo Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Traditional recommender systems rely on passive feedback mechanisms that limit users to simple choices such as like and dislike. However, these coarse-grained signals fail to capture users' nuanced behavior motivations and intentions. In turn, current systems cannot also distinguish which specific item attributes drive user satisfaction or dissatisfaction, resulting in inaccurate preference modeling. These fundamental limitations create a persistent gap between user intentions and system interpretations, ultimately undermining user satisfaction and harming system effectiveness.   To address these limitations, we introduce the Interactive Recommendation Feed (IRF), a pioneering paradigm that enables natural language commands within mainstream recommendation feeds. Unlike traditional systems that confine users to passive implicit behavioral influence, IRF empowers active explicit control over recommendation policies through real-time linguistic commands. To support this paradigm, we develop RecBot, a dual-agent architecture where a Parser Agent transforms linguistic expressions into structured preferences and a Planner Agent dynamically orchestrates adaptive tool chains for on-the-fly policy adjustment. To enable practical deployment, we employ simulation-augmented knowledge distillation to achieve efficient performance while maintaining strong reasoning capabilities. Through extensive offline and long-term online experiments, RecBot shows significant improvements in both user satisfaction and business outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21317</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 15:38:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SD3.5-Flash: Distribution-Guided Distillation of Generative Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21318</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21318.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hmrishav Bandyopadhyay, Rahim Entezari, Jim Scott, Reshinth Adithyan, Yi-Zhe Song, Varun Jampani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present SD3.5-Flash, an efficient few-step distillation framework that brings high-quality image generation to accessible consumer devices. Our approach distills computationally prohibitive rectified flow models through a reformulated distribution matching objective tailored specifically for few-step generation. We introduce two key innovations: "timestep sharing" to reduce gradient noise and "split-timestep fine-tuning" to improve prompt alignment. Combined with comprehensive pipeline optimizations like text encoder restructuring and specialized quantization, our system enables both rapid generation and memory-efficient deployment across different hardware configurations. This democratizes access across the full spectrum of devices, from mobile phones to desktop computers. Through extensive evaluation including large-scale user studies, we demonstrate that SD3.5-Flash consistently outperforms existing few-step methods, making advanced generative AI truly accessible for practical deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21318</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 16:07:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SciReasoner: Laying the Scientific Reasoning Ground Across Disciplines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21320</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2509.21320.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yizhou Wang, Chen Tang, Han Deng, Jiabei Xiao, Jiaqi Liu, Jianyu Wu, Jun Yao, Pengze Li, Encheng Su, Lintao Wang, Guohang Zhuang, Yuchen Ren, Ben Fei, Ming Hu, Xin Chen, Dongzhan Zhou, Junjun He, Xiangyu Yue, Zhenfei Yin, Jiamin Wu, Qihao Zheng, Yuhao Zhou, Huihui Xu, Chenglong Ma, Yan Lu, Wenlong Zhang, Chunfeng Song, Philip Torr, Shixiang Tang, Xinzhu Ma, Wanli Ouyang, Lei Bai&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 86&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We present a scientific reasoning foundation model that aligns natural language with heterogeneous scientific representations. The model is pretrained on a 206B-token corpus spanning scientific text, pure sequences, and sequence-text pairs, then aligned via SFT on 40M instructions, annealed cold-start bootstrapping to elicit long-form chain-of-thought, and reinforcement learning with task-specific reward shaping, which instills deliberate scientific reasoning. It supports four capability families, covering up to 103 tasks across workflows: (i) faithful translation between text and scientific formats, (ii) text/knowledge extraction, (iii) property prediction, (iv) property classification, (v) unconditional and conditional sequence generation and design. Compared with specialist systems, our approach broadens instruction coverage, improves cross-domain generalization, and enhances fidelity. We detail data curation and training and show that cross-discipline learning strengthens transfer and downstream reliability. The model, instruct tuning datasets and the evaluation code are open-sourced at https://huggingface.co/SciReason and https://github.com/open-sciencelab/SciReason.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21320</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 17:52:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
