<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugging Face Daily Papers</title>
    <link>https://huggingface.co/papers</link>
    <description>Daily research papers curated by the Hugging Face community.</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:02:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>SparseLoRA: Accelerating LLM Fine-Tuning with Contextual Sparsity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16500</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.16500.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Samir Khaki, Xiuyu Li, Junxian Guo, Ligeng Zhu, Chenfeng Xu, Konstantinos N. Plataniotis, Amir Yazdanbakhsh, Kurt Keutzer, Song Han, Zhijian Liu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 11&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-tuning LLMs is both computationally and memory-intensive. While parameter-efficient fine-tuning methods, such as QLoRA and DoRA, reduce the number of trainable parameters and lower memory usage, they do not decrease computational cost. In some cases, they may even slow down fine-tuning. In this paper, we introduce SparseLoRA, a method that accelerates LLM fine-tuning through contextual sparsity. We propose a lightweight, training-free SVD sparsity estimator that dynamically selects a sparse subset of weights for loss and gradient computation. Also, we systematically analyze and address sensitivity across layers, tokens, and training steps. Our experimental results show that SparseLoRA reduces computational cost by up to 2.2 times and a measured speedup of up to 1.6 times while maintaining accuracy across various downstream tasks, including commonsense and arithmetic reasoning, code generation, and instruction following.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16500</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 17:53:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tower+: Bridging Generality and Translation Specialization in   Multilingual LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17080</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17080.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ricardo Rei, Nuno M. Guerreiro, José Pombal, João Alves, Pedro Teixeirinha, Amin Farajian, André F. T. Martins&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Fine-tuning pretrained LLMs has been shown to be an effective strategy for reaching state-of-the-art performance on specific tasks like machine translation. However, this process of adaptation often implies sacrificing general-purpose capabilities, such as conversational reasoning and instruction-following, hampering the utility of the system in real-world applications that require a mixture of skills. In this paper, we introduce Tower+, a suite of models designed to deliver strong performance across both translation and multilingual general-purpose text capabilities. We achieve a Pareto frontier between translation specialization and multilingual general-purpose capabilities by introducing a novel training recipe that builds on Tower (Alves et al., 2024), comprising continued pretraining, supervised fine-tuning, preference optimization, and reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards. At each stage of training, we carefully generate and curate data to strengthen performance on translation as well as general-purpose tasks involving code generation, mathematics problem solving, and general instruction-following. We develop models at multiple scales: 2B, 9B, and 72B. Our smaller models often outperform larger general-purpose open-weight and proprietary LLMs (e.g., Llama 3.3 70B, GPT-4o). Our largest model delivers best-in-class translation performance for high-resource languages and top results in multilingual Arena Hard evaluations and in IF-MT, a benchmark we introduce for evaluating both translation and instruction-following. Our findings highlight that it is possible to rival frontier models in general capabilities, while optimizing for specific business domains, such as translation and localization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17080</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 15:30:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aha Moment Revisited: Are VLMs Truly Capable of Self Verification in   Inference-time Scaling?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17417</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17417.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingyuan Wu, Meitang Li, Jingcheng Yang, Jize Jiang, Kaizhuo Yan, Zhaoheng Li, Minjia Zhang, Klara Nahrstedt&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have demonstrated that inference-time computation techniques, such as decoding-time scaling and self-refinement, can significantly enhance reasoning capabilities without relying on external knowledge. A key driver of this success is the emergence of self-correction and self-verification behaviors, often elicited through reinforcement learning (RL). In this paper, we investigate whether these inference-time techniques extend effectively to vision-language models (VLMs), particularly those trained with RL. We find that while decoding strategies such as majority voting and best-of-N selection with self-verification all improve VLM reasoning performance, generation-reliant methods such as the former achieve significantly higher gains versus verification-reliant methods such as the latter. Additionally, the self-correction behavior often associated with RL-tuned models, such as aha moment, does not lead to measurable gains. We show via extensive experimentation within the inference-time scaling framework to identify a key root cause: RL-trained VLMs still lack robust self-verification capabilities across both visual and textual modalities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17417</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 18:23:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolving Prompts In-Context: An Open-ended, Self-replicating Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17930</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.17930.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianyu Wang, Zhiqiang Hu, Lidong Bing&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We propose a novel prompt design paradigm that challenges conventional wisdom in large language model (LLM) prompting. While conventional wisdom prioritizes well-crafted instructions and demonstrations for in-context learning (ICL), we show that pruning random demonstrations into seemingly incoherent "gibberish" can remarkably improve performance across diverse tasks. Notably, the "gibberish" always matches or surpasses state-of-the-art automatic prompt optimization techniques, achieving substantial gains regardless of LLM alignment. Nevertheless, discovering an effective pruning strategy is non-trivial, as existing attribution methods and prompt compression algorithms fail to deliver robust results, let alone human intuition. In terms of this, we propose a self-discover prompt optimization framework, PromptQuine, an evolutionary search framework that automatically searches for the pruning strategy by itself using only low-data regimes. Much like the emergent complexity in nature--such as symbiosis and self-organization--arising in response to resource constraints, our framework evolves and refines unconventional yet highly effective prompts by leveraging only the tokens present within the context. We demonstrate its effectiveness across classification, multi-choice question answering, generation and math reasoning tasks across LLMs, while achieving decent runtime efficiency. We hope our findings can guide mechanistic studies on in-context learning, and provide a call to action, to pave the way for more open-ended search algorithms for more effective LLM prompting.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17930</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 07:53:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ThinkSound: Chain-of-Thought Reasoning in Multimodal Large Language   Models for Audio Generation and Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21448</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.21448.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Huadai Liu, Jialei Wang, Kaicheng Luo, Wen Wang, Qian Chen, Zhou Zhao, Wei Xue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; While end-to-end video-to-audio generation has greatly improved, producing high-fidelity audio that authentically captures the nuances of visual content remains challenging. Like professionals in the creative industries, such generation requires sophisticated reasoning about items such as visual dynamics, acoustic environments, and temporal relationships. We present ThinkSound, a novel framework that leverages Chain-of-Thought (CoT) reasoning to enable stepwise, interactive audio generation and editing for videos. Our approach decomposes the process into three complementary stages: foundational foley generation that creates semantically coherent soundscapes, interactive object-centric refinement through precise user interactions, and targeted editing guided by natural language instructions. At each stage, a multimodal large language model generates contextually aligned CoT reasoning that guides a unified audio foundation model. Furthermore, we introduce AudioCoT, a comprehensive dataset with structured reasoning annotations that establishes connections between visual content, textual descriptions, and sound synthesis. Experiments demonstrate that ThinkSound achieves state-of-the-art performance in video-to-audio generation across both audio metrics and CoT metrics and excels in out-of-distribution Movie Gen Audio benchmark. The demo page is available at https://ThinkSound-Project.github.io.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21448</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 16:32:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RExBench: Can coding agents autonomously implement AI research   extensions?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22598</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.22598.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nicholas Edwards, Yukyung Lee, Yujun, Mao, Yulu Qin, Sebastian Schuster, Najoung Kim&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Agents based on Large Language Models (LLMs) have shown promise for performing sophisticated software engineering tasks autonomously. In addition, there has been progress towards developing agents that can perform parts of the research pipeline in machine learning and the natural sciences. We argue that research extension and its implementation is a critical capability for such systems, and introduce RExBench to support the evaluation of this capability. RExBench is a benchmark consisting of 12 realistic research experiment implementation tasks that aim to investigate research hypotheses that have not previously been implemented. Each task is set up as an extension to an existing research paper and codebase, accompanied by domain expert-written instructions. RExBench is robust to data contamination, and supports an automatic evaluation infrastructure that executes agent outputs to determine whether the success criteria are met. We use this benchmark to evaluate nine LLM agents implemented using three different frameworks: aider, Claude Code, and OpenHands. We find that all agents evaluated fail to autonomously implement the majority of the extensions. Although the success rate improves with additional human-written hints, the best performance under this setting remains below 40%. This indicates that current agents are still short of being able to handle realistic research extension tasks without substantial human guidance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22598</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 19:41:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VOCABTRIM: Vocabulary Pruning for Efficient Speculative Decoding in LLMs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22694</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.22694.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Raghavv Goel, Sudhanshu Agrawal, Mukul Gagrani, Junyoung Park, Yifan Zao, He Zhang, Tian Liu, Yiping Yang, Xin Yuan, Jiuyan Lu, Chris Lott, Mingu Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this paper, we introduce a simple training-free technique to improve the performance of drafter-based speculative decoding (SpD) methods that incorporates language modeling head (LM head) during drafting process. A drafter-based speculative decoding leverages one or more smaller language models, a.k.a. drafters or draft models, to sample a draft sequence or tree consisting of multiple tokens, followed by verification by a base LLM, a target model, accepting a subset as its valid generation. As it is usually considered that the speculative decoding requires one-to-one mapping between vocabularies of the target model and the draft model, it has been natural to share the vocabulary between them, or even share the LM head as in EAGLE or Medusa. We first identify that this draft token sampling scheme inherently contains an unnecessary inference overhead in drafting, especially for some target LLMs with very large vocabularies. Then, we propose a simple technique, VocabTrim, to mitigate the drafting overhead to improve the generation speed in memory-bound environment. VocabTrim reconstructs the drafter LM head to contain only a limited set of tokens, selected by the most frequently sampled from the vocabulary of the target model. While limiting the vocabulary in drafting slightly degrades the acceptance rate, it significantly reduces the drafting latency in memory-bound process which is often the case on edge devices, resulting in higher memory-bound speed up (MBSU). We show that our method can boost the memory-bound speed-up for Llama-3 models on Spec-Bench, specifically by 16% for Llama-3.2-3B-Instruct.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22694</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 00:26:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Degradation-Modeled Multipath Diffusion for Tunable Metalens Photography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22753</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.22753.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianing Zhang, Jiayi Zhu, Feiyu Ji, Xiaokang Yang, Xiaoyun Yuan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Metalenses offer significant potential for ultra-compact computational imaging but face challenges from complex optical degradation and computational restoration difficulties. Existing methods typically rely on precise optical calibration or massive paired datasets, which are non-trivial for real-world imaging systems. Furthermore, a lack of control over the inference process often results in undesirable hallucinated artifacts. We introduce Degradation-Modeled Multipath Diffusion for tunable metalens photography, leveraging powerful natural image priors from pretrained models instead of large datasets. Our framework uses positive, neutral, and negative-prompt paths to balance high-frequency detail generation, structural fidelity, and suppression of metalens-specific degradation, alongside pseudo data augmentation. A tunable decoder enables controlled trade-offs between fidelity and perceptual quality. Additionally, a spatially varying degradation-aware attention (SVDA) module adaptively models complex optical and sensor-induced degradation. Finally, we design and build a millimeter-scale MetaCamera for real-world validation. Extensive results show that our approach outperforms state-of-the-art methods, achieving high-fidelity and sharp image reconstruction. More materials: https://dmdiff.github.io/.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22753</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 04:48:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Listener-Rewarded Thinking in VLMs for Image Preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22832</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.22832.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alexander Gambashidze, Li Pengyi, Matvey Skripkin, Andrey Galichin, Anton Gusarov, Konstantin Sobolev, Andrey Kuznetsov, Ivan Oseledets&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Training robust and generalizable reward models for human visual preferences is essential for aligning text-to-image and text-to-video generative models with human intent. However, current reward models often fail to generalize, and supervised fine-tuning leads to memorization, demanding complex annotation pipelines. While reinforcement learning (RL), specifically Group Relative Policy Optimization (GRPO), improves generalization, we uncover a key failure mode: a significant drop in reasoning accuracy occurs when a model's reasoning trace contradicts that of an independent, frozen vision-language model ("listener") evaluating the same output. To address this, we introduce a listener-augmented GRPO framework. Here, the listener re-evaluates the reasoner's chain-of-thought to provide a dense, calibrated confidence score, shaping the RL reward signal. This encourages the reasoner not only to answer correctly, but to produce explanations that are persuasive to an independent model. Our listener-shaped reward scheme achieves best accuracy on the ImageReward benchmark (67.4%), significantly improves out-of-distribution (OOD) performance on a large-scale human preference dataset (1.2M votes, up to +6% over naive reasoner), and reduces reasoning contradictions compared to strong GRPO and SFT baselines. These results demonstrate that listener-based rewards provide a scalable, data-efficient path to aligning vision-language models with nuanced human preferences. We will release our reasoning model here: https://huggingface.co/alexgambashidze/qwen2.5vl_image_preference_reasoner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22832</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 09:53:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MARBLE: A Hard Benchmark for Multimodal Spatial Reasoning and Planning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22992</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.22992.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yulun Jiang, Yekun Chai, Maria Brbić, Michael Moor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The ability to process information from multiple modalities and to reason through it step-by-step remains a critical challenge in advancing artificial intelligence. However, existing reasoning benchmarks focus on text-only reasoning, or employ multimodal questions that can be answered by directly retrieving information from a non-text modality. Thus, complex reasoning remains poorly understood in multimodal domains. Here, we present MARBLE, a challenging multimodal reasoning benchmark that is designed to scrutinize multimodal language models (MLLMs) in their ability to carefully reason step-by-step through complex multimodal problems and environments. MARBLE is composed of two highly challenging tasks, M-Portal and M-Cube, that require the crafting and understanding of multistep plans under spatial, visual, and physical constraints. We find that current MLLMs perform poorly on MARBLE -- all the 12 advanced models obtain near-random performance on M-Portal and 0% accuracy on M-Cube. Only in simplified subtasks some models outperform the random baseline, indicating that complex reasoning is still a challenge for existing MLLMs. Moreover, we show that perception remains a bottleneck, where MLLMs occasionally fail to extract information from the visual inputs. By shedding a light on the limitations of MLLMs, we hope that MARBLE will spur the development of the next generation of models with the ability to reason and plan across many, multimodal reasoning steps.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22992</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 19:44:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ovis-U1 Technical Report</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23044</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.23044.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Guo-Hua Wang, Shanshan Zhao, Xinjie Zhang, Liangfu Cao, Pengxin Zhan, Lunhao Duan, Shiyin Lu, Minghao Fu, Xiaohao Chen, Jianshan Zhao, Yang Li, Qing-Guo Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 48&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; In this report, we introduce Ovis-U1, a 3-billion-parameter unified model that integrates multimodal understanding, text-to-image generation, and image editing capabilities. Building on the foundation of the Ovis series, Ovis-U1 incorporates a diffusion-based visual decoder paired with a bidirectional token refiner, enabling image generation tasks comparable to leading models like GPT-4o. Unlike some previous models that use a frozen MLLM for generation tasks, Ovis-U1 utilizes a new unified training approach starting from a language model. Compared to training solely on understanding or generation tasks, unified training yields better performance, demonstrating the enhancement achieved by integrating these two tasks. Ovis-U1 achieves a score of 69.6 on the OpenCompass Multi-modal Academic Benchmark, surpassing recent state-of-the-art models such as Ristretto-3B and SAIL-VL-1.5-2B. In text-to-image generation, it excels with scores of 83.72 and 0.89 on the DPG-Bench and GenEval benchmarks, respectively. For image editing, it achieves 4.00 and 6.42 on the ImgEdit-Bench and GEdit-Bench-EN, respectively. As the initial version of the Ovis unified model series, Ovis-U1 pushes the boundaries of multimodal understanding, generation, and editing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23044</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 00:40:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RoboScape: Physics-informed Embodied World Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23135</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.23135.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yu Shang, Xin Zhang, Yinzhou Tang, Lei Jin, Chen Gao, Wei Wu, Yong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; World models have become indispensable tools for embodied intelligence, serving as powerful simulators capable of generating realistic robotic videos while addressing critical data scarcity challenges. However, current embodied world models exhibit limited physical awareness, particularly in modeling 3D geometry and motion dynamics, resulting in unrealistic video generation for contact-rich robotic scenarios. In this paper, we present RoboScape, a unified physics-informed world model that jointly learns RGB video generation and physics knowledge within an integrated framework. We introduce two key physics-informed joint training tasks: temporal depth prediction that enhances 3D geometric consistency in video rendering, and keypoint dynamics learning that implicitly encodes physical properties (e.g., object shape and material characteristics) while improving complex motion modeling. Extensive experiments demonstrate that RoboScape generates videos with superior visual fidelity and physical plausibility across diverse robotic scenarios. We further validate its practical utility through downstream applications including robotic policy training with generated data and policy evaluation. Our work provides new insights for building efficient physics-informed world models to advance embodied intelligence research. The code is available at: https://github.com/tsinghua-fib-lab/RoboScape.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23135</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 08:19:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MEMFOF: High-Resolution Training for Memory-Efficient Multi-Frame   Optical Flow Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23151</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.23151.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vladislav Bargatin, Egor Chistov, Alexander Yakovenko, Dmitriy Vatolin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 15&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in optical flow estimation have prioritized accuracy at the cost of growing GPU memory consumption, particularly for high-resolution (FullHD) inputs. We introduce MEMFOF, a memory-efficient multi-frame optical flow method that identifies a favorable trade-off between multi-frame estimation and GPU memory usage. Notably, MEMFOF requires only 2.09 GB of GPU memory at runtime for 1080p inputs, and 28.5 GB during training, which uniquely positions our method to be trained at native 1080p without the need for cropping or downsampling. We systematically revisit design choices from RAFT-like architectures, integrating reduced correlation volumes and high-resolution training protocols alongside multi-frame estimation, to achieve state-of-the-art performance across multiple benchmarks while substantially reducing memory overhead. Our method outperforms more resource-intensive alternatives in both accuracy and runtime efficiency, validating its robustness for flow estimation at high resolutions. At the time of submission, our method ranks first on the Spring benchmark with a 1-pixel (1px) outlier rate of 3.289, leads Sintel (clean) with an endpoint error (EPE) of 0.963, and achieves the best Fl-all error on KITTI-2015 at 2.94%. The code is available at https://github.com/msu-video-group/memfof.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23151</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 09:01:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UrbanLLaVA: A Multi-modal Large Language Model for Urban Intelligence   with Spatial Reasoning and Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23219</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.23219.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jie Feng, Shengyuan Wang, Tianhui Liu, Yanxin Xi, Yong Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Urban research involves a wide range of scenarios and tasks that require the understanding of multi-modal data. Current methods often focus on specific data types and lack a unified framework in urban field for processing them comprehensively. The recent success of multi-modal large language models (MLLMs) presents a promising opportunity to overcome this limitation. In this paper, we introduce UrbanLLaVA, a multi-modal large language model designed to process these four types of data simultaneously and achieve strong performance across diverse urban tasks compared with general MLLMs. In UrbanLLaVA, we first curate a diverse urban instruction dataset encompassing both single-modal and cross-modal urban data, spanning from location view to global view of urban environment. Additionally, we propose a multi-stage training framework that decouples spatial reasoning enhancement from domain knowledge learning, thereby improving the compatibility and downstream performance of UrbanLLaVA across diverse urban tasks. Finally, we also extend existing benchmark for urban research to assess the performance of MLLMs across a wide range of urban tasks. Experimental results from three cities demonstrate that UrbanLLaVA outperforms open-source and proprietary MLLMs in both single-modal tasks and complex cross-modal tasks and shows robust generalization abilities across cities. Source codes and data are openly accessible to the research community via https://github.com/tsinghua-fib-lab/UrbanLLaVA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23219</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 13:04:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teaching a Language Model to Speak the Language of Tools</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23394</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.23394.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Simeon Emanuilov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; External tool integration through function-calling is essential for practical language model applications, yet most multilingual models lack reliable tool-use capabilities in non-English languages. Even state-of-the-art multilingual models struggle with determining when to use tools and generating the structured outputs required for function calls, often exhibiting language confusion when prompted in lower-resource languages. This work presents a methodology for adapting existing language models to enable robust tool use in any target language, using Bulgarian as a case study. The approach involves continued training of the BgGPT model series (2.6B, 9B, 27B parameters) on a novel bilingual dataset of 10,035 function-calling examples designed to support standardized protocols like MCP (Model Context Protocol). The research introduces TUCAN (Tool-Using Capable Assistant Navigator), which achieves up to 28.75% improvement in function-calling accuracy over base models while preserving core language understanding, as verified on established Bulgarian benchmarks. Beyond accuracy gains, TUCAN models demonstrate production-ready response formatting with clean, parsable function calls, contrasting with the verbose and inconsistent outputs of base models. The models, evaluation framework, and dataset are released to enable replication for other languages. This work demonstrates a practical approach for extending tool-augmented capabilities beyond English-centric systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23394</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 20:47:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consistent Time-of-Flight Depth Denoising via Graph-Informed Geometric   Attention</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23542</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.23542.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weida Wang, Changyong He, Jin Zeng, Di Qiu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Depth images captured by Time-of-Flight (ToF) sensors are prone to noise, requiring denoising for reliable downstream applications. Previous works either focus on single-frame processing, or perform multi-frame processing without considering depth variations at corresponding pixels across frames, leading to undesirable temporal inconsistency and spatial ambiguity. In this paper, we propose a novel ToF depth denoising network leveraging motion-invariant graph fusion to simultaneously enhance temporal stability and spatial sharpness. Specifically, despite depth shifts across frames, graph structures exhibit temporal self-similarity, enabling cross-frame geometric attention for graph fusion. Then, by incorporating an image smoothness prior on the fused graph and data fidelity term derived from ToF noise distribution, we formulate a maximum a posterior problem for ToF denoising. Finally, the solution is unrolled into iterative filters whose weights are adaptively learned from the graph-informed geometric attention, producing a high-performance yet interpretable network. Experimental results demonstrate that the proposed scheme achieves state-of-the-art performance in terms of accuracy and consistency on synthetic DVToF dataset and exhibits robust generalization on the real Kinectv2 dataset. Source code will be released at https://github.com/davidweidawang/GIGA-ToF{https://github.com/davidweidawang/GIGA-ToF}.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23542</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 06:29:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VMoBA: Mixture-of-Block Attention for Video Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23858</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.23858.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianzong Wu, Liang Hou, Haotian Yang, Xin Tao, Ye Tian, Pengfei Wan, Di Zhang, Yunhai Tong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 25&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; The quadratic complexity of full attention mechanisms poses a significant bottleneck for Video Diffusion Models (VDMs) aiming to generate long-duration, high-resolution videos. While various sparse attention methods have been proposed, many are designed as training-free inference accelerators or do not optimally capture the unique spatio-temporal characteristics inherent in video data when trained natively. This paper introduces Video Mixture of Block Attention (VMoBA), a novel sparse attention mechanism specifically adapted for VDMs. Motivated by an in-depth analysis of attention patterns within pre-trained video transformers, which revealed strong spatio-temporal locality, varying query importance, and head-specific concentration levels, VMoBA enhances the original MoBA framework with three key modifications: (1) a layer-wise recurrent block partition scheme (1D-2D-3D) to dynamically adapt to diverse spatio-temporal attention patterns and improve efficiency; (2) global block selection to prioritize the most salient query-key block interactions across an entire attention head; and (3) threshold-based block selection to dynamically determine the number of attended blocks based on their cumulative similarity. Extensive experiments demonstrate that VMoBA significantly accelerates the training of VDMs on longer sequences, achieving 2.92x FLOPs and 1.48x latency speedup, while attaining comparable or even superior generation quality to full attention. Furthermore, VMoBA exhibits competitive performance in training-free inference, offering 2.40x FLOPs and 1.35x latency speedup for high-res video generation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23858</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 13:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPIRAL: Self-Play on Zero-Sum Games Incentivizes Reasoning via   Multi-Agent Multi-Turn Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.24119</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.24119.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Bo Liu, Leon Guertler, Simon Yu, Zichen Liu, Penghui Qi, Daniel Balcells, Mickel Liu, Cheston Tan, Weiyan Shi, Min Lin, Wee Sun Lee, Natasha Jaques&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 26&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; Recent advances in reinforcement learning have shown that language models can develop sophisticated reasoning through training on tasks with verifiable rewards, but these approaches depend on human-curated problem-answer pairs and domain-specific reward engineering. We introduce SPIRAL, a self-play framework where models learn by playing multi-turn, zero-sum games against continuously improving versions of themselves, eliminating the need for human supervision. Through self-play, SPIRAL generates an infinite curriculum of progressively challenging problems as models must constantly adapt to stronger opponents. To enable this self-play training at scale, We implement a fully online, multi-turn, multi-agent reinforcement learning system for LLMs and propose role-conditioned advantage estimation (RAE) to stabilize multi-agent training. Using SPIRAL, self-play on zero-sum games produces reasoning capabilities that transfer broadly. Training Qwen3-4B-Base on Kuhn Poker alone achieves 8.6% improvement on math and 8.4% on general reasoning, outperforming SFT on 25,000 expert game trajectories. Analysis reveals that this transfer occurs through three cognitive patterns: systematic decomposition, expected value calculation, and case-by-case analysis. Multi-game training (TicTacToe, Kuhn Poker, Simple Negotiation) further enhances performance as each game develops distinct reasoning strengths. Applying SPIRAL to a strong reasoning model (DeepSeek-R1-Distill-Qwen-7B) can still lead to 2.0% average improvement. These results demonstrate that zero-sum games naturally develop transferable reasoning capabilities, highlighting a promising direction for autonomous reasoning development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.24119</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 17:58:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calligrapher: Freestyle Text Image Customization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.24123</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn-thumbnails.huggingface.co/social-thumbnails/papers/2506.24123.png" alt="Paper thumbnail" style="max-width: 300px; height: auto;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yue Ma, Qingyan Bai, Hao Ouyang, Ka Leong Cheng, Qiuyu Wang, Hongyu Liu, Zichen Liu, Haofan Wang, Jingye Chen, Yujun Shen, Qifeng Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Upvotes:&lt;/b&gt; 24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary:&lt;/b&gt; We introduce Calligrapher, a novel diffusion-based framework that innovatively integrates advanced text customization with artistic typography for digital calligraphy and design applications. Addressing the challenges of precise style control and data dependency in typographic customization, our framework incorporates three key technical contributions. First, we develop a self-distillation mechanism that leverages the pre-trained text-to-image generative model itself alongside the large language model to automatically construct a style-centric typography benchmark. Second, we introduce a localized style injection framework via a trainable style encoder, which comprises both Qformer and linear layers, to extract robust style features from reference images. An in-context generation mechanism is also employed to directly embed reference images into the denoising process, further enhancing the refined alignment of target styles. Extensive quantitative and qualitative evaluations across diverse fonts and design contexts confirm Calligrapher's accurate reproduction of intricate stylistic details and precise glyph positioning. By automating high-quality, visually consistent typography, Calligrapher surpasses traditional models, empowering creative practitioners in digital art, branding, and contextual typographic design.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.24123</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 17:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
